<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-bnz.512.6" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0&#10;				http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
<allow>
<principal>uid=BNZ,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
<principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
<dataset>
<shortName>knb-lter-bnz.512.6</shortName>
<title>The impact of permafrost thaw on ecosystem carbon balance: The radiocarbon value of ecosystem respiration from 2004 through 2012 I - Gradient Reco</title>
<creator>
<individualName>
<givenName>Edward</givenName>
<givenName>A.G.</givenName>
<surName>Schuur</surName>
</individualName>
<positionName>Senior Investigator</positionName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>University of Florida Department of Botany 220 Bartram Hall</deliveryPoint>
<city>Gainesville</city>
<administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>32611</postalCode>
<country>United States</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">(352) 392-7913</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">(352) 392-3993</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>tschuur@ufl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
<onlineUrl>http://www.biology.ufl.edu/People/faculty/tschuur.aspx</onlineUrl>
</creator>
<creator>
<individualName>
<givenName>Caitlin</givenName>
<givenName>Elizabeth</givenName>
<surName>Hicks-Pries</surName>
</individualName>
<positionName>Graduate Student</positionName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, University of Florida, PO Box 118526, 217 Bartram Hall</deliveryPoint>
<city>Gainesville</city>
<administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>32611</postalCode>
<country>United States</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">(413) 530-8481</phone>

<electronicMailAddress>chicks@ufl.edu</electronicMailAddress>

</creator>
<creator>
<organizationName>Bonanza Creek LTER</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>Boreal Ecology Cooperative Research Unit </deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>University of Alaska Fairbanks</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 756780 </deliveryPoint>
<city>Fairbanks</city>
<administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>99775</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">907-474-6364</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">907-474-6251</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>uaf-bnz-im-team@alaska.edu</electronicMailAddress>
<onlineUrl>http://www.lter.uaf.edu</onlineUrl>
</creator>
<metadataProvider>
<organizationName>Bonanza Creek LTER</organizationName>
<positionName>Data Manager</positionName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>Boreal Ecology Cooperative Research Unit </deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>University of Alaska Fairbanks</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 756780 </deliveryPoint>
<city>Fairbanks</city>
<administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>99775</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">907-474-6364</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">907-474-6251</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>uaf-bnz-im-team@alaska.edu</electronicMailAddress>
<onlineUrl>http://www.lter.uaf.edu</onlineUrl>
</metadataProvider>

<pubDate>2012-11-15</pubDate>
<abstract>
<para>In this larger study, we are asking the question: Is old carbon that comprises the bulk of the soil organic matter pool released in response to thawing of permafrost?  We are answering this question by using a combination of field and laboratory experiments to measure radiocarbon isotope ratios in soil organic matter, soil respiration, and decomposition in tundra ecosystems.  The objective of these proposed measurements is to develop a mechanistic understanding of the SOM sources contributing to C losses following permafrost thawing.  We are making these measurements at  an established tundra field site near Healy, Alaska in the foothills of the Alaska Range.  Field measurements  center on a natural experiment where permafrost has been observed to warm and thaw over the past several decades.  This area represents a gradient of sites each with a different degree of change due to permafrost thawing.  As such, this area is unique for addressing questions at the time and spatial scales relevant for change in arctic ecosystems.  This data set includes the growing season radiocarbon values of ecosystem and plant respiration at the thaw gradient and CiPEHR (a permafrost warming experiment). Depending on the year, the measurements were taken monthly during the growing season or just once a growing season.</para>
</abstract>
<keywordSet>
<keyword>carbon</keyword>
<keyword>ecosystem respiration</keyword>
<keyword>radiocarbon</keyword>
<keyword>permafrost</keyword>
<keyword>tundra</keyword>
<keywordThesaurus>Decomposition</keywordThesaurus>
</keywordSet>
<intellectualRights>
<section>
<title>Access to Data</title>
<para>While metadata will be freely available to those requesting it, the data manager will assure that any restrictions on access to data sets in the database will be enforced. Data will not be released without proper permission first being obtained from the investigator who generated the data. </para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Use of data</title>
<para> Researchers should receive adequate acknowledgment for the use of their data by others and should be provided with copies of publications using their data. Users of data from the data base must be aware that data is not to be sold or redistributed.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Citing Bonanza Creek LTER Datasets</title>
<para>It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Data Set in any publications or in the metadata of any derived data products that were produced using the Data Set. </para>
</section>
</intellectualRights>

<coverage>
<geographicCoverage id="geoReference">
<geographicDescription>Site information unavailable</geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates>
<westBoundingCoordinate>-149.2535833</westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>-149.2535833</eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>63.87836111</northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>63.87836111</southBoundingCoordinate>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
<temporalCoverage>
<rangeOfDates>
<beginDate>
<calendarDate>2004-09-01</calendarDate>
</beginDate>
<endDate>
<calendarDate>2012-09-01</calendarDate>
</endDate>
</rangeOfDates>
</temporalCoverage>
</coverage>
<maintenance>
<description>
<section>
<title>corrections</title>
<para>?14C data were reported at the same ?13C value to correct for mass-dependent fractionation effects. The ecosystem respiration radiocarbon values from the trap were corrected for atmospheric contamination based on a simple 2-pool mixing model, which uses trap and atmospheric 13C and 14C values and ecosystem 13C values from keeling plots (see Schuur and Trumbore 2006 for details). An average of all keeling plot 13C values was used for ecosystem respiration when ecosystem respiration 13C was not measured. Plant respiration 14C was not corrected.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Status</title>
<para>Ongoing</para>
</section>
</description>
</maintenance>
<contact>
<organizationName>Bonanza Creek LTER</organizationName>
<positionName>Data Manager</positionName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>Boreal Ecology Cooperative Research Unit </deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>University of Alaska Fairbanks</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 756780 </deliveryPoint>
<city>Fairbanks</city>
<administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>99775</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">907-474-6364</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">907-474-6251</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>uaf-bnz-im-team@alaska.edu</electronicMailAddress>
<onlineUrl>http://www.lter.uaf.edu</onlineUrl>
</contact>
<publisher>
<organizationName>Bonanza Creek LTER</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>Boreal Ecology Cooperative Research Unit </deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>University of Alaska Fairbanks</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 756780 </deliveryPoint>
<city>Fairbanks</city>
<administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>99775</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">907-474-6364</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">907-474-6251</phone>
</publisher>
<pubPlace>Bonanza Creek LTER</pubPlace>
<methods>
<methodStep>
<description>
<section>
<title>Experimental Design</title>
<para>The study site at the Eight Mile Lake watershed is located in the northern foothills of the Alaska Range.  Permafrost temperature has been monitored annually on a gentle north-facing slope at this site, in a 30 m deep borehole that was installed in 1985 before the permafrost started to thaw.  While permafrost thaw can sometimes result in water ponding depending on local topography, this landscape consists largely of relatively well-drained uplands.  In this watershed, we monitored three sites that represented differing amounts of change as a result of permafrost thaw based on observations of ground subsidence and depth of thaw.  Our minimal thaw site had the shallowest summer thaw depth and the least ground surface subsidence, and the vegetation was typical moist acidic tundra, dominated by the tussock-forming sedge, Eriophorum vaginatum, with coexisting deciduous and evergreen shrubs, and an understory of mosses and lichens.  A second site, located adjacent to the borehole, had moderate summer thaw depths and increased ground subsidence.  Here the vegetation composition was similar to our minimal thaw site, but with increased biomass of all plant groups.  Lastly, an extensive thaw site was located in an area where permafrost degradation had occurred at least several decades prior to the establishment of the borehole; thermokarst can already be observed in air photos of the area taken in 1954.  This site had the deepest summer thaw depth and the most ground subsidence, and the plant biomass has shifted to dominance by shrubs, including blueberry (Vaccinium uliginosum) and cloudberry (Rubus chamaemorus), at the expense of sedges.  Four radiocarbon measurements were collected from each site, but usually, only three were run for radiocarbon. At CiPEHR, there are two experimental warming treatments:  Winter warming (WW) increases soil temperature and ground thaw using snow fences; Summer warming (SW) increases growing season air temperature using open top chambers. Six chambers are in each treatment, but only samples from half the chambers were run in 2009.</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
<sampling>
<studyExtent>
<coverage>
<geographicCoverage>
<references>geoReference</references>
</geographicCoverage>
<temporalCoverage>
<rangeOfDates>
<beginDate>
<calendarDate>2004-09-01</calendarDate>
</beginDate>
<endDate>
<calendarDate>2012-09-01</calendarDate>
</endDate>
</rangeOfDates>
</temporalCoverage>
</coverage>
</studyExtent>
<samplingDescription>
<section>
<title>Sampling Frequency</title>
<para>monthly or annual</para>
</section>
</samplingDescription>
</sampling>
</methods>

</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
 <metadata>
 <unitList>
<unit id="WWWYYYY" />
<unit id="month" />
</unitList>
 </metadata>
 </additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>