<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-vcr.225.2" system="VCR" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
   <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst">
      <allow>
         <principal>public</principal>
         <permission>read</permission>
      </allow>
      <allow>
         <principal>uid=VCR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
         <permission>all</permission>
      </allow>
   </access>

<dataset id="225" system="VCR">
   <alternateIdentifier>VCR14221</alternateIdentifier>
   <title>1993 Landuse/Landcover of the Lower Delmarva Peninsula</title>
   <creator>
      <individualName>
         <givenName>David</givenName>
         <surName>Richardson</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>Department of Environmental Sciences, Clark Hall, University of Virginia</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>22903</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(434) 924-3193</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(434) 982-2137</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>dlr2n@virginia.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu/cgi-bin/w3e/msql/personnel/msql2/person.html?QID=">drichardson</userId>
   </creator>
   <creator>
      <individualName>
         <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
         <givenName>Guofan</givenName>
         <surName>Shao</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>Purdue University, Department of Forestry and Natural Resources</deliveryPoint>
         <city>West Lafayette</city>
         <administrativeArea>IN</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>47907</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">317-494-3630</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>gshao@fnr.purdue.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu/cgi-bin/w3e/msql/personnel/msql2/person.html?QID=">gshao</userId>
   </creator>
   <metadataProvider>
      <organizationName>Virginia Coast Reserve Long-Term Ecological Research Project</organizationName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>Department of Environmental Sciences, University of Virginia, 291 McCormick Road, PO Box 400123</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>22904-4123</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">434-924-7761</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">434-982-2137</phone>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu</onlineUrl>
   </metadataProvider>
   <pubDate>2014-02-17</pubDate>
   <abstract>
  <para>This generalized landuse/landcover classification of the lower Delmarva Peninsula south of Snow Hill and Princess Ann, MD focuses on major habitats and vegetative communities of the Virginia Coast Reserve LTER.&#160; The classification is based on a Landsat 5 Thematic Mapper (TM) satellite image taken on July 28, 1993 at 15:02 GMT (11:02 EDT), which is within 15 minutes of observed low tide as recorded by the VCRLTER tide gauge at Redbank, VA.</para>
   </abstract>
   <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">System State/Condition</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>VCRLTERCoreAreas</keywordThesaurus>
   </keywordSet>
   <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">geographic information systems</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">land cover</keyword>
   </keywordSet>
   <additionalInfo>
<section> 
 <title>Related Documents</title>
  <para>Guofan Shao, Dave Richardson, John Porter, Barry Truitt, and Guang Zhao.&#160; 1995.&#160; Changes of Virginia Barrier Islands from 1852/1871 to 1993 (poster presentation).&#160; ESRI user conference, Palm Springs, CA.</para>
</section>

   </additionalInfo>
   <intellectualRights>
            <section>
                <title>Data License</title>
                <para>Data and documentation is copyrighted by The Virginia Coast Reserve LTER
                    project of the University of Virginia (UVA), and ownership remains with the UVA.</para>
                <para>The UVA grants you (hereafter, Licensee) a license to use the data and
                    documentation for academic, and research purposes only, without a fee.</para>
                <para>Licensee may make derivative works. However, if Licensee distributes any
                    derivative work based on or derived from the data and documentation, then
                    Licensee will</para>
                <para>
                    <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>notify the VCR/LTER designated contact (typically the investigator
                                who collected the data) regarding its distribution of the derivative
                                work, and</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>clearly notify users that such derivative work is a modified
                                version and not the original data and documentation distributed by
                                the UVA.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>acknowledge the support of NSF Grants BSR-8702333-06, DEB-9211772,
                                DEB-9411974, DEB-0080381, DEB-0621014 and DEB-1237733 in any publications using the data and documentation.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>send to the address, above, two reprints of any publications
                                resulting from use of the data and documentation. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </para>
                <para>Any Licensee wishing to make commercial use of the data and documentation
                    should contact the UVA, c/o VCR/LTER, to negotiate an appropriate license for
                    such commercial use. Commercial use includes</para>
                <para>
                    <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>integration of all or part of the data and documentation into a
                                product for sale or license by or on behalf of Licensee to third
                                parties, or</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> distribution of the data or documentation to third parties that
                                need it to utilize a commercial product sold or licensed by or on
                                behalf of Licensee.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </para>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>UVA MAKES NO REPRESENTATIONS ABOUT THE SUITABILITY OF THIS DATA AND
                        DOCUMENTATION FOR ANY PURPOSE. IT IS PROVIDED "AS IS" WITHOUT EXPRESS OR
                        IMPLIED WARRANTY. THE UVA SHALL NOT BE LIABLE FOR ANY DAMAGES SUFFERED BY
                        THE USERS OF THIS DATA AND DOCUMENTATION.</emphasis>
                </para>
                <para>By using or copying this data and documentation, Licensee agrees to abide by
                    the copyright law and all other applicable laws of the U.S. including, but not
                    limited to, export control laws, and the terms of this license. UVA shall have
                    the right to terminate this license immediately by written notice upon
                    Licensee's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. Licensee may be
                    held legally responsible for any copyright infringement that is caused or
                    encouraged by Licensee's failure to abide by the terms of this license. </para>
            </section>
   </intellectualRights>
   <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
         <geographicDescription>ESHORE - Eastern Shore</geographicDescription>
         <boundingCoordinates>
            <westBoundingCoordinate>-75.240000</westBoundingCoordinate>
            <eastBoundingCoordinate>-76.240000</eastBoundingCoordinate>
            <northBoundingCoordinate>38.020000</northBoundingCoordinate>
            <southBoundingCoordinate>37.070000</southBoundingCoordinate>
         </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
         <singleDateTime>
            <calendarDate>1993-07-28</calendarDate>
         </singleDateTime>
      </temporalCoverage>
   </coverage>
   <maintenance>
      <description>
<para>Data are updated as needed</para>
      </description>
      <maintenanceUpdateFrequency>asNeeded</maintenanceUpdateFrequency>
   </maintenance>
   <contact>
      <individualName>
         <givenName>David</givenName>
         <surName>Richardson</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>Department of Environmental Sciences, Clark Hall, University of Virginia</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>22903</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(434) 924-3193</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(434) 982-2137</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>dlr2n@virginia.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu/cgi-bin/w3e/msql/personnel/msql2/person.html?QID=">drichardson</userId>
   </contact>
   <contact>
      <individualName>
         <givenName>John</givenName>
         <surName>Porter</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>UVA, Department of Environmental Sciences, 291 McCormick Road, P.O. Box 400123</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>22903-4123</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">434-924-8999</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">434-982-2137</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>jhp7e@virginia.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu/cgi-bin/w3e/msql/personnel/msql2/person.html?QID=">jporter</userId>
   </contact>
   <contact id="im">
      <positionName>Information manager - Virginia Coast Reserve Long-Term Ecological Research Project</positionName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>Department of Environmental Sciences, University of Virginia, 291 McCormick Road, PO Box 400123</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>22904-4123</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">434-924-8999</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">434-982-2137</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>jporter@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu/jhp7e.html</onlineUrl>
   </contact>
   <publisher>
      <organizationName>Virginia Coast Reserve Long-Term Ecological Research Project</organizationName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>Department of Environmental Sciences, University of Virginia, 291 McCormick Road, PO Box 400123</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>22904-4123</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">434-924-7761</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">434-982-2137</phone>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu</onlineUrl>
   </publisher>
   <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
   <methods>
      <methodStep>
         <description>
  <para>Methods:&#160;</para>
  <para>Georectification and initial classification were performed by Guofan Shao in 1994 using ERDAS 7.5 and ARC/INFO software.&#160; An updated classification, based in part on the earlier one, was performed by David Richardson in 2014 using ERDAS IMAGINE 2013 and ArcGIS 10.1 software.</para>
  <para>The original satellite image was georectified using ERDAS to 30 meter resolution with a positional accuracy of about 20 meters (RMS error 0.69 pixels). &#160;&#160;The georectified image was SUBSET to include only the VA portion of the Delmarva Penninsula , and then ERDAS's ISODATA and MAXCLAS routines were used to perform an unsupervised classification using TM bands 4, 5, and 2 to create 50 spectral cluster classes.&#160; Afterwards, the cluster classes were individually examined, and based on previous maps, aerial photos, and personal knowledge were assigned to one of 5 predetermined classes (Forest/shrub, Bareland/sand, Crop/grassland, Water, or Salt Marsh) using ERDAS's COLORMOD and RECODE routines.&#160; The GIS file was then converted to an ARC/INFO coverage.&#160; Then in ARC/INFO clusters of individual cells less than 1/3 ha (3600 square meters or 4 pixels) in area were ELIMINATED and DISOLVED to get rid of "salt and pepper" noise and to make the number of arcs and polygons not exceed the limits of ARC/INFO for the whole map.</para>
  <para>This initial classification formed the basis for the 1993 Northampton-only "Landuse and Vegetation Map" (part of the 1995 Northampton County Virginia Geographic Information system, VCRLTER dataset VCR14219).&#160; It was also used in a shoreline change analysis (Shao et al. 1995) and featured in a number of printed and online maps from the VCRLTER.</para>
  <para>A second updated classification was later performed to facilitate future landscape-scale change detection analyses and to replicate for archiving the data north of Northampton County, as the original full VCR dataset is no longer available.</para>
  <para>In the updated classification, the original georectified TM image was reclassified using the ISODATA routine into 150 spectral clusters using all seven TM bands. These cluster classes were again individually examined using the previous classification, false-color infrared and true-color aerial photos, and personal knowledge, and then each class was assigned to one of eleven distinguishable classes.&#160; These eleven classes were hierarchically grouped into the original five classes based on vegetative properties and similarities in aerial coverage.&#160; Pixels belonging to 10 of the spectral classes that were ambiguous and crossed class boundaries were subset from the georectified TM image and reclassified using ISODATA into 50 new spectral clusters.&#160; The refined clusters were reassigned to the appropriate one of eleven classes.&#160; Unlike in the original classification, no additional generalization or elimination based on minimum area thresholds was conducted.&#160; Reclassification of the resulting classified images and conversion from raster to vector format was carried out in ArcGIS 10.1.</para>
  <para>LANDUSE/LANDCOVER CLASSES:</para>
  <para> Unclassified (0)</para>
  <para> 0 = Nodata</para>
  <para> Water (1,2)</para>
  <para> 1 = Open water</para>
  <para> 2 = Shallow open water, tidal flats and bars</para>
  <para> Salt Marsh (3)</para>
  <para> 3 = Salt marsh</para>
  <para> Grassland/Cropland (4,5)</para>
  <para> 4 = Brackish (upper/high) marsh, freshwater marsh (including cattails), wet grassland, irrigated cropland</para>
  <para> 5 = Grassland, cropland, lawns, some areas of reed (Phragmites) marsh</para>
  <para> Forest/Shrub (6,7,8,9)</para>
  <para> 6 = Shrubby/scrub marsh, shrub-cedar thicket/forest transition zone (ecotone)</para>
  <para> 7 = Evergreen forest (predominantly pine and/or red cedar)</para>
  <para> 8 = Mixed forest (mostly pine-hardwood), dense Myrica-dominated shrub thickets</para>
  <para> 9 = Deciduous (hardwood)&#160; forest</para>
  <para> Bare Sand and Soil (10,11)</para>
  <para> 10 = Wet sand, exposed shoals and mud flats</para>
  <para> 11 = Bare sand and soil (beaches, shell, tilled cropland, other unvegetated areas)</para>
  <para>Classification Accuracy:</para>
  <para>Artificial man-made surfaces like asphalt and concrete pavement and tarred roofs may be included in classes 3, 10, and 11 depending on how dark or reflective they are as well as whether or not they take up one or more full pixels.</para>
  <para>Spectral mixing of signatures for subpixel-scale objects and patches (&lt;900 square meters) may result in incorrect classification of highly heterogeneous landscapes, including largely residential and commercial areas as well as inter-fingered marsh/shrub/forest ecotones on barrier islands.</para>
  <para>A quantitative accuracy assessment was conducted comparing the final classification to landcover field data collected at permanent monitoring plots on Parramore Island in 1996 (VCRLTER dataset VCR05117).&#160; Field data land cover classes were converted to TM classes as follows:</para>
  <para> PARR water (10) and mudflat (14) = TM Water (1,2)</para>
  <para> PARR low (1) and upper salt marsh (2) = TM Salt Marsh (3)</para>
  <para> PARR salt hay meadow (3) and grassland (11) = TM Grassland/Cropland (4,5)</para>
  <para> PARR shrub/reed marsh (4), evergreen/hardwood/mixed forest (5/6/7), Myrica/Smilax thicket (8/12) = TM Forest/Shrub (6,7,8,9)</para>
  <para> PARR bare sand (11) = TM Bare Sand and Soil (10,11)</para>
  <para>The 1996 landcover plots were located at the center of each monitoring plot and at distances of 7.5, 15, 30, and 60 m. from the center in the four cardinal directions (0, 90, 180, and 270 degrees).&#160; Excluding landcover plots with no data and treating landcover plots as if they were independent samples, there were 1794 landcover plots associated with 106 permanent monitoring plots.&#160; Landcover plot locations were mapped with ArcGIS and overlaid onto the classified TM image.&#160; Pixels and plots were considered coincident and in agreement if a pixel edge with the same classification as the plot was no more than 30 meters distant from the landcover plot.</para>
  <para>A PDF document is included with the dataset showing the base error classification matrix with the overall accuracy and the commission/omission error rates associated with each landcover class and hierarchical grouping.&#160; The PDF also contains the overall Kappa K-hat coefficient of agreement and the conditional K-hat coefficients for each class and grouping (Congalton et al. 1983, Jensen 2005).&#160;</para>
  <para>In summary, on Parramore Island there was relatively strong overall agreement between the TM classification and the field data (68% agreement, K-hat 0.62), which improved if only the hierarchical groupings were considered (79% agreement, K-hat 0.70).&#160; The agreement was quite strong for the water, salt marsh, and forest/thicket classes (conditional K-hats of 0.94, 0.89, and 0.90), moderate for beach and bare sand (0.56), and weak for the brackish marsh/grassland category.&#160; Disagreement within the high marsh zone was primarily driven by the failure of the TM classification to adequately capture numerous small-scale patches or linear shrub features, primarily Iva and/or Myrica hummocks and ecotones.&#160; Some disagreement may also be due to the lumping of Phragmities and Typha marshes with shrubby marsh in the field data but with grasslands in the TM data.&#160; Disagreement within open sand areas was possibly largely due to shore erosion and beach encroachment during the three years between the time of the satellite overflight and the field data collection, though failure to capture narrow strips of open sand in the relic dune areas on the north end of the island also contributed.</para>
  <para>A qualitative assessment of the full region covered found good agreement except for the following case:</para>
  <para>Brackish and freshwater areas within the extensive marshes on the bayside surrounding Messongo Creek and the Pocomoke and Big Annemessex Rivers in the northern region of the study area, especially the freshwater marshes along the Pocomoke River, were particularly difficult to distinguish spectrally from the woody shrub and forest classes.&#160; Similar misclassification patterns were observed in this region near Saxis, VA, in the original classification.&#160; As a result, confidence in the classification accuracy of brackish and freshwater marshes in this region is low.</para>
  <para>The exact cause for the poorer differentiation of open non-woody brackish and freshwater marshes in the northern bayside region is unknown.&#160; One possibility is that these areas had a higher abundance of broadleaf herbaceous freshwater wetland species than in the other geographic regions and that the spectral characteristics of these species shifted the overall spectral signature there to be more similar to broadleaf shrub and tree palustrine woodlands.&#160; Another possible explanation for the spectral differences of these marshes compared to the seaside and southern bayside marshes is that these marshes were captured at an entirely different stage of tidal inundation.&#160; The occurrence of peak high and low tides falls within a two to three hour window for the region stretching from Chincoteague Inlet to Fishermans Island to Cape Charles Harbor, with tidal stage progressing from north to south along the Atlantic coast and then continuing from south to north along the eastern shore of the Chesapeake Bay.&#160; The tides at Wachapreague and Redbank occur within the center of this window.&#160; This means that while most marshes in the image were observed relatively close to low tide, the marshes around Gaskins Point and Occohannock Creek were observed at close to high tide, and the marshes around Saxis were observed about 1.5-2 hours before high tide (possibly when the time since inundation and wetting of the surface would have been greatest for upper areas of the marsh subject to regular inundation).&#160;</para>
         </description>
      </methodStep>
   </methods>
      <spatialRaster id="tm93r30c11tif.tif">
         <alternateIdentifier>VCR14221-2</alternateIdentifier>
         <entityName>tm93r30c11tif</entityName>
         <entityDescription>1993 Classified Landsat 5 Thematic Mapper (TM) satellite image of the VA Eastern shore, in GeoTIFF format.  Zip file also contains a DBF lookup table matching landcover class codes to descriptions, and a PDF document describing a quantitative accuracy assessment conducted for Parramore Island.</entityDescription>
         <physical>
            <objectName>tm93r30c11tif.zip</objectName>
            <dataFormat>
               <externallyDefinedFormat>
                  <formatName>zip file with TIFF or GeoTIFF raster file(s) </formatName>
               </externallyDefinedFormat>
            </dataFormat>
               <distribution>
      <online>
         <url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-vcr.225.2&amp;urlHeadID=2&amp;urlTail=2/VCR14221/tm93r30c11tif.zip</url>
      </online>
      <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst">
         <allow>
            <principal>public</principal>
            <permission>read</permission>
         </allow>
         <allow>
            <principal>uid=VCR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
            <permission>all</permission>
         </allow>
      </access>
   </distribution>

         </physical>
         <coverage>
            <geographicCoverage>
               <geographicDescription>Eastern Shore of Virginia</geographicDescription>
               <boundingCoordinates>
                  <westBoundingCoordinate>-76.069488</westBoundingCoordinate>
                  <eastBoundingCoordinate>-75.159592</eastBoundingCoordinate>
                  <northBoundingCoordinate>38.267504</northBoundingCoordinate>
                  <southBoundingCoordinate>37.072880</southBoundingCoordinate>
               </boundingCoordinates>
            </geographicCoverage>
         </coverage>
         <attributeList>
            <attribute>
               <attributeName>VALUE</attributeName>
               <attributeDefinition>landuse/landcover class</attributeDefinition>
               <storageType typeSystem="http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html">Integer</storageType>
               <measurementScale>
                  <nominal>
                     <nonNumericDomain>
                        <enumeratedDomain>
                           <codeDefinition>
                              <code>0</code>
                              <definition>nodata</definition>
                              <source>VCRLTER</source>
                           </codeDefinition>
                           <codeDefinition>
                              <code>1</code>
                              <definition>Open water</definition>
                              <source>VCRLTER</source>
                           </codeDefinition>
                           <codeDefinition>
                              <code>2</code>
                              <definition>Shallow open water, tidal flats and bars</definition>
                              <source>VCRLTER</source>
                           </codeDefinition>
                           <codeDefinition>
                              <code>3</code>
                              <definition>Salt marsh</definition>
                              <source>VCRLTER</source>
                           </codeDefinition>
                           <codeDefinition>
                              <code>4</code>
                              <definition>Brackish (upper/high) marsh, freshwater marsh (including cattails),
                            wet grassland, irrigated cropland</definition>
                              <source>VCRLTER</source>
                           </codeDefinition>
                           <codeDefinition>
                              <code>5</code>
                              <definition>Grassland, cropland, lawns, some areas of reed (Phragmites)
                            marsh</definition>
                              <source>VCRLTER</source>
                           </codeDefinition>
                           <codeDefinition>
                              <code>6</code>
                              <definition>Shrubby/scrub marsh, shrub-cedar thicket/forest transition zone
                            (ecotone)</definition>
                              <source>VCRLTER</source>
                           </codeDefinition>
                           <codeDefinition>
                              <code>7</code>
                              <definition>Evergreen forest (predominantly pine and/or red cedar)</definition>
                              <source>VCRLTER</source>
                           </codeDefinition>
                           <codeDefinition>
                              <code>8</code>
                              <definition>Mixed forest (mostly pine-hardwood), dense Myrica-dominated shrub
                            thickets</definition>
                              <source>VCRLTER</source>
                           </codeDefinition>
                           <codeDefinition>
                              <code>9</code>
                              <definition>Deciduous (hardwood) forest</definition>
                              <source>VCRLTER</source>
                           </codeDefinition>
                           <codeDefinition>
                              <code>10</code>
                              <definition>Wet sand, exposed shoals and mud flats</definition>
                              <source>VCRLTER</source>
                           </codeDefinition>
                           <codeDefinition>
                              <code>11</code>
                              <definition>Bare sand and soil (beaches, shell, tilled cropland, other
                            unvegetated areas)</definition>
                              <source>VCRLTER</source>
                           </codeDefinition>
                        </enumeratedDomain>
                     </nonNumericDomain>
                  </nominal>
               </measurementScale>
               <missingValueCode>
                  <code>0</code>
                  <codeExplanation>nodata</codeExplanation>
               </missingValueCode>
            </attribute>
         </attributeList>
         <spatialReference>
            <horizCoordSysDef name="NAD_1927_UTM_Zone_18N">
               <projCoordSys>
                  <geogCoordSys name="D_North_American_1927">
                     <datum name="D_North_American_1927" />
                     <spheroid denomFlatRatio="294.9786982" name="Clarke_1866" semiAxisMajor="6378206.4" />
                     <primeMeridian longitude="0.0" name="Greenwich" />
                     <unit name="degree" />
                  </geogCoordSys>
                  <projection name="Transverse_Mercator">
                     <parameter name="False_Easting" value="500000.0" />
                     <parameter name="False_Northing" value="0.0" />
                     <parameter name="Central_Meridian" value="-75.0" />
                     <parameter name="Latitude_Of_Origin" value="0.0" />
                     <parameter name="Scale_Factor" value="0.9996" />
                     <unit name="meter" />
                  </projection>
               </projCoordSys>
            </horizCoordSysDef>
         </spatialReference>
         <georeferenceInfo>
            <cornerPoint>
               <xCoordinate>406434.187500</xCoordinate>
               <yCoordinate>4103272.000000</yCoordinate>
               <pointInPixel>center</pointInPixel>
               <corner>Lower Left</corner>
            </cornerPoint>
            <cornerPoint>
               <xCoordinate>406434.187500</xCoordinate>
               <yCoordinate>4235302.000000</yCoordinate>
               <pointInPixel>center</pointInPixel>
               <corner>Upper Left</corner>
            </cornerPoint>
            <cornerPoint>
               <xCoordinate>485814.187500</xCoordinate>
               <yCoordinate>4235302.000000</yCoordinate>
               <pointInPixel>center</pointInPixel>
               <corner>Upper Right</corner>
            </cornerPoint>
            <cornerPoint>
               <xCoordinate>485814.187500</xCoordinate>
               <yCoordinate>4103272.000000</yCoordinate>
               <pointInPixel>center</pointInPixel>
               <corner>Lower Right</corner>
            </cornerPoint>
         </georeferenceInfo>
         <horizontalAccuracy>
            <accuracyReport>Horizontal Accuracy Report not present</accuracyReport>
         </horizontalAccuracy>
         <verticalAccuracy>
            <accuracyReport>Vertical Accuracy Report not present</accuracyReport>
         </verticalAccuracy>
         <cellSizeXDirection>30.000000</cellSizeXDirection>
         <cellSizeYDirection>30.000000</cellSizeYDirection>
         <numberOfBands>1</numberOfBands>
         <rasterOrigin>Upper Left</rasterOrigin>
         <rows>4401</rows>
         <columns>2646</columns>
         <verticals>1</verticals>
         <cellGeometry>pixel</cellGeometry>
      </spatialRaster>
   <otherEntity>
      <entityName>tm93r30c11other.zip</entityName>
      <entityDescription>
1993 Classified Landsat 5 Thematic Mapper (TM) satellite image of the VA Eastern shore, in both ERDAS Imagine 2013 IMG raster format and ArcGIS 10.1 polygon shapefile vector format.  Zip file also contains a DBF lookup table matching landcover class codes to descriptions, and a PDF document describing a quantitative accuracy assessment conducted for Parramore Island.
      </entityDescription>
      <physical>
         <objectName>tm93r30c11other.zip</objectName>
         <characterEncoding>Binary</characterEncoding>
         <dataFormat>
            <externallyDefinedFormat>
               <formatName>zip</formatName>
            </externallyDefinedFormat>
         </dataFormat>
         <distribution>
            <online>
               <url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-vcr.225.2&amp;urlHeadID=2&amp;urlTail=3/VCR14221/tm93r30c11other.zip</url>
            </online>
            <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst">
               <allow>
                  <principal>public</principal>
                  <permission>read</permission>
               </allow>
               <allow>
                  <principal>uid=VCR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
                  <permission>all</permission>
               </allow>
            </access>
         </distribution>
      </physical>
      <entityType>file      </entityType>
   </otherEntity>

</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
   <metadata>
      <localtags>
         <system>VCRLTER</system>
         <weight>-4</weight>
      </localtags>
   </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>

</eml:eml>