<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-mcm.8002.1" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0  http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
	<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
		<allow>
			<principal>uid=MCM,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
			<permission>all</permission>
		</allow>
		<allow>
			<principal>public</principal>
			<permission>read</permission>
		</allow>
	</access>
	<dataset>
		<shortName>N and P Dynamics in Green Creek</shortName>
		<title>Nitrogen and Phosphorous Dynamics in Green Creek, January 1995. Field and Modeling data</title>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Robert</givenName>
				<surName>Runkel</surName>
			</individualName>
			<address>
				<deliveryPoint>3215 Marine Street, Suite E-127</deliveryPoint>
				<city>Boulder</city>
				<administrativeArea>CO</administrativeArea>
				<postalCode>80303</postalCode>
				<country>USA</country>
			</address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">303-541-3013</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>runkel@usgs.gov</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Diane</givenName>
				<surName>McKnight</surName>
			</individualName>
			<address>
				<deliveryPoint>INSTAAR</deliveryPoint>
				<deliveryPoint>1560 30th Street</deliveryPoint>
				<deliveryPoint>Campus Box 450 </deliveryPoint>
				<city>Boulder</city>
				<administrativeArea>CO</administrativeArea>
				<postalCode> 80309-0450</postalCode>
				<country>USA</country>
			</address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">(303)492-4687</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>mcknight@snobear.colorado.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<metadataProvider>
			<organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
				<deliveryPoint>Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
				<deliveryPoint>University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
				<deliveryPoint>MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
				<city>Albuquerque</city>
				<administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
				<postalCode>87131</postalCode>
				<country>USA</country>
			</address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">505-277-3418</phone>
			<phone phonetype="fax">505-277-0304</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>mcmdata@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</metadataProvider>
		<associatedParty>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Cathy</givenName>
				<surName>Tate</surName>
			</individualName>
			<role>author</role>
		</associatedParty>
		<associatedParty>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>John</givenName>
				<surName>Duff</surName>
			</individualName>
			<role>author</role>
		</associatedParty>
		<associatedParty>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Daryl</givenName>
				<surName>Moorhead</surName>
			</individualName>
			<role>contentProvider</role>
		</associatedParty>
		<abstract>
			<section>
				<para>Abstract copied from McKnight, D.M., Runkel, R.L., Tate, C.M., Duff, J.H., and Moorhead, D.L., 2004, Inorganic N and P dynamics of Antarctic glacial meltwater streams as controlled by hyporheic exchange and benthic autotrophic communities: Journal of the North American Benthological Society, v. 23, no. 2, p. 171-188. The McMurdo Dry Valleys of South Victoria Land, Antarctica, contain numerous glacial meltwater streams that drain into lakes on the valley floors. Many of the streams have abundant perennial mats of filamentous cyanobacteria. The algal mats grow during streamflow in the austral summer and are in a dormant freeze-dried state during the rest of the year. NO3 and soluble reactive P (SRP) concentrations were lower in streams with abundant algal mats than in streams with sparse algal mats. NO3 and SRP concentrations were higher in the hyporheic zone of a stream with abundant algal mats than in the stream itself. An experimental injection of LiCl, NaNO3, and K3PO4 was conducted in Green Creek, which has abundant algal mats. Substantial hyporheic exchange occurred. The NO3 and PO4 concentrations at 50 m below the injection were 55 &#956;M and 18 &#956;M, respectively, during the experiment. NO3 and PO4 concentrations were below the detection limit of 1 to 2 &#956;M at a site 497 m below the injection during the Cl tracer arrival, indicating a high capacity for nutrient uptake by algal communities. NO2 and NH4 were present at sites 226 and 327 m below the injection, indicating that, in addition to denitrification and algal uptake, dissimilatory NO3 reduction to NO2 and NH4 may be a NO3 sink during transport. Transport modelling with nutrient uptake represented as a 1st-order process yielded reach-scale parameters of 4.3 &#215; 10&#8722;5 to 3.9 &#215; 10&#8722;4/s and 1.4 &#215; 10&#8722;4 to 3.8 &#215; 10&#8722;4/s for uptake of NO3 and PO4, respectively. The best match with the observed data was a model in which PO4 uptake occurred only in the main channel and NO3 uptake occurred in the main channel and in the hyporheic zone. Hyporheic NO3 uptake was 7 to 16% of the total uptake for the different stream reaches. These results demonstrate that nutrient flux to the lakes is controlled by hyporheic exchange and nutrient uptake by algal mats in dry valley streams. Streams without algal mats contribute more nutrients to the lakes than streams with algal mats.</para>
			</section>
		</abstract>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword keywordType="theme">inorganic nitrogen</keyword>
			<keyword keywordType="theme">phosphorus cycling </keyword>
			<keyword keywordType="theme">hyporheic exchange</keyword>
			<keyword keywordType="theme">solute transport</keyword>
			<keyword keywordType="theme">bethic algae</keyword>
			<keyword keywordType="theme">synoptic survey</keyword>
			<keyword keywordType="theme">OTIS</keyword>
			<keyword keywordType="theme">tracer injection</keyword>
			<keyword keywordType="theme">Antarctic desert streams</keyword>
			<keyword keywordType="theme">LTER</keyword>
			<keyword keywordType="place">McMurdo Dry Valleys</keyword>
			<keyword keywordType="theme">MCM</keyword>
		</keywordSet>
		<additionalInfo>
			<section>
				<title>Notes about the modeling software </title>
				<para>
					<literalLayout> the flow routing i/o files do not seem to be readily available (the code Rob Runkel used to flow routing is not public, so the input files would be of little use)</literalLayout>
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Citation</title>
				<para> McKnight, D.M., Runkel, R.L., Tate, C.M., Duff, J.H., and Moorhead, D.L., 2004, Inorganic N and P dynamics of Antarctic glacial meltwater streams as controlled by hyporheic exchange and benthic autotrophic communities: Journal of the North American Benthological Society, v. 23, no. 2, p. 171-188.</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Representative Figure</title>
				<para>see "n_and_p_dyn_results.jpeg" in attached or linked through the "otherEntity" section of this metadata</para>
			</section>
		</additionalInfo>
		<intellectualRights>
			<section>
				<title>MCM LTER data may be used freely with the following restrictions:</title>
				<para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								<literalLayout>The Principal Investigator be sent a notice stating reasons for acquiring any
         data and a description of the publication intentions. </literalLayout>
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								<literalLayout>The Principal Investigator of the data set be sent a copy of the report or
         manuscript prior to submission and be adequately cited in any resultant
        publications.</literalLayout>
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								<literalLayout>A copy of any resultant publications should be sent to the McMurdo data
         manager and principal investigator.</literalLayout>
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								<literalLayout>The end-user follow the guidelines set forth in the LTER Network Data Access
         Policy, Data Access Requirements, and General Data Use Agreement found at
         http://www.mcmlter.org/data_guidelines.htm</literalLayout>
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
			</section>
		</intellectualRights>
		<coverage>
			<geographicCoverage>
				<geographicDescription>A glacial meltwater stream, 0.65 mi long, flowing NE from the extremity of Canada Glacier into the SW end of Lake Fryxell, close E of Bowles Creek, in Taylor Valley, Victoria Land. The name was suggested by hydrologist Diane McKnight, who named this creek after William J. Green of Miami University, Oxford, Ohio, who conducted research on the geochemistry of the Onyx River, 1980-81, and Lake Fryxell, Lake Hoare, and their feeder streams, 1982-83.</geographicDescription>
				<boundingCoordinates>
					<westBoundingCoordinate>163.0648</westBoundingCoordinate>
					<eastBoundingCoordinate>163.064</eastBoundingCoordinate>
					<northBoundingCoordinate>-77.6220</northBoundingCoordinate>
					<southBoundingCoordinate>-77.6226</southBoundingCoordinate>
					<boundingAltitudes>
						<altitudeMinimum>10</altitudeMinimum>
						<altitudeMaximum>1000</altitudeMaximum>
						<altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
					</boundingAltitudes>
				</boundingCoordinates>
			</geographicCoverage>
			<temporalCoverage>
				<rangeOfDates>
					<beginDate>
						<calendarDate>1995</calendarDate>
					</beginDate>
					<endDate>
						<calendarDate>1995</calendarDate>
					</endDate>
				</rangeOfDates>
			</temporalCoverage>
		</coverage>
		<purpose>
			<para> Quantify uptake of inorganic N and P in Green Creek, subject to unsteady flow caused by glacial meltwater.</para>
		</purpose>
		<maintenance>
			<description>
				<section>
					<para>
						<literalLayout>Jan, 2014 - Mike Goooseff and Rob Runkel provided Inigo San Gil metadata and CSV files to produce this metadata accompanying Oracle data tables from metadata info.</literalLayout>
					</para>
				</section>
			</description>
		</maintenance>
		<contact>
			<organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
				<deliveryPoint>Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
				<deliveryPoint>University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
				<deliveryPoint>MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
				<city>Albuquerque</city>
				<administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
				<postalCode>87131</postalCode>
				<country>USA</country>
			</address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">505-277-3418</phone>
			<phone phonetype="fax">505-277-0304</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>mcmdata@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<publisher>
			<organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
				<deliveryPoint>Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
				<deliveryPoint>University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
				<deliveryPoint>MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
				<city>Albuquerque</city>
				<administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
				<postalCode>87131</postalCode>
				<country>USA</country>
			</address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">505-277-3418</phone>
			<phone phonetype="fax">505-277-0304</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>mcmdata@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</publisher>
		<methods>
			<methodStep>
				<description>
					<section>
						<title>Field data collection</title>
						<para>A continuous tracer injection containing K3PO4, NaNO3 and LiCl was initiated on January 13, 1995.  Water samples were collected at 4 locations downstream (50, 226, 327, and 497 m downstream of the injection)..</para>
					</section>
					<section>
						<title>Field sample analysis</title>
						<para>Nutrient samples were analyzed using a Lachat Quickchem autoanalyzer with a detection limit of 0.04 uM. Samples were analyzed for lithium and chloride using a atomic absorption spectrometer and a ion chromatograph, respectively.</para>
					</section>
					<section>
						<title>Model approach</title>
						<para>Physical transport parameters were developed by fitting an advection-dispersion-storage model to observed chloride breakthrough curves.  First-order uptake rate coefficients were subsequently developed by fitting an advection-dispersion-storage-uptake model to the N and P data.</para>
					</section>
					<section>
						<title> Modeling code used</title>
						<para>Study consisted of both flow and transport modeling.  A kinematic wave model based on DR3M was used to develop a time-series of flow and cross-sectional area.  These time series were used as input to the OTIS solute transport model. The routing model is not publically available (although DR3M is at http://water.usgs.gov/software/DR3M/ ); OTIS is available at: http://water.usgs.gov/software/OTIS/</para>
					</section>
					<section>
						<title>OTIS Model input files:</title>
						<para>These input files are hard to describe using structured metadata constructs from EML or ISO. We provided copies in a zip file in the  other entities section of this metadata.  </para>
					</section>
					<section>
						<title>Flow routing input files are not available.</title>
						<para>Flow routing input files are not available.</para>
					</section>
				</description>
				<software>
					<title>dr3m - Distributed Routing Rainfall-Runoff Model--version II</title>
					<creator>
						<individualName>
							<givenName>W.M.</givenName>
							<surName>Alley</surName>
						</individualName>
					</creator>
					<creator>
						<individualName>
							<givenName>P.E.</givenName>
							<surName>Smith</surName>
						</individualName>
					</creator>
					<creator>
						<individualName>
							<givenName>D.R.</givenName>
							<surName>Dawdy</surName>
						</individualName>
					</creator>
					<pubDate>1982</pubDate>
					<abstract>
						<para>DR3M is a watershed model for routing storm runoff through a Branched system of pipes and (or) natural channels using rainfall as input.  DR3M provides detailed simulation of storm-runoff period selected by the user.  There is daily soil-moisture accounting between storms.  A drainage basin is represented as a set of overland-flow, channel, and reservoir segments, which jointly describe the drainage features of the basin.  This model is usually used to simulate small urban basins.  Interflow and base flow are not simulated.  Snow accumulation and snowmelt are not simulated.</para>
					</abstract>
					<additionalInfo>
						<section>
							<title>How to install DR3M</title>
							<para>http://water.usgs.gov/software/DR3M/code/UNIX/README</para>
						</section>
						<section>
							<title>citation</title>
							<para>Alley, W.M., and Smith, P.E., 1982, Distributed routing rainfall-runoff model--version II: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 82-344, 201 p.</para>
						</section>
						<section>
							<title>Method</title>
							<para>
								<literalLayout> The rainfall-excess components include soil-moisture accounting, pervious-area rainfall excess, impervious-area rainfall excess, and parameter optimization.  The Green-Ampt equation is used in the calculations of infiltration and pervious area rainfall excess.  A Rosenbrock optimization procedure may be used to aid in calibrating several of the infiltration and soil-moisture accounting parameters. Kinematic wave theory is used for both overland-flow and channel routing.  There are three solution techniques available:  method of characteristics, implicit finite difference method, and explicit finite difference method.  Two soil types may be defined.  Overland flow may be defined as turbulent or laminar.  Detention reservoirs may be simulated as linear storage or using a modified-Puls method. Channel segments may be defined as gutter, pipe, triangular cross section, or by explicitly specifying the kinematic channel parameters alpha and m.</literalLayout>
							</para>
						</section>
						<section>
							<title>History</title>
							<para>
								<itemizedlist>
									<listitem>
										<para> DR3M-version II, added option to output simulated time-series data to Watershed Data Management (WDM) file.  Output file
    modified to reduce width from 132 characters to 80 characters or less.</para>
									</listitem>
									<listitem>
										<para>DR3M-version II, WDM file replaces "card" input of time-series data.</para>
									</listitem>
									<listitem>
										<para>1982 - DR3M-version II, added two solution techniques for kinematic  wave routing.  Improved general output.</para>
									</listitem>
									<listitem>
										<para>1978 - Original DR3M version, incorporated the routing component from a version of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology catchment model into the lumped parameter rainfall-runoff model.</para></listitem>
									<listitem>
										<para>1972 - A lumped parameter rainfall-runoff model for small rural watersheds</para>
									</listitem>
								</itemizedlist>
							</para>
						</section>
						<section>
							<title>DATA REQUIREMENTS</title>
							<para>
								<literalLayout>Daily precipitation, daily evapotranspiration, and short-interval precipitation are required.  Short-interval discharge is required for the optimization option and to calibrate the model.  These time series are read from a WDM file.  Roughness and hydraulics parameters and sub-catchment areas are required to define the basin. Six parameters are required to calculate infiltration and soil-moisture accounting.  Up to three rainfall stations may be used.Two soil types may be defined.  A total of 99 flow planes, channels, pipes, reservoirs, and junctions may be used to define the basin.</literalLayout></para>
						</section>
						<section>
							<title>OUTPUT OPTIONS</title>
							<para>
								<literalLayout> The computed outflow from any flow plane, pipe, or channel segment for each storm period may be written to the output file or to the WDM file.  A summary of the measured and simulated rainfall, runoff, and peak flows is written to the output file.  A flat file  containing the storm rainfall, measured flow (if available), and simulated flow at user selected sites can be generated.  A flat file for each storm containing the total rainfall, the measured peak flow (if available), and the simulated peak flow for user-selected sites can be generated.</literalLayout></para>
						</section>
						<section>
							<title>SYSTEM REQUIREMENTS</title>
							<para>
								<literalLayout> DR3M is written in Fortran 77 with the following extension: use of include files. The UTIL, ADWDM, and WDM libraries from LIB are used. A subset of these libraries is provided with the code and may be used instead of the libraries, this subset uses INTEGER*4 and mixed type equivalence. For more information, see System Requirements in LIB.</literalLayout>
							</para>
						</section>
					</additionalInfo>
					<implementation>
						<distribution>
							<online>
								<url function="download">http://water.usgs.gov/software/DR3M/code/UNIX/dr3m2.1.source.tar.gz</url>
							</online>
						</distribution>
						<programmingLanguage>Fortran 77</programmingLanguage>
					</implementation>
					<version>II</version>
				</software>
				<software>
					<title>One-Dimensional Transport with Inflow and Storage </title>
					<creator>
						<individualName>
							<givenName>Robert</givenName>
							<surName>Runkel</surName>
						</individualName>
					</creator>
					<pubDate>1998</pubDate>
					<abstract>
						<para>OTIS is a mathematical simulation model used to characterize the fate and transport of water-borne solutes in streams and rivers. The governing equation underlying the model is the advection-dispersion equation with additional terms to account for transient storage, lateral inflow, first-order decay, and sorption. This equation and the associated equations describing transient storage and sorption are solved using a Crank-Nicolson finite-difference solution.

OTIS may be used in conjunction with data from field-scale tracer experiments to quantify the hydrologic parameters affecting solute transport. This application typically involves a trial-and-error approach wherein parameter estimates are adjusted to obtain an acceptable match between simulated and observed tracer concentrations. Additional applications include analyses of nonconservative solutes that are subject to sorption processes or first-order decay. OTIS-P, a modified version of OTIS, couples the solution of the governing equation with a nonlinear regression package. OTIS-P determines an optimal set of parameter estimates that minimize the squared differences between the simulated and observed concentrations, thereby automating the parameter estimation process.</para>
					</abstract>
					<additionalInfo>
						<section>
							<title>Documentation</title>
							<para>http://water.usgs.gov/software/OTIS/doc/</para>
						</section>
						<section>
							<title>citation</title>
							<para>Runkel, R.L., 1998, One-Dimensional Transport with Inflow and Storage (OTIS): A Solute Transport Model for Streams and Rivers: U.S. Geological Survey Water-Resources Investigations Report 98-4018, 73 p.</para>
						</section>
					</additionalInfo>
					<distribution>
						<online>
							<url function="information">http://water.usgs.gov/software/OTIS/</url>
						</online>
					</distribution>
					<implementation>
						<distribution>
							<online>
								<url function="download">http://water.usgs.gov/software/OTIS/download/otis.LIN.tar.Z</url>
							</online>
						</distribution>
						<programmingLanguage>Fortran</programmingLanguage>
					</implementation>
					<version>MOD40</version>
				</software>
			</methodStep>
		</methods>
		<dataTable>
			<entityName>GreenCreek_chl_no3_po4_field_data</entityName>
			<physical>
				<objectName>GreenCreek_chl_no3_po4_field_data</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
						<numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
						<recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
							<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://www.mcmlter.org/data/modeling/green_chl_no3_po4.csv</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<attributeList>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>DISTANCE</attributeName>
					<attributeDefinition>Distance from injection point, in meters</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType typeSystem="Text" />
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>integer</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>TIME (H)</attributeName>
					<attributeDefinition>The time the water sample was collected from the field, decimal hours</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType typeSystem="Date" />
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>hour</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>CHL (microM)</attributeName>
					<attributeDefinition>The concentration of Chloride in water as measured, in microMolar units.</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType typeSystem="Text" />
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microM</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>PO4 (microM)</attributeName>
					<attributeDefinition>The concentration of phosphates in water as measured, in microMolar units.</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType typeSystem="Text" />
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microM</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>NO3 (microM)</attributeName>
					<attributeDefinition>The concentration of nitrates in water as measured, in microMolar units.</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType typeSystem="Text" />
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microM</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
			</attributeList>
		</dataTable>
		<dataTable>
			<entityName>GreenCreek_Simulated_chl_no3_po4</entityName>
			<physical>
				<objectName>GreenCreek_Simulated_chl_no3_po4</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
						<numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
						<recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
							<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://www.mcmlter.org/data/modeling/green_simulated_chl_no3_po4.csv</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<attributeList>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>DISTANCE</attributeName>
					<attributeDefinition>Distance from injection point, in meters per simulation using OTIS</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType typeSystem="Text" />
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>integer</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>TIME (H)</attributeName>
					<attributeDefinition>The time the water point, decimal hours</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType typeSystem="Text" />
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>hour</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
								<attribute>
					<attributeName>CHL (microM)</attributeName>
					<attributeDefinition>The concentration of Chloride in water as simulated, in microMolar units.</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType typeSystem="Text" />
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microM</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>PO4 Conservative (microM)</attributeName>
					<attributeDefinition>The conservative concentration of phosphates in water as simulated, when solutes are not taken up. Measured in microMolar units.</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType typeSystem="Text" />
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microM</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>PO4 Decay (microM)</attributeName>
					<attributeDefinition>The concentration of phosphates in water as measured, when solute decays, taken up. Measure in microMolar units.</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType typeSystem="Text" />
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microM</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>NO3 Conservative (microM)</attributeName>
					<attributeDefinition>The concentration of nitrates in water as measured, when solutes are not taken up. Measured in microMolar units.</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType typeSystem="Text" />
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microM</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>NO3 Decay (microM)</attributeName>
					<attributeDefinition>The concentration of nitrates in water as measured, when solute decays, taken up. Measured in microMolar units.</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType typeSystem="Text" />
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microM</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
			</attributeList>
		</dataTable>
		<otherEntity>
			<entityName>otis_input</entityName>
			<entityDescription>The input files used up for the OTIS simulation.  Since they have a very partciular structure which cannot be described in this metadata specification, we post them with fewer metadata.  Please be advised to learn OTIS, using the extensive documentation at the USGS sites.</entityDescription>
			<physical>
				<objectName>greencreek_otis_simulation_input_files.zip</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://www.mcmlter.org/data/modeling/greencreek_otis_simulation_input_files.zip</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<entityType>zip archive of flat text files</entityType>
		</otherEntity>
		<otherEntity>
			<entityName>Representative Figure "green_creek_PandN_transport.jpeg"</entityName>
			<entityDescription>A graph of the injection of tracer and nutrients and response downstream, both with field data points and simulation results</entityDescription>
			<physical>
				<objectName>green_creek_PandN_transport.jpeg</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<attributeOrientation>row</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>not applies</fieldDelimiter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url>http://mcmlter.org/images/green_creek_PandN_transport.jpeg</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<entityType>Picture</entityType>
		</otherEntity>
	</dataset>
	<additionalMetadata>
<metadata>
<unitList>
   <unit abbreviation="&#181;M" id="microM" name="micromolar" />
  </unitList>
</metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>