<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-vcr.223.2" system="VCR" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
   <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst">
      <allow>
         <principal>public</principal>
         <permission>read</permission>
      </allow>
      <allow>
         <principal>uid=VCR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
         <permission>all</permission>
      </allow>
   </access>

<dataset id="223" system="VCR">
   <alternateIdentifier>VCR14219</alternateIdentifier>
   <title>VCRLTER-Northampton County GIS data archive, 1995.</title>
   <creator>
      <individualName>
         <givenName>John</givenName>
         <surName>Porter</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>UVA, Department of Environmental Sciences, 291 McCormick Road, P.O. Box 400123</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>22903-4123</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">434-924-8999</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">434-982-2137</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>jhp7e@virginia.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu/cgi-bin/w3e/msql/personnel/msql2/person.html?QID=">jporter</userId>
   </creator>
   <creator>
      <individualName>
         <givenName>Anne</givenName>
         <surName>Halpin</surName>
      </individualName>
   </creator>
   <creator>
      <individualName>
         <givenName>David</givenName>
         <surName>Richardson</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>Department of Environmental Sciences, Clark Hall, University of Virginia</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>22903</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(434) 924-3193</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(434) 982-2137</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>dlr2n@virginia.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu/cgi-bin/w3e/msql/personnel/msql2/person.html?QID=">drichardson</userId>
   </creator>
   <creator>
      <individualName>
         <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
         <givenName>Guofan</givenName>
         <surName>Shao</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>Purdue University, Department of Forestry and Natural Resources</deliveryPoint>
         <city>West Lafayette</city>
         <administrativeArea>IN</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>47907</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">317-494-3630</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>gshao@fnr.purdue.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu/cgi-bin/w3e/msql/personnel/msql2/person.html?QID=">gshao</userId>
   </creator>
   <metadataProvider>
      <organizationName>Virginia Coast Reserve Long-Term Ecological Research Project</organizationName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>Department of Environmental Sciences, University of Virginia, 291 McCormick Road, PO Box 400123</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>22904-4123</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">434-924-7761</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">434-982-2137</phone>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu</onlineUrl>
   </metadataProvider>
   <pubDate>1995-03-22</pubDate>
   <abstract>
  <para>This data archive is a collection of GIS files and FGDC metadata prepared in 1995 for the Northampton County Planning Office by the Virginia Coast Reserve LTER project at the University of Virginia with support from the Virginia Department of Environmental Quality (DEQ) and the National Science Foundation (NSF).&#160;</para>
  <para>Original data sources include: &#160;1:100,000-scale USGS digital line graph (DLG) hydrography and transportation data; &#160;1:6,000-scale boundary, road, and railroad data for the town of Cape Charles from VDOT;&#160; 1:190,000-scale county-wide general soil map data and 1:15,540-scale detailed soil data for the Cape Charles area digitized from printed USDA soil survey maps;&#160;&#160; a land use and vegetation cover dataset (30 m. resolution) created by the VCRLTER derived from a 1993 Landsat Thematic Mapper satellite image;&#160;&#160; 1:20,000-scale plant association maps for 10 seaside barrier and marsh islands between Hog and Smith Islands, inclusive, prepared by Cheryl McCaffrey for TNC in 1975 and published in the Virginia Journal of Science in 1990; and 1993 colonial bird nesting site data collected by The Center for Conservation Biology (with partners The Nature Conservancy, College of William and Mary, University of Virginia, USFWS, VA-DCR, and VA-DGIF).</para>
  <para>Contents:</para>
  <para>HYDROGRAPHY</para>
  <para>Based on USGS 1:100,000 Digital Line Graph (DLG) data.&#160; Files: h100k_arc_u84 (streams, shorelines, etc.) and h100k_poly_u84 (marshes, mudflats, etc.).</para>
  <para>Note that the hydrographic data has been superseded by the more recent and more detailed USGS National Hydrography Dataset, available for the entire state of Virginia at "ftp://nhdftp.usgs.gov/DataSets/Staged/States/FileGDB/HighResolution/NHDH_VA_931v210.zip" (see http://nhd.usgs.gov/data.html for more information).&#160; A static 2013 version of the NHD data that includes shapefiles extracted from the original ESRI geodatabase format data and covering just the watersheds of the Eastern Shore of VA can also be found in the VCRLTER Data Catalog (dataset VCR14223).</para>
  <para>TRANSPORTATION</para>
  <para>Based on USGS 1:100,000 Digital Line Graph (DLG) data for the full county, and 1:6,000 VDOT data for the Cape Charles township.</para>
  <para>Files: &#160;1:100k Transportation (lines) from USGS DLG data: rtf100k_arc_u84 (roads), rrf100k_arc_u84 (railroads), and mtf100k_arc_u84 (airports and utility transmission lines).</para>
  <para>Files: 1:6000 street, boundary, and rail line data for the town of Cape Charles, 1984, prepared by Virginia Department of Highways and Transportation Information Services (Division 1221 East Broad Street, Richmond, Virginia 23219). Streets correct through December 31,1983. Georeferencing corrected in 2014 for shapefiles only, using same methodology described for&#160; VCR14218 dataset.&#160; File : town_u84_adj (town_arc_u84old is the older unadjusted data).</para>
  <para>Note that the transportation data has been superseded by more recent and more detailed data contained in dataset VCR14222 of the VCRLTER Data Catalog.&#160; The VCR14222 data contains 2013 U.S. Census Bureau TIGER/Line road and airfield data supplemented by railroad and transmission lines digitized from high resolution VGIN-VBMP 2013 aerial imagery and additionally has boat launch locations not available here.</para>
  <para>SOILS</para>
  <para>General soil map for Northampton county (1:190k), and detailed soil map for Cape Charles and Cheriton areas (1:15,540) from published the USDA Soil Conservation Service's&#160; 1989 "Soil Survey of Northampton County, Virginia" digitized at UVA by Ray Dukes Smith: soilorig_poly_u84 (uses original shorelines from source maps), soil_poly_u84 (substitutes shorelines from 1993 landcover classification data), and cc_soil_poly_u84 (Cape Charles &amp; Cheriton detailed data, map sheets 13 and 14).&#160;</para>
  <para>Note that the soil data has been superseded by more recent and more detailed SSURGO soil data from the USDA's Natural Resources Conservation Service (NRCS), which has seamless soil data from the 1:15,540 map series in tabular and GIS formats for the full county, as well as for all counties in VA and other states. &#160;A static 2013 version of the SSURGO data that contains merged data for Accomack and Northampton Counties can be found in the VCRLTER Data Catalog (dataset VCR14220).</para>
  <para>LANDUSE/LANDCOVER</para>
  <para>VCR Landuse and Vegetation Cover, 1993, created by Guofan Shao (VCRLTER) based on 30m resolution Landsat Thematic Mapper (TM) satellite imagery taken on July 28, 1993. Cropped to include just Northampton County.&#160; &#160;Landcover is divided into 5 classifications: (1) Forest or shrub, (2) Bare Land or Sand, (3) Planted Cropland, Grassland, or Upland Marsh, (4) Open Water, and (5) Low Salt Marsh. File = nhtm93s3_poly_u84.&#160; No spatial adjustments necessary.</para>
  <para>An outline of the county showing the shorelines based on the above 1993 TM classification is included as the shapefile:outline_poly_u84; however, no spatial adjustment has been applied.</para>
  <para>Note that a similar landuse/landcover classification based on the same 1993 Landsat TM image and spanning both Accomack and Northampton Counties, VA (plus portions of MD south of Snow Hill and Princess Ann), is also available in the VCRLTER Data Catalog (dataset VCR14221).</para>
  <para>PLANT ASSOCIATIONS</para>
  <para>Barrier Island Vegetation Maps (1:20,000) for islands of the Virginia Coast Reserve (TNC) that are within Northampton County, including Wreck Island (VA DCR) but excluding Fishermans Island (US FWS).&#160; By C.A. McCaffrey, based on air photos from 1974 and subsequent ground-truthing.&#160; Individual shapefiles for each major island: hog_u84_adj, cobb_u84_adj, wreck_u84_adj, shipshoal_u84_adj, myrtle_u84_adj, and smith_u84_adj.&#160; Note that in 2014 the georeferencing was fixed, as described in VCRLTER dataset VCR14218, but was only applied to the converted shapefiles, not the original e00 files.</para>
  <para>Note that the full original dataset, including vegetation maps for Parramore, Cedar, and Metompkin Islands in Accomack County, is available in the VCRLTER Data Catalog (dataset VCR14218).</para>
  <para>BIRD NESTING SITES</para>
  <para>Nesting sites for colonial waterbirds in Northampton County, VA, 1993.&#160; File: Birds_pt_u84.&#160; Spatial location generally marks a point in the center or at the edge of the colony.&#160; No spatial adjustments deemed necessary due to the error associated with the location measurement.&#160; Attribute information includes location; species; common name; number of adults, chicks, eggs and nests; land owner; and management area. Plovers and other endangered/threatened species included in the original database are not available in this version, nor are data for nesting sites in other counties or during other years.</para>
  <para>For more information concerning the original Virginia colonial waterbird survey data (1975-present), please see "http://www.ccbbirds.org/what-we-do/research/species-of-concern/species-of-concern-projects/va-colonial-waterbird-survey/" or contact The Center for Conservation Biology (http://www.ccbbirds.org).&#160; To view more recent bird colony locations, visit their online mapping application at "http://www.ccbbirds.org/maps/".</para>
   </abstract>
   <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">geographic information systems</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">hydrography</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">transportation</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">soil</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">plant communities</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">birds</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">land cover</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">geographic information systems</keyword>
   </keywordSet>
   <intellectualRights>
            <section>
                <title>Data License</title>
                <para>Data and documentation is copyrighted by The Virginia Coast Reserve LTER
                    project of the University of Virginia (UVA), and ownership remains with the UVA.</para>
                <para>The UVA grants you (hereafter, Licensee) a license to use the data and
                    documentation for academic, and research purposes only, without a fee.</para>
                <para>Licensee may make derivative works. However, if Licensee distributes any
                    derivative work based on or derived from the data and documentation, then
                    Licensee will</para>
                <para>
                    <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>notify the VCR/LTER designated contact (typically the investigator
                                who collected the data) regarding its distribution of the derivative
                                work, and</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>clearly notify users that such derivative work is a modified
                                version and not the original data and documentation distributed by
                                the UVA.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>acknowledge the support of NSF Grants BSR-8702333-06, DEB-9211772,
                                DEB-9411974, DEB-0080381, DEB-0621014 and DEB-1237733 in any publications using the data and documentation.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>send to the address, above, two reprints of any publications
                                resulting from use of the data and documentation. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </para>
                <para>Any Licensee wishing to make commercial use of the data and documentation
                    should contact the UVA, c/o VCR/LTER, to negotiate an appropriate license for
                    such commercial use. Commercial use includes</para>
                <para>
                    <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>integration of all or part of the data and documentation into a
                                product for sale or license by or on behalf of Licensee to third
                                parties, or</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> distribution of the data or documentation to third parties that
                                need it to utilize a commercial product sold or licensed by or on
                                behalf of Licensee.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </para>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>UVA MAKES NO REPRESENTATIONS ABOUT THE SUITABILITY OF THIS DATA AND
                        DOCUMENTATION FOR ANY PURPOSE. IT IS PROVIDED "AS IS" WITHOUT EXPRESS OR
                        IMPLIED WARRANTY. THE UVA SHALL NOT BE LIABLE FOR ANY DAMAGES SUFFERED BY
                        THE USERS OF THIS DATA AND DOCUMENTATION.</emphasis>
                </para>
                <para>By using or copying this data and documentation, Licensee agrees to abide by
                    the copyright law and all other applicable laws of the U.S. including, but not
                    limited to, export control laws, and the terms of this license. UVA shall have
                    the right to terminate this license immediately by written notice upon
                    Licensee's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. Licensee may be
                    held legally responsible for any copyright infringement that is caused or
                    encouraged by Licensee's failure to abide by the terms of this license. </para>
            </section>
      <section>
<title>Additional Conditions:</title>
  <para> Permission for use of this data is provided by the Northampton County Planning Office in cooperation with the VCR-LTER program at the University of Virginia. Any use of this data should respectfully cite the Virginia Department of Environmental Quality, grant DEQ-???????, with computational support from NSF support grants BSR-8702333-06 and DEB-9211772. </para>
      </section>
   </intellectualRights>
   <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
         <geographicDescription>NHAMPCOUNT - Southern county of Eastern Shore,VA</geographicDescription>
         <boundingCoordinates>
            <westBoundingCoordinate>-75.791667</westBoundingCoordinate>
            <eastBoundingCoordinate>-76.083333</eastBoundingCoordinate>
            <northBoundingCoordinate>37.500000</northBoundingCoordinate>
            <southBoundingCoordinate>37.088889</southBoundingCoordinate>
         </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
         <singleDateTime>
            <calendarDate>1995-03-22</calendarDate>
         </singleDateTime>
      </temporalCoverage>
   </coverage>
   <maintenance>
      <description>
<para>Data are updated as needed</para>
      </description>
      <maintenanceUpdateFrequency>asNeeded</maintenanceUpdateFrequency>
   </maintenance>
   <contact>
      <individualName>
         <givenName>John</givenName>
         <surName>Porter</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>UVA, Department of Environmental Sciences, 291 McCormick Road, P.O. Box 400123</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>22903-4123</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">434-924-8999</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">434-982-2137</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>jhp7e@virginia.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu/cgi-bin/w3e/msql/personnel/msql2/person.html?QID=">jporter</userId>
   </contact>
   <contact id="im">
      <positionName>Information manager - Virginia Coast Reserve Long-Term Ecological Research Project</positionName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>Department of Environmental Sciences, University of Virginia, 291 McCormick Road, PO Box 400123</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>22904-4123</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">434-924-8999</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">434-982-2137</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>jporter@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu/jhp7e.html</onlineUrl>
   </contact>
   <publisher>
      <organizationName>Virginia Coast Reserve Long-Term Ecological Research Project</organizationName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>Department of Environmental Sciences, University of Virginia, 291 McCormick Road, PO Box 400123</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>22904-4123</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">434-924-7761</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">434-982-2137</phone>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu</onlineUrl>
   </publisher>
   <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
   <methods>
      <methodStep>
         <description>
  <para>Original e00 file data in NAD83 VA state plane south (feet) projection.&#160; Converted shapefiles have been converted to WGS84 UTM 18N (meters) projection.&#160; Shapefiles with georeferencing corrections have names ending in "_adj".</para>
  <para>Georeferencing errors exist in many of these coverages due to a NAD27-direct-to-NAD83 transformation bug in an earlier version of the Arc/Info&#160; 7.x program used during the time the data was compiled.&#160; These errors have only been fixed in the shapefile formatted data, and only for data originating from VCRLTER sources (excludes USGS DLG data and USDA SSURGO soil data, but includes VDOT Cape Charles street data).</para>
  <para>Additional source-less ECOMAP data:</para>
  <para>These files were received by UVA on tape from a project called EcoMap, about which no information is currently available.&#160; There were no text files received with them giving the data source, quality or attribute information.&#160; They were originally included in the archive in case metadata was later made available.&#160; However, because there continues to be not enough information here to make these coverages useful , they have not been converted to shapefiles, though they are still available as ArcInfo E00 files.</para>
         </description>
      </methodStep>
   </methods>
   <otherEntity>
      <entityName>VCR14219</entityName>
      <entityDescription>
Data is stored within a zip file as a collection of ArcInfo E00 export files in the "e00_sp" directory (original data) as well as a collection of converted shapefiles in the "shapefiles" directory.  Additional metadata for each coverage is stored in the "docs" directory.


      </entityDescription>
      <physical>
         <objectName>NorthamptonGIS1995.zip</objectName>
         <characterEncoding>Binary</characterEncoding>
         <dataFormat>
            <externallyDefinedFormat>
               <formatName>Esoteric</formatName>
            </externallyDefinedFormat>
         </dataFormat>
         <distribution>
            <online>
               <url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-vcr.223.2&amp;urlHeadID=2&amp;urlTail=1/VCR14219/VCR14219/NorthamptonGIS1995.zip</url>
            </online>
            <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst">
               <allow>
                  <principal>public</principal>
                  <permission>read</permission>
               </allow>
               <allow>
                  <principal>uid=VCR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
                  <permission>all</permission>
               </allow>
            </access>
         </distribution>
      </physical>
      <entityType>file      </entityType>
   </otherEntity>

</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
   <metadata>
      <localtags>
         <system>VCRLTER</system>
         <weight>-2</weight>
      </localtags>
   </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>

</eml:eml>