<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-hbr.116.6" scope="system" system="knb-lter-hbr" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 http://www.hubbardbrook.org/eml/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><title>Soil:atmosphere fluxes of carbon dioxide, nitrous oxide and methane</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Peter M.</givenName><surName>Groffman</surName></individualName><organizationName>Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Box AB</deliveryPoint><city>Millbrook</city><administrativeArea>NY</administrativeArea><postalCode>12545</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>GroffmanP@caryinstitute.org</electronicMailAddress></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><organizationName>Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>U.S. Forest Service</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>271 Mast Rd.</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">603-868-7643</phone><phone phonetype="fax">603-868-7604</phone><onlineUrl>http://www.hubbardbrook.org</onlineUrl></metadataProvider><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Adam</givenName><surName>Welman</surName></individualName><role>associated researcher</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Jason</givenName><surName>Demers</surName></individualName><role>associated researcher</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Lisa</givenName><surName>Martel</surName></individualName><role>associated researcher</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Abraham</givenName><surName>Parker</surName></individualName><role>associated researcher</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Evan</givenName><surName>Grant</surName></individualName><role>associated researcher</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Jackie</givenName><surName>Wilson</surName></individualName><role>associated researcher</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Lynn</givenName><surName>Christenson</surName></individualName><role>associated researcher</role></associatedParty><keywordSet><keyword>soil</keyword><keyword>methane</keyword><keyword>nitrous oxide</keyword><keyword>carbon dioxide</keyword><keyword>CO2</keyword><keyword>CH4</keyword><keyword>N20</keyword><keyword>trace gas</keyword><keyword>Hubbard Brook</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><para><literalLayout>Data from the 1997 &#8211; 2000 freeze plot studies (sugar maple and yellow birch) are published in Groffman et al. (2006a).  Data from the Bear Brook and watershed 1 sites from 2002 and 2003 are published in Groffman et al. (2006b). Other data will be published in manuscripts that are currently in preparation by the investigators.  People are free to use these data for informational purposes but they cannot be used in any publication without permission of the author.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>LTER Network Data Access Requirements</title><para><literalLayout>The access to all LTER data is subject to requirements set forth by this policy document to enable data providers to track usage, evaluate its impact in the community, and confirm users' acceptance of the terms of acceptable use. These requirements are standardized across the LTER Network to provide contractual exchange of data between Site Data Providers, Network Data Providers, and Data Users that can be encoded into electronic form and exchanged between computers. This will allow direct access to data via a common portal once these requirements have been fulfilled. The following information may be required directly or by proxy prior to the transference of any data object:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Registration</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Name</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Affiliation</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Email address</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Full Contact Info</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptance of the General Public Use Agreement or Restricted Data Use Agreement, as applicable</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>A Statement of Intended Use that is compliant with the above agreements. Such statements may be made submitted explicitly or made implicitly via the data access portal interface.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section><section><title>Conditions of Data Use</title><para><literalLayout>The re-use of scientific data has the potential to greatly increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines, and thus is fostered, supported and encouraged. Permission to use this dataset is granted to the Data User free of charge subject to the following terms:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptable Use. Use of the dataset will be restricted to academic, research, educational, government, recreational, or other not-for-profit professional purposes. The Data User is permitted to produce and distribute derived works from this dataset provided that they are released under the same license terms as those accompanying this Data Set. Any other uses for the Data Set or its derived products will require explicit permission from the dataset owner.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Redistribution. The data are provided for use by the Data User. The metadata and this license must accompany all copies made and be available to all users of this Data Set. The Data User will not redistribute the original Data Set beyond this collaboration sphere.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Citation. It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Data Set in any publications or in the metadata of any derived data products that were produced using the Data Set. Citation should take the following general form: Creator, Year of Data Publication, Title of Dataset, Publisher, Dataset identifier.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acknowledgement. The Data User should acknowledge any institutional support or specific funding awards referenced in the metadata accompanying this dataset in any publications where the Data Set contributed significantly to its content. Acknowledgements should identify the supporting party, the party that received the support, and any identifying information such as grant numbers.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Notification. The Data User will notify the Data Set Contact when any derivative work or publication based on or derived from the Data Set is distributed. The Data User will provide the data contact with two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the Data Set and will provide copies, or on-line access to, any derived digital products. Notification will include an explanation of how the Data Set was used to produce the derived work.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Collaboration. The Data Set has been released in the spirit of open scientific collaboration. Data Users are thus strongly encouraged to consider consultation, collaboration and/or co-authorship with the Data Set Creator.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist><literalLayout>By accepting this Data Set, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. The Data Owner shall have the right to terminate this agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement.</literalLayout><literalLayout>By viewing or downloading the data, I certify that I accept the conditions herein</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Disclaimer</title><para><literalLayout>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation contained in this Data Set, complete accuracy of data and metadata cannot be guaranteed. All data and metadata are made available "as is". The Data User holds all parties involved in the production or distribution of the Data Set harmless for damages resulting from its use or interpretation.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Definitions</title><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set</emphasis><literalLayout>Digital data and its metadata derived from any research activity such as field observations, collections, laboratory analysis, experiments, or the post-processing of existing data and identified by a unique identifier issued by a recognized cataloging authority such as a site, university, agency, or other organization.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data User</emphasis><literalLayout>ndividual to whom access has been granted to this Data Set, including his or her immediate collaboration sphere, defined here as the institutions, partners, students and staff with whom the Data User collaborates, and with whom access must be granted, in order to fulfill the Data User's intended use of the Data Set</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Creator</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution that produced the Data Set</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Owner</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution that holds intellectual property rights to the dataset. Note that this may or may not be defined as a legal copyright. If no other party is designated in the metadata as Data Set Owner, it may be presumed that these rights are held by the Data Set Creator.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Distributor</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution providing access to the Data Sets.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Contact</emphasis><literalLayout>party designated in the accompanying metadata of the Data Set as the primary contact for the Data Set.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://www.hubbardbrook.org/data/data_policy.php?firstname=metacat&amp;lastname=user&amp;affiliation=Other&amp;view=1&amp;accept=1&amp;comments=none&amp;phone=6035551212&amp;email=none@loopback.com&amp;target=trace_gas.txt</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Bear Brook Watershed (west of Watershed 6)</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.743462</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.735649</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>43.957001</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>43.949928</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Watershed 1</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.731339</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.726311</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>43.959286</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>43.952053</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>SM1</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.741392</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.741392</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>43.950408</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>43.950408</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>SM2</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.747275</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.747275</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>43.939433</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>43.939433</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>YB1</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.735058</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.735058</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>43.936356</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>43.936356</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>YB2</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.746986</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.746986</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>43.928469</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>43.928469</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>UV</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.717232</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.717232</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>43.949860</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>43.949860</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>LV</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.717155</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.717155</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>43.948059</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>43.948059</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>EK</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.778091</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.778091</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>43.918686</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>43.918686</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>WK</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.778091</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.778091</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>43.918686</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>43.918686</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><alternativeTimeScale><timeScaleName>Month Year</timeScaleName><timeScaleAgeEstimate>October 1997</timeScaleAgeEstimate></alternativeTimeScale></beginDate><endDate><alternativeTimeScale><timeScaleName>Ongoing</timeScaleName><timeScaleAgeEstimate>Ongoing</timeScaleAgeEstimate></alternativeTimeScale></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Peter M.</givenName><surName>Groffman</surName></individualName><organizationName>Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Box AB</deliveryPoint><city>Millbrook</city><administrativeArea>NY</administrativeArea><postalCode>12545</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(845)-677-7600 x128</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(845)-677-5976</phone><electronicMailAddress>GroffmanP@caryinstitute.org</electronicMailAddress></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>U.S Forest Service</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>U.S. Forest Service</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>271 Mast Rd.</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">603-868-7643</phone><phone phonetype="fax">603-868-7604</phone><onlineUrl>http://www.hubbardbrook.org</onlineUrl></publisher><pubPlace>Hubbard Brook LTER</pubPlace><methods><methodStep><description><section><title>LOCATION DESCRIPTION</title><para><literalLayout>Soil atmosphere fluxes of the trace gases; carbon dioxide (CO2), nitrous oxide (N2O) and methane (CH4) have been measured at several locations at the Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest. (HBEF):</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>1.  &#8220;Freeze&#8221; study reference plots. In 1997, as part of a study of the relationships between snow depth, soil freezing and nutrient cycling (http://www.ecostudies.org/people_sci_groffman_snow_summary.html), we established eight 10 x 10-m plots located within four stands; two dominated (80%) by sugar maple and two dominated by yellow birch, with one snow reduction (freeze) and one reference plot in each stand.  Trace gas fluxes were measured at approximately monthly intervals on these plots from October 1997 through September 2000.  In 2001, we established eight new 10-m x 10-m plots (4 treatment, 4 reference) in four new sites; two high elevation, north facing and two low elevation, south facing maple-beech-birch stands.  Trace gas fluxes were measured at approximately monthly intervals on these plots from May 2001 through November 2004.  To establish plots for the &#8220;freeze&#8221; study, we cleared minor amounts of understory vegetation from all (both freeze and reference) plots (to facilitate shoveling).  We then installed soil solution samplers (zero tension lysimeters), thermistors for soil temperature monitoring, water content (time domain) reflectometers (for measuring soil moisture), soil atmosphere sampling probes, minirhizotron access tubes, and trace gas flux measurement chambers (described below).  All plots were equipped with dataloggers to allow for continuous monitoring of soil moisture and temperature.  Treatments (keep plots snow free by shoveling through the end of January) were applied in the winters of 1997/98, 1998/99, 2002/2003 and 2003/2004.  Only data from the reference (non-treated) reference plots are posted.</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>2.	Bear Brook Watershed.  Trace gas sampling is coordinated with long-term monitoring of microbial biomass and activity:  (http://www.hubbardbrook.org/new_site/data/dataset.php?id=67) that is keyed to the &#8220;west of watershed 6 litter trap transects&#8221; described by Hughes and Fahey (1994).  These are four 100 m transects, 50 m apart with five traps per transect located at low, mid, upper and high elevations - 20 traps per elevation. Trace gas sampling locations are located within 15 m of five traps at each elevation.  Litter quality, quantity and composition have been monitored on these transects since 1984 and microbial biomass and activity have been monitored since 1994.  Trace gas sampling on this watershed began in August 2002 and is ongoing.</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>3.	Watershed 1.  Trace gas sampling locations were co-located with long-term microbial biomass and activity monitoring sites, that are located near a subset of the lysimeter sites established for the calcium addition study on this watershed.  Our sites include the "spruce/fir" Lysimeter Site 2 at the top of Watershed 1, the "high" Lysimeter Site 3, the "mid" Lysimeter Site 4, and the "low" Lysimeter Site 6.  These site types and elevations correspond to those in the Bear Brook Watershed.   At each lysimeter site we chose replicate plots that were all within ~30 m of the center lysimeter stake. Trace gas sampling on this watershed began in October 2002 and is ongoing.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>DATA DESCRIPTION</title><para><literalLayout>When plots were snow free, we used the gas flux chamber design described by Bowden, et al. (1990, 1991).  This design calls for 287-mm diameter (ID) by 40 mm high polyvinyl chloride (PVC) cylinder chambers with gas sampling ports in the center of the chamber top.  The chambers are placed on top of PVC base rings of the same diameter that are permanently installed 5 cm into the soil, immediately prior to measurement.  For snow-covered plots, aluminum chambers (approximately 5 L) fitted with septa were inserted 5 cm into the snowpack just prior to measurement.  In all seasons, 9-mL gas samples were collected using fine-needle polypropylene syringes 0, 10, 20 and 30 min following placement of the chamber on the base.  Samples were transferred to evacuated glass vials which were stored at room temperature prior to analysis by gas chromatography (GC) using electron capture detection for N2O, thermal conductivity detection for CO2 and flame ionization detection for CH4 .  Fluxes are calculated from the linear rate of change in gas concentration, the chamber internal volume and soil surface area.  There are 3 to 5 chambers in each plot.</literalLayout></para></section></description><citation scope="document"><title>Effects of nitrogen additions on annual nitrous oxide fluxes from temperate forest soils in the northeastern United States</title><creator id="bowden" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>R.</givenName><surName>Bowden</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="melillo" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>J.</givenName><surName>Melillo</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="steudler" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>P.</givenName><surName>Steudler</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="aber" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>J.</givenName><surName>Aber</surName></individualName></creator><pubDate>1991</pubDate><language>english</language><article><journal>Journal of Geophysical Research &#8211; Atmospheres</journal><volume>96(D5)</volume><pageRange>9321-9328</pageRange></article></citation><citation scope="document"><title>Annual nitrous oxide fluxes from temperate forest soils in the northeastern United States</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>R.</givenName><surName>Bowden</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="steudler1" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>P.</givenName><surName>Steudler</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="melillo1" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>J.</givenName><surName>Melillo</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="aber1" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>J.</givenName><surName>Aber</surName></individualName></creator><pubDate>1990</pubDate><article><journal>Journal of Geophysical Research &#8211; Atmospheres</journal><volume>96(D5)</volume><pageRange>13,997-14,005</pageRange></article></citation><citation scope="document"><title>Snow depth, soil freezing and trace gas fluxes in a northern hardwood forest</title><creator id="groffman" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>P.</givenName><surName>Groffman</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="hardy" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>J.</givenName><surName>Hardy</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="driscoll" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>C.</givenName><surName>Driscoll</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="fahey" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>T.</givenName><surName>Fahey</surName></individualName></creator><pubDate>2006</pubDate><article><journal>Global Change Biology</journal><volume>12</volume><pageRange>1748-1760</pageRange></article></citation><citation scope="document"><title>Calcium additions reduce nitrogen cycling in a northern hardwood forest</title><creator id="groffman1" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>P.</givenName><surName>Groffman</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="fisk" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>M.</givenName><surName>Fisk</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="driscoll1" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>C.</givenName><surName>Driscoll</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="likens" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>G.</givenName><surName>Likens</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="fahey1" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>T.</givenName><surName>Fahey</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="eagar" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>C.</givenName><surName>Eagar</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="pardo" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>L.</givenName><surName>Pardo</surName></individualName></creator><pubDate>2006</pubDate><article><journal>Ecosystems</journal><volume>9</volume><pageRange>1289-1305</pageRange></article></citation><citation scope="document"><title>Litterfall dynamics and ecosystem recovery during forest development</title><creator id="hughes" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>J.W.</givenName><surName>Hughes</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="fahey2" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>T.</givenName><surName>Fahey</surName></individualName></creator><pubDate>1994</pubDate><article><journal>Forest Ecology and Management</journal><volume>63</volume><pageRange>181-198</pageRange></article></citation></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=HBR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>trace_gas</entityName><entityDescription>Soil:atmosphere fluxes of carbon dioxide, nitrous oxide and methane</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>trace_gas.txt</objectName><characterEncoding>ASCII</characterEncoding><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n\r</recordDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>0x20</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://www.hubbardbrook.org/research/data/soil/soth/micbio.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><additionalInfo><section><title>DATA DESCRIPTION</title><para><literalLayout>The data is physically located at the Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies in Millbrook, NY</literalLayout></para></section></additionalInfo><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>DATE</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Sample date</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>YYYY-MMDD</formatString><dateTimePrecision>1 day</dateTimePrecision><dateTimeDomain><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">1997-10-10</minimum></bounds></dateTimeDomain></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>SITE</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Location of plots</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>WS1</code><definition>Watershed 1</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>W6</code><definition>Bear Brook "West of Watershed 6"</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>SM1</code><definition>&#8220;Freeze&#8221; study reference plot sugar maple 1</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>SM2</code><definition>&#8220;Freeze&#8221; study reference plot sugar maple 2</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>YB1</code><definition>&#8220;Freeze&#8221; study reference plot yellow birch 1</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>YB2</code><definition>&#8220;Freeze&#8221; study reference plot yellow birch 2</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>UV</code><definition>&#8220;Freeze&#8221; study reference plot &#8220;upper valley&#8221;</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>LV</code><definition>&#8220;Freeze&#8221; study reference plot &#8220;lower valley&#8221;</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>EK</code><definition>&#8220;Freeze&#8221; study reference plot &#8220;east Kineo&#8221;</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>WK</code><definition>&#8220;Freeze&#8221; study reference plot &#8220;west Kineo&#8221;</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>ELEV</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Elevation within watershed</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>SF or S/F</code><definition>Spruce/Fir, ~790m,  SF (WS6); Lysimeter Site #2 (WS1)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>H</code><definition>High, ~750m, litter traps 101-120 (WS6); Lysimeter #3 (WS1)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>U</code><definition>Upper, ~675m, litter traps 121-140 (WS6)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>M</code><definition>Mid, ~600m, litter traps 141-160 (WS6); Lysimeter #4 (WS1)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>L</code><definition>Low, ~525m, litter traps 161-180 (WS6); Lysimeter #6 (WS1)</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>.</code><codeExplanation>Data missing or not taken at this time</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>CHAMBER</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Individual flux chamber</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Chamber number</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>CO2</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Carbon dioxide flux</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsPerMeterSquarePerHour</customUnit></unit><precision>.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>.</code><codeExplanation>Data missing or not taken at this time</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>N2O</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Nitrous oxide flux</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>nanogramsPerCentimeterSquarePerHour</customUnit></unit><precision>.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>.</code><codeExplanation>Data missing or not taken at this time</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>CH4</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Methane flux</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>milligramsPerMeterSquarePerDay</customUnit></unit><precision>.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>.</code><codeExplanation>Data missing or not taken at this time</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><unitList><unit abbreviation="g m-2 h-1" id="gramsPerMeterSquarePerHour" name="gramsPerMeterSquarePerHour" unitType="amountOfSubstanceWeightFlux"><description>grams per square meter per hour (area flux)</description></unit><unit abbreviation="ng cm-2 h-1" id="nanogramsPerCentimeterSquarePerHour" name="nanogramsPerCentimeterSquarePerHour" unitType="amountOfSubstanceWeightFlux"><description>nanograms per square centimeter per hour (areal flux)</description></unit><unit abbreviation="mg m-2 d-1" id="milligramsPerMeterSquarePerDay" name="milligramsPerMeterSquarePerDay" unitType="amountOfSubstanceWeightFlux"><description>milligrams per square meter per day (areal flux)</description></unit></unitList></additionalMetadata></eml:eml>