<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-hbr.119.2" scope="system" system="knb-lter-hbr" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 http://www.hubbardbrook.org/eml/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><title>Sulfate isotopes in precipitation and streamwater</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Christine</givenName><surName>Alewell</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of Basel</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Environmental Geosciences</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Department of Geosciences</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Bernoullistrasse 30</deliveryPoint><city>Basel</city><postalCode>CH-4056</postalCode><country>Switzerland</country></address><electronicMailAddress>christine.alewell@unibas.ch</electronicMailAddress></creator><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Myron</givenName><surName>Mitchell</surName></individualName><organizationName>SUNY-ESF</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>1 Forestry Drive</deliveryPoint><city>Syracuse</city><administrativeArea>NY</administrativeArea><postalCode>13210</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>mitchell@syr.edu</electronicMailAddress></creator><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Gene</givenName><surName>Likens</surName></individualName><organizationName>Institute of Ecosystems Studies</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>65 Sharon Turnpike</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>P.O. Box AB</deliveryPoint><city>Millbrook</city><administrativeArea>NY</administrativeArea><postalCode>12545</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>LikensG@ecostudies.org</electronicMailAddress></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><organizationName>Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>U.S. Forest Service</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>271 Mast Rd.</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">603-868-7643</phone><phone phonetype="fax">603-868-7604</phone><onlineUrl>http://www.hubbardbrook.org</onlineUrl></metadataProvider><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Roy</givenName><surName>Krouse</surName></individualName><role>associated researcher</role></associatedParty><keywordSet><keyword>sulfur</keyword><keyword>sulfate</keyword><keyword>stream</keyword><keyword>precipitation</keyword><keyword>isotope</keyword><keyword>chemistry</keyword><keyword>Hubbard Brook</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><title>LTER Network Data Access Requirements</title><para><literalLayout>The access to all LTER data is subject to requirements set forth by this
            policy document to enable data providers to track usage, evaluate its impact in the
            community, and confirm users' acceptance of the terms of acceptable use. These
            requirements are standardized across the LTER Network to provide contractual exchange of
            data between Site Data Providers, Network Data Providers, and Data Users that can be
            encoded into electronic form and exchanged between computers. This will allow direct
            access to data via a common portal once these requirements have been fulfilled. The
            following information may be required directly or by proxy prior to the transference of
            any data object:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Registration</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Name</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Affiliation</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Email address</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Full Contact Info</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptance of the General Public Use Agreement or Restricted Data Use
                  Agreement, as applicable</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>A Statement of Intended Use that is compliant with the above
                  agreements. Such statements may be made submitted explicitly or made implicitly
                  via the data access portal interface.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section><section><title>Conditions of Data Use</title><para><literalLayout>The re-use of scientific data has the potential to greatly increase
            communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines, and thus is
            fostered, supported and encouraged. Permission to use this dataset is granted to the
            Data User free of charge subject to the following terms:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptable Use. Use of the dataset will be restricted to academic,
                  research, educational, government, recreational, or other not-for-profit
                  professional purposes. The Data User is permitted to produce and distribute
                  derived works from this dataset provided that they are released under the same
                  license terms as those accompanying this Data Set. Any other uses for the Data Set
                  or its derived products will require explicit permission from the dataset owner.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Redistribution. The data are provided for use by the Data User. The
                  metadata and this license must accompany all copies made and be available to all
                  users of this Data Set. The Data User will not redistribute the original Data Set
                  beyond this collaboration sphere.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Citation. It is considered a matter of professional ethics to
                  acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite
                  the Data Set in any publications or in the metadata of any derived data products
                  that were produced using the Data Set. Citation should take the following general
                  form: Creator, Year of Data Publication, Title of Dataset, Publisher, Dataset
                  identifier.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acknowledgement. The Data User should acknowledge any institutional
                  support or specific funding awards referenced in the metadata accompanying this
                  dataset in any publications where the Data Set contributed significantly to its
                  content. Acknowledgements should identify the supporting party, the party that
                  received the support, and any identifying information such as grant
                numbers.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Notification. The Data User will notify the Data Set Contact when any
                  derivative work or publication based on or derived from the Data Set is
                  distributed. The Data User will provide the data contact with two reprints of any
                  publications resulting from use of the Data Set and will provide copies, or
                  on-line access to, any derived digital products. Notification will include an
                  explanation of how the Data Set was used to produce the derived
                work.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Collaboration. The Data Set has been released in the spirit of open
                  scientific collaboration. Data Users are thus strongly encouraged to consider
                  consultation, collaboration and/or co-authorship with the Data Set
                Creator.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist><literalLayout>By accepting this Data Set, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of
            this agreement. The Data Owner shall have the right to terminate this agreement
            immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with,
            any of its terms. The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or
            encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement.</literalLayout><literalLayout>By viewing or downloading the data, I certify that I accept the conditions
            herein</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Disclaimer</title><para><literalLayout>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and
            documentation contained in this Data Set, complete accuracy of data and metadata cannot
            be guaranteed. All data and metadata are made available "as is". The Data User holds all
            parties involved in the production or distribution of the Data Set harmless for damages
            resulting from its use or interpretation.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Definitions</title><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set</emphasis><literalLayout>Digital data and its metadata derived from any research activity such
                  as field observations, collections, laboratory analysis, experiments, or the
                  post-processing of existing data and identified by a unique identifier issued by a
                  recognized cataloging authority such as a site, university, agency, or other
                  organization.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data User</emphasis><literalLayout>ndividual to whom access has been granted to this Data Set, including
                  his or her immediate collaboration sphere, defined here as the institutions,
                  partners, students and staff with whom the Data User collaborates, and with whom
                  access must be granted, in order to fulfill the Data User's intended use of the
                  Data Set</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Creator</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution that produced the Data Set</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Owner</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution that holds intellectual property rights to
                  the dataset. Note that this may or may not be defined as a legal copyright. If no
                  other party is designated in the metadata as Data Set Owner, it may be presumed
                  that these rights are held by the Data Set Creator.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Distributor</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution providing access to the Data
                Sets.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Contact</emphasis><literalLayout>party designated in the accompanying metadata of the Data Set as the
                  primary contact for the Data Set.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://www.hubbardbrook.org/data/dataset.php?id=119</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Precip Watershed 6 (Raingage 11)</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.735443</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.735443</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>43.950092</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>43.950092</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Precip RG (Raingage 22 at Robert S. Pierce Ecosystem Laboratory)</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.701859</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.701859</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>43.943943</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>43.943943</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Stream Watershed 6 (at the weir)</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.735641</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.735641</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>43.949940</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>43.949940</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Stream Watershed 5 (at the weir)</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.731918</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.731918</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>43.948845</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>43.948845</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1966-01-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>1994-12-31</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Myron</givenName><surName>Mitchell</surName></individualName><organizationName>SUNY-ESF</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>1 Forestry Drive</deliveryPoint><city>Syracuse</city><administrativeArea>NY</administrativeArea><postalCode>13210</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>mitchell@syr.edu</electronicMailAddress></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>U.S Forest Service</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>U.S. Forest Service</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>271 Mast Rd.</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">603-868-7643</phone><phone phonetype="fax">603-868-7604</phone><onlineUrl>http://www.hubbardbrook.org</onlineUrl></publisher><pubPlace>Hubbard Brook LTER</pubPlace><methods><methodStep><description><section><title>ABSTRACT</title><para><literalLayout>Sulfur deposition in the northeastern U.S. has been decreasing since
                the 1970s and there has been a concomitant decrease in the SO4 lost from drainage
                waters from forest catchments of this region. It has been established previously
                that the SO4 lost from drainage waters exceeds SO4 inputs in bulk precipitation, but
                the cause for this imbalance has not been resolved. The use of stable S isotopes and
                the availability of archived bulk precipitation and stream water samples at the
                Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest (HBEF) in New Hampshire provided a unique
                opportunity to evaluate potential sources and sinks of S by analyzing the long-term
                patterns (1966&#8211;1994) of the d34S values of SO4 . In bulk precipitation adjacent to
                the Ecosystem Laboratory and near Watershed 6 the d34S values were greater (mean:
                4.5 and 4.2l, respectively) and showed more variation (variance: 0.49 and 0.30) than
                stream samples from Watersheds 5 (W5) and 6 (W6) (mean: 3.2 and 3.7; variance: 0.09
                and 0.08, respectively). These results are consistent with other studies in forest
                catchments that have combined results for mass balances with stable S isotopes.
                These results indicate that for those sites, including the HBEF, where atmospheric
                inputs are 10 kg S ha-1 yr-1, most of the deposited SO4 cycles through the biomass
                before it is released to stream water. Results from W5, which had a whole-tree
                harvest in 1983&#8211;1984 showed that adsorption/desorption processes play an important
                role in regulating net SO4 retention for this watershed-ecosystem. Although the
                isotopic results suggest the importance of S mineralization, conclusive evidence
                that there is net mineralization has not yet been shown. However, S mass balances
                and the isotopic result are consistent with the mineralization of organic S being a
                major contributor to the SO4 in stream waters at the HBEF.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>METHODS</title><para><literalLayout>At both W5 and W6, stream samples are collected weekly just above the
                weirs which are used for measuring stream flow. Archived solutions, which had been
                stored in clean polyethylene bottles, collected from 1966 through 1994 were sampled.
                The policy of the Hubbard Brook Ecosystem Study is to allow each approved request to
                sample no more than 10% of the volume of the archived samples. To yield sufficient
                sulfate for the stable isotope analysis, weekly samples of the solutions were
                subsampled and combined to form composited half-year samples divided into &#8220;summer&#8221;
                (June 1 through November 30) and &#8220;winter&#8221; (December 1 through May 31) samples that
                encompass the water year that begins on June 1 and ends on May 31 of the next
                calendar year. These composited water samples then were analyzed for sulfate with
                ion Chromatography at SUNY-ESF. Sulfate in the solutions was precipitated as BaSO4
                by adding BaCl2 and the S isotopic composition of the BaSO4 measured on-line with an
                elemental analyzer coupled to an isotope ratio mass spectrometer.</literalLayout></para></section></description><citation scope="document"><title>ources of stream sulfate at the Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest: long-term
            analysis using stable isotopes</title><creator id="alewell" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>C.</givenName><surName>Alewell</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="mitchell" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>M.</givenName><surName>Mitchell</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="likens" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>G.</givenName><surName>Likens</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="krouse" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>R.</givenName><surName>Krouse</surName></individualName></creator><pubDate>1999</pubDate><language>english</language><article><journal>Biogeochemistry</journal><volume>44</volume><pageRange>281-299</pageRange></article></citation></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=HBR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>sulfur_isotopes</entityName><entityDescription>Sulfate isotopes in precipitation and streamwater</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>sulfur_isotopes</objectName><characterEncoding>ASCII</characterEncoding><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n\r</recordDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>0x20</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://www.hubbardbrook.org/data/dataset.php?id=119</url></online></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>YEAR</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Year sample was collected</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>YYYY</formatString></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>SAMPLE_TYPE</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Sample type</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>precip</code><definition>Precipitation sample</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>stream</code><definition>Stream sample</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>LOCATION</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Location where sample was collected</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>W6</code><definition>Watershed 6</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>W5</code><definition>Watershed 5</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>RG</code><definition>Rain gage 22</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>SEASON</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Season sample was collected</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>Winter</code><definition>December 1 through May 31</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>Summer</code><definition>June 1 through November 30</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>d34S</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Delta 34S (per mil)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>perMil</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-9999.99</code><codeExplanation>Not measured</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>SO4</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Sulfate concentration</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>microMolesPerLiter</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-9999.9</code><codeExplanation>Not measured</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><unitList><unit abbreviation="ppt" id="perMil" name="perMil" unitType="perMil"><description>perMil (ppt)</description></unit><unit abbreviation="umol/L" id="microMolesPerLiter" name="microMolesPerLiter" unitType="concentration"><description>microMolesPerLiter (umol/L)</description></unit></unitList></additionalMetadata></eml:eml>