<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-luq.124.3" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 C:/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><shortName>LUQMetadata124</shortName><title>Factors influencing decomposition of leaves for five plant species at El Verde</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Mirna</givenName><surName>Santana</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName><positionName>Graduate Student</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Biological Sciences</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>PO Box 413</deliveryPoint><city>Milwaukee</city><administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea><postalCode>53201</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(806)742-2590</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(806)742-2963</phone><electronicMailAddress>msantana@uwm.edu</electronicMailAddress></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Mirna</givenName><surName>Santana</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName><positionName>Graduate Student</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Biological Sciences</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>PO Box 413</deliveryPoint><city>Milwaukee</city><administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea><postalCode>53201</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(806)742-2590</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(806)742-2963</phone><electronicMailAddress>msantana@uwm.edu</electronicMailAddress></metadataProvider><language>english</language><abstract><para><literalLayout>We evaluated the influences of leaf quality, climate and microsite on the decomposition of leaves of five tropical tree species. Single-species litterbags were used to determine weight loss during the first three months of decomposition in the Luquillo Experimental Forest, Puerto Rico. Significant differences were found in decomposition rates among leaf species (Inga fagifolia &lt; I. vera &lt; Manilkara bidentata &lt; C-roton poecilanthus &lt;&lt; Sapium laurocerasus), but only S. laurocerasus differed significantly from the other species. Lignin had a suggestive negative correlation with leaf decomposition while carbon content and the lignin:N ratio were significantly correlated with mass loss. Content of N, P, Ca, and polyphenol were not significantly correlated with mass loss, but several of the litter quality variables were correlated with each other. Leaf species decomposed faster under canopies of their source trees than in a common plot where the source species were absent. Decomposition in two species in the Euphorbiaceae, S. laurocerasus and C. poecilanthus, was significantly affected by microsite. Leaching losses during the first three weeks were greater under source trees than in the common plot, and may have been associated with differences in canopy structure and throughfall. Differences in detrital communities, however, could have contributed to the differences in decomposition between microsites. Leaves of all species decomposed significantly faster in the wet than in the dry period (P = 0.001) despite little climatic variation in this subtropical wet forest type. This suggests that decomposition of tropical leaf litter might be sensitive to microclimatic changes on the forest floor resulting from either global climate change, or from natural or anthropogenic disturbances that open the canopy.</literalLayout></para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>THESIS</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><title>ADEQUATE ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><para><literalLayout>The scientists, the LEF-LTER Program, and the USDA International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITF) must receive adequate acknowledgement for the use of data by other scientists, and the LEF LTER program must receive two copies of any publication using that data. One copy will be placed at the IITF library and one copy will stay with the LEF LTER Data Manager. A suggested format for this acknowledgement will be distributed along with the requested data.</literalLayout></para><section><title>Acknowledgements for NSF Support.</title><para><literalLayout>The following paragraph should be included in the acknowledgements of all publications funded in any way by current and future LTER grants:</literalLayout><literalLayout>This research was performed under grant #DEB-0218039 from the National Science Foundation to the Institute of Tropical Ecosystem Studies (IEET), University of Puerto Rico, and the International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITFR) as part of the Long-Term Ecological Research Program in the Luquillo Experimental Forest. Additional support was provided by the Forest Service (U.S. Department of Agriculture) and the University of Puerto Rico.</literalLayout></para></section></section></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb124/metadata/lterdb124.htm#DATA</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage id="geoReference" scope="document"><geographicDescription>The Luquillo Experimental Forest (LEF) covers 11,231 hectares and reaches 1079 m above sea level. It has a warm and wet climate and includes a variety of tropical habitats and forest types and streams, and a high diversity of plants and animals. A key feature of these ecosystems is disturbance. Hurricanes, landslides, and human disturbance have shaped the forest, and research by LUQ has stimulated a new appreciation of the significance of large-scale disturbances in tropical forested ecosystems and the key role of plants and animals in shaping the response to these events. Hurricanes occurring one and 10 years after LUQ began in 1988 provided landscape-scale natural experiments which are still followed closely.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-65.92</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-65.7</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>18.35</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>18.23</southBoundingCoordinate><boundingAltitudes><altitudeMinimum>20</altitudeMinimum><altitudeMaximum>1060</altitudeMaximum><altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits></boundingAltitudes></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Jean</givenName><surName>Lodge</surName></individualName><organizationName>USDA Forest Service</organizationName><positionName>Principal Investigator</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Forest Products Lab</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>PO Box 1377</deliveryPoint><city>Luquillo</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00773-1377</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(787)889-7445</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(787)889-7477</phone><electronicMailAddress>djlodge@caribe.net</electronicMailAddress></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>Luquillo Experimental Forest LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>University of Puerto Rico, Rio Piedras</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>P. O. Box 21910</deliveryPoint><city>San Juan</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00931-1910</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(787) 764 - 0000 (ext. 4940)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(787) 772 -1481</phone><electronicMailAddress>nbrokaw@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://luq.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></publisher><methods><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Plant species &#8211; We used five common plants from the mature tabonuco forest as well as the mid-successional forest. Species selection was based primarily on nitrogen and phosphorus content, leaf structure, presence or absence of latex, and plant phylogenetic relationships. The five leaf species used in these experiments were:&#160;Inga vera and I. fagifolia&#160;in the Leguminosae; Croton poecilanthus and Sapium laurocerasus in the Euphobiaceae; and Manilkara bidentata in the Sapotaceae. 

The plant species were paired based on their physical and chemical characteristics (Tables 1, 2) to facilitate comparisons. Species in the first pair, I. vera and I. fagifolia, share the same family and genus and have high N and lignin concentrations, but they differ slightly in their levels of polyphenols. Species in the second pair, M. bidentata and C. poecilanthus, share similar nutrient concentrations, leaf structure and latex, but they belong to different families. Species in the third pair, C. poecilanthus and S. laurocerasus, share the same family and have latex, but they differ in nutrient and lignin concentrations as well as leaf structure. Sapium laurocerasus leaves are thin and smooth while C. poecilanthus leaves are thicker and have a heavier cuticle with peltate hairs.

Thickness of the leaves, epidermal cells, epidermal cell walls, and waxy cuticles were measured on hand-cut cross-sections using an ocular micrometer at 200-600x (five leaves per species). Ten fresh leaves per species were weighed and their areas were estimated using a grid. Water uptake (g water/cm2) was then determined by submerging the same leaves in deionized water for two hours and re-weighing (Taylor &amp; Parkinson, 1988b). 

Leaf litter collection &#8211; Only recently fallen senescent leaves of the selected species were collected. These leaves represent the normal substrates for primary fungal decomposers. Most leaves were collected the same day they abscised, but some senescent leaves where collected directly from their trees. Leaf collection took place during April and in early May for the first experiment, and at the end of July for the second set of experiments. Leaves of each species were collected from at least five trees. For field experiments, leaves were dried at 50&#186;C for 72 h. The 50&#176;C temperature was used to avoid major changes in plant chemistry and to control for differences in initial water content between leaf species (W. Silver, personal communication). Additional leaves were collected for chemical analyses and were dried according to each laboratory's protocols as described below.

Effects of leaf structure and quality on decomposition. &#8211; Litter bags (20 x 20 cm) made with 2 mm mesh plastic screening were used for these experiments. Litter bags containing three grams of oven-dried (50&#176;C) leaves of a single species were placed in a common plot. The first experimental sets were decomposed from May through July 2000.&#160;A total of 45 bags were used, nine bags per plant species.&#160;Bags were placed in the field under a tree of their own species for the first week to allow colonization by their normal decomposers, and subsequently moved to the common plot located in mature tabonuco forest. Three replicates per plant species were collected after three, six and twelve weeks of decomposition. After each collection, bags with the decomposed leaves were oven dried at 65&#176;C for 72 h and weighed to calculate rates of decomposition (difference between the initial and the final dry weight). We used correlation analyses to determine the relationship between leaf quality and decomposition and correlations among leaf quality factors. 

Another set of bags, five replicates for each species, was set in the common plot from the end of August to November 2000. This set was collected after 12 wks&#160;and was used to compare the effects of dry versus wet periods on decomposition. This set was also used to compare decomposition of leaves in the common plot with leaves simultaneouslyplaced under their source trees to determine the effect of microsite on decomposition.Effect of site on decomposition &#8211;We used two types of sites: the common plot in tabonuco forest as described above was used as a &#8216;foreign site&#8217;, and the forest floor under trees of the same species as those in the litterbags as a &#8216;source site&#8217;. The experiment was conducted only during the wet period. In the &#8216;source site&#8217; set, each plant species was represented by five trees located at least 100 apart. Under each of these five trees per species, we placed three litterbags of the same species; one bag was collected on each sample date. A total of 25 trees and 75 leaf litterbags were used in the source tree decomposition experiment. A total of 25 bags were placed in the common plot, five of each leaf species. Five replicate bags of each species were retrieved after 3, 6 and 12 wks of decomposition from under the source trees, and after 12 weeks from the common plot. After collection, litter was processed as described above. 

In addition, we compared early stage leaching losses in the two types of sites. The amount of rainfall during the first phase of decomposition (3 wks) did not differ significantly between the dry and wet period experiments described below (207 and 197 mm in the dry and wet period experiments, respectively). We were therefore able to compare initial mass loss attributed primarily by leaching between sites (two-way ANOVA), even though these experiments occurred at different times.

Influence of wet and dry periods on decomposition rates. &#8211; For these experiments, comparisons were made of decomposition rates during the dry and wet periods in the common plot. The dry period was from May through July 2000 and the wet period from August-November 2000 (Fig. 1). Five replicates were used in the experiment during the wet period, and three replicates were used per collection time during the dry period.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep></methods><project scope="document"><title>Decomposition Fungal - Plant Interactions</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Mirna</givenName><surName>Santana</surName></individualName><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><abstract><para><literalLayout>Rates of decomposition depend on the particular interactions between producers and decomposer food webs.&#160;This interactions are determined by the intrinsic characteristics of both plant and decomposers and are as well influenced by abiotic factors. Field studies were designed to determine the influences of environmental parameters such as climate and microsite variation on the decomposition rates of five tree species from The Luquillo Experimental Forest (LEF). This also allowed us to determine the influence of leaf quality on the decomposer community and whether leaf physical, structural or phylogenetic relationships could be used as predictors of decomposition rates. Microcosms were used to separated the contribution of interactions between dominant plants and fungal species in decomposition rates. The rates of decomposition were determined by mass loss in both the field and microcosms experiments.&#160;In the microcosms systems, CO2 evolution by the decomposition of each of the five leaf litter substrates, by fungal species isolated from that particular leaf or from any of the other litter types, was obtained by using sodium hydroxide traps. There were significant differences in decomposition rates among leaf litter types both in field and microcosms experiments.&#160;There was also a significant effect of dry and wet periods in decomposition rates.&#160;Leaf litter decomposed faster under their&#160;tree sources than in a common plot.&#160;Among the leaf quality parameters, the lignin and nitrogen to lignin ratios were the best predictors of decomposition rates. Non polar elements, water soluble (simple sugars), P and Ca were positively correlated with percent mass loss (PML) while C was negatively correlated with PML. In the microcosms experiments we did not found specificity between fungi and their substrate (where the fungus was isolated), neither to substrates that were chemically, physically or structurally related to the plant were the fungi was originally isolated. Nevertheless, there were differential responses of particular fungi to plant substrates as well as influences of plant species on the fungal decomposers performance.&#160;The differential contributions of leaf species to carbon budgets (mass remaining and CO2 release) may be important in determining management practices for forest and agricultural systems. We found that species such as Manilkara bidentata&#160;may retain carbon in the ecosystem while other species such as Sapium laurocerasus decomposed rapidly and therefore, released nutrients quickly but with greater carbon losses. The absence of tight links between plants and fungal decomposer may indicate adaptation of fungi to changes in resource availability in a disturbed forest. Alternatively, this might indicate that the presence of a fungi in a particular substrate does not depend on the substrate's chemical o physical composition but on the presence of other members of the detrivoral community.&#160;Although the presence of generalist basidiomycetes made an important contribution to the decomposition of leaf species, the diversity of the decomposer and detrivoral community might be important in maintaining nutrient balances in the ecosystems since random encounters of plants, decomposers and detrivores may determine the residence time of a substrate on the forest floor.</literalLayout></para></abstract><funding><para><literalLayout>LTER</literalLayout></para></funding></project><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=LUQ,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>matureTabonucodecomposition-MaytoJuly.txt</entityName><entityDescription>Decomposition rates on the common plot mature tabonuco forest-Dry Period</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>matureTabonucodecomposition-MaytoJuly.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb124/data/matureTabonucodecomposition-MaytoJuly.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReferencematureTabonucodecomposition-MaytoJuly.txt" scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2000-05-06</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2000-07-21</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><method><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Plant species &#8211; We used five common plants from the mature tabonuco forest as well as the mid-successional forest. Species selection was based primarily on nitrogen and phosphorus content, leaf structure, presence or absence of latex, and plant phylogenetic relationships. The five leaf species used in these experiments were:&#160;Inga vera and I. fagifolia&#160;in the Leguminosae; Croton poecilanthus and Sapium laurocerasus in the Euphobiaceae; and Manilkara bidentata in the Sapotaceae. 

The plant species were paired based on their physical and chemical characteristics (Tables 1, 2) to facilitate comparisons. Species in the first pair, I. vera and I. fagifolia, share the same family and genus and have high N and lignin concentrations, but they differ slightly in their levels of polyphenols. Species in the second pair, M. bidentata and C. poecilanthus, share similar nutrient concentrations, leaf structure and latex, but they belong to different families. Species in the third pair, C. poecilanthus and S. laurocerasus, share the same family and have latex, but they differ in nutrient and lignin concentrations as well as leaf structure. Sapium laurocerasus leaves are thin and smooth while C. poecilanthus leaves are thicker and have a heavier cuticle with peltate hairs.

Thickness of the leaves, epidermal cells, epidermal cell walls, and waxy cuticles were measured on hand-cut cross-sections using an ocular micrometer at 200-600x (five leaves per species). Ten fresh leaves per species were weighed and their areas were estimated using a grid. Water uptake (g water/cm2) was then determined by submerging the same leaves in deionized water for two hours and re-weighing (Taylor &amp; Parkinson, 1988b). 

Leaf litter collection &#8211; Only recently fallen senescent leaves of the selected species were collected. These leaves represent the normal substrates for primary fungal decomposers. Most leaves were collected the same day they abscised, but some senescent leaves where collected directly from their trees. Leaf collection took place during April and in early May for the first experiment, and at the end of July for the second set of experiments. Leaves of each species were collected from at least five trees. For field experiments, leaves were dried at 50&#186;C for 72 h. The 50&#176;C temperature was used to avoid major changes in plant chemistry and to control for differences in initial water content between leaf species (W. Silver, personal communication). Additional leaves were collected for chemical analyses and were dried according to each laboratory's protocols as described below.

Effects of leaf structure and quality on decomposition. &#8211; Litter bags (20 x 20 cm) made with 2 mm mesh plastic screening were used for these experiments. Litter bags containing three grams of oven-dried (50&#176;C) leaves of a single species were placed in a common plot. The first experimental sets were decomposed from May through July 2000.&#160;A total of 45 bags were used, nine bags per plant species.&#160;Bags were placed in the field under a tree of their own species for the first week to allow colonization by their normal decomposers, and subsequently moved to the common plot located in mature tabonuco forest. Three replicates per plant species were collected after three, six and twelve weeks of decomposition. After each collection, bags with the decomposed leaves were oven dried at 65&#176;C for 72 h and weighed to calculate rates of decomposition (difference between the initial and the final dry weight). We used correlation analyses to determine the relationship between leaf quality and decomposition and correlations among leaf quality factors. 

Another set of bags, five replicates for each species, was set in the common plot from the end of August to November 2000. This set was collected after 12 wks&#160;and was used to compare the effects of dry versus wet periods on decomposition. This set was also used to compare decomposition of leaves in the common plot with leaves simultaneouslyplaced under their source trees to determine the effect of microsite on decomposition.Effect of site on decomposition &#8211;We used two types of sites: the common plot in tabonuco forest as described above was used as a &#8216;foreign site&#8217;, and the forest floor under trees of the same species as those in the litterbags as a &#8216;source site&#8217;. The experiment was conducted only during the wet period. In the &#8216;source site&#8217; set, each plant species was represented by five trees located at least 100 apart. Under each of these five trees per species, we placed three litterbags of the same species; one bag was collected on each sample date. A total of 25 trees and 75 leaf litterbags were used in the source tree decomposition experiment. A total of 25 bags were placed in the common plot, five of each leaf species. Five replicate bags of each species were retrieved after 3, 6 and 12 wks of decomposition from under the source trees, and after 12 weeks from the common plot. After collection, litter was processed as described above. 

In addition, we compared early stage leaching losses in the two types of sites. The amount of rainfall during the first phase of decomposition (3 wks) did not differ significantly between the dry and wet period experiments described below (207 and 197 mm in the dry and wet period experiments, respectively). We were therefore able to compare initial mass loss attributed primarily by leaching between sites (two-way ANOVA), even though these experiments occurred at different times.

Influence of wet and dry periods on decomposition rates. &#8211; For these experiments, comparisons were made of decomposition rates during the dry and wet periods in the common plot. The dry period was from May through July 2000 and the wet period from August-November 2000 (Fig. 1). Five replicates were used in the experiment during the wet period, and three replicates were used per collection time during the dry period.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReferencematureTabonucodecomposition-MaytoJuly.txt</references></temporalCoverage></coverage></studyExtent><samplingDescription><section><para><literalLayout>every three weeks</literalLayout></para></section></samplingDescription></sampling></method><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Species name</attributeName><attributeLabel>Plantspecies</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Species name of the leaves used in the experiments</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Species name of the leaves used in the experiments</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Code of species</attributeName><attributeLabel>Speciescode</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Code assigned to each species</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>4</code><definition>Croton poecilanthus</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>2</code><definition>Inga fagifolia</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>1</code><definition>Inga vera</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>3</code><definition>Manilkara bidentata</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>5</code><definition>Sapium laurocerasus</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Number of weeks</attributeName><attributeLabel>Time_weeks</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Number of weeks the sample were allowed to decompose in the field before collection; (5 only in "Fresh Leaves decomposition under tree species sources mid-successional forest" file )</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Initial weight of mass</attributeName><attributeLabel>Initialmass_g</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>50 Centigrades dry weight before placed on the field</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Final weight of mass</attributeName><attributeLabel>FinalMass_g</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>50 Centigrades dry weight after collection from the field</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Percent mass remaining</attributeName><attributeLabel>percentMassRemaining</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Percent of the remaining leaf weight.Calculated asInitial Mass(g)/ Final Mass(g)]/100</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Percent leaf mass lost</attributeName><attributeLabel>percentMassLoss</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Percent leaf weight lost.Calculated as100 -Percent mass remaining.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute></attributeList></dataTable><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>matureTabonucodecomposition-EndofAugtoNov.txt</entityName><entityDescription>Decomposition rates on the common plot mature tabonuco forest-Wet Period</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>matureTabonucodecomposition-EndofAugtoNov.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb124/data/matureTabonucodecomposition-EndofAugtoNov.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReferencematureTabonucodecomposition-EndofAugtoNov.txt" scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2000-08-30</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2000-11-17</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><method><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Plant species &#8211; We used five common plants from the mature tabonuco forest as well as the mid-successional forest. Species selection was based primarily on nitrogen and phosphorus content, leaf structure, presence or absence of latex, and plant phylogenetic relationships. The five leaf species used in these experiments were:&#160;Inga vera and I. fagifolia&#160;in the Leguminosae; Croton poecilanthus and Sapium laurocerasus in the Euphobiaceae; and Manilkara bidentata in the Sapotaceae. 

The plant species were paired based on their physical and chemical characteristics (Tables 1, 2) to facilitate comparisons. Species in the first pair, I. vera and I. fagifolia, share the same family and genus and have high N and lignin concentrations, but they differ slightly in their levels of polyphenols. Species in the second pair, M. bidentata and C. poecilanthus, share similar nutrient concentrations, leaf structure and latex, but they belong to different families. Species in the third pair, C. poecilanthus and S. laurocerasus, share the same family and have latex, but they differ in nutrient and lignin concentrations as well as leaf structure. Sapium laurocerasus leaves are thin and smooth while C. poecilanthus leaves are thicker and have a heavier cuticle with peltate hairs.

Thickness of the leaves, epidermal cells, epidermal cell walls, and waxy cuticles were measured on hand-cut cross-sections using an ocular micrometer at 200-600x (five leaves per species). Ten fresh leaves per species were weighed and their areas were estimated using a grid. Water uptake (g water/cm2) was then determined by submerging the same leaves in deionized water for two hours and re-weighing (Taylor &amp; Parkinson, 1988b). 

Leaf litter collection &#8211; Only recently fallen senescent leaves of the selected species were collected. These leaves represent the normal substrates for primary fungal decomposers. Most leaves were collected the same day they abscised, but some senescent leaves where collected directly from their trees. Leaf collection took place during April and in early May for the first experiment, and at the end of July for the second set of experiments. Leaves of each species were collected from at least five trees. For field experiments, leaves were dried at 50&#186;C for 72 h. The 50&#176;C temperature was used to avoid major changes in plant chemistry and to control for differences in initial water content between leaf species (W. Silver, personal communication). Additional leaves were collected for chemical analyses and were dried according to each laboratory's protocols as described below.

Effects of leaf structure and quality on decomposition. &#8211; Litter bags (20 x 20 cm) made with 2 mm mesh plastic screening were used for these experiments. Litter bags containing three grams of oven-dried (50&#176;C) leaves of a single species were placed in a common plot. The first experimental sets were decomposed from May through July 2000.&#160;A total of 45 bags were used, nine bags per plant species.&#160;Bags were placed in the field under a tree of their own species for the first week to allow colonization by their normal decomposers, and subsequently moved to the common plot located in mature tabonuco forest. Three replicates per plant species were collected after three, six and twelve weeks of decomposition. After each collection, bags with the decomposed leaves were oven dried at 65&#176;C for 72 h and weighed to calculate rates of decomposition (difference between the initial and the final dry weight). We used correlation analyses to determine the relationship between leaf quality and decomposition and correlations among leaf quality factors. 

Another set of bags, five replicates for each species, was set in the common plot from the end of August to November 2000. This set was collected after 12 wks&#160;and was used to compare the effects of dry versus wet periods on decomposition. This set was also used to compare decomposition of leaves in the common plot with leaves simultaneouslyplaced under their source trees to determine the effect of microsite on decomposition.Effect of site on decomposition &#8211;We used two types of sites: the common plot in tabonuco forest as described above was used as a &#8216;foreign site&#8217;, and the forest floor under trees of the same species as those in the litterbags as a &#8216;source site&#8217;. The experiment was conducted only during the wet period. In the &#8216;source site&#8217; set, each plant species was represented by five trees located at least 100 apart. Under each of these five trees per species, we placed three litterbags of the same species; one bag was collected on each sample date. A total of 25 trees and 75 leaf litterbags were used in the source tree decomposition experiment. A total of 25 bags were placed in the common plot, five of each leaf species. Five replicate bags of each species were retrieved after 3, 6 and 12 wks of decomposition from under the source trees, and after 12 weeks from the common plot. After collection, litter was processed as described above. 

In addition, we compared early stage leaching losses in the two types of sites. The amount of rainfall during the first phase of decomposition (3 wks) did not differ significantly between the dry and wet period experiments described below (207 and 197 mm in the dry and wet period experiments, respectively). We were therefore able to compare initial mass loss attributed primarily by leaching between sites (two-way ANOVA), even though these experiments occurred at different times.

Influence of wet and dry periods on decomposition rates. &#8211; For these experiments, comparisons were made of decomposition rates during the dry and wet periods in the common plot. The dry period was from May through July 2000 and the wet period from August-November 2000 (Fig. 1). Five replicates were used in the experiment during the wet period, and three replicates were used per collection time during the dry period.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReferencematureTabonucodecomposition-EndofAugtoNov.txt</references></temporalCoverage></coverage></studyExtent><samplingDescription><section><para><literalLayout>only on the twelfth week</literalLayout></para></section></samplingDescription></sampling></method><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Species name</attributeName><attributeLabel>Plantspecies</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Species name of the leaves used in the experiments</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Species name of the leaves used in the experiments</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Code of species</attributeName><attributeLabel>Speciescode</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Code assigned to each species</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>4</code><definition>Croton poecilanthus</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>2</code><definition>Inga fagifolia</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>1</code><definition>Inga vera</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>3</code><definition>Manilkara bidentata</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>5</code><definition>Sapium laurocerasus</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Number of weeks</attributeName><attributeLabel>Time_weeks</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Number of weeks the sample were allowed to decompose in the field before collection; (5 only in "Fresh Leaves decomposition under tree species sources mid-successional forest" file )</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Initial weight of mass</attributeName><attributeLabel>Initialmass_g</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>50 Centigrades dry weight before placed on the field</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Final weight of mass</attributeName><attributeLabel>FinalMass_g</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>50 Centigrades dry weight after collection from the field</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Percent mass remaining</attributeName><attributeLabel>percentMassRemaining</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Percent of the remaining leaf weight.Calculated asInitial Mass(g)/ Final Mass(g)]/100</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Percent leaf mass lost</attributeName><attributeLabel>percentMassLoss</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Percent leaf weight lost.Calculated as100 -Percent mass remaining.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute></attributeList></dataTable><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>undertreespeciesdecomposition-EndofAugtoNov.txt</entityName><entityDescription>Decomposition rates under tree species sources mid-successional forest-Wet Period</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>undertreespeciesdecomposition-EndofAugtoNov.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb124/data/undertreespeciesdecomposition-EndofAugtoNov.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReferenceundertreespeciesdecomposition-EndofAugtoNov.txt" scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2000-08-30</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2000-11-17</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><method><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Plant species &#8211; We used five common plants from the mature tabonuco forest as well as the mid-successional forest. Species selection was based primarily on nitrogen and phosphorus content, leaf structure, presence or absence of latex, and plant phylogenetic relationships. The five leaf species used in these experiments were:&#160;Inga vera and I. fagifolia&#160;in the Leguminosae; Croton poecilanthus and Sapium laurocerasus in the Euphobiaceae; and Manilkara bidentata in the Sapotaceae. 

The plant species were paired based on their physical and chemical characteristics (Tables 1, 2) to facilitate comparisons. Species in the first pair, I. vera and I. fagifolia, share the same family and genus and have high N and lignin concentrations, but they differ slightly in their levels of polyphenols. Species in the second pair, M. bidentata and C. poecilanthus, share similar nutrient concentrations, leaf structure and latex, but they belong to different families. Species in the third pair, C. poecilanthus and S. laurocerasus, share the same family and have latex, but they differ in nutrient and lignin concentrations as well as leaf structure. Sapium laurocerasus leaves are thin and smooth while C. poecilanthus leaves are thicker and have a heavier cuticle with peltate hairs.

Thickness of the leaves, epidermal cells, epidermal cell walls, and waxy cuticles were measured on hand-cut cross-sections using an ocular micrometer at 200-600x (five leaves per species). Ten fresh leaves per species were weighed and their areas were estimated using a grid. Water uptake (g water/cm2) was then determined by submerging the same leaves in deionized water for two hours and re-weighing (Taylor &amp; Parkinson, 1988b). 

Leaf litter collection &#8211; Only recently fallen senescent leaves of the selected species were collected. These leaves represent the normal substrates for primary fungal decomposers. Most leaves were collected the same day they abscised, but some senescent leaves where collected directly from their trees. Leaf collection took place during April and in early May for the first experiment, and at the end of July for the second set of experiments. Leaves of each species were collected from at least five trees. For field experiments, leaves were dried at 50&#186;C for 72 h. The 50&#176;C temperature was used to avoid major changes in plant chemistry and to control for differences in initial water content between leaf species (W. Silver, personal communication). Additional leaves were collected for chemical analyses and were dried according to each laboratory's protocols as described below.

Effects of leaf structure and quality on decomposition. &#8211; Litter bags (20 x 20 cm) made with 2 mm mesh plastic screening were used for these experiments. Litter bags containing three grams of oven-dried (50&#176;C) leaves of a single species were placed in a common plot. The first experimental sets were decomposed from May through July 2000.&#160;A total of 45 bags were used, nine bags per plant species.&#160;Bags were placed in the field under a tree of their own species for the first week to allow colonization by their normal decomposers, and subsequently moved to the common plot located in mature tabonuco forest. Three replicates per plant species were collected after three, six and twelve weeks of decomposition. After each collection, bags with the decomposed leaves were oven dried at 65&#176;C for 72 h and weighed to calculate rates of decomposition (difference between the initial and the final dry weight). We used correlation analyses to determine the relationship between leaf quality and decomposition and correlations among leaf quality factors. 

Another set of bags, five replicates for each species, was set in the common plot from the end of August to November 2000. This set was collected after 12 wks&#160;and was used to compare the effects of dry versus wet periods on decomposition. This set was also used to compare decomposition of leaves in the common plot with leaves simultaneouslyplaced under their source trees to determine the effect of microsite on decomposition.Effect of site on decomposition &#8211;We used two types of sites: the common plot in tabonuco forest as described above was used as a &#8216;foreign site&#8217;, and the forest floor under trees of the same species as those in the litterbags as a &#8216;source site&#8217;. The experiment was conducted only during the wet period. In the &#8216;source site&#8217; set, each plant species was represented by five trees located at least 100 apart. Under each of these five trees per species, we placed three litterbags of the same species; one bag was collected on each sample date. A total of 25 trees and 75 leaf litterbags were used in the source tree decomposition experiment. A total of 25 bags were placed in the common plot, five of each leaf species. Five replicate bags of each species were retrieved after 3, 6 and 12 wks of decomposition from under the source trees, and after 12 weeks from the common plot. After collection, litter was processed as described above. 

In addition, we compared early stage leaching losses in the two types of sites. The amount of rainfall during the first phase of decomposition (3 wks) did not differ significantly between the dry and wet period experiments described below (207 and 197 mm in the dry and wet period experiments, respectively). We were therefore able to compare initial mass loss attributed primarily by leaching between sites (two-way ANOVA), even though these experiments occurred at different times.

Influence of wet and dry periods on decomposition rates. &#8211; For these experiments, comparisons were made of decomposition rates during the dry and wet periods in the common plot. The dry period was from May through July 2000 and the wet period from August-November 2000 (Fig. 1). Five replicates were used in the experiment during the wet period, and three replicates were used per collection time during the dry period.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReferenceundertreespeciesdecomposition-EndofAugtoNov.txt</references></temporalCoverage></coverage></studyExtent><samplingDescription><section><para><literalLayout>every three weeks</literalLayout></para></section></samplingDescription></sampling></method><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Species name</attributeName><attributeLabel>Plantspecies</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Species name of the leaves used in the experiments</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Species name of the leaves used in the experiments</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Code of species</attributeName><attributeLabel>Speciescode</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Code assigned to each species</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>4</code><definition>Croton poecilanthus</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>2</code><definition>Inga fagifolia</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>1</code><definition>Inga vera</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>3</code><definition>Manilkara bidentata</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>5</code><definition>Sapium laurocerasus</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Number of weeks</attributeName><attributeLabel>Time_weeks</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Number of weeks the sample were allowed to decompose in the field before collection; (5 only in "Fresh Leaves decomposition under tree species sources mid-successional forest" file )</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Initial weight of mass</attributeName><attributeLabel>Initialmass_g</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>50 Centigrades dry weight before placed on the field</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Final weight of mass</attributeName><attributeLabel>FinalMass_g</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>50 Centigrades dry weight after collection from the field</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Percent mass remaining</attributeName><attributeLabel>percentMassRemaining</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Percent of the remaining leaf weight.Calculated asInitial Mass(g)/ Final Mass(g)]/100</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Percent leaf mass lost</attributeName><attributeLabel>percentMassLoss</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Percent leaf weight lost.Calculated as100 -Percent mass remaining.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute></attributeList></dataTable><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>Freshleavesdecomposition-EndofAugtoNov.txt</entityName><entityDescription>Fresh Leaves decomposition under tree species sources mid-successional forest</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>Freshleavesdecomposition-EndofAugtoNov.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb124/data/Freshleavesdecomposition-EndofAugtoNov.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReferenceFreshleavesdecomposition-EndofAugtoNov.txt" scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2000-08-30</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2000-10-05</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><method><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Plant species &#8211; We used five common plants from the mature tabonuco forest as well as the mid-successional forest. Species selection was based primarily on nitrogen and phosphorus content, leaf structure, presence or absence of latex, and plant phylogenetic relationships. The five leaf species used in these experiments were:&#160;Inga vera and I. fagifolia&#160;in the Leguminosae; Croton poecilanthus and Sapium laurocerasus in the Euphobiaceae; and Manilkara bidentata in the Sapotaceae. 

The plant species were paired based on their physical and chemical characteristics (Tables 1, 2) to facilitate comparisons. Species in the first pair, I. vera and I. fagifolia, share the same family and genus and have high N and lignin concentrations, but they differ slightly in their levels of polyphenols. Species in the second pair, M. bidentata and C. poecilanthus, share similar nutrient concentrations, leaf structure and latex, but they belong to different families. Species in the third pair, C. poecilanthus and S. laurocerasus, share the same family and have latex, but they differ in nutrient and lignin concentrations as well as leaf structure. Sapium laurocerasus leaves are thin and smooth while C. poecilanthus leaves are thicker and have a heavier cuticle with peltate hairs.

Thickness of the leaves, epidermal cells, epidermal cell walls, and waxy cuticles were measured on hand-cut cross-sections using an ocular micrometer at 200-600x (five leaves per species). Ten fresh leaves per species were weighed and their areas were estimated using a grid. Water uptake (g water/cm2) was then determined by submerging the same leaves in deionized water for two hours and re-weighing (Taylor &amp; Parkinson, 1988b). 

Leaf litter collection &#8211; Only recently fallen senescent leaves of the selected species were collected. These leaves represent the normal substrates for primary fungal decomposers. Most leaves were collected the same day they abscised, but some senescent leaves where collected directly from their trees. Leaf collection took place during April and in early May for the first experiment, and at the end of July for the second set of experiments. Leaves of each species were collected from at least five trees. For field experiments, leaves were dried at 50&#186;C for 72 h. The 50&#176;C temperature was used to avoid major changes in plant chemistry and to control for differences in initial water content between leaf species (W. Silver, personal communication). Additional leaves were collected for chemical analyses and were dried according to each laboratory's protocols as described below.

Effects of leaf structure and quality on decomposition. &#8211; Litter bags (20 x 20 cm) made with 2 mm mesh plastic screening were used for these experiments. Litter bags containing three grams of oven-dried (50&#176;C) leaves of a single species were placed in a common plot. The first experimental sets were decomposed from May through July 2000.&#160;A total of 45 bags were used, nine bags per plant species.&#160;Bags were placed in the field under a tree of their own species for the first week to allow colonization by their normal decomposers, and subsequently moved to the common plot located in mature tabonuco forest. Three replicates per plant species were collected after three, six and twelve weeks of decomposition. After each collection, bags with the decomposed leaves were oven dried at 65&#176;C for 72 h and weighed to calculate rates of decomposition (difference between the initial and the final dry weight). We used correlation analyses to determine the relationship between leaf quality and decomposition and correlations among leaf quality factors. 

Another set of bags, five replicates for each species, was set in the common plot from the end of August to November 2000. This set was collected after 12 wks&#160;and was used to compare the effects of dry versus wet periods on decomposition. This set was also used to compare decomposition of leaves in the common plot with leaves simultaneouslyplaced under their source trees to determine the effect of microsite on decomposition.Effect of site on decomposition &#8211;We used two types of sites: the common plot in tabonuco forest as described above was used as a &#8216;foreign site&#8217;, and the forest floor under trees of the same species as those in the litterbags as a &#8216;source site&#8217;. The experiment was conducted only during the wet period. In the &#8216;source site&#8217; set, each plant species was represented by five trees located at least 100 apart. Under each of these five trees per species, we placed three litterbags of the same species; one bag was collected on each sample date. A total of 25 trees and 75 leaf litterbags were used in the source tree decomposition experiment. A total of 25 bags were placed in the common plot, five of each leaf species. Five replicate bags of each species were retrieved after 3, 6 and 12 wks of decomposition from under the source trees, and after 12 weeks from the common plot. After collection, litter was processed as described above. 

In addition, we compared early stage leaching losses in the two types of sites. The amount of rainfall during the first phase of decomposition (3 wks) did not differ significantly between the dry and wet period experiments described below (207 and 197 mm in the dry and wet period experiments, respectively). We were therefore able to compare initial mass loss attributed primarily by leaching between sites (two-way ANOVA), even though these experiments occurred at different times.

Influence of wet and dry periods on decomposition rates. &#8211; For these experiments, comparisons were made of decomposition rates during the dry and wet periods in the common plot. The dry period was from May through July 2000 and the wet period from August-November 2000 (Fig. 1). Five replicates were used in the experiment during the wet period, and three replicates were used per collection time during the dry period.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReferenceFreshleavesdecomposition-EndofAugtoNov.txt</references></temporalCoverage></coverage></studyExtent><samplingDescription><section><para><literalLayout>Only on the fifth week</literalLayout></para></section></samplingDescription></sampling></method><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Species name</attributeName><attributeLabel>Plantspecies</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Species name of the leaves used in the experiments</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Species name of the leaves used in the experiments</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Code of species</attributeName><attributeLabel>Speciescode</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Code assigned to each species</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>4</code><definition>Croton poecilanthus</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>2</code><definition>Inga fagifolia</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>1</code><definition>Inga vera</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>3</code><definition>Manilkara bidentata</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>5</code><definition>Sapium laurocerasus</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Number of weeks</attributeName><attributeLabel>Time_weeks</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Number of weeks the sample were allowed to decompose in the field before collection; (5 only in "Fresh Leaves decomposition under tree species sources mid-successional forest" file )</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Initial weight of mass</attributeName><attributeLabel>Initialmass_g</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>50 Centigrades dry weight before placed on the field</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Final weight of mass</attributeName><attributeLabel>FinalMass_g</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>50 Centigrades dry weight after collection from the field</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Percent mass remaining</attributeName><attributeLabel>percentMassRemaining</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Percent of the remaining leaf weight.Calculated asInitial Mass(g)/ Final Mass(g)]/100</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Percent leaf mass lost</attributeName><attributeLabel>percentMassLoss</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Percent leaf weight lost.Calculated as100 -Percent mass remaining.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset></eml:eml>