<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-ntl.247.2" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0  http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
	<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
		<allow>
			<principal>uid=NTL, o=lter, dc=ecoinformatics, dc=org</principal>
			<permission>all</permission>
		</allow>
		<allow>
			<principal>public</principal>
			<permission>read</permission>
		</allow>
	</access>
	<dataset>
		<alternateIdentifier system="NTL-DEIMS">5663</alternateIdentifier>
		<shortName>LRMAJION1</shortName>
		<title>Little Rock Lake Experiment at North Temperate Lakes LTER: Major Ions 1996 - 2000</title>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Timothy</givenName>
				<surName>Kratz</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>10810 County Highway N</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Boulder Junction</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>54512</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">(715) 356-9494</phone>
			<phone phonetype="fax">(715) 356-6866</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>tkkratz@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Carl</givenName>
				<surName>Watras</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>10810 County Hwy N</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Boulder Junction</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>54512</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">(715) 356-9494</phone>
			<phone phonetype="fax">(715) 356-6866</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>cjwatras@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<metadataProvider>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</metadataProvider>
		<pubDate>2003</pubDate>
		<language>english</language>
		<abstract>
			<para>The Little Rock Acidification Experiment was a joint project involving the USEPA (Duluth
				Lab), University of Minnesota-Twin Cities, University of Wisconsin-Superior, University of
				Wisconsin-Madison, and the Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources. Little Rock Lake is a
				bi-lobed lake in Vilas County, Wisconsin, USA. In 1983 the lake was divided in half by an
				impermeable curtain and from 1984-1989 the northern basin of the lake was acidified with
				sulfuric acid in three two-year stages. The target pHs for 1984-5, 1986-7, and 1988-9 were
				5.7, 5.2, and 4.7, respectively. Starting in 1990 the lake was allowed to recover naturally
				with the curtain still in place. Data were collected through 2000. The main objective was to
				understand the population, community, and ecosystem responses to whole-lake acidification.
				Funding for this project was provided by the USEPA and NSF. Parameters characterizing the
				major ions of the treatment and reference basins of Little Rock Lake are measured at one
				station in the deepest part of each basin at the top and bottom of the epilimnion,
				mid-thermocline, and top, middle, and bottom of the hypolimnion. These parameters include
				chloride, sulfate, calcium, magnesium, sodium, potassium, iron, and manganese Sampling
				Frequency: varies - Number of sites: 2 </para>
		</abstract>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>calcium</keyword>
			<keyword>chloride</keyword>
			<keyword>inorganic nutrients</keyword>
			<keyword>iron</keyword>
			<keyword>magnesium</keyword>
			<keyword>manganese</keyword>
			<keyword>potassium</keyword>
			<keyword>sodium</keyword>
			<keyword>sulfate</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>LTER Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>Ca</keyword>
			<keyword>Cl</keyword>
			<keyword>Fe</keyword>
			<keyword>K</keyword>
			<keyword>Mg</keyword>
			<keyword>Mn</keyword>
			<keyword>NTL LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>Na</keyword>
			<keyword>North Temperate Lakes - LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>SO4</keyword>
			<keyword>major ions</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>NTL Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<intellectualRights>
			<section>
				<title>Data Policies</title>
				<para>Copyright Board of Regents, University of Wisconsin, Madison. This information is
					released to the public and may be used for academic, educational, or commercial purposes
					subject to the following restrictions: The Data User must realize that these data sets are
					being actively used by others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary
					to prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the NTL lead Principal
					Investigator, leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu, to check on other uses of the data. Where
					appropriate, the Data User may be encouraged to consider collaboration and/or
					co-authorship with original investigators.</para>
				<para>The Data User must realize that the data may be misinterpreted if taken out of
					context. We request that you provide the NTL lead Principal Investigator, ATTN: Data
					Access, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison, 680 North Park St.,
					Madison, WI 53706 with a copy of any manuscript using the data so that it may be reviewed
					and comments provided on the presentation of our data.</para>
				<para>The Data User must acknowledge use of the data by an appropriate citation (see
					Citation) of the NTL-LTER database. A generic citation for our databases is: name of data
					set, North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research program, NSF, contact person for
					data set, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison. The data set name and
					contact person for each data set can be found in the metadata header of the online data
					sets.</para>
				<para>The Data User must send two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the
					data to the address above. We would like to include such manuscripts in our LTER
					publications list.</para>
				<para>The Data User must not redistribute original data and documentation without permission
					from Emily Stanley, lead Principal Investigator, (ehstanley@wisc.edu).</para>
				<para>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation,
					complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is".
					The North Temperate Lakes LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or
					misinterpretation of data sets. Data users should be aware that we periodically update
					data sets.</para>
				<para>Our goal is to release all long term data associated with core research areas within 2
					years of collection. These data and accompanying metadata will be available for download
					from the NTL-LTER web site.</para>
				<para>By using these data, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement.
					Thank you for your cooperation. </para>
			</section>
		</intellectualRights>
		<distribution>
			<online>
				<url function="information">http://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/node/5663</url>
			</online>
		</distribution>
		<coverage>
			<geographicCoverage>
				<geographicDescription>Little Rock Lake,Vilas County, WI, USA
</geographicDescription>
				<boundingCoordinates>
					<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.707</westBoundingCoordinate>
					<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.696</eastBoundingCoordinate>
					<northBoundingCoordinate>46.001</northBoundingCoordinate>
					<southBoundingCoordinate>45.994</southBoundingCoordinate>
				</boundingCoordinates>
			</geographicCoverage>
			<temporalCoverage>
				<rangeOfDates>
					<beginDate>
						<calendarDate>1996-07-15</calendarDate>
					</beginDate>
					<endDate>
						<calendarDate>2000-10-23</calendarDate>
					</endDate>
				</rangeOfDates>
			</temporalCoverage>
		</coverage>
		<maintenance>
			<description>
				<para>completed </para>
			</description>
		</maintenance>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Information Manager</positionName>
			<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
			<organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<publisher>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</publisher>
		<pubPlace>North Temperate Lakes</pubPlace>
		<methods>
			<methodStep>
				<description>
					<section>
						<para>Chloride, Sulfate Samples for chloride and sulfate are collected together with a
							peristaltic pump and tubing and in-line filtered (through a 0.40 micron polycarbonate
							filter) into new, 20 ml HDPE plastic containers with conical caps. The samples are
							stored refrigerated at 4 degrees Celsius until analysis, which should occur within 6
							months. The samples are analyzed for chloride (and sulfate) simultaneously by Ion
							Chromatography, using a hydroxide eluent. The detection limit for chloride is
							approximately 0.01 ppm and the analytical range for the method extends to 100 ppm. The
							detection limit for sulfate is approximately 0.01 ppm and the analytical range for the
							method extends to 60 ppm. Method Log: Prior to January 1998 samples, chloride was
							determined on a Dionex DX10 Ion Chromatograph, using a chemical fiber suppressor. From
							1998 to 2011, chloride was determined by a Dionex model DX500, using an
							electro-chemical suppressor. From January 2011 until present, chloride is determined
							by a Dionex model ICS 2100 using an electro-chemical suppressor. &#194;&#160; </para>
					</section>
					<section>
						<para>Calcium, silicon, magnesium, sodium, potassium, iron, and manganese Samples for
							calcium analysis (as well as dissolved nitrogen and phosphorus, silicon, magnesium,
							sodium, potassium, iron, and manganese) are collected together with a peristaltic pump
							and tubing and in-line filtered (through a 40 micron polycarbonate filter) into 120 ml
							LDPE bottles and acidified to a 1percent HCl matrix by adding 1 ml of ultra pure
							concentrated HCl to 100 mls of sample. For every sample acidification event, three
							acid blanks are created by adding the same acid used on the samples to 100 mls of
							ultra pure water supplied from the lab. Once acidified, the samples are stable at room
							temperature until analysis, which should occur within one year. Until acidification,
							the samples should be refrigerated at 4 degrees Celsius. Calcium, as well as
							magnesium, sodium, potassium, iron, and manganese are analyzed simultaneously on an
							optical inductively-coupled plasma emission spectrophotometer (ICP-OES). The acidified
							samples are directly aspirated into the instrument without a digestion. Calcium is
							analyzed at 317.933 nm and at 315.887 nm and viewed axially for low-level analysis and
							radially for high level analysis. The detection limit for calcium is 0.06 ppm with an
							analytical range of the method extends to 50 ppm. The detection limit for iron is 0.02
							ppm with an analytical range of the method extends to 20 ppm. The detection limit for
							magnesium is 0.03 ppm with an analytical range of the method extends to 50 ppm. The
							detection limit for manganese is 0.01 ppm with an analytical range of the method
							extends to 2 ppm. The detection limit for potassium is 0.06 ppm with an analytical
							range of the method extends to 10 ppm. The detection limit for sodium is 0.06 ppm with
							an analytical range of the method extends to 50 ppm. Method Log: Prior to January
							2002, Calcium, magnesium, sodium, potassium, iron, and manganese were determined on a
							Perkin-Elmer model 503 Atomic Absorption Spectrophotometer. Lanthanum at a 0.8percent
							concentration was added as a matrix modifier to suppress chemical interferences. From
							January 2002 to present, samples are analyzed for calcium on a Perkin-Elmer model 4300
							DV ICP. Dissolved reactive silica is determined by the Heteropoly Blue Method and the
							absorption is measured at 820 nm. The detection limit for silicon is 6 ppb and the
							analytical range is 15000 ppb. Method Log These determinations were performed manually
							using a Bausch and Lomb Spectrophotometer from the beginning of the project until
							April 1984. From 1984 through 2005, dissolved reactive silicon was determined on a
							Technicon Auto Analyzer II. From January 2006 to present, samples are run on an
							Astoria-Pacific Astoria II Autoanalyzer. </para>
					</section>
				</description>
			</methodStep>
		</methods>
		<project>
			<title>Little Rock Acidification Experiment</title>
			<personnel>
				<individualName>
					<givenName>Timothy</givenName>
					<surName>Kratz</surName>
				</individualName>
				<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
				<address>
        <deliveryPoint>10810 County Highway N</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Boulder Junction</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>54512</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
				<phone phonetype="voice">(715) 356-9494</phone>
				<phone phonetype="fax">(715) 356-6866</phone>
				<electronicMailAddress>tkkratz@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
				<role>project personnel</role>
			</personnel>
			<abstract>
				<para>The Little Rock Acidification Experiment was a joint project involving the USEPA
					(Duluth Lab), University of Minnesota-Twin Cities, University of Wisconsin-Superior,
					University of Wisconsin-Madison, and the Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources.&#194;&#160;
					Little Rock Lake is a bi-lobed lake in Vilas County, Wisconsin, USA.&#194;&#160; In 1983 the lake was
					divided in half by an impermeable curtain and from 1984-1989 the northern basin of the
					lake was acidified with sulfuric acid in three two-year stages.&#194;&#160; The target pHs for
					1984-5, 1986-7, and 1988-9 were 5.7, 5.2, and 4.7, respectively.&#194;&#160; Starting in 1990 the
					lake was allowed to recover naturally with the curtain still in place.&#194;&#160; The main objective
					was to understand the population, community, and ecosystem responses to whole-lake
					acidification.&#194;&#160; Funding for this project was provided by the USEPA and NSF. </para>
			</abstract>
		</project>
		<dataTable>
			<entityName>lr_majorion</entityName>
			<entityDescription>Little Rock Lake Experiment: Major Ions</entityDescription>
			<physical>
				<objectName>lrmajorion</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
						<recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
							<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-ntl.247&amp;urlTail=ntl/data/5663_v1.csv</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<attributeList>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>lakeid</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>lake name abbreviation</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>lake name abbreviation</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<enumeratedDomain>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>LR</code>
										<definition>Little Rock Lake</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
								</enumeratedDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>year4</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>year</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>year</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>nominalYear</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<precision>1</precision>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>daynum</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>day of year</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>day of year</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>nominalDay</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<precision>1</precision>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
								<bounds>
									<minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum>
									<maximum exclusive="false">366</maximum>
								</bounds>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>sampledate</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>sample date</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>sample date</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>date</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<dateTime>
							<formatString>yyyy-MM-dd</formatString>
						</dateTime>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>depth</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>sample depth meter</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>depth at which the sample or measurement was taken</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>rep</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>replicate number</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>replicate number</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>replicate number</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>sta</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>station abbreviation</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>station abbreviation</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<enumeratedDomain>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>1</code>
										<definition>Treatment</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>2</code>
										<definition>Reference</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
								</enumeratedDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>cl</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>Cl</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>chloride</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>so4</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>SO4</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>SO4</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>ca</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>Ca</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>calcium</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>mg</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>Mg</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>Mg</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>na</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>Na</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>Na</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>k</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>K</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>K</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>fe</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>Fe</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>Fe</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>mn</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>Mn</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>Mn</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>flagcl</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>data flag for Cl</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>data flag for Cl</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<enumeratedDomain>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>E</code>
										<definition>Average of duplicate analyses</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>L</code>
										<definition>Data point and blind value differ by more than 15% </definition>
									</codeDefinition>
								</enumeratedDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>flagso4</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>data flag for SO4</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>data flag for SO4</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<enumeratedDomain>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>E</code>
										<definition>Average of duplicate analyses</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>L</code>
										<definition>Data point and blind value differ by more than 15% </definition>
									</codeDefinition>
								</enumeratedDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>flagca</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>data flag for Ca</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>data flag for Ca</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<enumeratedDomain>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>E</code>
										<definition>Average of duplicate analyses</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>L</code>
										<definition>Data point and blind value differ by more than 15% </definition>
									</codeDefinition>
								</enumeratedDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>flagmg</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>data flag for Mg</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>data flag for Mg</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<enumeratedDomain>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>E</code>
										<definition>Average of duplicate analyses</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>L</code>
										<definition>Data point and blind value differ by more than 15% </definition>
									</codeDefinition>
								</enumeratedDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>flagna</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>data flag for Na</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>data flag for Na</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<enumeratedDomain>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>E</code>
										<definition>Average of duplicate analyses</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>L</code>
										<definition>Data point and blind value differ by more than 15% </definition>
									</codeDefinition>
								</enumeratedDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>flagk</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>data flag for K</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>data flag for K</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<enumeratedDomain>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>E</code>
										<definition>Average of duplicate analyses</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>L</code>
										<definition>Data point and blind value differ by more than 15% </definition>
									</codeDefinition>
								</enumeratedDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>flagfe</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>data flag for Fe</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>data flag for Fe</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<enumeratedDomain>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>E</code>
										<definition>Average of duplicate analyses</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>L</code>
										<definition>Data point and blind value differ by more than 15% </definition>
									</codeDefinition>
								</enumeratedDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>flagmn</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>data flag for Mn</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>data flag for Mn</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<enumeratedDomain>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>E</code>
										<definition>Average of duplicate analyses</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>L</code>
										<definition>Data point and blind value differ by more than 15% </definition>
									</codeDefinition>
								</enumeratedDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
			</attributeList>
		</dataTable>
	</dataset>
	<additionalMetadata>
		<metadata>
			<ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1     http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
				<ns2:unit abbreviation="mg/l" constantToSI="0" id="milligramPerLiter" multiplierToSI="0.001" name="milligramPerLiter" parentSI="kilogramPerCubicMeter" unitType="massDensity">
					<ns2:description>milligrams / liter</ns2:description>
				</ns2:unit>
			</ns2:unitList>
		</metadata>
	</additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>