<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-bes.424.56 " system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 ./eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"> 
<dataset>
<title>Stream chemistry data for Upper Gwynns Falls tributary watersheds BES ID 424-</title>
<creator>
<individualName>
<surName>Peter Groffman ,     Email: groffmanp@ecostudies.org</surName>
</individualName>
</creator>
<pubDate>2007-02-19</pubDate>
<abstract><para>
In the Baltimore urban long-term ecological research (LTER) project, (Baltimore Ecosystem Study, BES) we use the watershed approach to evaluate integrated ecosystem function. The LTER research is centered on the Gwynns Falls watershed, a 17,150 ha catchment that traverses a gradient from the urban core of Baltimore, through older urban residential (1900 - 1950) and suburban (1950- 1980) zones, rapidly suburbanizing areas and a rural/suburban fringe. Our long-term sampling network includes four longitudinal sampling sites along the Gwynns Falls as well as several small (40 - 100 ha) watersheds located within or near to the Gwynns Falls. The longitudinal sites provide data on water and nutrient fluxes in the different land use zones of the watershed (rural/suburban, rapidly suburbanizing, old suburban, urban core) and the small watersheds provide more focused data on specific land use areas (forest, agriculture, rural/suburban, urban). Each of the gaging sites is continuously monitored for discharge and is sampled weekly for chemistry. Additional chemical sampling is carried out in a supplemental set of sites to provide a greater range of land use. Weekly analyses includes nitrate, phosphate, total nitrogen, total phosphorus, chloride and sulfate, total suspended solids, turbidity, fecal coliforms, temperature, dissolved oxygen and pH. Cations, dissolved organic carbon and nitrogen and  metals are measured on selected samples. 

This dataset is for a series of Upper Gwynns Falls tributary sites that were sampled from April 1999 to August 2000 Johns Hopkins University graduate student Mark Colosimo.  These sites had been studied in the mid-1980&#65533;s and the objective of this dissertation work was to evaluate changes in stream physical, chemical and biological properties over time, comparing rapidly suburbanizing tributary subwatersheds (Red Run, Horsehead Branch) with older more stable suburban areas (Scotts Level Branch, Holly Branch).   

There were two sites in the Red Run drainage.  This watershed drains approximately 19 km2 and has been rapidly suburbanizing since the early 1990s.  Percent impervious surface was approximately 10% as of 2002. Sampling station Red Run 1 (RR1) was approximately 35 m upstream of the crossing of Painters Mill Bridge Road, and 350 m upstream of the confluence with the Gwynns Falls.  Sampling station Red Run 2 (RR2) was farther upstream, between the Pleasant Hill and Dolfield road crossings. 

There were two sites along Scotts Level Branch, an older suburban watershed which was approximately 25% impervious surface in 1970.  Site SL1 drains approximately 11 km2 and is located at the outlet of the sub-watershed, just above the confluence with Gwynns Falls. Site SL2 is at the McDonogh Rd. bridge crossing.

The Horsehead Branch (HH) sampling site was located at the McDonogh Road crossing.  It drains approximately 5 km2  that has undergone rapid urbanization since the mid 1980s.  As of 1997 percent impervious surface was approximately 12%.

The Holly Bank (HB) sampling site was located just upstream of Gwynnbrook Ave. Seventy percent of land in this drainage is classified residential.

The Gwynns Falls at McDonogh (GF5) site was located at the McDonogh school / McDonogh road crossing of the Gwynns Falls and samples a drainage area of approximately 51 km2, with approximately 20% impervious surface.
</para></abstract>
<keywordSet>
<keyword keywordType="theme">stream, watershed, nitrate, phosphate, nitrogen, phosphorus, chloride, sulfate RG: Baltimore Ecosystem Study</keyword>
</keywordSet>
<keywordSet>
<keyword keywordType="place">Baltimore, MD, Washington, D.C, Chesapeake Bay, Baltimore-Washington, Maryland</keyword>
</keywordSet>
<distribution>
<online>
<url>http://beslter.org/pub/stream/upper_gwynns_falls_tributaries_final_chemistry_for_www_text.txt</url>
</online>
</distribution>
<coverage>
<geographicCoverage>
<geographicDescription>The Baltimore Ecosystem Study ultimately will conduct research and educational activities throughout the Baltimore metropolitan area. This large area includes Baltimore City, Baltimore County, and the counties of Ann Arundel, Carrol, Harford, Howard, and Montgomery. Gwynns Falls includes agricultural lands, recently suburbanized areas, established suburbs, and dense urban areas having residential, commercial and open spaces. In addition, a reference area has been established in a forested catchment of the Gunpowder drainage in Oregon Ridge County Park. </geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates>
<westBoundingCoordinate>-77.314183</westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>-76.012008</eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>39.724847</northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>38.708367</southBoundingCoordinate>
<boundingAltitudes>
<altitudeMinimum>50</altitudeMinimum>
<altitudeMaximum>700</altitudeMaximum>
<altitudeUnits>feet</altitudeUnits>
</boundingAltitudes>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
</coverage>
<contact>
<individualName>
<givenName>Jonathan</givenName>
<surName>Walsh</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies</organizationName>
<positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>IES</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>Box AB, 65 Sharon Tpke</deliveryPoint>
<city>Millbrook</city>
<administrativeArea>NY</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>12545</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">845-677-7600</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">  </phone>
<electronicMailAddress>walshj@ecostudies.org</electronicMailAddress>
</contact>
<publisher>
<organizationName> The scientists, the BES-LTER Program, and the Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies must receive adequate acknowledgement for the use of data by other scientists, and the BES LTER program must receive two copies of any publication using that data.   Baltimore Ecosystem Study</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>Room 134 TRC Building</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint> University of Maryland, Baltimore County</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint> 5200 Westland Blvd</deliveryPoint>
<city>Baltimore</city>
<administrativeArea>MD</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>21227</postalCode>
</address>
</publisher>
<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
<allow>
<principal>uid="BES",o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
<principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
</dataset>
</eml:eml>