<?xml version="1.0"?>
<resource xmlns:dcite="http://datacite.org/schema/kernel-3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://datacite.org/schema/kernel-3 http://schema.datacite.org/meta/kernel-3/metadata.xsd">
  <identifier identifierType="DOI">10.1594/IEDA/100053</identifier>
  <creators>
    <creator>
      <creatorName>Jordan, Erika K.</creatorName>
      <nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="GeoPass">191</nameIdentifier>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <creatorName>Lieu, Warren</creatorName>
      <nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="GeoPass">193</nameIdentifier>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <creatorName>Stern, Robert J.</creatorName>
      <nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="GeoPass">192</nameIdentifier>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <creatorName>Carr, Michael J.</creatorName>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <creatorName>Feigenson, Mark D.</creatorName>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <creatorName>Gill, James B.</creatorName>
      <nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="GeoPass">390</nameIdentifier>
    </creator>
  </creators>
  <titles>
    <title>CentAm &amp; IBM Geochem Database version 1.02</title>
  </titles>
  <publisher>Integrated Earth Data Applications (IEDA)</publisher>
  <publicationYear>2012</publicationYear>
  <subjects>
    <subject subjectScheme="ECL">Geochemistry</subject>
  </subjects>
  <dates>
    <date dateType="Available">2012-04-07</date>
  </dates>
  <language>eng</language>
  <resourceType resourceTypeGeneral="Collection"/>
  <alternateIdentifiers>
    <alternateIdentifier alternateIdentifierType="URL">http://www.earthchem.org/library/browse/view?id=270</alternateIdentifier>
  </alternateIdentifiers>
  <formats>
    <format>text/plain</format>
    <format>application/pdf</format>
    <format>application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet</format>
  </formats>
  <version>1.0</version>
  <contributors>
    <contributor contributorType="Editor">
      <contributorName>EarthChem Library (ECL)</contributorName>
      <nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="DOI">10.17616/R3V644</nameIdentifier>
    </contributor>
  </contributors>
  <rightsList>
    <rights rightsURI="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 United States [CC BY-NC-SA 3.0]</rights>
  </rightsList>
  <descriptions>
    <description descriptionType="Abstract">The CentAm &amp; IBM Geochem Database version 1.02 consists of high-quality geochemical data collected over the last two decades from the magmatic arcs of the two NSF MARGINS Subduction Factory focus sites: 1) the Central America (CentAm) arc system, including Costa Rica, Nicaragua, El Salvador, and Guatemala; 2) and the Izu-Bonin-Mariana (IBM) arc system, extending from Japan to Guam. The CentAm and IBM arc systems were chosen for this project because they represent two end members of subduction factories. CentAm has a high sediment input and a young, hot, dry subducting slab.  The IBM system has a low sediment input and an old, cold, wet subducting slab. This data was filtered and compiled to explore the magma characteristics of the respective arcs and to interpret their magmagenetic conditions such as sediment input, fluid-flux, and mantle and altered oceanic crustal components. To create the database, volcanic geochemical data for whole rock samples was downloaded from the EarthChem data portal (www.earthchem.org) (managed by the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory of Columbia University). Four datasets are included in separate worksheets within the Excel workbook, which include separate major and trace element datasets for CentAm and IBM.  Each dataset contains metadata for each sample and major and trace element, isotope, and calculated normative mineral compositions.  The workbook also contains an explanation of methods and a list of data references.  Supplemental documents include a detailed explanation of the datasets and filter processes and an EndNote library text file.</description>
    <description descriptionType="Other">geochemistry; lavas; major elements; trace elements; isotopes</description>
  </descriptions>
  <geoLocations>
    <geoLocation>
      <geoLocationBox>13.64 139.42 34.75 145.863</geoLocationBox>
    </geoLocation>
    <geoLocation>
      <geoLocationPlace>Izu-Bonin-Mariana, Central America, IBM, CAVA, Western, Pacific, Subduction Zone</geoLocationPlace>
    </geoLocation>
  </geoLocations>
</resource>
