<?xml version="1.0"?>
<resource xmlns:dcite="http://datacite.org/schema/kernel-3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://datacite.org/schema/kernel-3 http://schema.datacite.org/meta/kernel-3/metadata.xsd">
  <identifier identifierType="DOI">10.1594/IEDA/100494</identifier>
  <creators>
    <creator>
      <creatorName>Salehikhoo, Fatemeh</creatorName>
      <nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="GeoPass">1613</nameIdentifier>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <creatorName>Li, Li</creatorName>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <creatorName>Brantley, Susan</creatorName>
    </creator>
  </creators>
  <titles>
    <title>Effects of Mineral Spatial Patterns on Magnesite Dissolution Rates</title>
  </titles>
  <publisher>Integrated Earth Data Applications (IEDA)</publisher>
  <publicationYear>2014</publicationYear>
  <subjects>
    <subject subjectScheme="ECL">Chemistry:Sediment</subject>
    <subject subjectScheme="ECL">Kinetics</subject>
  </subjects>
  <dates>
    <date dateType="Available">2015-11-15</date>
  </dates>
  <language>eng</language>
  <resourceType resourceTypeGeneral="Dataset"/>
  <alternateIdentifiers>
    <alternateIdentifier alternateIdentifierType="URL">http://www.earthchem.org/library/browse/view?id=801</alternateIdentifier>
  </alternateIdentifiers>
  <formats>
    <format>application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet</format>
  </formats>
  <version>1.0</version>
  <contributors>
    <contributor contributorType="Editor">
      <contributorName>EarthChem Library (ECL)</contributorName>
      <nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="DOI">10.17616/R3V644</nameIdentifier>
    </contributor>
  </contributors>
  <rightsList>
    <rights rightsURI="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/us/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 United States [CC BY-NC-SA 3.0]</rights>
  </rightsList>
  <relatedIdentifiers>
    <relatedIdentifier relatedIdentifierType="DOI" relationType="IsCitedBy">10.1016/j.gca.2013.01.010</relatedIdentifier>
  </relatedIdentifiers>
  <descriptions>
    <description descriptionType="Abstract">This data set archives several years data of flow-through column experiments exploring the largely unknown effects of mineral spatial distribution on dissolution rates using columns packed with the same magnesite mass but with different distributions within a quartz matrix. Variables include the spatial distribution of the reactive mineral magnesite, orientation of the magnesite zone to the main flow direction, length scale, flow rates, and size contrast between magnesite and quartz grains. The columns with lengths varying from 5 to 22 cm were flushed with acidic solutions (pH 4.0) at flow velocities varying from 0.015 to 7.2 m/d. The largest rate difference was observed between a Mixed column containing uniformly distributed magnesite and a One-zone column containing magnesite in one cylindrical zone in the center of the column (flow-parallel One-zone column). Breakthrough data show that the zonation in the One-zone columns, especially when the grain sizes of magnesite are smaller than that of the quartz, limits magnesite dissolution by a factor of 1.5  4.0 compared to the Mixed column. The magnitude of the rate difference increases with increasing flow rates. Under low flow rate conditions, the pore fluids reach chemical equilibrium and reaction kinetics does not play an important role. For those conditions, the mineral distribution does not make a difference. Under high flow conditions, however, the effects of the mineral distribution are maximized because column-scale rates exhibit kinetic control due to low residence times. The rate differences between the Mixed and the flow-parallel One-zone cases are much larger than the 14% maximum difference observed between the Mixed column and the flow-perpendicular One-zone column. Thedata set identifies general principles that govern mineral dissolution rates in heterogeneous porous media. It will advance our models of the multi-component geochemical reactions in natural, heterogeneous porous media and will provide valuable insights on the laboratory-field rate discrepancy.</description>
    <description descriptionType="Other">magnesite, spatial distribution, dissolution, reaction rate, column experiment</description>
  </descriptions>
</resource>
