<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-mcm.42.6" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0  http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
            <allow>
                <principal>uid=MCM,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
                <permission>all</permission>
            </allow>
            <allow>
                <principal>public</principal>
                <permission>read</permission>
            </allow>
        </access>
<dataset>
<shortName>limno_bacteria</shortName>
<title>Bacterial Production (Thymidine Uptake) in McMurdo Dry Valley Lakes</title>
<creator>
 <individualName>
   <givenName>John</givenName>
   <surName>Priscu</surName>
 </individualName>
 <address>
  <deliveryPoint> Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
  <deliveryPoint>309 Lewis Hall</deliveryPoint>
  <deliveryPoint>   Montana State University </deliveryPoint>
  <city>Bozeman</city>
  <administrativeArea>MT</administrativeArea>
  <postalCode> 59717</postalCode>
  <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(406)994-3250</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>jpriscu@montana.edu</electronicMailAddress>
</creator>
<metadataProvider>
 <organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
 <address>
  <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
  <deliveryPoint>University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
  <deliveryPoint>MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
  <city>Albuquerque</city>
  <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
  <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
  <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">505-277-3418</phone>
 <phone phonetype="fax">505-277-0304</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>mcmdata@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
</metadataProvider>
<abstract>
   <section>
     <para>An important part of the McMurdo Long Term Ecological Research (LTER) is monitoring of spatial and temporal patterns, and processes thatcontrol bacterial production in perennial ice-covered lakes. This data setquantifies thymidine uptake by bacteria and can be used to estimatebacterial production.</para>
   </section>
</abstract>
<keywordSet>
  <keyword keywordType="theme"> lake</keyword>
  <keyword keywordType="theme"> limnology</keyword>
  <keyword keywordType="theme"> thymidine</keyword>
  <keyword keywordType="theme"> bacteria</keyword>
  <keyword keywordType="theme"> production</keyword>
  <keyword keywordType="theme"> Antarctica</keyword>
  <keyword keywordType="place">McMurdo Dry Valleys</keyword>
  <keyword keywordType="theme">MCM</keyword>
</keywordSet>
<additionalInfo>
            <section>
                <title>Comments</title>
                <para>
                    <literalLayout> The energy of activation was experimentally derived for Lake
                        Bonney (Priscu, unpublished). If the average of the kill treatment uptake
                        exceeds live treatment uptake, uptake is reported as zero.</literalLayout>
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Citations</title>
                <para>
                    <literalLayout> </literalLayout>
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Notes</title>
                <para>
                    <literalLayout> Data contained in these files has been subjected to quality
                        control standards imposed by the investigator. The user of this data should
                        be aware that, while efforts have been taken to ensure that these data are
                        of the highest quality, there is no guarantee of perfection for the data
                        contained herein and the possibility of errors exists. If you encounter
                        questionable data, please contact the MCM LTER data manager corrected or
                        qualified. Thus, these data may be modified and future data will be
                        appended.</literalLayout>
                </para>
            </section>
        </additionalInfo>
<intellectualRights>
            <section>
                <title>MCM LTER data may be used freely with the following restrictions:</title>
                <para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                <literalLayout>The Principal Investigator be sent a notice stating
                                    reasons for acquiring any data and a description of the
                                    publication intentions. </literalLayout>
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                <literalLayout>The Principal Investigator of the data set be sent a
                                    copy of the report or manuscript prior to submission and be
                                    adequately cited in any resultant publications.</literalLayout>
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                <literalLayout>A copy of any resultant publications should be sent
                                    to the McMurdo data manager and principal
                                investigator.</literalLayout>
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                <literalLayout>The end-user follow the guidelines set forth in the
                                    LTER Network Data Access Policy, Data Access Requirements, and
                                    General Data Use Agreement found at
                                    http://www.mcmlter.org/data_guidelines.htm</literalLayout>
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            </section>
        </intellectualRights>
<distribution>
            <online>
                <url>http://www.mcmlter.org/queries/limno_results.jsp?begDate=01/01/0001&amp;endDate=01/01/3000&amp;dataType=BACT_PROD</url>
            </online>
        </distribution>
<coverage>
            <geographicCoverage>
                <geographicDescription> Samples were collected from the East Lake Bonney, West Lake
                    Bonney, Lake Hoare, and Lake Fryxell limnological sampling stations, located in
                    the McMurdo Dry Valleys of Antarctica.</geographicDescription>
                
                <boundingCoordinates>
                    <westBoundingCoordinate>162</westBoundingCoordinate>
                    <eastBoundingCoordinate>163.6</eastBoundingCoordinate>
                    <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.2</northBoundingCoordinate>
                    <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.8</southBoundingCoordinate>
                    
                    <boundingAltitudes>
                        <altitudeMinimum>0</altitudeMinimum>
                        <altitudeMaximum>1000</altitudeMaximum>
                        <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
                    </boundingAltitudes>
                </boundingCoordinates>
            </geographicCoverage>
            <temporalCoverage>
                <rangeOfDates>
                    <beginDate>
                        <calendarDate>1993</calendarDate>
                    </beginDate>
                    <endDate>
                        <calendarDate>2006</calendarDate>
                    </endDate>
                </rangeOfDates>
            </temporalCoverage>
        </coverage>
<maintenance>
            <description>
                <section>
                    <para>
                        <literalLayout> Data from this table was submitted to INSTAAR by John
                            Priscu's team at Montana State University. The raw data files listed
                            under 'file name' are the names of the original files submitted. The
                            1993/94 and 1994/95 datasets are Microsoft Excel version 6.0 files, and
                            the 1995/96, 1996/97 and 1997/98 datasets are ascii text files. Upon
                            arrival at INSTAAR, the data manager fine-tuned the location codes and
                            limno runs to match those provided in the "locations, dates, codes for
                            lake chemistry, biology samples" file. The file was imported into
                            Microsoft Access on INSTAAR's Unix system, and can currently be found
                            there. The file was then exported in ascii, comma delimited text and
                            MS-DOS text (table layout) on the MCM LTER web site. Both of these files
                            are linked to this web page above. Information for the metadata was
                            obtained from the Metatdr9697.rtf file. The file was called up using
                            Microsoft Word version 6.0. Text from this file was used to create this
                            page in html format.</literalLayout>
                    </para>
                </section>
                <section><para>Per A. Chiuchiolo and J. Priscu suggestion, 4 columns were added to the data table to reflect new methodologies: Starting season 06/07, we included Leucine measurements in our bacterial production assay, and we also started a new method and did comparisons with the old method.</para></section>
            </description>
        </maintenance>
<contact>
<organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
  <address>
 <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Albuquerque</city>
   <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">505-277-3418</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">505-277-0304</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>mcmdata@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        </contact>
<publisher>
<organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
  <address>
 <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Albuquerque</city>
   <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">505-277-3418</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">505-277-0304</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>mcmdata@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        </publisher>
<methods>
   <methodStep>
       <description>
         <para>Lake water samples were collected at specific depths with a five-liter Niskin bottle during normal LTER limnological sampling. Sub-samples were decanted into three 1-L Nalgene bottles (2-light and 1-amber), two-500 mL amber Nalgene bottles, three-150 mL borosilicate glass bottles, two-20 mL scintillation vials, and one-30 mL serum vial. Five-20 mL scintillation vials (3-live treatments, 2-kill treatments) were prepared at each depth for TDR analysis. TDR samples (10 mL) were taken from the one-liter amber Nalgene bottle and placed in each scintillation vial. 0.5 mL filtered formalin (0.2 micro m) was pipetted into each killed treatment vial. 3H Thymidine was pipetted into each vial (final concentration of 20 nM thymidine), first the live treatments and then the kill treatments. Samples were incubated in the dark at 1-4 degC for 20 hours (thymidine incorporation has been shown to be linear for 20 hours under these conditions, Priscu unpublished). At the end of the incubation period 10 mL of ice cold 10 percent TCA was added to stop thymidine uptake and precipitate nucleotides. Vials were stored at 4 degC until filtered. Each sample was filtered through a 0.2 micro m Nucleopore polycarbonate membrane filter. Both the scintillation vial and filter tower were rinsed three times with 5 percent TCA. Each filter was placed into a new scintillation vial and 15 mL of Cytoscint cocktail was added. Samples were counted with a pre-calibrated (3H) liquid scintillation counter. </para>
         <para>Thymidine uptake rate (TDR nM d-1) was calculated using the following equation:</para>
         <para><literalLayout> nM TDR/day = (DPML - DPMK) * a /(alpha * t) </literalLayout></para>
         <para>where DPML is the average dpm for the live treatment, DPMK is the average dpm for the kill treatment, a is the final concentration of thymidine in each vial (20nM), alpha is the total dpm added to each vial, and t is the incubation period. </para>
         <para>The thymidine uptake rate was adjusted to the ambient lake temperature using the Arrhenius equation:</para>
         <para>
          <literalLayout> TDRadj = TDR * e^(Ea (( 1 / (CI + 273 K)) - ( 1 / (CA + 273K))) / R ) </literalLayout>
         </para>
         <para> where Ea is the energy of activation (12,600 cal mol-1, Q10 = 2.2), degCI is the incubation temperature (degC), degCA is the ambient lake water temperature at specific depth, and R is a gas constant (1.987 cal mol-1 K-1).</para>
         <para>During the 0607 season, the Priscu group did a comparison of the "filtration method" used in previous seasons (see above and also Appendix 6.11 "Previously used Methods" of the Limnological Methods Manual; Takacs, C.T. and J.C. Priscu. 1998. Bacterioplankton dynamics in the McMurdo Dry Valley lakes: Production and biomass loss over four seasons. Microbial Ecology 36:239-250), with the "centrifugation method" used by the Palmer (PAL) LTER (Fuhrman, J. A. and F. Azam. 1982. Thymidine incorporation as a measure of heterotrophic bacterioplankton production in marine surface waters: evaluation and field results. Marine Biology 66:109-120). Results showed no significant difference between the two methods (ELB 0-20 m: mean and standard deviation of nM TDR/d determined via filtration method, 0.0114 and 0.0097, respectively; mean and standard deviation of nM TDR/d determined via centrifugation method, 0.0129 and 0.0131, respectively; paired t-test T value, -1.063; P value, 0.328). We therefore continued measurement of bacterial production in seasons following the 0607 season using the centrifugation method.  We also complemented our thymidine data with 3H-leucine incorporation data, as is done in the PAL LTER, for selected seasons for comparative purposes. </para>
         <para>The new method via centrifugation is as follows:</para>
         <para>Lake water samples were collected at specific depths with a five-liter Niskin bottle during normal LTER limnological sampling. Sub-samples were decanted into two 1-L Nalgene bottles (amber). Five-2 mL microcentrifuge tubes (3-live treatments, 2-kill treatments) were prepared at each depth for TDR or Leu analysis. 3H Thymidine or Leucine was pipetted into each live treatment tube (final concentration of 20 nM). Samples (1.5 mL) were taken from a one-liter amber Nalgene bottle and placed in each tube (both live and kill treatments). Live tubes were capped, inverted several times, and incubated in the dark at 1-4 deg C for 20 hours (thymidine incorporation has been shown to be linear for 20 hours under these conditions, Priscu unpublished). 100 micro L of ice cold 100 percent TCA was added to each kill treatment tube. Tubes were capped, inverted several times, and placed on ice for 15 minutes. 3H Thymidine or Leucine was pipetted into each kill treatment tube (final concentration of 20 nM). Tubes were capped and incubated in the dark at 1-4 deg C for 20 hours. At the end of the incubation period, 100 micro L of ice cold 100 percent TCA was added to the live treatment tubes to stop thymidine or leucine uptake and precipitate nucleotides. Samples were inverted and placed on ice for 15-30 minutes. All tubes were stored at 4 deg C until processing. Each sample was centrifuged at 14,000 (~15,000 x g) for 15 minutes. Supernatant was poured out and tube was tapped to get the last drops out of the tube. 1 ml of cold 5 percent TCA was added to each tube. Tubes were re-spun for 5 minutes, supernatant poured out, and tube tapped to get the last drops out. 1 ml of cold 80 percent ethanol was added to each tube. Tubes were re-spun for 5 minutes, supernatant poured out, and tube tapped to get the last drops out. Tubes were dried overnight in fume hood with caps off. 1 ml of Cytoscint ES scintillation cocktail was added to each tube, tubes were vortexed, and samples were counted with a pre-calibrated (3H) liquid scintillation counter. </para>
         <para>Thymidine or Leucine uptake rate (TDR or Leu nM d-1) was calculated using the following equation:</para>
         <para><literalLayout>nM TDR or Leu day -1 = ((DPML - DPMK) * a) / (alpha * t)</literalLayout></para>
         <para>where DPML is the average dpm for the live treatment, DPMK is the average dpm for the kill treatment, a is the final concentration of thymidine in each vial (20nM), alpha is the total dpm added to each vial, and t is the incubation period. </para>
         <para>The thymidine or leucine uptake rate was adjusted to the ambient lake temperature using the Arrhenius equation:</para>
         <para><literalLayout>TDR or LEU adj = TDR or Leu * e^(Ea (( 1 / (CI + 273 K)) - ( 1 / (CA + 273 K))) / R ) </literalLayout></para>
         <para>where Ea is the energy of activation (12,600 cal mol-1, Q10 = 2.2), degCI is the incubation temperature (degC), degCA is the ambient lake water temperature (degC) at specific depth, and R is a gas constant (1.987 cal mol-1 K-1).</para>
        </description>
    </methodStep>
</methods>
<dataTable>         
   <entityName>LIMNO_BACT_PROD_Units_And_Column_Descriptions</entityName>
            <physical>
                <objectName>LIMNO_BACT_PROD_Units_And_Column_Descriptions</objectName>
                <dataFormat>
                    <textFormat>
                        <numHeaderLines>28</numHeaderLines>
                        <numFooterLines>1</numFooterLines>
<recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter>
                        <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
                        <simpleDelimited>
                            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
                            <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
                        </simpleDelimited>
                    </textFormat>
                </dataFormat>
<distribution>
<online>
<url function="download">http://www.mcmlter.org/queries/limno_results.jsp?begDate=01/01/0001&amp;endDate=01/01/3000&amp;dataType=BACT_PROD</url>
</online>
</distribution>
            </physical>
            <attributeList>
                <attribute>
                    <attributeName>DATASET_CODE</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Code to ID the data table</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Code to ID the data table</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                    <missingValueCode>
                        <code>Required entry</code>
                        <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
                    </missingValueCode>
                </attribute>
                <attribute>
                    <attributeName>LIMNO_RUN</attributeName>
                    <attributeLabel>Limno Run</attributeLabel>
                    <attributeDefinition>Code for lake's sampling location and date</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Code for lake's sampling location and
                                    date</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                    <missingValueCode>
                        <code>Required entry</code>
                        <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
                    </missingValueCode>
                </attribute>
                <attribute>
                    <attributeName>LOCATION NAME</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Name of lake where measurement was made</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Name of lake where measurement was made</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                    <missingValueCode>
                        <code>Required entry</code>
                        <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
                    </missingValueCode>
                </attribute>
                <attribute>
                    <attributeName>LOCATION CODE</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Code for site where measurement was made</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Code for site where measurement was
                                    made</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                    <missingValueCode>
                        <code>Required entry</code>
                        <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
                    </missingValueCode>
                </attribute>
                <attribute>
                    <attributeName>DATE_TIME</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Date on which sample was gathered</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="Date" />
                    <measurementScale>
                        <dateTime>
                          <formatString>mm/dd/yyyy</formatString>
                         </dateTime>
                    </measurementScale>
                    <missingValueCode>
                        <code>Required entry</code>
                        <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
                    </missingValueCode>
                </attribute>
                <attribute>
                    <attributeName>DEPTH (m)</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Distance below ice from which sample was drawn</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>1</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                                <bounds>
                                    <minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum>
                                    <maximum exclusive="false">25</maximum>
                                </bounds>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                    <missingValueCode>
                        <code>Required entry</code>
                        <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
                    </missingValueCode>
                </attribute>
                <attribute>
                    <attributeName>TDR (nM TDR/d)</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Thymidine uptake rate using tritiated thymidine and the filtration method.</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <customUnit>nMTDR/day</customUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>0.001</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                                <bounds>
                                    <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                                    <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
                                </bounds>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                    <missingValueCode>
                        <code>Null</code>
                        <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
                    </missingValueCode>
                </attribute>
                <attribute>
                    <attributeName>TDR COMMENTS</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Helpful hints about the sample</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Helpful hints about the sample</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                    <missingValueCode>
                        <code>Null</code>
                        <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
                    </missingValueCode>
                </attribute>
                <attribute>
                    <attributeName>FILE NAME</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Name of file in which data was submitted</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Name of file in which data was
                                    submitted</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                    <missingValueCode>
                        <code>Null</code>
                        <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
                    </missingValueCode>
                </attribute>
                <attribute>
                    <attributeName>DEPTH MASL</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Depth referred to the Sea level. Distance below Mean Average Sea water level reference from which sample was drawn</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>     
                                <standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
                            </unit>   
                            <precision>1</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                            </numericDomain>   
                        </ratio>       
                    </measurementScale>  
                </attribute>
                <attribute>
                    <attributeName>TDR CENT (nM TDR/day)</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Thymidine uptake rate using tritiated thymidine and the centrifugation method.</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <customUnit>nMTDR/day</customUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>0.001</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                                <bounds>
                                    <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                                    <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
                                </bounds>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                    <missingValueCode>
                        <code>Null</code>
                        <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
                    </missingValueCode>
                </attribute>
                <attribute>
                    <attributeName>TDR CENT COMMENTS</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Helpful hints about the sample</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Helpful hints about the sample</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                    <missingValueCode>
                        <code>Null</code>
                        <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
                    </missingValueCode>
                </attribute>
                <attribute>
                    <attributeName>LEU CENT (nM Leu/day)</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Leucine uptake rate using tritiated leucine and the centrifugation method</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <customUnit>nM Leu/day</customUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>0.001</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                                <bounds>
                                    <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                                    <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
                                </bounds>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                    <missingValueCode>
                        <code>Null</code>
                        <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
                    </missingValueCode>
                </attribute>
                <attribute>
                    <attributeName>LEU CENT COMMENTS</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Helpful hints about the sample</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Helpful hints about the sample</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                    <missingValueCode>
                        <code>Null</code>
                        <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
                    </missingValueCode>
                </attribute>
            </attributeList>
        </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
<metadata>
<unitList>
   <unit id="nMTDR/day" />
   <unit id="nM Leu/day" />
</unitList>
</metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>