<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-nin.16384.3" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 c:/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><alternateIdentifier>LTER.NIN.MET.txt</alternateIdentifier><shortName>knb-lter-nin.16384.2</shortName><title>Meteorological data for North Inlet.</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation><givenName>F.</givenName><givenName>John</givenName><surName>Vernberg</surName></individualName></creator><creator scope="document"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation><givenName>B.</givenName><surName>Kjerfve</surName></individualName></creator><creator scope="document"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation><givenName>W.</givenName><givenName>K.</givenName><surName>Michener</surName></individualName></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint><city>Albuquerque</city><administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea><postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">505 277 2535</phone><phone phonetype="fax">505 277 2541</phone><electronicMailAddress>dman@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></metadataProvider><pubDate>2006</pubDate><language>english</language><abstract><para><literalLayout>The purpose of the meteorological weather station is:
     To archive weather data for the North Inlet Estuary LTER site;
     For short and long-term studies at North Inlet, and for comparisons
     to other LTER sites.</literalLayout></para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">weather</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">meteorology</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">North Inlet Estuary</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">Baruch Institute</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">Georgetown, South Carolina</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><title>LTER Network Data Access Requirements</title><para><literalLayout>The access to all LTER data is subject to requirements set forth by this policy document to enable data providers to track usage, evaluate its impact in the community, and confirm users' acceptance of the terms of acceptable use. These requirements are standardized across the LTER Network to provide contractual exchange of data between Site Data Providers, Network Data Providers, and Data Users that can be encoded into electronic form and exchanged between computers. This will allow direct access to data via a common portal once these requirements have been fulfilled. The following information may be required directly or by proxy prior to the transference of any data object:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Registration</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Name</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Affiliation</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Email address</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Full Contact Info</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptance of the General Public Use Agreement or Restricted Data Use Agreement, as applicable</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>A Statement of Intended Use that is compliant with the above agreements. Such statements may be made submitted explicitly or made implicitly via the data access portal interface.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section><section><title>Conditions of Data Use</title><para><literalLayout>The re-use of scientific data has the potential to greatly increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines, and thus is fostered, supported and encouraged. Permission to use this dataset is granted to the Data User free of charge subject to the following terms:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptable Use. Use of the dataset will be restricted to academic, research, educational, government, recreational, or other not-for-profit professional purposes. The Data User is permitted to produce and distribute derived works from this dataset provided that they are released under the same license terms as those accompanying this Data Set. Any other uses for the Data Set or its derived products will require explicit permission from the dataset owner.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Redistribution. The data are provided for use by the Data User. The metadata and this license must accompany all copies made and be available to all users of this Data Set. The Data User will not redistribute the original Data Set beyond this collaboration sphere.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Citation. It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Data Set in any publications or in the metadata of any derived data products that were produced using the Data Set. Citation should take the following general form: Creator, Year of Data Publication, Title of Dataset, Publisher, Dataset identifier.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acknowledgement. The Data User should acknowledge any institutional support or specific funding awards referenced in the metadata accompanying this dataset in any publications where the Data Set contributed significantly to its content. Acknowledgements should identify the supporting party, the party that received the support, and any identifying information such as grant numbers.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Notification. The Data User will notify the Data Set Contact when any derivative work or publication based on or derived from the Data Set is distributed. The Data User will provide the data contact with two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the Data Set and will provide copies, or on-line access to, any derived digital products. Notification will include an explanation of how the Data Set was used to produce the derived work.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Collaboration. The Data Set has been released in the spirit of open scientific collaboration. Data Users are thus strongly encouraged to consider consultation, collaboration and/or co-authorship with the Data Set Creator.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist><literalLayout>By accepting this Data Set, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. The Data Owner shall have the right to terminate this agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Disclaimer</title><para><literalLayout>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation contained in this Data Set, complete accuracy of data and metadata cannot be guaranteed. All data and metadata are made available "as is". The Data User holds all parties involved in the production or distribution of the Data Set harmless for damages resulting from its use or interpretation.</literalLayout></para></section></intellectualRights><distribution id="distributionReference" scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-nin.16384.3&amp;urlTail=nin_met_1989.txt</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage id="geoReference" scope="document"><geographicDescription>North Inlet encompasses about 2,630 hectares of tidal marshes and wetlands near Georgetown, South Carolina, USA. North Inlet-Winyah Bay features high quality, ocean-dominated waters and salt marshes in North Inlet, contrasting with the brackish waters and marshes of Winyah Bay. The bay estuary is dominated by riverine discharges from a watershed impacted by agricultural, municipal and industrial development. Former rice fields  and canals provide another system for study within the Reserve. The Debidue site is located at the confluence of Town Creek and Debidue Creek. The Bread and Butter site is located along the western shoreline of Town Creek adjacent to the mouth of Clambank Creek.   
     Oyster Landing in Crab Haul creek within the NORTH INLET ESTUARY SYSTEM Georgetown, South Carolina.  33,20 lat. 79,11 long.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-79.2936</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-79.1042</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>33.357</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>33.2125</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReference" scope="document"><singleDateTime><calendarDate>1983</calendarDate></singleDateTime></temporalCoverage></coverage><maintenance><description><section><title>Entry verification</title><para><literalLayout>Pre Sept. 21, 1989     Data were edited on a daily basis from the LA50 80 character printout.       When the Magnetic tape is read, the data were processed through the     program "Metclean", which cleans and reformats the data.  A number of     error checking routines were performed within this program.  These data     were then written to an ascii file and visually checked for errors that     could have occurred during uploading.     Oct. 14 1989 through Dec. 31 1990     The National Center for Atmospheric Research, Boulder, CO. was responsible     for data acquisition and verification during this period.  A temporary     Meteorological Station was loaned to the Baruch Institute by NCAR after     Hurricane Hugo.     Post Dec. 30, 1990     Data were down loaded once a week from the data logger that is stored     in the NEMA enclosure on the met station tower at Oyster Landing.     These data were then visually edited to identify any errors.  The     data were then formatted to be consistent with the preexisting data     sets. Data were transferred in six month blocks to a SUN workstation     and then archived on 8mm tapes.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Data last update while at North Inlet</title><para><literalLayout>This data set was last updated Oct. 1992</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Data last archive date while at North Inlet</title><para><literalLayout>October 1992</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Last Modification at LTER Network Office</title><para><literalLayout>Data files format was converted from delimited to comma separated. Data was revised for consistency, agreement with metadata. Date: November 2006</literalLayout></para></section></description></maintenance><contact scope="document"><organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint><city>Albuquerque</city><administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea><postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">505 277 2535</phone><phone phonetype="fax">505 277 2541</phone><electronicMailAddress>dman@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint><city>Albuquerque</city><administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea><postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">505 277 2535</phone><phone phonetype="fax">505 277 2541</phone><electronicMailAddress>dman@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></publisher><pubPlace>Long Term Ecological Research Network Office</pubPlace><methods><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Pre Sept. 21, 1989

     The meteorological system which was in place prior to Hurricane Hugo at
     the Baruch Marine Laboratory was designed by the Climatronics Corporation
     of Bohemia, NY. (Job number 7244 on March 3, 1982).  The system consisted
     of a remote meteorological system with telemetry and an IMP 803 cassette
     data acquisition system.

     System Description

     The system was designed to measure and transmit wind speed, wind 
     direction, air temperature, barometric pressure, solar radiation, 
     precipitation, water level, water temperature and conductivity data.
     This consisted of the following components:

         Remote Site

     1.  Wind Speed and Direction sensors with cross arm
            Climatronics Wind Mark III  
     2.  Naturally Aspirated Temperature Shield w/
            YSI 703 -  Dual Element Air Temperature Thermistor
     3.  Solar Radiation sensor with mount
            Eppley radiometer
     4.  Barometric Pressure sensor
            YSI transducer
     5.  Precipitation Gage
            Belfort Instruments tipping bucket gauge
     6.  Water Depth
             Enviro-Labs Water Level sensor
     7.  Water Temperature
             YSI 701 - Water Temperature Thermistor
     8.  Conductivity Meter
             YSI Conductivity Sensor, glass conductivity cell and
             temperature compensator
     9.  Remote Meteorological System mainframe in a NEMA
         environmental Enclosure (with mounting hardware),
         housing the following equipment: 
           signal conditioning electronics, Modem Transmitter,
           conductivity meter and line protectors.
     10. 10 Meter Aluminum Tower with guying kit
     11. Cables, connectors and a sensor mounting boom



     The system was configured as follows:
     The wind cross arm was mounted to the 4 foot extension mast located
     at the top of the tower.  The temperature shield and solar radiation
     sensor were mounted on a tower boom near the top of the tower.  The
     precipitation gage was mounted on a level surface approximately 20
     meters from the tower base.  The barometric pressure sensor was mounted
     inside of the NEMA enclosure .  The water temperature, water level and
     conductivity cables were placed in a rigid PVC well in the water.

     All of the sensor cables were wired through the signal line
     protector except the conductivity cell.  The remote meteorological
     site's NEMA enclosure housed the signal conditioning electronics,
     the conductivity meter, an AC/DC converter and a battery back-up
     pack.

         Base Site

     1.  Pre-wired Instrument Cabinet containing a mainframe with a power
         supply and Modem Receiver, a multiplexing (MUX) recorder and
         an IMP-803 Microprocessor based Cassette Data Acquisition System.
     2.  2,500 feet of telemetry cable.

     All sensors were scanned once per second except the following:
     Wind Direction -  Mean of 120 scans per hour
     Water Level, Precipitation - instantaneous values at the time indicated

     These readings are 24 hours per day, every day of the year beginning
     June 3, 1982 except when individual probes or the entire meteorological
     station was down.


                               *** NOTE ***
                      Sept. 21, 1989 through Dec. 31 1990
                     NCAR Temporary Meteorological Station
     
     The Meteorological system used during this time period was
     borrowed from the National Center for Atmospheric Research, Boulder
     Colorado. NCAR designed and built the system.  This system sent
     a signal every 15 minutes by satellite to a computer at NCAR in
     Boulder, CO.  Once there, the data were recorded to tapes.  These
     tapes were then sent to the Baruch Marine Laboratory. The data were
     reformatted and downloaded by the University of South Carolina,     Computer Services Division.

     The NCAR system was designed tomeasure and transmit windspeed, wind direction, dry air temperature, wet air temperature,
     barometric pressure, solar radiation, precipitation, Dew Point,
     and Relative Humidity data.


     Post Dec. 31, 1990

     The current meteorological system was designed by Climatronics
     Corp.  It is a Campbell Scientific CR10 measurement and control
     module.  The system was designed to measure and transmit wind speed,
     wind direction, air temperature, barometric pressure, solar
     radiation, precipitation, water level, water temperature and
     conductivity data.  This system consists of the following components.

                                Remote Site

     1.  Wind Speed and Direction sensors with cross arm
            Climatronics Wind Mark III  
     2.  Naturally Aspirated Temperature Shield w/ 
            YSI 703 -  Dual element Air Temperature Thermistor
     3.  Solar Radiation sensor with mount
            Eppley 8-48 radiometer
     4.  Barometric Pressure sensor
            YSI 2014 transducer
     5.  Precipitation Gage
            Sierra-Misco 2500-8 Tipping bucket Precipitation gauge.
            (This sensor has not been installed as of November 1992,
            due to logistic problems with the new sea water lines in the
            board walk.)
     6.  Water Depth
             Keller PSI PT108V-50-15PSI Water Level sensor
     7.  Water Temperature
             YSI 070/44018/NA/RN/300 - Water Temperature Thermistor
     8.  Conductivity Meter
             Rosemont 1181T-00-02-99 Water Conductivity probe.
     9.  Remote Meteorological System mainframe in a NEMA
         environmental enclosure (with mounting hardware),
         housing the following equipment: 
         signal conditioning electronics, modem transmitter,
         conductivity meter and line protectors, CR10 data logger
     10. 10 Meter Aluminum Tower with guying kit
     11. Cables, connectors and a sensor mounting boom.

     As of November 1992:

     Because the field laboratory has not been completely reconstructed,
     the remote phone line has not been installed to the Met station tower.
     Therefore, once a week the storage module that records data is
     retrieved from the field, and the data are downloaded to the
     PC in the data management office using a program called SMCOM,
     written by Campbell Scientific.  These data are reformatted and
     appended to the yearly data set.  The data are archived in six month
     blocks.

     The system is configured as follows:
     The wind cross arm is mounted to the 4 foot extension mast located
     at the top of the tower.  The temperature shield and solar radiation
     sensor are mounted on the tower boom near the top of the tower.  The
     barometric pressure sensor is mounted outside of the NEMA enclosure.
     The water temperature, water level and conductivity cables are placed
     in a rigid PVC well in the water.

     All of the sensor cables are wired through the signal line
     protector.  The remote meteorological site's NEMA enclosure houses
     the Campbell control module, the storage module, the Rosemont
     conductivity transmitter, and a backup 12 volt battery.
     The primary power source is a solar panel.

     All sensors are scanned once a second, and an hourly mean is 
     generated on the hour.  Water Level is the only exception.  On 
     the Raw data, a six minute instantaneous value is recorded. and
     an hourly instantaneous value is recorded on the hour.  The six 
     minute reading is discarded from the final data set.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Experimental Design</title><para><literalLayout>Monitoring of meteorological paramaters at Oyster Landing, North Inlet,
     Georgetown, SC.</literalLayout></para></section></description></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=LNO,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>ALL</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>READ</permission></allow></access><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>knb-lter-nin.16384.2</entityName><entityDescription>data table for project LTER.NIN.MET.txt</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>nin_met_1989.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><references>distributionReference</references></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReference</references></temporalCoverage></coverage><additionalInfo><section><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Variables 7,9,10,11,14,15 are means of 3600 observations per 
     hour.  This mean represents conditions for the preceding hour.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Pre Sept. 21, 1989. Variable 8 represents the mean of 120 
     observations per hour.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Variables 12, 13 represent the instantaneous values at the 
     time indicated.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>When variables 5(hour)=25 and variable 6(minute)=HI, this 
     record represents the instantaneous daily maximum values for 
     variables 7,9,10,11,12,14,15.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>When variables 5(hour)=25 and variable 6(minute)=LO, this 
     record represents the instantaneous daily minimum values for 
     variables 7,9,10,11,12,14,15.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>When variables 5(hour)=25 and variable 6(minutes)=HI, or LO 
     then variable 8 (wind Direction) is not recorded.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>When variables 5(hour)=25 and variable 6(minutes)=HI, or LO 
     the value indicated for variable 13(water Level) only represents 
     the maximum or minimum for the previous 6 minute interval.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section></additionalInfo><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Date</attributeName><attributeLabel>Date</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Date sample was collected</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>YYMMDD</formatString></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Julian Day</attributeName><attributeLabel>Julian day</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Julian day sample was collected</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>(DD)D</formatString></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Time</attributeName><attributeLabel>Time</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Time the sample was collected military format</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>HHMM</formatString></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Wind velocity</attributeName><attributeLabel>Wind Velocity</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Wind velocity</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>metersPerSecond</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0.0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">50.0</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Wind direction</attributeName><attributeLabel>Wind Direction</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Wind direction</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">540</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Air temperature</attributeName><attributeLabel>Air Temperature</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Temperature of the Air</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">-20</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">50.0</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Water temperature</attributeName><attributeLabel>Water Temperature</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>temperature of the water</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0.0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">50.0</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Solar Radiation</attributeName><attributeLabel>Solar Radiation</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Solar Radiation</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>Langley</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0.0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">50.0</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Precipitation</attributeName><attributeLabel>Precipitation</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Precipitation</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>millimeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0.0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">25.0</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Water level</attributeName><attributeLabel>Water Level</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Water level</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>meter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0.0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">3.0</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Conductivity</attributeName><attributeLabel>Conductivity</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Conductivity</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>miliVoltsPerCentimeter</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0.0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">2.0</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Barometric Pressure</attributeName><attributeLabel>Barometric Pressure</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Barometric Pressure</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>millibar</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">940</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">1040</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><unitList><unit id="Langley" /><unit id="miliVoltsPerCentimeter" /></unitList></additionalMetadata></eml:eml>