<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-nin.2672.3" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 c:/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><alternateIdentifier>LTER.NIN.MEIO.txt</alternateIdentifier><shortName>knb-lter-nin.2672.2</shortName><title>Meiobenthos abundance. Long-term variability and dynamics of estuarine meiobenthic populations (1973-1992).</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation><givenName>Bruce</givenName><surName>Coull</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of South Carolina</organizationName></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint><city>Albuquerque</city><administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea><postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">505 277 2535</phone><phone phonetype="fax">505 277 2541</phone><electronicMailAddress>dman@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></metadataProvider><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Dennis</givenName><givenName>M.</givenName><surName>Allen</surName></individualName><role>Secondary production, invertebrates</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Keith</givenName><surName>Bildstein</surName></individualName><role>Avian dynamics</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Elizabeth</givenName><surName>Blood</surName></individualName><role>Nutrient dynamics</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>William</givenName><givenName>H.</givenName><surName>Conner</surName></individualName><role>Freshwater marshes</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Bruce</givenName><givenName>C.</givenName><surName>Coull</surName></individualName><role>Meiofauna, population dynamics</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Richard</givenName><givenName>F.</givenName><surName>Dame</surName></individualName><role>Primary populations, vascular plants, ecosystem models</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>John</givenName><givenName>M.</givenName><surName>Dean</surName></individualName><role>Fish populations, secondary production</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Donald</givenName><givenName>G.</givenName><surName>Edwards</surName></individualName><role>Statistical evaluation</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Robert</givenName><givenName>J.</givenName><surName>Feller</surName></individualName><role>Population dynamics, secondary production</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Leonard</givenName><givenName>R.</givenName><surName>Gardner</surName></individualName><role>Geochemistry, primary production</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Bjorn</givenName><surName>Kjerfve</surName></individualName><role>Physical oceanography</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Henry</givenName><givenName>N.</givenName><surName>McKeller</surName></individualName><role>Nutrient modeling</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>William</givenName><givenName>K.</givenName><surName>Michener</surName></individualName><role>Data management</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>James</givenName><surName>Morris</surName></individualName><role>Spartina production</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Stephen</givenName><givenName>E.</givenName><surName>Stancyk</surName></individualName><role>Zooplankton</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>F.</givenName><givenName>John</givenName><surName>Vernberg</surName></individualName><role>Physiological ecology</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Thomas</givenName><surName>Williams</surName></individualName><role>Hydrology</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Richard</givenName><givenName>G.</givenName><surName>Zingmark</surName></individualName><role>Primary production, algae</role></associatedParty><pubDate>2006</pubDate><language>english</language><abstract><para><literalLayout>The original purpose of this research was to determine if natural
     meiobenthic assemblages exhibited continuity over time and to monitor
     several physical variables to determine if these influenced long-term
     temporal patterns.  The most recent study focused on variation and the
     relations of meiobenthos abundance with environmental factors over 11
     years.  Typically marine benthic community studies are limited temporally
     and the majority of previously published 'longterm' meiofauna results (all
     taxa) were based on about a year's duration.</literalLayout></para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">meiobenthic assemblages</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">North Inlet Estuary</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">Baruch Institute</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">Georgetown, South Carolina</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><title>LTER Network Data Access Requirements</title><para><literalLayout>The access to all LTER data is subject to requirements set forth by this policy document to enable data providers to track usage, evaluate its impact in the community, and confirm users' acceptance of the terms of acceptable use. These requirements are standardized across the LTER Network to provide contractual exchange of data between Site Data Providers, Network Data Providers, and Data Users that can be encoded into electronic form and exchanged between computers. This will allow direct access to data via a common portal once these requirements have been fulfilled. The following information may be required directly or by proxy prior to the transference of any data object:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Registration</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Name</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Affiliation</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Email address</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Full Contact Info</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptance of the General Public Use Agreement or Restricted Data Use Agreement, as applicable</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>A Statement of Intended Use that is compliant with the above agreements. Such statements may be made submitted explicitly or made implicitly via the data access portal interface.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section><section><title>Conditions of Data Use</title><para><literalLayout>The re-use of scientific data has the potential to greatly increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines, and thus is fostered, supported and encouraged. Permission to use this dataset is granted to the Data User free of charge subject to the following terms:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptable Use. Use of the dataset will be restricted to academic, research, educational, government, recreational, or other not-for-profit professional purposes. The Data User is permitted to produce and distribute derived works from this dataset provided that they are released under the same license terms as those accompanying this Data Set. Any other uses for the Data Set or its derived products will require explicit permission from the dataset owner.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Redistribution. The data are provided for use by the Data User. The metadata and this license must accompany all copies made and be available to all users of this Data Set. The Data User will not redistribute the original Data Set beyond this collaboration sphere.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Citation. It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Data Set in any publications or in the metadata of any derived data products that were produced using the Data Set. Citation should take the following general form: Creator, Year of Data Publication, Title of Dataset, Publisher, Dataset identifier.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acknowledgement. The Data User should acknowledge any institutional support or specific funding awards referenced in the metadata accompanying this dataset in any publications where the Data Set contributed significantly to its content. Acknowledgements should identify the supporting party, the party that received the support, and any identifying information such as grant numbers.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Notification. The Data User will notify the Data Set Contact when any derivative work or publication based on or derived from the Data Set is distributed. The Data User will provide the data contact with two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the Data Set and will provide copies, or on-line access to, any derived digital products. Notification will include an explanation of how the Data Set was used to produce the derived work.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Collaboration. The Data Set has been released in the spirit of open scientific collaboration. Data Users are thus strongly encouraged to consider consultation, collaboration and/or co-authorship with the Data Set Creator.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist><literalLayout>By accepting this Data Set, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. The Data Owner shall have the right to terminate this agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Disclaimer</title><para><literalLayout>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation contained in this Data Set, complete accuracy of data and metadata cannot be guaranteed. All data and metadata are made available "as is". The Data User holds all parties involved in the production or distribution of the Data Set harmless for damages resulting from its use or interpretation.</literalLayout></para></section></intellectualRights><distribution id="distributionReference" scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-nin.2672.3&amp;urlTail=nin_meio_1972.txt</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage id="geoReference" scope="document"><geographicDescription>North Inlet encompasses about 2,630 hectares of tidal marshes and wetlands near Georgetown, South Carolina, USA. North Inlet-Winyah Bay features high quality, ocean-dominated waters and salt marshes in North Inlet, contrasting with the brackish waters and marshes of Winyah Bay. The bay estuary is dominated by riverine discharges from a watershed impacted by agricultural, municipal and industrial development. Former rice fields  and canals provide another system for study within the Reserve. The Debidue site is located at the confluence of Town Creek and Debidue Creek. The Bread and Butter site is located along the western shoreline of Town Creek adjacent to the mouth of Clambank Creek.   
     The study site is the North Inlet marsh, a 3000 hectare high salinity
     estuary dominated by Spartina alterniflora, located approximately 6 km 
     east of Georgetown, South Carolina.  The marsh is bordered on the east by
     two barrier islands; on the south by a larger brackish estuary, Winyah 
     Bay; and on the west and north by a mixed oak-pine forested peninsula.

     Debidue Site (DD) - Debidue is a sand-bottomed site located 
     approximately .5 km inside the Inlet mouth adjacent to the confluence of
     two major marsh creeks, Debidue and Town Creeks. The site is at the lower
     end of an extensive sand bar and is subject to strong current and wave
     action.

     Bread and Butter Site (BB) - This site is located on a muddy subtidal bank 
     of Bread and Butter Creek, about 100 m inside the mouth of this medium 
     sized creek.  The creek is 1.5 km SW of the Debidue site in the center of
     the marsh.  The creek is 10 m wide at low tide at the sample site and is
     sheltered from strong current and wave action.  The creek is lined with 
     mud banks and oyster bars and the sediment at the sampling site is fine,
     silty mud.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-79.2936</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-79.1042</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>33.357</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>33.2125</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReference" scope="document"><singleDateTime><calendarDate>1972</calendarDate></singleDateTime></temporalCoverage></coverage><maintenance><description><section><title>Entry verification</title><para><literalLayout>Verification was performed at the input step using a program       which creates a hardcopy to compare against the original sheets.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Data last update while at North Inlet</title><para><literalLayout>December 12, 1992</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Data last archive date while at North Inlet</title><para><literalLayout>December 12, 1992</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Last Modification at LTER Network Office</title><para><literalLayout>Data files format was converted from delimited to comma separated. Data was revised for consistency, agreement with metadata. Date: November 2006</literalLayout></para></section></description></maintenance><contact scope="document"><organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint><city>Albuquerque</city><administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea><postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">505 277 2535</phone><phone phonetype="fax">505 277 2541</phone><electronicMailAddress>dman@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint><city>Albuquerque</city><administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea><postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">505 277 2535</phone><phone phonetype="fax">505 277 2541</phone><electronicMailAddress>dman@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></publisher><pubPlace>Long Term Ecological Research Network Office</pubPlace><methods><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Each core sample was extruded and immediately fixed in 10 percent borax-buffered
     formalin with Rose Bengal.  Salinity was measured by refractometer and Eh
     (September 1972 - December 1976) by platinum electrode.  Oxidizable 
     organic matter was determined using the wet dichromate method (Walkley and
     Black 1934). Granulometric parameters were measured by wet sieving through
     phi series sieves to 63 micrometers, and drying and weighing the sediment
     retained on the sieves.  An aliquot of the material passing the 63
     micrometer sieve was removed for pipette analysis (Folk 1968).  Sorting
     coefficient was calculated using methods by Trask (1932).

     Mud samples were extracted using Ludox centrifugation (de Jonge and Bowmann
     1977); the sand samples by the shaking-supernatant technique of Wieser
     (1960).  All animals retained on a 63 micrometer sieve were enumerated to
     major taxon; every copepod and every 4th nematode was removed for species
     identification. Since all sorted samples were formalin fixed, soft-bodied
     taxa abundance (e.g. gastrotrichs, turbellarians, ciliates) was probably
     underestimated (Hulings and Gray 1971).  Ciliates may have been further
     underestimated since the samples were collected on a 63 micrometer sieve;
     thus only the larger ciliates (e.g. Tracheloraphis spp.) were retained.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Experimental Design</title><para><literalLayout>The study sites (1 sand, 1 mud) in North Inlet, South Carolina, USA, were
     sampled monthly from January 1973 through December 1980 and every two 
     weeks from January 1981 - December 1983.  At each site 4 replicate core
     samples were taken up to March 1976, 3 replicates from April 1976 -
     December 1980 and 2 replicates from January 1981 December 1983.  All cores
     were taken to the depth of the redox potential discontinuity (RPD);
     typically 1 to 2 centimeters in mud; 4 to 10 centimeters in sand.  Both
     sites are subtidal, located 1 meter below MLW.  Sediment samples were
     collected for organic analysis up to 1978, and for sediment size 
     analysis monthly or quarterly (up to September 1979) and then monthly
     (March - December 1983).  Four data sets were collected to assess potential
     temperature effects: (1) surface-sediment temperature measurements taken 
     at the time of meiofauna sample collection (January 1973 - December 1983);
     (2) minimum and maximum daily air temperature recorded at the Georgetown
     County, SC, Airport from January 1935 - December 1978 (44 yr); (3) daily
     surface water temperatures from the mouth of the North Inlet estuary, June
     1979 - December 1983; (4) heating and cooling degree days data collected 
     at the Charleston Airport, Charleston, SC, December 1968 - April 1984.</literalLayout></para></section></description></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=LNO,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>ALL</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>READ</permission></allow></access><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>knb-lter-nin.2672.2</entityName><entityDescription>data table for project LTER.NIN.MEIO.txt</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>nin_meio_1972.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><references>distributionReference</references></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReference</references></temporalCoverage></coverage><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>date</attributeName><attributeLabel>DATE</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Date sample was obtained</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>MMDDYY</formatString></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>site</attributeName><attributeLabel>SITE</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Site where sample was collected</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>BB</code><definition>Bread and Butter</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>DD</code><definition>Debidue Site</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Nematodes</attributeName><attributeLabel>NEMA</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>density of nematodes</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>1/10cm^2</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Copepods</attributeName><attributeLabel>COPE</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>density of copepods</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>1/10cm^2</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Copepod nauplii</attributeName><attributeLabel>NAUP</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>density of Copepod nauplii</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>1/10cm^2</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Ostracods</attributeName><attributeLabel>OSTR</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Density of Ostracods</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>1/10cm^2</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Gastrotrichs</attributeName><attributeLabel>GAST</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Density of/ Gastrotrichs</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>1/10cm^2</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Ciliates</attributeName><attributeLabel>CILI</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Density of Ciliates</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>1/10cm^2</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Turbelarians</attributeName><attributeLabel>TURB</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Density of Turbelarians</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>1/10cm^2</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Polychaetes</attributeName><attributeLabel>POLY</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Density of Polychaetes</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>1/10cm^2</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Bivalves</attributeName><attributeLabel>BIVA</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Density of bivalves</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>1/10cm^2</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><unitList><unit id="1/10cm^2" /></unitList></additionalMetadata></eml:eml>