<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-nin.8734.3" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 c:/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><alternateIdentifier>LTER.NIN.DWS.txt</alternateIdentifier><shortName>knb-lter-nin.8734.2</shortName><title>Daily Water Sample Nutrient Data for North Inlet.</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation><givenName>F.</givenName><givenName>John</givenName><surName>Vernberg</surName></individualName></creator><creator scope="document"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation><givenName>Elizabeth</givenName><surName>Blood</surName></individualName></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint><city>Albuquerque</city><administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea><postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">505 277 2535</phone><phone phonetype="fax">505 277 2541</phone><electronicMailAddress>dman@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></metadataProvider><pubDate>2006</pubDate><language>english</language><abstract><para><literalLayout>To establish a long term data base on the nutrient dynamics of a salt
     marsh estuarine system.  This data can be used in correlation
     with a number of other estuarine data sets to obtain a broader
     definition of the over all estuarine ecosystem.</literalLayout></para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">nutrient dynamics</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">North Inlet Estuary</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">Baruch Institute</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">Georgetown, South Carolina</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><title>LTER Network Data Access Requirements</title><para><literalLayout>The access to all LTER data is subject to requirements set forth by this policy document to enable data providers to track usage, evaluate its impact in the community, and confirm users' acceptance of the terms of acceptable use. These requirements are standardized across the LTER Network to provide contractual exchange of data between Site Data Providers, Network Data Providers, and Data Users that can be encoded into electronic form and exchanged between computers. This will allow direct access to data via a common portal once these requirements have been fulfilled. The following information may be required directly or by proxy prior to the transference of any data object:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Registration</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Name</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Affiliation</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Email address</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Full Contact Info</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptance of the General Public Use Agreement or Restricted Data Use Agreement, as applicable</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>A Statement of Intended Use that is compliant with the above agreements. Such statements may be made submitted explicitly or made implicitly via the data access portal interface.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section><section><title>Conditions of Data Use</title><para><literalLayout>The re-use of scientific data has the potential to greatly increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines, and thus is fostered, supported and encouraged. Permission to use this dataset is granted to the Data User free of charge subject to the following terms:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptable Use. Use of the dataset will be restricted to academic, research, educational, government, recreational, or other not-for-profit professional purposes. The Data User is permitted to produce and distribute derived works from this dataset provided that they are released under the same license terms as those accompanying this Data Set. Any other uses for the Data Set or its derived products will require explicit permission from the dataset owner.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Redistribution. The data are provided for use by the Data User. The metadata and this license must accompany all copies made and be available to all users of this Data Set. The Data User will not redistribute the original Data Set beyond this collaboration sphere.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Citation. It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Data Set in any publications or in the metadata of any derived data products that were produced using the Data Set. Citation should take the following general form: Creator, Year of Data Publication, Title of Dataset, Publisher, Dataset identifier.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acknowledgement. The Data User should acknowledge any institutional support or specific funding awards referenced in the metadata accompanying this dataset in any publications where the Data Set contributed significantly to its content. Acknowledgements should identify the supporting party, the party that received the support, and any identifying information such as grant numbers.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Notification. The Data User will notify the Data Set Contact when any derivative work or publication based on or derived from the Data Set is distributed. The Data User will provide the data contact with two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the Data Set and will provide copies, or on-line access to, any derived digital products. Notification will include an explanation of how the Data Set was used to produce the derived work.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Collaboration. The Data Set has been released in the spirit of open scientific collaboration. Data Users are thus strongly encouraged to consider consultation, collaboration and/or co-authorship with the Data Set Creator.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist><literalLayout>By accepting this Data Set, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. The Data Owner shall have the right to terminate this agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Disclaimer</title><para><literalLayout>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation contained in this Data Set, complete accuracy of data and metadata cannot be guaranteed. All data and metadata are made available "as is". The Data User holds all parties involved in the production or distribution of the Data Set harmless for damages resulting from its use or interpretation.</literalLayout></para></section></intellectualRights><distribution id="distributionReference" scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-nin.8734.3&amp;urlTail=nin_dws_1985.txt</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage id="geoReference" scope="document"><geographicDescription>North Inlet encompasses about 2,630 hectares of tidal marshes and wetlands near Georgetown, South Carolina, USA. North Inlet-Winyah Bay features high quality, ocean-dominated waters and salt marshes in North Inlet, contrasting with the brackish waters and marshes of Winyah Bay. The bay estuary is dominated by riverine discharges from a watershed impacted by agricultural, municipal and industrial development. Former rice fields  and canals provide another system for study within the Reserve. The Debidue site is located at the confluence of Town Creek and Debidue Creek. The Bread and Butter site is located along the western shoreline of Town Creek adjacent to the mouth of Clambank Creek.       Town Creek water samples -- 33.19'38" Lat.,  79.10'0" Long.  Clambank Creek water samples -- 33.20'0" Lat.,  79.11'33" Long. Oyster Landing water samples in Crab Haul Creek --        33.21'2" Lat.,  79.11'27" Long.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-79.2936</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-79.1002</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>33.357</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>33.1925</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReference" scope="document"><singleDateTime><calendarDate>1983</calendarDate></singleDateTime></temporalCoverage></coverage><maintenance><description><section><title>Entry verification</title><para><literalLayout>Known Nutrient parameters are entered into a "Raw Nutrient Run Book" for     every tray of samples that are run.  This book contains parameters, and     pertinent notes associated with each tray.  The following parameters are     in the "Raw Nutrient Run Book":          Tray Number        Chemistry          Std. Cup.#         Std. Cal.#          Dummy              Std. Conc.          Sample             Chem.#  (sample ID)          Drift              Dilution     This book is basically a NOTE book for the chemist running the samples.     When a tray is run, raw peak height numbers are written onto the ticker     tape or printout, which is kept in the chemistry lab.  This data is hand     copied into a "Master Nutrient Raw Peak Height Book".  ** NOTE ** (There     is no re-editing of the data that is written into the "Master Nutrient     Raw Peak Height Book".)  The ticker tape and "Raw Nutrient Run Book" are     kept in the fire proof cabinet at the Baruch Marine Lab, Georgetown, SC.     A "Nutrient Parameter Book" and the "Master Nurtient Raw Peak Height Book"     are kept in the chemistry lab at the Baruch Marine Lab, Georgetown SC.     The following data is in the "Nutrient Parameter Book":          Tray#     Average Peak Height of standard          Cups      Oxidizer Reagent Blank          Drift     Standard Concentration     This book is necessary to run the correction programs.     At this point, a Data Manager entered the information from the "Master     Nutrient Raw Peak Height Book" into a CMS file.  This data, once entered     was verified for typographical errors by the Data Manager.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Data last update while at North Inlet</title><para><literalLayout>October 1992.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Data last archive date while at North Inlet</title><para><literalLayout>October 1992.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Last Modification at LTER Network Office</title><para><literalLayout>Data files format was converted from delimited to comma separated. Data was revised for consistency, agreement with metadata. Date: November 2006</literalLayout></para></section></description></maintenance><contact scope="document"><organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint><city>Albuquerque</city><administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea><postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">505 277 2535</phone><phone phonetype="fax">505 277 2541</phone><electronicMailAddress>dman@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint><city>Albuquerque</city><administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea><postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">505 277 2535</phone><phone phonetype="fax">505 277 2541</phone><electronicMailAddress>dman@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></publisher><pubPlace>Long Term Ecological Research Network Office</pubPlace><methods><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>The Daily Water Sample program was started in 1978 to moniter the
     daily nutrient cycling within the North Inlet Estuary System.
     The original sampling site was at Town Creek.  Later samples were
     taken at Clambank and Oyster Landing as well. Samples were taken 365 
     days a year at the same time every day, approximately 10:00 AM EST.  
     The samples were filtered at the Lab to separate the particulates from 
     the water.  The filtered water was then run through a colorimeter and 
     the nutrient value peak heights derived were recorded on a ticker tape 
     type printout.  These values were recorded into a master nutrient note 
     book, and entered onto a CMS file by the Data Management Department at 
     the lab.  The filters that were used in the filtering process were first
     weighted, burnt off and cleaned, then they were weighted with the
     particulates dried onto them.  These filters were then cooked again for 
     24 hours at 450 degrees.  This was done to determine the inorganic
     particulates that were left.  All data files have since been stored
     on a SUN workstation and backed up on 8mm tapes at both the field lab
     and the data management office at the University of South Carolina.

     Analysis methods for the individual variables are described below:

     Ortho-Phosphate

     The basic method was the Technicon Industrial Method No. 155-71W (1973),
     which was a modification of the Murphy and Riley (1962) single solution
     method.  The method depended on the formation of a phospomolybdate blue
     complex, the color of which is read at a wavelength of 880 mm.

     Sulfate

     For this automated procedure for sulfate (Technicon Industrial Method
     No. 118-71W/B), the sample was first passed through a cation-exchange
     column to remove interferences.  The sample containing sulfate was then
     reacted with barium chloride at a pH of 2.5-3.0 to form barium sulfate.
     Excess barium reacted with methylthmol blue to form a blue-colored 
 was gray; if it was all chelated with barium, the color was blue.
     Initially, the barium chloride and methylthymol blue were equimolar and
     equivalent to the highest concentration of sulfate ion expected; thus
     the amount of uncomplexed methylthymol blue, measured at 460 mm, was equal
     to the sulfate present.

     Nitrate/Nitrite
 
     The basic method was Technicon Industrial Method No. 158-71W/B, which
     utilized the reaction in which nitrate was reduced to nitrite by a copper-
     cadmium reductor column.   The nitrite ion then reacted with 
     sulfanilamide under acidic conditions to form a diazo compound.  This 
     compound then coupled with N-1-napthylethylenediamine dihydrochloride
     to form a reddish-purple azo dye.

     Chlorides

     The basic method was Technicon Industrial Method No. 99-70W/B.  This 
     automated procedure for the determination of chloride depended upon the
     the liberation of thiocyanate ion from mercuric thiocyanate by the 
     formation of unionized but soluble mercuric chloride.  In the presence
     of ferric ion, the liberated thiocyanate formed a highly colored ferric
     thiocyanate proportional to the original chloride concentration.

     Ammonia

     This method was from "The Automated Analysis of Nutrients in Seawater:  A
     Manual of Techniques" by Gilbert and Loder (1977), a Woods Hole 
     Oceanographic Institution publication No. WHO-77-47.  This method was
     dependent upon the Berthelot Reaction, during which the formation of a
     blue colored compound closely related to indophenol occurred when the 
     solution of an ammonium salt was added to sodium phenoxide, followed
     by the addition of sodium hypochlorite.  A solution of potassium sodium
     tartrate and sodium citrate was added to the sample stream to eliminate
     the precipitation of the hydroxides of calcium and magnesium.

     Total Nitrogen -Total PhosphorusThe procedure consisted of an alkaline persulfate oxidation followed by
     automated analysis for nitrogen (as nitrate) and phosphorus (as phosphate)
     on a Technicon Auto Analyzer.

     With alkaline persulfate digestion, all nitrogen in the sample was 
     oxidized to nitrate, which was then reduced by cadmium and analyzed as
     nitrite.  The precision and recovery of this method compared favorably
     with a Kjeldahl procedure (D'Elia et al., 1977).  The main advantage of
     the persulfate oxidation was the speed and convenience with which it was
     accomplished.  Unlike the Kjeldahl method, which recovered only organic
     and NH4 - nitrogen, the persulfate oxidation also included NO3 and
     NO2 nitrogen.

     The procedure described by D'Elia (1977) has been so the digest could be
     analyzed using an autoanalyzer (Gilbert et al., 1977).  This semi-
     automated procedure combined the persulfate oxidation with automated
     nitrate and phosphate analysis to provide simultaneous analysis for total
     persulfate nitrogen (TPN) and total persulfate phosphorus (TPP).  
     Gilbert's procedure was further modified to use a smaller sample size so
     that the digestion flask could double as the sampler tray cup (Loder,
     1978).  Using this method, many samples could be run quickly with a 
     minimum of handling.

     Carbon (prior to September 1989)

     Particulate Carbon

     20 ml of daily water sample was filtered through a precombusted (24 hr @
     450 C) Whatman GFF 0.7 micron glass filter.  The filter was waved over
     concentrated HCl to eliminate inorganic carbon, then placed in a 
     precombusted ampule and frozen.  Batches were dried at 60 C for 48 hrs.
     0.1 gr of precombusted (48 hr @ 750 C) reagent grade CuO was added to 
     each ampule, the ampule was then purged with pure oxygen and sealed,
     using an Oceanigraphics International Purging and Sealing Unit #524PS.
     Ampules were etched, then heated to 580 C for 4 hrs.  Sorted ampules were
     then analyzed on an Oceanigraphics International #524C TOC Analyzer by
     comparing infrared absorption peak heights (Horiba PIR 2000) on an LDC
     strip chart recorder with those of KHP (Potassium Hydrogen Phthalate)
     standards.  Standards were prepared by microsyringing a series of volumes
     of a KHP solution into ampules and processing them as samples.  Reagent 
     blanks were subtracted and average concentration of duplicate samples
     was calculated for each DWS site.

     Dissolved Organic Carbon 

     The daily water sample was filtered through a precombusted (24 hr @ 450 C)
     Whatman GFF 0.7 micron glass filter.  An aliquot of filtrate was 
     refrigerated.  Samples were purged of inorganic carbon by adding 25percent 
     phosphoric acid to lower the pH to 2 and bubbling for 10 minutes with
     pure oxygen.  The pH was then neutralized using ammonium hydroxide to 
     protect the oxidizing catalyst.  Every 5 minutes, using a Hamilton 
     CR-700-200 spring loaded syringe, a 100 microliter sample was injected
     into a Beckman 915A TOC Analyzer and infrared absorption peak heights
     were compared to those of KHP standard solutions to calculate carbon
     concentration.

     Carbon (after September 1989)

     Dissolved Organic Carbon

     Water samples were filtered through a precombusted Whatman GFF 7.0 micron
     glass filter.  Samples were purged of inorganic carbon by adding 10
     percent HCl and sparged with ultra zero grade air.  A 40 microliter 
     aliquot was injected, via a autosampler, into a Shimadzu TOC-500
     organic carbon analyzer.  A non-dispersive infrared gas analyzer was
     utilized to measure the carbon dioxide produced and samples were run in
     triplicate with means reported.

     ***NOTE***  A Whatman GFF 7.0 micron glass fiber filter was used 
     throughout the LTER Daily Water Sample analysis.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Experimental Design</title><para><literalLayout>Water samples are taken daily at three stations in the North Inlet Estuary System at 10:00 AM EST, 365 days a year.</literalLayout></para></section></description></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=LNO,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>ALL</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>READ</permission></allow></access><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>knb-lter-nin.8734.2</entityName><entityDescription>data table for project LTER.NIN.DWS.txt</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>nin_dws_1985.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><references>distributionReference</references></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReference</references></temporalCoverage></coverage><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Date</attributeName><attributeLabel>Date</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Date sample was taken</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>(D)DMMYY</formatString></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>transect</attributeName><attributeLabel>transect</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The transect identifier string</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>TC</code><definition>Town Creek</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>CB</code><definition>Clambank</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>OL</code><definition>Oyster Landing</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Water Temperature</attributeName><attributeLabel>Water Temperature</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Temperature of the water</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">50</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-9.9</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Salinity</attributeName><attributeLabel>SAL</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Salinity</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>Parts per 1000</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">36</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>9.9</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Total Nitrogen Whole</attributeName><attributeLabel>TNW</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Total Nitrogen Whole</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>microgramsPerLiter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">129</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>99.9</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Total Nitrogen Filtered</attributeName><attributeLabel>TNF</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Total Nitrogen Filtered</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>microgramsPerLiter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">133</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>99.9</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Total Phosphorus Whole</attributeName><attributeLabel>TPW</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Total Phosphorus Whole</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>microgramsPerLiter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">10.6</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-9.9</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Total Phosphorus Filtered</attributeName><attributeLabel>TPF</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Total Phosphorus Filtered</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>microgramsPerLiter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">10.4</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-9.9</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>OrthoPhosphate</attributeName><attributeLabel>POP</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>OrthoPhosphate concentration</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>microgramsPerLiter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">9.999</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>9.999</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>9.900</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Ammonia</attributeName><attributeLabel>NHN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Ammonia Concentrate</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>microgramsPerLiter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">31.7</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-9.9</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Nitrate / Nitrite</attributeName><attributeLabel>NNN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Concentration of Nitrate/Nitrite</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>microgramsPerLiter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">9.32</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>9.99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>9.90</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Chemistry Number</attributeName><attributeLabel>CHEM#</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Chemistry number</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>microgramsPerLiter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">9.32</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Total Organic Carbon</attributeName><attributeLabel>TOC</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Total Organic Carbon</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>milligramsPerLiter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">22.6</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-9.9</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Dissolved Organic Carbon</attributeName><attributeLabel>DOC</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Dissolved Organic Carbon</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>milligramsPerLiter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">38.6</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-9.9</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Particulate Organic Carbon</attributeName><attributeLabel>POC</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Particulate Organic Carbon</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>milligramsPerLiter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">16.6</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-9.9</code><codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><unitList><unit id="Parts per 1000" /></unitList></additionalMetadata></eml:eml>