<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><gmi:MI_Metadata
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco"
  xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc"
  xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv"
  xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2"
  xmlns:gsr="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gsr"
  xmlns:gss="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gss"
  xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts"
  xmlns:gmi="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmi"
  xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmi http://www.ngdc.noaa.gov/metadata/published/xsd/schema.xsd">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset/3822</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gco:CharacterString>eng; USA</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">utf8</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="005">dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevelName>
    <gco:CharacterString>Highest level of data collection, from a common set of sensors or instrumentation, usually within the same research project</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevelName>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  <gmd:organisationName>
    <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/affiliation/191.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Biological and Chemical Oceanography Data Management Office (BCO-DMO)</gmx:Anchor>
  </gmd:organisationName>
  <gmd:contactInfo>
    <gmd:CI_Contact>
		  <gmd:phone>
		    <gmd:CI_Telephone>
				  <gmd:voice>
				    <gco:CharacterString>Unavailable</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:voice>
				  <gmd:facsimile>
				    <gco:CharacterString>508-289-2009</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:facsimile>
				</gmd:CI_Telephone>
		  </gmd:phone>
		  <gmd:address>
		    <gmd:CI_Address>
				  <gmd:deliveryPoint>
				    <gco:CharacterString>WHOI MS#36</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:deliveryPoint>
				  <gmd:city>
				    <gco:CharacterString>Woods Hole</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:city>
				  <gmd:administrativeArea>
				    <gco:CharacterString>MA</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:administrativeArea>
				  <gmd:postalCode>
				    <gco:CharacterString>02543</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:postalCode>
				  <gmd:country>
				    <gco:CharacterString>USA</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:country>
				  <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
				    <gco:CharacterString>info@bco-dmo.org</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
		    </gmd:CI_Address>
		  </gmd:address>
      <gmd:onlineResource>
          <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
            <gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:URL>http://www.bco-dmo.org</gmd:URL>
            </gmd:linkage>
          </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
        </gmd:onlineResource>
		  <gmd:hoursOfService>
        <gco:CharacterString>Monday - Friday 8:00am - 5:00pm</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:hoursOfService>
		  <gmd:contactInstructions>
		    <gco:CharacterString>For questions regarding this resource, please contact BCO-DMO via the email address provided.</gco:CharacterString>
		  </gmd:contactInstructions>
		</gmd:CI_Contact>
  </gmd:contactInfo>
  <gmd:role>
    <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="pointOfContact" codeSpace="007">pointOfContact</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
  </gmd:role>
</gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2012-12-20</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115-2 Geographic Information - Metadata - Part 2: Extensions for Imagery and Gridded Data</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115-2:2009(E)</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo xlink:href="https://www.ngdc.noaa.gov/docucomp/895cc120-95ed-11e0-aa80-0800200c9a66" xlink:title="WGS 84 / World Mercator"/>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset/3822.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">GT11 - FIA-AlFeMn from the U.S. GEOTRACES NAT project of the U.S. GEOTRACES program</gmx:Anchor>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2013-10-14</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="publication" codeSpace="002">publication</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:citedResponsibleParty>
           <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
              <gmd:individualName>
                <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/person/50550.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Dr Christopher Measures</gmx:Anchor>
              </gmd:individualName>
              <gmd:organisationName>
                <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/affiliation/62.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">University of Hawaii</gmx:Anchor>
              </gmd:organisationName>
              <gmd:positionName>
               <gco:CharacterString></gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:positionName>
              <gmd:role>
                <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="principalInvestigator" codeSpace="008">principalInvestigator</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
              </gmd:role>
            </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
          </gmd:citedResponsibleParty>
          <gmd:presentationForm>
            <gmd:CI_PresentationFormCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_PresentationFormCode" codeListValue="documentDigital">documentDigital</gmd:CI_PresentationFormCode>
          </gmd:presentationForm>
          </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>Shipboard flow injection analyis (FIA) of dissolved Al, Fe, and Mn. Dataset Description: &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Shipboard flow injection analysis (FIA) data of dissolved metals from the GT11 cruise (KN204-01). Samples were collected using GO-FLO bottles and filtered through 0.2 µm Acropak filters. Concentrations and quality flags are reported for each metal.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Related files and references:&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Measures, C.I., J. Yang, and J.A. Resing, J., 1995. Determination of iron in seawater by flow injection analysis using in-line preconcention and spectrophotometric detection, Mar. Chem., 50, 3-12. doi: &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0304-4203(95)00022-J&amp;quot; target=&amp;quot;_blank&amp;quot;&amp;gt;10.1016/0304-4203(95)00022-J&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Resing, J., Measures, C.I., 1994.&amp;amp;nbsp; Fluorometric determination of A1 in seawater by FIA with in-line pre concentration. Anal. Chem. 66, 4105-4111. doi: &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/ac00094a039&amp;quot; target=&amp;quot;_blank&amp;quot;&amp;gt;10.1021/ac00094a039&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Resing, J. A. and M. J. Mottl, 1992. Determination of Manganese in seawater using flow injection analysis with on-line preconcentration and spectrophotometric, Analytical Chemistry, 64, 2682-2687. doi: &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/ac00046a006&amp;quot; target=&amp;quot;_blank&amp;quot;&amp;gt;10.1021/ac00046a006&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Please note that some US GEOTRACES data may not be final, pending intercalibration results and further analysis. If you are interested in following changes to US GEOTRACES NAT data, there is an RSS feed available via the BCO-DMO&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.bco-dmo.org/project/2066&amp;quot;&amp;gt;US GEOTRACES project page&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;(scroll down and expand the &amp;quot;Datasets&amp;quot; section).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt; Acquisition Description: &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Sampling Methods&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;The samples (with the exception of surface samples) were collected for trace metal determinations at 21 stations from the RV Knorr using a custom-built US GEOTRACES trace metal clean rosette consisting of an epoxy painted Al rosette frame containing 24x12 L GO-FLO bottles (Cutter and Bruland, 2012). Immediately after the package was recovered, the tops of the GO-FLO bottles were covered with plastic bags and the bottles were removed from the frame and carried into the US GEOTRACES clean van for sub-sampling. The GO-FLO bottles were pressurized to 10 psi using 0.2 µm-filtered compressed air and samples were filtered through 0.2 µm Acropak filters. All sub-sampling was undertaken in the clean van using rigorous trace metal protocols. Surface samples are from the towed fish surface sampling system.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Analytical Methods&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;FIA Sample Preparation&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;: Samples were drawn into pre-numbered 125 ml PMP bottles after three rinses and were stored in plastic bags in the dark at room temperature before determination which was usually within 12 -36 hours of collection. Prior to determination samples were acidified by the addition of 125 ul sub-boiling distilled 6N HCl (hereinafter 6N HCl) and were microwaved in groups of 4 for 3 minutes in a 900 W microwave oven to achieve a temperature of 60+10 °C. Samples were allowed to cool for at least 1 hour prior to determination. Samples were determined in groups of 8.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;FIA Standards&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;: Shipboard mixed standards (Al and Fe, Mn) were prepared in the shore-based laboratory by serial dilution of commercial Al, Fe, and Mn standards (BDH Aristar) into distilled water which was acidified with the equivalent of 4 ml sub-boiled 6N HCl. Standards for instrument calibration were prepared daily from filtered seawater by acidifying 1 L of low Fe seawater from a previous cast with 1 ml of 6N HCl and microwaving for 5 minutes to reach a temperature of 60 + 10°C. After 1 hour, 200 + 2 ml of the cooled seawater was added to each of three 250 ml PMP bottles each of which had been rinsed three times with the microwaved seawater and shaken dry. Working standards were prepared by adding 0, +100µL, +200µL spikes of the shipboard mixed standard to these bottles, to yield a standard curve of +20.77nM and +31.53nM for Al, +0.97nM and +1.94nM for Fe, +3.84nM and +7.68nM for Mn. The system blank from the addition of the acid and buffer to samples was determined by double spiking a replicate sample i.e. by adding 2 x 125 ul 6N HCl and 5 ml of sample buffer to the replicate bottle and comparing the resulting signal to the original sample.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Dissolved Al Concentrations&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;: Dissolved Al was determined using a Flow Injection Analysis scheme with fluorometric detection. Major components were a Rabbit peristaltic pump, a Dynamax FL-1 fluorometer, a Rainin A/D board and a Macintosh G3 computer running Rainin MacIntegrator v 1.4.3 to log and reduce data. The analytical scheme produces a complex between lumogallion and dissolved Al which when excited at 484 nm produces flourescence at 552 nm. Detailed description of the methodology is published in Resing and Measures (1994).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;A 3-minute pre-concentration of sample (~9 ml) onto an 8-hydroxyquinoline (8-HQ) resin column yielded a detection limit of 0.24 and a precision of 4.8% at 1.67 nM.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Dissolved Fe&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;: Dissolved Fe was determined using a Flow Injection Analysis scheme with spectrophotometric detection (Rainin Dynamax UV-C). Major components were a Rabbit peristaltic pump, a Dynamax FL-1 fluorometer, a Rainin A/D board and a Macintosh G3 computer running Rainin MacIntegrator v 1.4.3 to log and reduce data. The spectrophotometric detection of the iron eluted from the column is achieved through its catalytic effect on the oxidation of N,N-dimethylp-phenylenediamine dihydrochloride (DPD) the oxidised product is measured at 514 nm. Detailed description of the methodology is published in Measures et al (1995).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;A 3-minute pre-concentration of sample (~9 ml) onto an 8-hydroxyquinoline (8-HQ) resin column yielded a detection limit of 0.064 nM and a precision of 2.8%.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Dissolved Mn&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;: Dissolved Mn was determined using a Flow Injection Analysis scheme with spectrophotometric detection (Rainin Dynamax UV-C). Major components were a Rabbit peristaltic pump, a Dynamax FL-1 fluorometer, a Rainin A/D board and a Macintosh G3 computer running Rainin MacIntegrator v 1.4.3 to log and reduce data. The spectrophotometric detection of the manganese eluted from the column is achieved through its catalytic effect on the formation of malachite green which is measured at 620 nm. Detailed description of the methodology is published in Resing and Mottl (1992).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;A 3-minute pre-concentration of sample (~9 ml) onto an 8-hydroxyquinoline (8-HQ) resin column yielded a detection limit of 0.03 nM and a precision of 2.9% at 0.05 nM.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Calculation of FIA data&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;: Calculation of sample concentrations was by dividing the peak height derived from sample using the A/D software by the calculated slope of the standard curve. Variations in the slope of the standard curve during a day's run were corrected by the following procedure.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The change in the value of the slope of the standard curve between each run of standards was divided by the number of samples run between those standards to provide a calculated value for the slope of the standard curve at the point each sample was run. The value of the peak height for each sample was then recalculated by the estimated ratio of the standard curve slope at the point that sample was run. The estimate of the slope at each sample run is calculated by: (Initial slope + (incremental change per sample X # of samples run since initial standard was run)). The sample concentration is then calculated from the initial standard curve slope.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Data correction with shore-based ICPMS data&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Shipboard determined dissolved Fe and Mn have been corrected using the shore-based ICPMS data that was measured by co-PI Dr. Jingfeng Wu. That data will be submitted separately.&amp;amp;nbsp; The corrected FIA data was calculated using the slope and the intercept of the correlation plot between the ICPMS data and FIA data on each of the days the FIA was run.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Shipboard dissolved Fe: Shipboard calculation:&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;The Fe concentration of samples was determined by dividing the sample peak height by the slope of the Fe standard solution. The standard curve was produced by adding +0 µL (+0 nM), +100 µL (+0.972 nM), +200 µL (+1.944 nM) of the shipboard standard solution into 200 mL aliquots of seawater. This seawater was obtained from a 1L sample of seawater (usually from near the chlorophyll max) that had been filtered through a 0.2 µm pore-size Acropack cartridge, acidified with 1 ml of 6N HCl (sub boiling distilled) and microwaved to achieve a temperature of 60 + 10°C. A typical standard curve is shown in Figure 1.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Figure 1. Fe standard curve from the standard addition method. (click on the image to view a larger version) &amp;lt;!-- height=&amp;quot;374&amp;quot; --&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://bcodata.whoi.edu/US_GEOTRACES/AtlanticSection/CMeasures_Hatta/GT11_Figure1.png&amp;quot; target=&amp;quot;_blank&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img alt=&amp;quot;&amp;quot; src=&amp;quot;http://bcodata.whoi.edu/US_GEOTRACES/AtlanticSection/CMeasures_Hatta/GT11_Figure1.png&amp;quot; style=&amp;quot;width:519px&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The shipboard standard solution was 1.944 µM and had been prepared by gravimmetric dilution from a high purity standard solution (1000 µg/mL) at the shore-based laboratory of University of Hawaii. Overall precision is 2.8%, and the average detection limit is 0.064 nM.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Shipboard dissolved Fe: Blank calculation:&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;At sea the blank calculation of the data was made using the value derived from a sample that had been spiked with EDTA. This process yields a sample that should have no uncomplexed Fe thus allowing subtraction of the system blank.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Shore based adjustment of the shipboard data was made by comparison with the shore-based ICP MS data measured by J. Wu at U Miami. A plot of each station's data (FIA vs ICP MS) yielded a slope and intercept that was then used to recalculate the shipboard data. This indicated that the shipboard blank correction was underestimating the system blank.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Table 1.&amp;amp;nbsp; Slope and intercept between shipboard FIA (substituted EDTA blank) and ICPMS data&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Station&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; Slope&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; Intercept&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; R2&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-01&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.470&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; -0.022&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.944&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-02&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.272&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.057&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.869&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-03&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.144&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.205&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.948&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-06&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.079&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.277 &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.930&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-08&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.036&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.208&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.948&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-10&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.399&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.103&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.974&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-12&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.114&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.441&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.797&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-14&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.152&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.199&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.947&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-16&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.216&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.105 &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.988&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-18&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.943&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.180 &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.932&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-20&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.980&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.256&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.903&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-22&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.967&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.394&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.964&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-24&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.605&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.318&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.964&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;The ICPMS data reported by Miami (Dr. Wu) were only for full depth stations. Two of the demi stations were determined at sea on the same day that full depth stations were run specifically GT11-17 and GT 16; GT11-23 and GT11-22.&amp;amp;nbsp; Thus, these samples were adjusted using the same slope and intercept used for the full depth station. However, the other demi station samples were determined on separate days. Thus, the samples cannot currently be adjusted with existing ICPMS data.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The following demi stations have not been adjusted and are not reported: USGT11-05, USGT11-11, USGT11-13, USGT11-18, and USGT11-21.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Shipboard dissolved Fe: Accuracy results:&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;There are no shipboard results for the recoveries of Certified Reference Materials (CRMs) or consensus reference materials (e.g., SAFe water) as these samples are too acid to be run using this protocol. Instead these data are corrected using the shore-based ICP MS values which are calibrated against SaFe samples.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Shipboard dissolved Mn: Details about calibration:&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;The Mn concentration of sample was calculated using the quadratic polynomial (x= the peak height, y= the Mn standard concentrations, y= M0+M1x+M2x^2). The coefficients (M0, M1, M2) of the polynomial were obtained based on the standard curve.&amp;amp;nbsp; This was produced by the standard addition method adding (+0µL (+0 nM), +100µL (+3.842 nM), +200 µL (+7.683 nM) of the spike standard solution added into the 200mL of seawater which had been filtered through a 0.2µm pore-size Acropack cartridge.). A typical standard curve is shown in Figure 2.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Figure 2. Mn standard curve from the standard addition method, the polynomial fit, and the coefficients of the polynomial approximation. (click on the image to view a larger version) &amp;lt;!-- height=&amp;quot;374&amp;quot; --&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://bcodata.whoi.edu/US_GEOTRACES/AtlanticSection/CMeasures_Hatta/GT11_Figure2.png&amp;quot; target=&amp;quot;_blank&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img alt=&amp;quot;&amp;quot; src=&amp;quot;http://bcodata.whoi.edu/US_GEOTRACES/AtlanticSection/CMeasures_Hatta/GT11_Figure2.png&amp;quot; style=&amp;quot;width:519px&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;The shipboard standard solution was 7.683 µM and had been prepared by gravimmetric dilution from a high purity standard solution (1000µg/mL) at the shore-based laboratory of University of Hawaii. The precision of the method, the relative standard deviation (RSD, %), and detection limit (3sigma; D.L.) were calculated on each analysis day from the triplicate analysis of a spiked standard seawater solution. Results are shown in Mn Table 1, below.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Overall average precision (from Mn Table 1 below) is 2.9%, and the average detection limit is 0.05 nM.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Shipboard dissolved Mn: Blank calculation:&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;There is no blank calculation of the data made at sea. Shore based adjustment of the shipboard data was made by comparison between the shore-based ICP MS data measured by J Wu at RSMAS, and the shipboard calculated data, the intercept being the blank offset between the methodologies. The ICPMS data has been submitted separately.&amp;amp;nbsp; In general, the difference was very small (average difference was + 0.029nM) which is similar to the analytical uncertainty of the shipboard method. The detailed value of the blank for each station is shown in Mn Table 2.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Shipboard dissolved Mn: Accuracy results:&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;There are no shipboard result for the recoveries of Certified Reference Materials (CRMs) or consensus reference materials (e.g., SAFe water) as these samples are too acid to be run using this protocol. Instead these data are corrected to the shore-based ICP MS values which are calibrated against SaFe samples.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Mn Table 1.&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt; Precision, Relative Standard Deviation, and Detection Limit of the shipboard FIA method for dissolved Mn&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Concentration of std. solution for the precision (nM)&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; RSD %&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; D.L (nM)&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-01&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.243&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 2.1&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.079&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-02&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.027&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 3.4&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.103&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-03&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.653&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 2.2&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.043&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-05&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.533&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 3.9&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.062&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-06&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.620&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.6&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.030&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-08&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.443&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.6 &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.021&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-10&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.109&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 2.1&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.070&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-11&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.708&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 3.6&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.076&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-12&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.396&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 3.2&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.038&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-13&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.271&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 2.7&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.022&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-14&amp;amp;amp;15&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.334&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.5&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.015&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-16&amp;amp;amp;17&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.183&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.1&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.006&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-18&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.160&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 4.2 &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.020&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-19&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.128&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.2&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.005&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-20&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.371&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.2&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.050&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-21&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.713&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 8.5&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.181&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-22&amp;amp;amp;23&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.123&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 4.9&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.018&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-24&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.563&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 3.6&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.061&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Mn Table 2.&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Station&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; Blank (Intercept)&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; Memo&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-01&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0298&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-02&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0626&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-03&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; -0.0151&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-05&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.000&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-06&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0812&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-08&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0099&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-10&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0546&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-11&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.000&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-12&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0610&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-13&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.000&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-14&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0383&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-15*&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0383&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-16 (hydrothermal plume)&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; -0.00910 &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-17&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; -0.0091&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-18&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0154&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-19&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.000&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-20&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.256&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; Blank problem&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-21&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.029&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; No ICP MS use average blank correction&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-22&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; -0.0047&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-23&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; -0.0047&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-24&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; -0.0334&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Shipboard dissolved Al data: UH Shipboard methodology&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;UH Dissolved Al samples are run at sea using standards prepared from a bulk standard which has been diluted using gravimetry. We make two bottles of each working standard and take both bottles to sea but only use one of the bottles at sea (unless we think a bottle has been compromised). We bring both the unused and the partially used bottles of standard back to our laboratory for long term intercalibration. Aliquots of the shipboard standard are added to 200ml seawater samples that are obtained from a single bottle of 1L of seawater that has been acidified and microwaved and then cooled, to produce a standard curve that has +0, +20.77, +31.53 nM added Al. The concentration of Al in any sample is obtained by dividing the peak height of the sample by the slope of the peak height/nM of the standard curve. The intercept of the standard curve is not used since the &amp;quot;0&amp;quot; standard is not a true 0, but is the amount of Al already in the water used to produce the standards.&amp;amp;nbsp; We have not found that there is any procedural blank in this method (from double spiking samples with buffer and acid) and thus do not subtract any blank from the calculated values.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Comparison between UH and NIOZ Al data sets at BATS &amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;In our opinion, the offset between the University of Hawaii and the NIOZ Al data sets in the Atlantic crossover station at Bermuda (Station S), appears to be a result of standard disagreement. This conclusion is based on the following analysis.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;A plot of the two profiles shows the vertical distribution of the two data sets (24 NIOZ samples collected 12 June 2010 and 36 UH samples collected 19 November 2011). There are significant differences between the two profiles in the upper waters, particularly the surface waters, but this is hardly surprising given the 1.5 years between the two occupations and the times of year that they were conducted (June and November). Given that the upper water concentrations of dissolved Al are predominantly a function of atmospheric deposition and its incorporation into subsurface waters&amp;amp;nbsp; (Sub-Tropical Mode Waters) through subduction processes we have not attempted to derive conclusions from this part of the water column since they are likely to be highly temporally variable.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;We are also excluding the data deeper than 4002 m since the shape of the two profiles which both appear to be oceanographically consistent appear to be quite different from each other, which we take to also be a difference due to variations in the strength of, or presence of, a bottom nepheloid layer between the two occupations.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Instead we focus on the region from 974m to 4002m where there is a clear and consistent offset between the two data sets.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;A complicating factor in making the comparison though is that the samples from the&amp;amp;nbsp; two data sets are not at the same depths. In order to make a cross plot we have binned the two data sets to correspond to similar sampling depths (see attached table for the binning). Most of the samples are within ~50m depth, but two samples, (`3600 and 3900 are ~ 100m apart).&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;The plot of the 9 corresponding data points from the two, shows a very clear correlation between the data sets&amp;amp;nbsp; (R=0.993) with a slope of 1.251. Virtually all of the data fall exactly on this line. If the somewhat anomalous point at 2500m in the UH data set is eliminated R increases slightly to R=0.9965 and the slope drops slightly to 1.24.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;The implication of this is that the difference between these data sets is the result of a simple standard offset. A blank offset would lead to a constant difference between the data sets, which is not what this plot implies.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;We do not have access to the NIOZ standards and have been informed by R. Middag that there are no aliquots left of the standard they actually used at sea. He is trying to track down the original stock standard that their shipboard standard was prepared from and we plan to obtain an aliquot of this to check against our standard.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Meanwhile, in an attempt to identify any possible source of the offset in our own standards we have rerun both our original concentrated standard used to produce our shipboard standards as well as the actual standards that we used on board ship during both GT10 and GT11 cruises. The results are as follows:&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;- UH Concentrated standard (used to produce the shipboard standards) was diluted to produce a standard curve. (Standard A)&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;- GT10 and GT11 shipboard standards were then run and calculated against this concentrated standard curve.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;- Another concentrated Al standard (Standard B) was procured from a different laboratory at UH and a dilution was made of this standard and it was run against Standard A.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Results of the standard intercomparison as a % of the expected value--all relative to Standard A:&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;GT10 93.0%&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;GT11 95.3%&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Standard B 95.5%&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Conclusions:&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt; Relative to Standard B, Standard A is 4.5% high, which could be the result of evaporation in that bottle. However these results which imply our standard maybe 4.5% high are preliminary and we intend to rerun all the standards again when we can get an aliquot of the NIOZ standard. We are also purchasing a new stock standard to evaluate the agreement between Standards A and B.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;An evaporated stock standard will lead to an underestimate in the true value of the sample, so if anything our current understanding of our Al values is that they maybe 4.5% lower than the true value. We note an ~2.5% offset between the GT10 and GT11 standards which maybe a result of evaporation of the GT10 shipboard standard. We will compare the unused GT10 standard with the newly purchased concentrated standard when it arrives. We also hope to have an aliquot of the NIOZ standard at that point.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;We also note that the NIOZ data are reported as per kg, whereas ours are volume based (we measure by volume at sea and so report in those units). Depending on the value they used to convert their data (we are assuming here that their values were originally on a per volume basis), the NIOZ data would be ~2.8% lower than the UH data.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/award/55124.rdf" xlink:title="OCE-0928741" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Funding provided by NSF Ocean Sciences (NSF OCE) Award Number: OCE-0928741 Award URL: http://nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=0928741</gmx:Anchor>
      </gmd:credit>
        <gmd:credit>
        <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/award/55125.rdf" xlink:title="OCE-1137812" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Funding provided by NSF Ocean Sciences (NSF OCE) Award Number: OCE-1137812 Award URL: http://nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1137812</gmx:Anchor>
      </gmd:credit>
        <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed">completed</gmd:MD_ProgressCode>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:pointOfContact>
        <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
          <gmd:individualName>
            <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/person/50550.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Dr Christopher Measures</gmx:Anchor>
          </gmd:individualName>
          <gmd:organisationName>
            <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/affiliation/62.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">University of Hawaii</gmx:Anchor>
          </gmd:organisationName>
          <gmd:contactInfo>
            <gmd:CI_Contact>
            <gmd:phone>
                <gmd:CI_Telephone>
                  <gmd:voice>
                    <gco:CharacterString>(808) 956-8693</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gmd:voice>
                </gmd:CI_Telephone>
              </gmd:phone>
            <gmd:address>
                <gmd:CI_Address>
                                  <gmd:deliveryPoint>
                    <gco:CharacterString>Department of Oceanography, University of Hawai`i at Manoa 1000 Pope Road, MSB 512</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gmd:deliveryPoint>
                                  <gmd:city>
                    <gco:CharacterString>Honolulu</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gmd:city>                  <gmd:administrativeArea>
                    <gco:CharacterString>HI</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gmd:administrativeArea>                  <gmd:postalCode>
                    <gco:CharacterString>96822</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gmd:postalCode>                  <gmd:country>
                    <gco:CharacterString>USA</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gmd:country>                  <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                    <gco:CharacterString>chrism@soest.hawaii.edu</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                </gmd:CI_Address>
              </gmd:address>
            </gmd:CI_Contact>
          </gmd:contactInfo>
          <gmd:role>
            <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="pointOfContact" codeSpace="007">pointOfContact</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
          </gmd:role>
        </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      </gmd:pointOfContact>
            <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="asNeeded" codeSpace="009">asNeeded</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
          <gmd:maintenanceNote>
            <gco:CharacterString>Dataset Version: 14 Oct 2013</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:maintenanceNote>
          </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
            <gmd:descriptiveKeywords>
        <gmd:MD_Keywords>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31403.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1102.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">cruise_id</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31404.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/987.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">station</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31405.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1682.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">lon_360</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31406.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/731.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">longitude</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31407.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/730.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">latitude</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31408.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/761.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">cast</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31409.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1695.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">depth_bottom</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31410.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1854.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">bot_Nis</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31411.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/960.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">sample</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31412.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/732.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">pressure</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31413.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1945.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">trace_metal_conc</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31414.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1143.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">q_flag</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31415.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1945.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">trace_metal_conc</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31416.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1143.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">q_flag</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31417.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1945.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">trace_metal_conc</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31418.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1143.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">q_flag</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31564.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1929.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Cruise Name</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33129.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/987.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">station</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33130.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/808.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">depth</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33131.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/829.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">event</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33132.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/757.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">bottle</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-instrument/5985.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/instrument/411.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">GO-FLO Bottle</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-instrument/5986.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/instrument/549.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">GeoFish</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-instrument/5961.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/instrument/657.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Flow Injection Analyzer</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-instrument/5962.rdf" xlink:title="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/instrument/683.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Flow injection lumogallion system with fluorometer</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
        <gmd:type>
            <gmd:MD_KeywordTypeCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_KeywordTypeCode" codeListValue="theme" codeSpace="005">theme</gmd:MD_KeywordTypeCode>
          </gmd:type>
          <gmd:thesaurusName>
            <gmd:CI_Citation>
              <gmd:title>
                <gco:CharacterString>None, User defined</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:title>
              <gmd:date gco:nilReason="unknown"/>
            </gmd:CI_Citation>
          </gmd:thesaurusName>
        </gmd:MD_Keywords>
      </gmd:descriptiveKeywords>
            <gmd:descriptiveKeywords>
        <gmd:MD_Keywords>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1102.rdf" xlink:title="Parameter" xlink:actuate="onRequest">cruise id</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/987.rdf" xlink:title="Parameter" xlink:actuate="onRequest">station</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1682.rdf" xlink:title="Parameter" xlink:actuate="onRequest">longitude from 0 to 360 degrees</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/731.rdf" xlink:title="Parameter" xlink:actuate="onRequest">longitude</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/730.rdf" xlink:title="Parameter" xlink:actuate="onRequest">latitude</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/761.rdf" xlink:title="Parameter" xlink:actuate="onRequest">cast</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1695.rdf" xlink:title="Parameter" xlink:actuate="onRequest">depth_bottom</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1854.rdf" xlink:title="Parameter" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Niskin bottle number</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/960.rdf" xlink:title="Parameter" xlink:actuate="onRequest">sample identification</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/732.rdf" xlink:title="Parameter" xlink:actuate="onRequest">water pressure</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1945.rdf" xlink:title="Parameter" xlink:actuate="onRequest">trace metal concentration</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1143.rdf" xlink:title="Parameter" xlink:actuate="onRequest">quality flag</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/1929.rdf" xlink:title="Parameter" xlink:actuate="onRequest">cruise name</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/808.rdf" xlink:title="Parameter" xlink:actuate="onRequest">depth</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/829.rdf" xlink:title="Parameter" xlink:actuate="onRequest">event</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/parameter/757.rdf" xlink:title="Parameter" xlink:actuate="onRequest">bottle</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
        <gmd:type>
            <gmd:MD_KeywordTypeCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_KeywordTypeCode" codeListValue="featureType">featureType</gmd:MD_KeywordTypeCode>
          </gmd:type>
          <gmd:thesaurusName>
            <gmd:CI_Citation>
              <gmd:title>
                <gco:CharacterString>BCO-DMO Standard Parameters</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:title>
              <gmd:date gco:nilReason="unknown"/>
            </gmd:CI_Citation>
          </gmd:thesaurusName>
        </gmd:MD_Keywords>
      </gmd:descriptiveKeywords>
            <gmd:descriptiveKeywords>
        <gmd:MD_Keywords>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/instrument/411.rdf" xlink:title="Instrument" xlink:actuate="onRequest">GO-FLO Bottle</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/instrument/549.rdf" xlink:title="Instrument" xlink:actuate="onRequest">GeoFish Towed near-Surface Sampler</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/instrument/657.rdf" xlink:title="Instrument" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Flow Injection Analyzer</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/instrument/683.rdf" xlink:title="Instrument" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Flow injection lumogallion system with fluorometer</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
        <gmd:type>
            <gmd:MD_KeywordTypeCode codeList="http://www.ngdc.noaa.gov/metadata/published/xsd/schema/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_KeywordTypeCode" codeListValue="instrument">instrument</gmd:MD_KeywordTypeCode>
          </gmd:type>
          <gmd:thesaurusName>
            <gmd:CI_Citation>
              <gmd:title>
                <gco:CharacterString>BCO-DMO Standard Instruments</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:title>
              <gmd:date gco:nilReason="unknown"/>
            </gmd:CI_Citation>
          </gmd:thesaurusName>
        </gmd:MD_Keywords>
      </gmd:descriptiveKeywords>
            <gmd:descriptiveKeywords>
        <gmd:MD_Keywords>
                <gmd:keyword>
          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/deployment/58786.rdf" xlink:title="Cruise" xlink:actuate="onRequest">KN204-01</gmx:Anchor>
        </gmd:keyword>
        <gmd:type>
            <gmd:MD_KeywordTypeCode codeList="http://www.ngdc.noaa.gov/metadata/published/xsd/schema/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_KeywordTypeCode" codeListValue="service">service</gmd:MD_KeywordTypeCode>
          </gmd:type>
          <gmd:thesaurusName>
            <gmd:CI_Citation>
              <gmd:title>
                <gco:CharacterString>Deployment Activity</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:title>
              <gmd:date gco:nilReason="unknown"/>
            </gmd:CI_Citation>
          </gmd:thesaurusName>
        </gmd:MD_Keywords>
      </gmd:descriptiveKeywords>
            <gmd:descriptiveKeywords>
        <gmd:MD_Keywords>
        <gmd:keyword>
            <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/deployment/58786.rdf" xlink:title="Deployment Location" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Subtropical northern Atlantic Ocean</gmx:Anchor>
          </gmd:keyword>
          <gmd:type>
            <gmd:MD_KeywordTypeCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_KeywordTypeCode" codeListValue="place" codeSpace="002">place</gmd:MD_KeywordTypeCode>
          </gmd:type>
          <gmd:thesaurusName>
            <gmd:CI_Citation>
              <gmd:title>
                <gco:CharacterString>Locations</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:title>
              <gmd:date gco:nilReason="unknown"/>
            </gmd:CI_Citation>
          </gmd:thesaurusName>
        </gmd:MD_Keywords>
      </gmd:descriptiveKeywords>
      <gmd:resourceConstraints>
        <gmd:MD_LegalConstraints>
          <gmd:accessConstraints>
            <gmd:MD_RestrictionCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_RestrictionCode" codeListValue="otherRestrictions" codeSpace="008">otherRestrictions</gmd:MD_RestrictionCode>
          </gmd:accessConstraints>
          <gmd:useConstraints>
            <gmd:MD_RestrictionCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_RestrictionCode" codeListValue="otherRestrictions" codeSpace="008">otherRestrictions</gmd:MD_RestrictionCode>
          </gmd:useConstraints>
          <gmd:otherConstraints>
            <gco:CharacterString>Access Constraints: none. Use Constraints: Please follow guidelines at: http://www.bco-dmo.org/terms-use Distribution liability: Under no circumstances shall BCO-DMO be liable for any direct, incidental, special, consequential, indirect, or punitive damages that result from the use of, or the inability to use, the materials in this data submission. If you are dissatisfied with any materials in this data submission your sole and exclusive remedy is to discontinue use.</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:otherConstraints>
        </gmd:MD_LegalConstraints>
      </gmd:resourceConstraints>
      <gmd:aggregationInfo>
          <gmd:MD_AggregateInformation>
            <gmd:aggregateDataSetName>
              <gmd:CI_Citation>
                <gmd:title>
                  <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/program/2022.rdf" xlink:title="Program" xlink:actuate="onRequest">U.S. GEOTRACES</gmx:Anchor>
                </gmd:title>
                <gmd:date gco:nilReason="inapplicable"/>
                <gmd:citedResponsibleParty>
                  <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
                    <gmd:contactInfo>
                      <gmd:CI_Contact>
                        <gmd:onlineResource>
                          <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
                          <gmd:linkage>
                            <gmd:URL>http://www.geotraces.org/</gmd:URL>
                          </gmd:linkage>
                          <gmd:name>
                            <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/program/2022.rdf" xlink:title="Program Name" xlink:actuate="onRequest">U.S. GEOTRACES</gmx:Anchor>
                          </gmd:name>
                          <gmd:description>
                            <gco:CharacterString>GEOTRACES is a SCOR sponsored program; and funding for program infrastructure development is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation.GEOTRACES gained momentum following a special symposium, S02: Biogeochemical cycling of trace elements and isotopes in the ocean and applications to constrain contemporary marine processes (GEOSECS II), at a 2003 Goldschmidt meeting convened in Japan. The GEOSECS II acronym referred to the Geochemical Ocean Section Studies To determine full water column distributions of selected trace elements and isotopes, including their concentration, chemical speciation, and physical form, along a sufficient number of sections in each ocean basin to establish the principal relationships between these distributions and with more traditional hydrographic parameters;* To evaluate the sources, sinks, and internal cycling of these species and thereby characterize more completely the physical, chemical and biological processes regulating their distributions, and the sensitivity of these processes to global change; and* To understand the processes that control the concentrations of geochemical species used for proxies of the past environment, both in the water column and in the substrates that reflect the water column.GEOTRACES will be global in scope, consisting of ocean sections complemented by regional process studies. Sections and process studies will combine fieldwork, laboratory experiments and modelling. Beyond realizing the scientific objectives identified above, a natural outcome of this work will be to build a community of marine scientists who understand the processes regulating trace element cycles sufficiently well to exploit this knowledge reliably in future interdisciplinary studies.</gco:CharacterString>
                          </gmd:description>
                          <gmd:function>
                            <gmd:CI_OnLineFunctionCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_OnLineFunctionCode" codeListValue="information"/>
                          </gmd:function>
                      </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
                    </gmd:onlineResource>
                  </gmd:CI_Contact>
                </gmd:contactInfo>
                <gmd:role/>
              </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
            </gmd:citedResponsibleParty>
          </gmd:CI_Citation>
        </gmd:aggregateDataSetName>
          <gmd:aggregateDataSetIdentifier>
            <gmd:MD_Identifier>
              <gmd:code>
                <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/program/2022.rdf" xlink:title="Program Acronym" xlink:actuate="onRequest">U.S. GEOTRACES</gmx:Anchor>
              </gmd:code>
            </gmd:MD_Identifier>
          </gmd:aggregateDataSetIdentifier>
          <gmd:associationType>
            <gmd:DS_AssociationTypeCode codeList="http://www.ngdc.noaa.gov/metadata/published/xsd/schema/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#DS_AssociationTypeCode" codeListValue="largerWorkCitation">largerWorkCitation</gmd:DS_AssociationTypeCode>
          </gmd:associationType>
          <gmd:initiativeType>
            <gmd:DS_InitiativeTypeCode codeList="http://www.ngdc.noaa.gov/metadata/published/xsd/schema/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#DS_InitiativeTypeCode" codeListValue="program">program</gmd:DS_InitiativeTypeCode>
          </gmd:initiativeType>
        </gmd:MD_AggregateInformation>
      </gmd:aggregationInfo><gmd:aggregationInfo>
        <gmd:MD_AggregateInformation>
          <gmd:aggregateDataSetName>
              <gmd:CI_Citation>
                <gmd:title>
                  <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/project/2066.rdf" xlink:title="Project" xlink:actuate="onRequest">U.S. GEOTRACES North Atlantic Transect</gmx:Anchor>
                </gmd:title>
                <gmd:date gco:nilReason="inapplicable"/>
                <gmd:citedResponsibleParty>
                  <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
                    <gmd:contactInfo>
                      <gmd:CI_Contact>
                        <gmd:onlineResource>
                          <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
                          <gmd:linkage>
                            <gmd:URL>http://www.geotraces.org/</gmd:URL>
                          </gmd:linkage>
                          <gmd:name>
                            <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/project/2066.rdf" xlink:title="Project Name" xlink:actuate="onRequest">U.S. GEOTRACES North Atlantic Transect</gmx:Anchor>
                          </gmd:name>
                          <gmd:description>
                            <gco:CharacterString>http://bcodata.whoi.edu/US_GEOTRACES/AtlanticSection/GEOTRACES_Atl_stas.jpg</gco:CharacterString>
                          </gmd:description>
                          <gmd:function>
                            <gmd:CI_OnLineFunctionCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_OnLineFunctionCode" codeListValue="information"/>
                          </gmd:function>
                      </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
                    </gmd:onlineResource>
                  </gmd:CI_Contact>
                </gmd:contactInfo>
                <gmd:role/>
              </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
            </gmd:citedResponsibleParty>
          </gmd:CI_Citation>
        </gmd:aggregateDataSetName>
          <gmd:aggregateDataSetIdentifier>
            <gmd:MD_Identifier>
              <gmd:code>
                <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/project/2066.rdf" xlink:title="Project Acronym" xlink:actuate="onRequest">U.S. GEOTRACES NAT</gmx:Anchor>
              </gmd:code>
            </gmd:MD_Identifier>
          </gmd:aggregateDataSetIdentifier>
          <gmd:associationType>
            <gmd:DS_AssociationTypeCode codeList="http://www.ngdc.noaa.gov/metadata/published/xsd/schema/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#DS_AssociationTypeCode" codeListValue="largerWorkCitation">largerWorkCitation</gmd:DS_AssociationTypeCode>
          </gmd:associationType>
          <gmd:initiativeType>
            <gmd:DS_InitiativeTypeCode codeList="http://www.ngdc.noaa.gov/metadata/published/xsd/schema/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#DS_InitiativeTypeCode" codeListValue="project">project</gmd:DS_InitiativeTypeCode>
          </gmd:initiativeType>
        </gmd:MD_AggregateInformation>
      </gmd:aggregationInfo>
      <gmd:language>
        <gco:CharacterString>eng; USA</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>oceans</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
       <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent id="boundingExtent"><gmd:description>
            <gco:CharacterString>Subtropical northern Atlantic Ocean</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:description><gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox id="boundingGeographicBoundingBox">
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-69.8029</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-24.5</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>17.4</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>39.701</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        <gmd:temporalElement>
            <gmd:EX_TemporalExtent>
              <gmd:extent>
                <gml:TimeInstant frame="#ISO-8601" gml:id="ID">
                  <gml:timePosition>2013-10-14</gml:timePosition>
                </gml:TimeInstant>
              </gmd:extent>
            </gmd:EX_TemporalExtent>
          </gmd:temporalElement>
          </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:contentInfo>
    <gmd:MD_FeatureCatalogueDescription>
      <gmd:includedWithDataset>
        <gco:Boolean>0</gco:Boolean>
      </gmd:includedWithDataset>
      <gmd:featureCatalogueCitation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>BCO-DMO catalogue of parameters from GT11 - FIA-AlFeMn from the U.S. GEOTRACES NAT project of the U.S. GEOTRACES program</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:date gco:nilReason="unknown"/>
          <gmd:citedResponsibleParty>
            <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  <gmd:organisationName>
    <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/affiliation/191.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Biological and Chemical Oceanography Data Management Office (BCO-DMO)</gmx:Anchor>
  </gmd:organisationName>
  <gmd:contactInfo>
    <gmd:CI_Contact>
		  <gmd:phone>
		    <gmd:CI_Telephone>
				  <gmd:voice>
				    <gco:CharacterString>Unavailable</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:voice>
				  <gmd:facsimile>
				    <gco:CharacterString>508-289-2009</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:facsimile>
				</gmd:CI_Telephone>
		  </gmd:phone>
		  <gmd:address>
		    <gmd:CI_Address>
				  <gmd:deliveryPoint>
				    <gco:CharacterString>WHOI MS#36</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:deliveryPoint>
				  <gmd:city>
				    <gco:CharacterString>Woods Hole</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:city>
				  <gmd:administrativeArea>
				    <gco:CharacterString>MA</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:administrativeArea>
				  <gmd:postalCode>
				    <gco:CharacterString>02543</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:postalCode>
				  <gmd:country>
				    <gco:CharacterString>USA</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:country>
				  <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
				    <gco:CharacterString>info@bco-dmo.org</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
		    </gmd:CI_Address>
		  </gmd:address>
      <gmd:onlineResource>
          <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
            <gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:URL>http://www.bco-dmo.org</gmd:URL>
            </gmd:linkage>
          </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
        </gmd:onlineResource>
		  <gmd:hoursOfService>
        <gco:CharacterString>Monday - Friday 8:00am - 5:00pm</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:hoursOfService>
		  <gmd:contactInstructions>
		    <gco:CharacterString>For questions regarding this resource, please contact BCO-DMO via the email address provided.</gco:CharacterString>
		  </gmd:contactInstructions>
		</gmd:CI_Contact>
  </gmd:contactInfo>
  <gmd:role>
    <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="pointOfContact" codeSpace="007">pointOfContact</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
  </gmd:role>
</gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
          </gmd:citedResponsibleParty>
          <gmd:otherCitationDetails>
            <gco:CharacterString>
            http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31403.rdf
	Name: cruise_id
	Units: text
	Description: Official cruise identifier e.g. KN199-04 = R/V Knorr cruise number 199-04. 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31404.rdf
	Name: station
	Units: unitless
	Description: Station identifier; provided in original data submission. 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31405.rdf
	Name: lon_360
	Units: decimal degrees
	Description: Longitude ranging from 0 to 360 degrees. 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31406.rdf
	Name: lon
	Units: decimal degrees
	Description: Longitude ranging from 0 to +/- 180. Negative values = West. Added by BCO-DMO based on lon_360. 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31407.rdf
	Name: lat
	Units: decimal degrees
	Description: Latitude ranging from 0 to +/- 180. Positive values = North. 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31408.rdf
	Name: cast
	Units: unitless
	Description: Cast identifier, numbered consecutively within a station. PI-supplied values were identical to those in the intermediate US GEOTRACES master file. Originally submitted as 'CAST No.', this parameter name has been changed to conform to BCO-DMO's GEOTRACES naming conventions. 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31409.rdf
	Name: depth_w
	Units: meters
	Description: Bottom depth from the log sheet during each cast. 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31410.rdf
	Name: sample_bottle_GEOTRC
	Units: unitless
	Description: Unique identification numbers given to samples taken from bottles; rangies from 1 to 24; often used synonymously with bottle number. PI-supplied values were identical to those in the intermediate US GEOTRACES master file. Originally submitted as 'GO-Flo No.', this parameter name has been changed to conform to BCO-DMO's GEOTRACES naming conventions. 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31411.rdf
	Name: sample_GEOTRC
	Units: unitless
	Description: Unique identifying number for US GEOTRACES samples; ranges from 5033 to 6078 for KN199-04 and from 6112 to 8148 for KN204-01. PI-supplied values were identical to those in the intermediate US GEOTRACES master file. Originally submitted as 'GEO Sample No.', this parameter name has been changed to conform to BCO-DMO's GEOTRACES naming conventions. 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31412.rdf
	Name: press
	Units: db
	Description: Pressure in decibars. 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31413.rdf
	Name: Al
	Units: nM
	Description: Dissolved aluminum concentration. 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31414.rdf
	Name: Al_flag
	Units: unitless
	Description: Quality flag for Al. 2 = good; 3 = questionable; 4 = bad; 9 = missing data. 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31415.rdf
	Name: Fe
	Units: nM
	Description: Dissolved iron concentration. (lt = 'less than') 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31416.rdf
	Name: Fe_flag
	Units: unitless
	Description: Quality flag for Fe. 2 = good; 3 = questionable; 4 = bad; 9 = missing data. 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31417.rdf
	Name: Mn
	Units: nM
	Description: Dissolved manganese concentration. 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31418.rdf
	Name: Mn_flag
	Units: unitless
	Description: Quality flag for Mn. 2 = good; 3 = questionable; 4 = bad; 9 = missing data. 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31564.rdf
	Name: cruise_name
	Units: text
	Description: GEOTRACES cruise identifier. 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33129.rdf
	Name: station_GEOTRC
	Units: dimensionless
	Description: GEOTRACES station number; ranges from 1 through 12 for KN199-04 and 1 through 24 for KN204-01. Stations 7 and 9 were skipped on KN204-01. Some GeoFish stations are denoted as X_to_Y indicating the tow occurred between stations X and Y.  Values were added from the intermediate US GEOTRACES master file (see Processing Description). 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33130.rdf
	Name: depth_GEOTRC_CTD
	Units: meters
	Description: Observation/sample depth in meters; calculated from CTD pressure.  PI-supplied values were identical to those in the intermediate US GEOTRACES master file. Originally submitted as 'Depth [m]', this parameter name has been changed to conform to BCO-DMO's GEOTRACES naming conventions. 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33131.rdf
	Name: event_GEOTRC
	Units: dimensionless
	Description: Unique identifying number for US GEOTRACES sampling events; ranges from 2001 to 2225 for KN199-04 events and from 3001 to 3282 for KN204-01 events. Values were added from the intermediate US GEOTRACES master file (see Processing Description). 
http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33132.rdf
	Name: bottle_GEOTRC
	Units: dimensionless
	Description: Alphanumeric characters identifying bottle type (e.g. NIS representing Niskin and GF representing GOFLO) and position on a CTD rosette. Values were added from the intermediate US GEOTRACES master file (see Processing Description). 
</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:otherCitationDetails>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:featureCatalogueCitation>
      <gmd:featureCatalogueCitation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>GB/NERC/BODC &gt; British Oceanographic Data Centre, Natural Environment Research Council, United Kingdom</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:date gco:nilReason="unknown"/>
          <gmd:citedResponsibleParty xlink:href="https://www.ngdc.noaa.gov/docucomp/3D8FE2C9DA324D40939C8D007587E011" xlink:title="GB/NERC/BODC &gt; British Oceanographic Data Centre, Natural Environment Research Council, United Kingdom"/>
          <gmd:otherCitationDetails>
            <gco:CharacterString>
            http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P09/current/LONX/ 
	Name: LONGITUDE 
	Description: The angular distance east or west east or west of Greenwich to the point of interest. 
http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P09/current/LATX/ 
	Name: LATITUDE 
	Description: The angular distance north or south from the equator, measured along the meridian of the point of interest. 
http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P02/current/ACYC/ 
	Name: Reference numbers 
	Description: Data record, event, sample or measurement reference numbers 
http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P01/current/PRESPR01/ 
	Name: Pressure (spatial co-ordinate) exerted by the water body by profiling pressure sensor and corrected to read zero at sea level 
	Description: The force per unit area exerted by the water column on a mobile sensor located in the water column. 
http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P03/current/C035/ 
	Name: Metal and metalloid concentrations 
	Description: Parameters pertaining to metal and trace metalloid (i.e. excluding Si) concentrations in any material. 
http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P03/current/C035/ 
	Name: Metal and metalloid concentrations 
	Description: Parameters pertaining to metal and trace metalloid (i.e. excluding Si) concentrations in any material. 
http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P03/current/C035/ 
	Name: Metal and metalloid concentrations 
	Description: Parameters pertaining to metal and trace metalloid (i.e. excluding Si) concentrations in any material. 
http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P09/current/DEPH/ 
	Name: DEPTH BELOW SEA SURFACE 
	Description: The distance of a sensor or sampling point below the sea surface. 
</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:otherCitationDetails>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:featureCatalogueCitation>
    </gmd:MD_FeatureCatalogueDescription>
  </gmd:contentInfo>
  <gmd:contentInfo>
    <gmi:MI_CoverageDescription>
      <gmd:attributeDescription>
        <gco:RecordType>Parameters for this dataset</gco:RecordType>
      </gmd:attributeDescription>
      <gmd:contentType>
        <gmd:MD_CoverageContentTypeCode codeList="MD_CoverageContentTypeCode" codeListValue="physicalMeasurement">physicalMeasurement</gmd:MD_CoverageContentTypeCode>
      </gmd:contentType>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31403.rdf" xlink:title="cruise id" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>cruise_id</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType>                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>cruise id</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Official cruise identifier e.g. KN199-04 = R/V Knorr cruise number 199-04.; General Description: cruise designation; name</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits31403">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31403.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31403.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>text</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31404.rdf" xlink:title="station" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>station</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType>                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>station</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Station identifier; provided in original data submission.; General Description: consecutive station number</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits31404">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31404.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31404.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>unitless</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31405.rdf" xlink:title="longitude from 0 to 360 degrees" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>lon_360</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType>                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>longitude from 0 to 360 degrees</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Longitude ranging from 0 to 360 degrees.; General Description: longitude ranging from 0 to 360 degrees; especially useful for data collected during sampling transects that cross the dateline</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits31405">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31405.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31405.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>decimal degrees</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31406.rdf" xlink:title="longitude" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>lon</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType xlink:href="http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P09/current/LONX/" xlink:title="LONGITUDE" xlink:actuate="onRequest">                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>longitude</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Longitude ranging from 0 to +/- 180. Negative values = West. Added by BCO-DMO based on lon_360.; General Description: longitude, in decimal degrees, East is positive, negative denotes West; Reported in some datsets as degrees, minutes NERC Description: The angular distance east or west east or west of Greenwich to the point of interest.</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits31406">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31406.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31406.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>decimal degrees</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31407.rdf" xlink:title="latitude" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>lat</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType xlink:href="http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P09/current/LATX/" xlink:title="LATITUDE" xlink:actuate="onRequest">                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>latitude</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Latitude ranging from 0 to +/- 180. Positive values = North.; General Description: latitude, in decimal degrees, North is positive, negative denotes South; Reported in some datasets as degrees, minutes NERC Description: The angular distance north or south from the equator, measured along the meridian of the point of interest.</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits31407">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31407.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31407.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>decimal degrees</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31408.rdf" xlink:title="cast" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>cast</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType>                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>cast</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Cast identifier, numbered consecutively within a station. PI-supplied values were identical to those in the intermediate US GEOTRACES master file. Originally submitted as 'CAST No.', this parameter name has been changed to conform to BCO-DMO's GEOTRACES naming conventions.; General Description: cast or profile number</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits31408">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31408.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31408.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>unitless</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31409.rdf" xlink:title="depth_bottom" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>depth_w</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType>                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>depth_bottom</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Bottom depth from the log sheet during each cast.; General Description: bottom depth</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits31409">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31409.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31409.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>meters</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31410.rdf" xlink:title="Niskin bottle number" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>sample_bottle_GEOTRC</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType>                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>Niskin bottle number</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Unique identification numbers given to samples taken from bottles; rangies from 1 to 24; often used synonymously with bottle number. PI-supplied values were identical to those in the intermediate US GEOTRACES master file. Originally submitted as 'GO-Flo No.', this parameter name has been changed to conform to BCO-DMO's GEOTRACES naming conventions.; General Description: Niskin sample bottle number</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits31410">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31410.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31410.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>unitless</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31411.rdf" xlink:title="sample identification" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>sample_GEOTRC</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType xlink:href="http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P02/current/ACYC/" xlink:title="Reference numbers" xlink:actuate="onRequest">                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>sample identification</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Unique identifying number for US GEOTRACES samples; ranges from 5033 to 6078 for KN199-04 and from 6112 to 8148 for KN204-01. PI-supplied values were identical to those in the intermediate US GEOTRACES master file. Originally submitted as 'GEO Sample No.', this parameter name has been changed to conform to BCO-DMO's GEOTRACES naming conventions.; General Description: unique sample identification or number; any combination of alpha numeric characters; precise definition is file dependent NERC Description: Data record, event, sample or measurement reference numbers</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits31411">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31411.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31411.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>unitless</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31412.rdf" xlink:title="water pressure" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>press</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType xlink:href="http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P01/current/PRESPR01/" xlink:title="Pressure (spatial co-ordinate) exerted by the water body by profiling pressure sensor and corrected to read zero at sea level" xlink:actuate="onRequest">                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>water pressure</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Pressure in decibars.; General Description: water pressure at measurement; depth reported as pressure; positive number increasing with water depth NERC Description: The force per unit area exerted by the water column on a mobile sensor located in the water column.</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits31412">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31412.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31412.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>db</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31413.rdf" xlink:title="trace metal concentration" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>Al</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType xlink:href="http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P03/current/C035/" xlink:title="Metal and metalloid concentrations" xlink:actuate="onRequest">                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>trace metal concentration</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Dissolved aluminum concentration.; General Description: Concentration of a trace metal in seawater. Refer to dataset for element name and units. NERC Description: Parameters pertaining to metal and trace metalloid (i.e. excluding Si) concentrations in any material.</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits31413">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31413.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31413.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>nM</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31414.rdf" xlink:title="quality flag" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>Al_flag</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType>                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>quality flag</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Quality flag for Al. 2 = good; 3 = questionable; 4 = bad; 9 = missing data.; General Description: quality flag; based on a PI established code; identifies a problem/quality issue with sample(s) from a given water bottle or single observation</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits31414">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31414.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31414.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>unitless</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31415.rdf" xlink:title="trace metal concentration" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>Fe</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType xlink:href="http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P03/current/C035/" xlink:title="Metal and metalloid concentrations" xlink:actuate="onRequest">                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>trace metal concentration</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Dissolved iron concentration. (lt = 'less than'); General Description: Concentration of a trace metal in seawater. Refer to dataset for element name and units. NERC Description: Parameters pertaining to metal and trace metalloid (i.e. excluding Si) concentrations in any material.</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits31415">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31415.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31415.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>nM</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31416.rdf" xlink:title="quality flag" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>Fe_flag</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType>                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>quality flag</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Quality flag for Fe. 2 = good; 3 = questionable; 4 = bad; 9 = missing data.; General Description: quality flag; based on a PI established code; identifies a problem/quality issue with sample(s) from a given water bottle or single observation</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits31416">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31416.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31416.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>unitless</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31417.rdf" xlink:title="trace metal concentration" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>Mn</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType xlink:href="http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P03/current/C035/" xlink:title="Metal and metalloid concentrations" xlink:actuate="onRequest">                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>trace metal concentration</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Dissolved manganese concentration.; General Description: Concentration of a trace metal in seawater. Refer to dataset for element name and units. NERC Description: Parameters pertaining to metal and trace metalloid (i.e. excluding Si) concentrations in any material.</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits31417">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31417.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31417.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>nM</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31418.rdf" xlink:title="quality flag" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>Mn_flag</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType>                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>quality flag</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Quality flag for Mn. 2 = good; 3 = questionable; 4 = bad; 9 = missing data.; General Description: quality flag; based on a PI established code; identifies a problem/quality issue with sample(s) from a given water bottle or single observation</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits31418">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31418.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31418.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>unitless</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31564.rdf" xlink:title="cruise name" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>cruise_name</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType>                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>cruise name</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: GEOTRACES cruise identifier.; General Description: The cruise_name is a local name chosen by project investigators for a research expedition on a vessel, as opposed to the formal/official cruise ID asserted by the vessel operator.</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits31564">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31564.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/31564.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>text</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33129.rdf" xlink:title="station" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>station_GEOTRC</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType>                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>station</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: GEOTRACES station number; ranges from 1 through 12 for KN199-04 and 1 through 24 for KN204-01. Stations 7 and 9 were skipped on KN204-01. Some GeoFish stations are denoted as X_to_Y indicating the tow occurred between stations X and Y.  Values were added from the intermediate US GEOTRACES master file (see Processing Description).; General Description: consecutive station number</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits33129">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33129.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33129.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>dimensionless</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33130.rdf" xlink:title="depth" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>depth_GEOTRC_CTD</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType xlink:href="http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P09/current/DEPH/" xlink:title="DEPTH BELOW SEA SURFACE" xlink:actuate="onRequest">                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>depth</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Observation/sample depth in meters; calculated from CTD pressure.  PI-supplied values were identical to those in the intermediate US GEOTRACES master file. Originally submitted as 'Depth [m]', this parameter name has been changed to conform to BCO-DMO's GEOTRACES naming conventions.; General Description: observation/sample depth, in meters; best estimate; usually but not always calculated from pressure; calculated either from CTD pressure using Fofonoff and Millard (1982; UNESCO Tech Paper #44) algorithm adjusted for 1980 equation of state for seawater (EOS80) or simply equivalent to nominal depth as recorded during sampling if CTD pressure was unavailable NERC Description: The distance of a sensor or sampling point below the sea surface.</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits33130">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33130.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33130.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>meters</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33131.rdf" xlink:title="event" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>event_GEOTRC</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType>                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>event</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Unique identifying number for US GEOTRACES sampling events; ranges from 2001 to 2225 for KN199-04 events and from 3001 to 3282 for KN204-01 events. Values were added from the intermediate US GEOTRACES master file (see Processing Description).; General Description: event or operation number; often derived from date/time (MMDDHHmm) of sampling and when combined with year (YYYY) is a unique sampling identifier/data processing key.  Date/time is not necessarily in GMT.</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits33131">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33131.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33131.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>dimensionless</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      <gmd:dimension>
        <gmd:MD_Band>
          <gmd:sequenceIdentifier xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33132.rdf" xlink:title="bottle" xlink:actuate="onRequest">
            <gco:MemberName>
              <gco:aName>
                <gco:CharacterString>bottle_GEOTRC</gco:CharacterString>
              </gco:aName>
              <gco:attributeType>                <gco:TypeName>
                  <gco:aName>
                    <gco:CharacterString>bottle</gco:CharacterString>
                  </gco:aName>
                </gco:TypeName>
              </gco:attributeType>
            </gco:MemberName>
          </gmd:sequenceIdentifier>
          <gmd:descriptor>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI-supplied Description: Alphanumeric characters identifying bottle type (e.g. NIS representing Niskin and GF representing GOFLO) and position on a CTD rosette. Values were added from the intermediate US GEOTRACES master file (see Processing Description).; General Description: water bottle number, generally assigned to a position on a CTD rosette, identifies all samples drawn from a given bottle</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:descriptor>
          <gmd:units>
            <gml:UnitDefinition gml:id="_parameterUnits33132">
             <gml:identifier codeSpace="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33132.rdf">http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/dataset-parameter/33132.rdf</gml:identifier>
             <gml:name>dimensionless</gml:name>
          </gml:UnitDefinition>
          </gmd:units>
        </gmd:MD_Band>
      </gmd:dimension>
      </gmi:MI_CoverageDescription>
  </gmd:contentInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributor>
        <gmd:MD_Distributor>
          <gmd:distributorContact>
            <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  <gmd:organisationName>
    <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/affiliation/191.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Biological and Chemical Oceanography Data Management Office (BCO-DMO)</gmx:Anchor>
  </gmd:organisationName>
  <gmd:contactInfo>
    <gmd:CI_Contact>
		  <gmd:phone>
		    <gmd:CI_Telephone>
				  <gmd:voice>
				    <gco:CharacterString>Unavailable</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:voice>
				  <gmd:facsimile>
				    <gco:CharacterString>508-289-2009</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:facsimile>
				</gmd:CI_Telephone>
		  </gmd:phone>
		  <gmd:address>
		    <gmd:CI_Address>
				  <gmd:deliveryPoint>
				    <gco:CharacterString>WHOI MS#36</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:deliveryPoint>
				  <gmd:city>
				    <gco:CharacterString>Woods Hole</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:city>
				  <gmd:administrativeArea>
				    <gco:CharacterString>MA</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:administrativeArea>
				  <gmd:postalCode>
				    <gco:CharacterString>02543</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:postalCode>
				  <gmd:country>
				    <gco:CharacterString>USA</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:country>
				  <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
				    <gco:CharacterString>info@bco-dmo.org</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
		    </gmd:CI_Address>
		  </gmd:address>
      <gmd:onlineResource>
          <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
            <gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:URL>http://www.bco-dmo.org</gmd:URL>
            </gmd:linkage>
          </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
        </gmd:onlineResource>
		  <gmd:hoursOfService>
        <gco:CharacterString>Monday - Friday 8:00am - 5:00pm</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:hoursOfService>
		  <gmd:contactInstructions>
		    <gco:CharacterString>For questions regarding this resource, please contact BCO-DMO via the email address provided.</gco:CharacterString>
		  </gmd:contactInstructions>
		</gmd:CI_Contact>
  </gmd:contactInfo>
  <gmd:role>
    <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="pointOfContact" codeSpace="007">pointOfContact</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
  </gmd:role>
</gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
          </gmd:distributorContact>
        </gmd:MD_Distributor>
      </gmd:distributor>
      <gmd:transferOptions>
        <gmd:MD_DigitalTransferOptions>
        <gmd:onLine>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>http://www.bco-dmo.org/dataset/3822/data/download</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:function>
                <gmd:CI_OnLineFunctionCode codeList="http://www.ngdc.noaa.gov/metadata/published/xsd/schema/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_OnLineFunctionCode" codeListValue="download">download</gmd:CI_OnLineFunctionCode>
              </gmd:function>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onLine>
        </gmd:MD_DigitalTransferOptions>
      </gmd:transferOptions>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <gmd:dataQualityInfo>
    <gmd:DQ_DataQuality>
      <gmd:scope>
        <gmd:DQ_Scope>
          <gmd:level>
            <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="http://www.ngdc.noaa.gov/metadata/published/xsd/schema/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset">dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
          </gmd:level>
        </gmd:DQ_Scope>
      </gmd:scope>
      <gmd:lineage>
        <gmd:LI_Lineage>
          <gmd:processStep xlink:title="Acquisition Description">
            <gmd:LI_ProcessStep>
              <gmd:description>
                <gco:CharacterString>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Sampling Methods&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;The samples (with the exception of surface samples) were collected for trace metal determinations at 21 stations from the RV Knorr using a custom-built US GEOTRACES trace metal clean rosette consisting of an epoxy painted Al rosette frame containing 24x12 L GO-FLO bottles (Cutter and Bruland, 2012). Immediately after the package was recovered, the tops of the GO-FLO bottles were covered with plastic bags and the bottles were removed from the frame and carried into the US GEOTRACES clean van for sub-sampling. The GO-FLO bottles were pressurized to 10 psi using 0.2 µm-filtered compressed air and samples were filtered through 0.2 µm Acropak filters. All sub-sampling was undertaken in the clean van using rigorous trace metal protocols. Surface samples are from the towed fish surface sampling system.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Analytical Methods&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;FIA Sample Preparation&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;: Samples were drawn into pre-numbered 125 ml PMP bottles after three rinses and were stored in plastic bags in the dark at room temperature before determination which was usually within 12 -36 hours of collection. Prior to determination samples were acidified by the addition of 125 ul sub-boiling distilled 6N HCl (hereinafter 6N HCl) and were microwaved in groups of 4 for 3 minutes in a 900 W microwave oven to achieve a temperature of 60+10 °C. Samples were allowed to cool for at least 1 hour prior to determination. Samples were determined in groups of 8.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;FIA Standards&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;: Shipboard mixed standards (Al and Fe, Mn) were prepared in the shore-based laboratory by serial dilution of commercial Al, Fe, and Mn standards (BDH Aristar) into distilled water which was acidified with the equivalent of 4 ml sub-boiled 6N HCl. Standards for instrument calibration were prepared daily from filtered seawater by acidifying 1 L of low Fe seawater from a previous cast with 1 ml of 6N HCl and microwaving for 5 minutes to reach a temperature of 60 + 10°C. After 1 hour, 200 + 2 ml of the cooled seawater was added to each of three 250 ml PMP bottles each of which had been rinsed three times with the microwaved seawater and shaken dry. Working standards were prepared by adding 0, +100µL, +200µL spikes of the shipboard mixed standard to these bottles, to yield a standard curve of +20.77nM and +31.53nM for Al, +0.97nM and +1.94nM for Fe, +3.84nM and +7.68nM for Mn. The system blank from the addition of the acid and buffer to samples was determined by double spiking a replicate sample i.e. by adding 2 x 125 ul 6N HCl and 5 ml of sample buffer to the replicate bottle and comparing the resulting signal to the original sample.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Dissolved Al Concentrations&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;: Dissolved Al was determined using a Flow Injection Analysis scheme with fluorometric detection. Major components were a Rabbit peristaltic pump, a Dynamax FL-1 fluorometer, a Rainin A/D board and a Macintosh G3 computer running Rainin MacIntegrator v 1.4.3 to log and reduce data. The analytical scheme produces a complex between lumogallion and dissolved Al which when excited at 484 nm produces flourescence at 552 nm. Detailed description of the methodology is published in Resing and Measures (1994).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;A 3-minute pre-concentration of sample (~9 ml) onto an 8-hydroxyquinoline (8-HQ) resin column yielded a detection limit of 0.24 and a precision of 4.8% at 1.67 nM.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Dissolved Fe&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;: Dissolved Fe was determined using a Flow Injection Analysis scheme with spectrophotometric detection (Rainin Dynamax UV-C). Major components were a Rabbit peristaltic pump, a Dynamax FL-1 fluorometer, a Rainin A/D board and a Macintosh G3 computer running Rainin MacIntegrator v 1.4.3 to log and reduce data. The spectrophotometric detection of the iron eluted from the column is achieved through its catalytic effect on the oxidation of N,N-dimethylp-phenylenediamine dihydrochloride (DPD) the oxidised product is measured at 514 nm. Detailed description of the methodology is published in Measures et al (1995).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;A 3-minute pre-concentration of sample (~9 ml) onto an 8-hydroxyquinoline (8-HQ) resin column yielded a detection limit of 0.064 nM and a precision of 2.8%.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Dissolved Mn&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;: Dissolved Mn was determined using a Flow Injection Analysis scheme with spectrophotometric detection (Rainin Dynamax UV-C). Major components were a Rabbit peristaltic pump, a Dynamax FL-1 fluorometer, a Rainin A/D board and a Macintosh G3 computer running Rainin MacIntegrator v 1.4.3 to log and reduce data. The spectrophotometric detection of the manganese eluted from the column is achieved through its catalytic effect on the formation of malachite green which is measured at 620 nm. Detailed description of the methodology is published in Resing and Mottl (1992).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;A 3-minute pre-concentration of sample (~9 ml) onto an 8-hydroxyquinoline (8-HQ) resin column yielded a detection limit of 0.03 nM and a precision of 2.9% at 0.05 nM.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Calculation of FIA data&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;: Calculation of sample concentrations was by dividing the peak height derived from sample using the A/D software by the calculated slope of the standard curve. Variations in the slope of the standard curve during a day's run were corrected by the following procedure.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The change in the value of the slope of the standard curve between each run of standards was divided by the number of samples run between those standards to provide a calculated value for the slope of the standard curve at the point each sample was run. The value of the peak height for each sample was then recalculated by the estimated ratio of the standard curve slope at the point that sample was run. The estimate of the slope at each sample run is calculated by: (Initial slope + (incremental change per sample X # of samples run since initial standard was run)). The sample concentration is then calculated from the initial standard curve slope.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Data correction with shore-based ICPMS data&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Shipboard determined dissolved Fe and Mn have been corrected using the shore-based ICPMS data that was measured by co-PI Dr. Jingfeng Wu. That data will be submitted separately.&amp;amp;nbsp; The corrected FIA data was calculated using the slope and the intercept of the correlation plot between the ICPMS data and FIA data on each of the days the FIA was run.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Shipboard dissolved Fe: Shipboard calculation:&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;The Fe concentration of samples was determined by dividing the sample peak height by the slope of the Fe standard solution. The standard curve was produced by adding +0 µL (+0 nM), +100 µL (+0.972 nM), +200 µL (+1.944 nM) of the shipboard standard solution into 200 mL aliquots of seawater. This seawater was obtained from a 1L sample of seawater (usually from near the chlorophyll max) that had been filtered through a 0.2 µm pore-size Acropack cartridge, acidified with 1 ml of 6N HCl (sub boiling distilled) and microwaved to achieve a temperature of 60 + 10°C. A typical standard curve is shown in Figure 1.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Figure 1. Fe standard curve from the standard addition method. (click on the image to view a larger version) &amp;lt;!-- height=&amp;quot;374&amp;quot; --&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://bcodata.whoi.edu/US_GEOTRACES/AtlanticSection/CMeasures_Hatta/GT11_Figure1.png&amp;quot; target=&amp;quot;_blank&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img alt=&amp;quot;&amp;quot; src=&amp;quot;http://bcodata.whoi.edu/US_GEOTRACES/AtlanticSection/CMeasures_Hatta/GT11_Figure1.png&amp;quot; style=&amp;quot;width:519px&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The shipboard standard solution was 1.944 µM and had been prepared by gravimmetric dilution from a high purity standard solution (1000 µg/mL) at the shore-based laboratory of University of Hawaii. Overall precision is 2.8%, and the average detection limit is 0.064 nM.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Shipboard dissolved Fe: Blank calculation:&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;At sea the blank calculation of the data was made using the value derived from a sample that had been spiked with EDTA. This process yields a sample that should have no uncomplexed Fe thus allowing subtraction of the system blank.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Shore based adjustment of the shipboard data was made by comparison with the shore-based ICP MS data measured by J. Wu at U Miami. A plot of each station's data (FIA vs ICP MS) yielded a slope and intercept that was then used to recalculate the shipboard data. This indicated that the shipboard blank correction was underestimating the system blank.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Table 1.&amp;amp;nbsp; Slope and intercept between shipboard FIA (substituted EDTA blank) and ICPMS data&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Station&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; Slope&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; Intercept&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; R2&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-01&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.470&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; -0.022&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.944&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-02&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.272&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.057&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.869&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-03&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.144&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.205&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.948&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-06&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.079&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.277 &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.930&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-08&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.036&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.208&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.948&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-10&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.399&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.103&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.974&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-12&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.114&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.441&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.797&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-14&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.152&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.199&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.947&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-16&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.216&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.105 &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.988&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-18&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.943&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.180 &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.932&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-20&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.980&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.256&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.903&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-22&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.967&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.394&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.964&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-24&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.605&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.318&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.964&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;The ICPMS data reported by Miami (Dr. Wu) were only for full depth stations. Two of the demi stations were determined at sea on the same day that full depth stations were run specifically GT11-17 and GT 16; GT11-23 and GT11-22.&amp;amp;nbsp; Thus, these samples were adjusted using the same slope and intercept used for the full depth station. However, the other demi station samples were determined on separate days. Thus, the samples cannot currently be adjusted with existing ICPMS data.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The following demi stations have not been adjusted and are not reported: USGT11-05, USGT11-11, USGT11-13, USGT11-18, and USGT11-21.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Shipboard dissolved Fe: Accuracy results:&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;There are no shipboard results for the recoveries of Certified Reference Materials (CRMs) or consensus reference materials (e.g., SAFe water) as these samples are too acid to be run using this protocol. Instead these data are corrected using the shore-based ICP MS values which are calibrated against SaFe samples.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Shipboard dissolved Mn: Details about calibration:&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;The Mn concentration of sample was calculated using the quadratic polynomial (x= the peak height, y= the Mn standard concentrations, y= M0+M1x+M2x^2). The coefficients (M0, M1, M2) of the polynomial were obtained based on the standard curve.&amp;amp;nbsp; This was produced by the standard addition method adding (+0µL (+0 nM), +100µL (+3.842 nM), +200 µL (+7.683 nM) of the spike standard solution added into the 200mL of seawater which had been filtered through a 0.2µm pore-size Acropack cartridge.). A typical standard curve is shown in Figure 2.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Figure 2. Mn standard curve from the standard addition method, the polynomial fit, and the coefficients of the polynomial approximation. (click on the image to view a larger version) &amp;lt;!-- height=&amp;quot;374&amp;quot; --&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://bcodata.whoi.edu/US_GEOTRACES/AtlanticSection/CMeasures_Hatta/GT11_Figure2.png&amp;quot; target=&amp;quot;_blank&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img alt=&amp;quot;&amp;quot; src=&amp;quot;http://bcodata.whoi.edu/US_GEOTRACES/AtlanticSection/CMeasures_Hatta/GT11_Figure2.png&amp;quot; style=&amp;quot;width:519px&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;The shipboard standard solution was 7.683 µM and had been prepared by gravimmetric dilution from a high purity standard solution (1000µg/mL) at the shore-based laboratory of University of Hawaii. The precision of the method, the relative standard deviation (RSD, %), and detection limit (3sigma; D.L.) were calculated on each analysis day from the triplicate analysis of a spiked standard seawater solution. Results are shown in Mn Table 1, below.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Overall average precision (from Mn Table 1 below) is 2.9%, and the average detection limit is 0.05 nM.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Shipboard dissolved Mn: Blank calculation:&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;There is no blank calculation of the data made at sea. Shore based adjustment of the shipboard data was made by comparison between the shore-based ICP MS data measured by J Wu at RSMAS, and the shipboard calculated data, the intercept being the blank offset between the methodologies. The ICPMS data has been submitted separately.&amp;amp;nbsp; In general, the difference was very small (average difference was + 0.029nM) which is similar to the analytical uncertainty of the shipboard method. The detailed value of the blank for each station is shown in Mn Table 2.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Shipboard dissolved Mn: Accuracy results:&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;There are no shipboard result for the recoveries of Certified Reference Materials (CRMs) or consensus reference materials (e.g., SAFe water) as these samples are too acid to be run using this protocol. Instead these data are corrected to the shore-based ICP MS values which are calibrated against SaFe samples.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Mn Table 1.&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt; Precision, Relative Standard Deviation, and Detection Limit of the shipboard FIA method for dissolved Mn&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Concentration of std. solution for the precision (nM)&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; RSD %&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; D.L (nM)&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-01&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.243&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 2.1&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.079&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-02&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.027&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 3.4&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.103&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-03&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.653&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 2.2&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.043&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-05&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.533&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 3.9&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.062&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-06&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.620&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.6&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.030&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-08&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.443&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.6 &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.021&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-10&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.109&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 2.1&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.070&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-11&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.708&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 3.6&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.076&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-12&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.396&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 3.2&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.038&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-13&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.271&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 2.7&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.022&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-14&amp;amp;amp;15&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.334&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.5&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.015&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-16&amp;amp;amp;17&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.183&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.1&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.006&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-18&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.160&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 4.2 &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.020&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-19&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.128&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.2&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.005&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-20&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.371&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1.2&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.050&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-21&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.713&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 8.5&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.181&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-22&amp;amp;amp;23&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.123&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 4.9&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.018&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-24&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.563&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 3.6&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; 0.061&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Mn Table 2.&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Station&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; Blank (Intercept)&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; Memo&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-01&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0298&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-02&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0626&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-03&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; -0.0151&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-05&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.000&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-06&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0812&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-08&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0099&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-10&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0546&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-11&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.000&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-12&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0610&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-13&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.000&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-14&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0383&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-15*&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0383&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-16 (hydrothermal plume)&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; -0.00910 &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-17&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; -0.0091&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-18&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.0154&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-19&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.000&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-20&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.256&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; Blank problem&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-21&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 0.029&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; No ICP MS use average blank correction&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-22&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; -0.0047&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-23&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; -0.0047&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;USGT11-24&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; -0.0334&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Shipboard dissolved Al data: UH Shipboard methodology&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;UH Dissolved Al samples are run at sea using standards prepared from a bulk standard which has been diluted using gravimetry. We make two bottles of each working standard and take both bottles to sea but only use one of the bottles at sea (unless we think a bottle has been compromised). We bring both the unused and the partially used bottles of standard back to our laboratory for long term intercalibration. Aliquots of the shipboard standard are added to 200ml seawater samples that are obtained from a single bottle of 1L of seawater that has been acidified and microwaved and then cooled, to produce a standard curve that has +0, +20.77, +31.53 nM added Al. The concentration of Al in any sample is obtained by dividing the peak height of the sample by the slope of the peak height/nM of the standard curve. The intercept of the standard curve is not used since the &amp;quot;0&amp;quot; standard is not a true 0, but is the amount of Al already in the water used to produce the standards.&amp;amp;nbsp; We have not found that there is any procedural blank in this method (from double spiking samples with buffer and acid) and thus do not subtract any blank from the calculated values.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Comparison between UH and NIOZ Al data sets at BATS &amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;In our opinion, the offset between the University of Hawaii and the NIOZ Al data sets in the Atlantic crossover station at Bermuda (Station S), appears to be a result of standard disagreement. This conclusion is based on the following analysis.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;A plot of the two profiles shows the vertical distribution of the two data sets (24 NIOZ samples collected 12 June 2010 and 36 UH samples collected 19 November 2011). There are significant differences between the two profiles in the upper waters, particularly the surface waters, but this is hardly surprising given the 1.5 years between the two occupations and the times of year that they were conducted (June and November). Given that the upper water concentrations of dissolved Al are predominantly a function of atmospheric deposition and its incorporation into subsurface waters&amp;amp;nbsp; (Sub-Tropical Mode Waters) through subduction processes we have not attempted to derive conclusions from this part of the water column since they are likely to be highly temporally variable.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;We are also excluding the data deeper than 4002 m since the shape of the two profiles which both appear to be oceanographically consistent appear to be quite different from each other, which we take to also be a difference due to variations in the strength of, or presence of, a bottom nepheloid layer between the two occupations.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Instead we focus on the region from 974m to 4002m where there is a clear and consistent offset between the two data sets.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;A complicating factor in making the comparison though is that the samples from the&amp;amp;nbsp; two data sets are not at the same depths. In order to make a cross plot we have binned the two data sets to correspond to similar sampling depths (see attached table for the binning). Most of the samples are within ~50m depth, but two samples, (`3600 and 3900 are ~ 100m apart).&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;The plot of the 9 corresponding data points from the two, shows a very clear correlation between the data sets&amp;amp;nbsp; (R=0.993) with a slope of 1.251. Virtually all of the data fall exactly on this line. If the somewhat anomalous point at 2500m in the UH data set is eliminated R increases slightly to R=0.9965 and the slope drops slightly to 1.24.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;The implication of this is that the difference between these data sets is the result of a simple standard offset. A blank offset would lead to a constant difference between the data sets, which is not what this plot implies.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;We do not have access to the NIOZ standards and have been informed by R. Middag that there are no aliquots left of the standard they actually used at sea. He is trying to track down the original stock standard that their shipboard standard was prepared from and we plan to obtain an aliquot of this to check against our standard.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Meanwhile, in an attempt to identify any possible source of the offset in our own standards we have rerun both our original concentrated standard used to produce our shipboard standards as well as the actual standards that we used on board ship during both GT10 and GT11 cruises. The results are as follows:&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;- UH Concentrated standard (used to produce the shipboard standards) was diluted to produce a standard curve. (Standard A)&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;- GT10 and GT11 shipboard standards were then run and calculated against this concentrated standard curve.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;- Another concentrated Al standard (Standard B) was procured from a different laboratory at UH and a dilution was made of this standard and it was run against Standard A.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Results of the standard intercomparison as a % of the expected value--all relative to Standard A:&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;GT10 93.0%&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;GT11 95.3%&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Standard B 95.5%&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Conclusions:&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt; Relative to Standard B, Standard A is 4.5% high, which could be the result of evaporation in that bottle. However these results which imply our standard maybe 4.5% high are preliminary and we intend to rerun all the standards again when we can get an aliquot of the NIOZ standard. We are also purchasing a new stock standard to evaluate the agreement between Standards A and B.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;An evaporated stock standard will lead to an underestimate in the true value of the sample, so if anything our current understanding of our Al values is that they maybe 4.5% lower than the true value. We note an ~2.5% offset between the GT10 and GT11 standards which maybe a result of evaporation of the GT10 shipboard standard. We will compare the unused GT10 standard with the newly purchased concentrated standard when it arrives. We also hope to have an aliquot of the NIOZ standard at that point.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;We also note that the NIOZ data are reported as per kg, whereas ours are volume based (we measure by volume at sea and so report in those units). Depending on the value they used to convert their data (we are assuming here that their values were originally on a per volume basis), the NIOZ data would be ~2.8% lower than the UH data.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:description>
            </gmd:LI_ProcessStep>
          </gmd:processStep>
          <gmd:processStep xlink:title="Processing Description">
            <gmd:LI_ProcessStep>
              <gmd:description>
                <gco:CharacterString>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;!--[if gte mso 9]&amp;gt;&amp;lt;xml&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:WordDocument&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:View&amp;gt;Normal&amp;lt;/w:View&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:Zoom&amp;gt;0&amp;lt;/w:Zoom&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:TrackMoves /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:TrackFormatting /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:PunctuationKerning /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:ValidateAgainstSchemas /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:SaveIfXMLInvalid&amp;gt;false&amp;lt;/w:SaveIfXMLInvalid&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:IgnoreMixedContent&amp;gt;false&amp;lt;/w:IgnoreMixedContent&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:AlwaysShowPlaceholderText&amp;gt;false&amp;lt;/w:AlwaysShowPlaceholderText&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:DoNotPromoteQF /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LidThemeOther&amp;gt;EN-US&amp;lt;/w:LidThemeOther&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LidThemeAsian&amp;gt;X-NONE&amp;lt;/w:LidThemeAsian&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LidThemeComplexScript&amp;gt;X-NONE&amp;lt;/w:LidThemeComplexScript&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:Compatibility&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:BreakWrappedTables /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:SnapToGridInCell /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:WrapTextWithPunct /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:UseAsianBreakRules /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:DontGrowAutofit /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:SplitPgBreakAndParaMark /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:EnableOpenTypeKerning /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:DontFlipMirrorIndents /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:OverrideTableStyleHps /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/w:Compatibility&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:DoNotOptimizeForBrowser /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;m:mathPr&amp;gt;&amp;lt;m:mathFont m:val=&amp;quot;Cambria Math&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;m:brkBin m:val=&amp;quot;before&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;m:brkBinSub m:val=&amp;quot;--&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;m:smallFrac m:val=&amp;quot;off&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;m:dispDef /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;m:lMargin m:val=&amp;quot;0&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;m:rMargin m:val=&amp;quot;0&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;m:defJc m:val=&amp;quot;centerGroup&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;m:wrapIndent m:val=&amp;quot;1440&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;m:intLim m:val=&amp;quot;subSup&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;m:naryLim m:val=&amp;quot;undOvr&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/m:mathPr&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/w:WordDocument&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/xml&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![endif]--&amp;gt;&amp;lt;!--[if gte mso 9]&amp;gt;&amp;lt;xml&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LatentStyles DefLockedState=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; DefUnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot;DefSemiHidden=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; DefQFormat=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; DefPriority=&amp;quot;99&amp;quot;LatentStyleCount=&amp;quot;267&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;0&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Normal&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;9&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;heading 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;0&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;heading 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;0&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;heading 3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;9&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;heading 4&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;9&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;heading 5&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;9&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;heading 6&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;9&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;heading 7&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;9&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;heading 8&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;9&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;heading 9&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;39&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;toc 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;39&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;toc 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;39&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;toc 3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;39&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;toc 4&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;39&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;toc 5&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;39&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;toc 6&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;39&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;toc 7&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;39&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;toc 8&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;39&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;toc 9&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;35&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;10&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Title&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;1&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Default Paragraph Font&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;11&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Subtitle&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;22&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Strong&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;20&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Emphasis&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;59&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Table Grid&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Placeholder Text&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;1&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;No Spacing&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;60&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light Shading&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;61&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light List&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;62&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light Grid&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;63&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Shading 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;64&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Shading 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;65&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium List 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;66&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium List 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;67&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;68&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;69&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;70&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Dark List&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;71&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful Shading&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;72&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful List&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;73&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful Grid&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;60&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light Shading Accent 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;61&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light List Accent 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;62&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light Grid Accent 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;63&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Shading 1 Accent 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;64&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Shading 2 Accent 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;65&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium List 1 Accent 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Revision&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;34&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;List Paragraph&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;29&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Quote&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;30&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Intense Quote&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;66&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium List 2 Accent 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;67&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 1 Accent 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;68&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 2 Accent 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;69&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 3 Accent 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;70&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Dark List Accent 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;71&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful Shading Accent 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;72&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful List Accent 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;73&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful Grid Accent 1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;60&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light Shading Accent 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;61&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light List Accent 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;62&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light Grid Accent 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;63&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Shading 1 Accent 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;64&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Shading 2 Accent 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;65&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium List 1 Accent 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;66&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium List 2 Accent 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;67&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 1 Accent 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;68&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 2 Accent 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;69&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 3 Accent 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;70&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Dark List Accent 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;71&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful Shading Accent 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;72&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful List Accent 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;73&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful Grid Accent 2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;60&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light Shading Accent 3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;61&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light List Accent 3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;62&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light Grid Accent 3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;63&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Shading 1 Accent 3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;64&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Shading 2 Accent 3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;65&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium List 1 Accent 3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;66&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium List 2 Accent 3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;67&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 1 Accent 3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;68&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 2 Accent 3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;69&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 3 Accent 3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;70&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Dark List Accent 3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;71&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful Shading Accent 3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;72&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful List Accent 3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;73&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful Grid Accent 3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;60&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light Shading Accent 4&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;61&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light List Accent 4&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;62&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light Grid Accent 4&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;63&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Shading 1 Accent 4&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;64&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Shading 2 Accent 4&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;65&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium List 1 Accent 4&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;66&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium List 2 Accent 4&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;67&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 1 Accent 4&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;68&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 2 Accent 4&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;69&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 3 Accent 4&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;70&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Dark List Accent 4&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;71&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful Shading Accent 4&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;72&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful List Accent 4&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;73&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful Grid Accent 4&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;60&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light Shading Accent 5&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;61&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light List Accent 5&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;62&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light Grid Accent 5&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;63&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Shading 1 Accent 5&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;64&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Shading 2 Accent 5&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;65&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium List 1 Accent 5&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;66&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium List 2 Accent 5&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;67&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 1 Accent 5&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;68&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 2 Accent 5&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;69&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 3 Accent 5&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;70&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Dark List Accent 5&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;71&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful Shading Accent 5&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;72&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful List Accent 5&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;73&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful Grid Accent 5&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;60&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light Shading Accent 6&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;61&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light List Accent 6&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;62&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Light Grid Accent 6&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;63&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Shading 1 Accent 6&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;64&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Shading 2 Accent 6&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;65&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium List 1 Accent 6&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;66&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium List 2 Accent 6&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;67&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 1 Accent 6&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;68&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 2 Accent 6&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;69&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Medium Grid 3 Accent 6&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;70&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Dark List Accent 6&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;71&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful Shading Accent 6&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;72&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful List Accent 6&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;73&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Colorful Grid Accent 6&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;19&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Subtle Emphasis&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;21&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Intense Emphasis&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;31&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Subtle Reference&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;32&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Intense Reference&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;33&amp;quot; SemiHidden=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;UnhideWhenUsed=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Book Title&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;37&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;Bibliography&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;w:LsdException Locked=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; Priority=&amp;quot;39&amp;quot; QFormat=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; Name=&amp;quot;TOC Heading&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/w:LatentStyles&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/xml&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![endif]--&amp;gt;&amp;lt;!--[if gte mso 10]&amp;gt;&amp;lt;style&amp;gt;/* Style Definitions */table.MsoNormalTable{mso-style-name:&amp;quot;Table Normal&amp;quot;;mso-tstyle-rowband-size:0;mso-tstyle-colband-size:0;mso-style-noshow:yes;mso-style-priority:99;mso-style-parent:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;;mso-padding-alt:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;mso-para-margin-top:0in;mso-para-margin-right:0in;mso-para-margin-bottom:10.0pt;mso-para-margin-left:0in;mso-pagination:widow-orphan;font-size:10.0pt;font-family:&amp;quot;Cambria&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;serif&amp;quot;;mso-ascii-font-family:Cambria;mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;mso-hansi-font-family:Cambria;mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;}&amp;lt;/style&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![endif]--&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Quality Flags:&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Data have been flagged using the WOCE system of flags. Good is 2. Questionable is 3. Bad is 4. Samples that appear to be contaminated have been flagged 3.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Determination of contamination was by agreement with ICP MS data after adjustment (see above).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;For dissolved Fe, samples in which both the ICP MS and the FIA data appear to be bad (not oceanographically consistent) have been flagged 4.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Flagged data from GT11 (2011 cruise):&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Total reported sample count: 420&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Flag 2 (Good): 368&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Flag 3 (Questionable): 49&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Flag 4 (Bad): 3&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;BCO-DMO Processing Notes&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;- Parameter names were modified to conform with BCO-DMO conventions.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;- '-999' values were replaced with 'nd' to indicate 'no data'.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;- The 'lon' parameter was calculated using the 'lon_360' values provided in the original data submission. (lon = lon_360 - 360).&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;- Original data submission received on 12/18/12 was replaced with updated data received on 12/21/12, in which a small error and quality flags have been corrected.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;- 04 March 2013: joined to master GEOTRACES file for consistency with other GEOTRACES datasets. Note: removed BTL_ISO_DateTime_UTC because values were all 'nd'.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;- Dataset updated to new version on 22 May 2013.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;- The dataset was again updated to a newer version (including updates and error fixes) on 14 October 2013 (most recent version).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Additional GEOTRACES Processing:&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;After the data were submitted to the International Data Management Office, BODC, the office noticed that important identifying information was missing in many datasets. With the agreement of BODC and the US GEOTRACES lead PIs, BCO-DMO added standard US GEOTRACES information, such as the US GEOTRACES event number, to each submitted dataset lacking this information. To accomplish this, BCO-DMO compiled a 'master' dataset composed of the following parameters: station_GEOTRC, cast_GEOTRC (bottle and pump data only), event_GEOTRC, sample_GEOTRC, sample_bottle_GEOTRC (bottle data only), bottle_GEOTRC (bottle data only), depth_GEOTRC_CTD (bottle data only), depth_GEOTRC_CTD_rounded (bottle data only), BTL_ISO_DateTime_UTC (bottle data only), and GeoFish_id (GeoFish data only). This added information will facilitate subsequent analysis and inter comparison of the datasets.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;Bottle parameters in the master file were taken from the GT-C_Bottle_GT10, GT-C_Bottle_GT11, ODF_Bottle_GT10, and ODF_Bottle_GT11 datasets. Non-bottle parameters, including those from GeoFish tows, Aerosol sampling, and McLane Pumps, were taken from the Event_Log_GT10 and Event_Log_GT11 datasets. McLane pump cast numbers missing in event logs were taken from the Particulate Th-234 dataset submitted by Ken Buesseler.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;A standardized BCO-DMO method (called &amp;quot;join&amp;quot;) was then used to merge the missing parameters to each US GEOTRACES dataset, most often by matching on sample_GEOTRC or on some unique combination of other parameters.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;If the master parameters were included in the original data file and the values did not differ from the master file, the original data columns were retained and the names of the parameters were changed from the PI-submitted names to the standardized master names. If there were differences between the PI-supplied parameter values and those in the master file, both columns were retained. If the original data submission included all of the master parameters, no additional columns were added, but parameter names were modified to match the naming conventions of the master file.&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;See the dataset parameters documentation for a description of which parameters were supplied by the PI and which were added via the join method.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:description>
            </gmd:LI_ProcessStep>
          </gmd:processStep>
        </gmd:LI_Lineage>
      </gmd:lineage>
   </gmd:DQ_DataQuality>
  </gmd:dataQualityInfo>
  <gmd:metadataMaintenance>
    <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="asNeeded" codeSpace="009">asNeeded</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
      </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
      <gmd:maintenanceNote>
        <gco:CharacterString>7.x-1.1</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:maintenanceNote>
      <gmd:contact>
        <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  <gmd:organisationName>
    <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/affiliation/191.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Biological and Chemical Oceanography Data Management Office (BCO-DMO)</gmx:Anchor>
  </gmd:organisationName>
  <gmd:contactInfo>
    <gmd:CI_Contact>
		  <gmd:phone>
		    <gmd:CI_Telephone>
				  <gmd:voice>
				    <gco:CharacterString>Unavailable</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:voice>
				  <gmd:facsimile>
				    <gco:CharacterString>508-289-2009</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:facsimile>
				</gmd:CI_Telephone>
		  </gmd:phone>
		  <gmd:address>
		    <gmd:CI_Address>
				  <gmd:deliveryPoint>
				    <gco:CharacterString>WHOI MS#36</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:deliveryPoint>
				  <gmd:city>
				    <gco:CharacterString>Woods Hole</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:city>
				  <gmd:administrativeArea>
				    <gco:CharacterString>MA</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:administrativeArea>
				  <gmd:postalCode>
				    <gco:CharacterString>02543</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:postalCode>
				  <gmd:country>
				    <gco:CharacterString>USA</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:country>
				  <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
				    <gco:CharacterString>info@bco-dmo.org</gco:CharacterString>
				  </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
		    </gmd:CI_Address>
		  </gmd:address>
      <gmd:onlineResource>
          <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
            <gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:URL>http://www.bco-dmo.org</gmd:URL>
            </gmd:linkage>
          </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
        </gmd:onlineResource>
		  <gmd:hoursOfService>
        <gco:CharacterString>Monday - Friday 8:00am - 5:00pm</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:hoursOfService>
		  <gmd:contactInstructions>
		    <gco:CharacterString>For questions regarding this resource, please contact BCO-DMO via the email address provided.</gco:CharacterString>
		  </gmd:contactInstructions>
		</gmd:CI_Contact>
  </gmd:contactInfo>
  <gmd:role>
    <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="pointOfContact" codeSpace="007">pointOfContact</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
  </gmd:role>
</gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      </gmd:contact>
    </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
  </gmd:metadataMaintenance>
  <gmi:acquisitionInformation>
    <gmi:MI_AcquisitionInformation>
    <gmi:instrument>
        <gmi:MI_Instrument>
          <gmi:identifier>
            <gmd:MD_Identifier>
              <gmd:code>
                <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/instrument/411.rdf" xlink:title="GO-FLO Bottle" xlink:actuate="onRequest">GO-FLO Bottle</gmx:Anchor>
              </gmd:code>
            </gmd:MD_Identifier>
          </gmi:identifier>
          <gmi:type>
            <gco:CharacterString>GO-FLO Bottle</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmi:type>
          <gmi:description>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI Supplied Instrument Name: GO-FLO Bottle PI Supplied Instrument Description:Sampleswere collected using a  custom-built US GEOTRACES trace metal clean rosette consisting of an  epoxy painted Al rosette frame containing 24x12 L GO-FLO bottles Instrument Name: GO-FLO Bottle Instrument Short Name:GO-FLO   Instrument Description: GO-FLO bottle cast used to collect water samples for pigment, nutrient, plankton, etc. The GO-FLO sampling bottle is specially designed to avoid sample contamination at the surface, internal spring contamination, loss of sample on deck (internal seals), and exchange of water from different depths. Community Standard Description: http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/L05/current/30/</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmi:description>
        </gmi:MI_Instrument>
      </gmi:instrument>
      <gmi:instrument>
        <gmi:MI_Instrument>
          <gmi:identifier>
            <gmd:MD_Identifier>
              <gmd:code>
                <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/instrument/549.rdf" xlink:title="GeoFish Towed near-Surface Sampler" xlink:actuate="onRequest">GeoFish</gmx:Anchor>
              </gmd:code>
            </gmd:MD_Identifier>
          </gmi:identifier>
          <gmi:type>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoFish</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmi:type>
          <gmi:description>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI Supplied Instrument Name: GeoFish PI Supplied Instrument Description:Surface samples are from the towed fish surface sampling system. Instrument Name: GeoFish Towed near-Surface Sampler Instrument Short Name:GeoFish   Instrument Description: The GeoFish towed sampler is a custom designed near surface (&amp;lt;2m) sampling system for the collection of trace metal clean seawater. It consists of a PVC encapsulated lead weighted torpedo and separate PVC depressor vane supporting the intake utilizing all PFA Teflon tubing connected to a deck mounted, air-driven, PFA Teflon dual-diaphragm pump which provides trace-metal clean seawater at up to 3.7L/min. The GeoFish is towed at up to 13kts off to the side of the vessel outside of the ship's wake to avoid possible contamination from the ship's hull. It was developed by Geoffrey Smith and Ken Bruland (University of California, Santa Cruz). Community Standard Description: http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/L05/current/31/</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmi:description>
        </gmi:MI_Instrument>
      </gmi:instrument>
      <gmi:instrument>
        <gmi:MI_Instrument>
          <gmi:identifier>
            <gmd:MD_Identifier>
              <gmd:code>
                <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/instrument/657.rdf" xlink:title="Flow Injection Analyzer" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Flow Injection Analyzer</gmx:Anchor>
              </gmd:code>
            </gmd:MD_Identifier>
          </gmi:identifier>
          <gmi:type>
            <gco:CharacterString>Flow Injection Analyzer</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmi:type>
          <gmi:description>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI Supplied Instrument Name: Flow Injection Analyzer PI Supplied Instrument Description:Dissolved Fe and Mn were determined using a Flow Injection Analysis scheme with  spectrophometric detection (Rainin Dynamax UV-C). Major components of  the scheme include a Rabbit peristaltic pump, a Dynamax FL-1  fluorometer, a Rainin A/D board, and a Macintosh G3 computer running  Rainin MacIntegrator v 1.4.3 to log and reduce data. Instrument Name: Flow Injection Analyzer Instrument Short Name:FIA   Instrument Description: An instrument that performs flow injection analysis. Flow injection analysis (FIA) is an approach to chemical analysis that is accomplished by injecting a plug of sample into a flowing carrier stream. FIA is an automated method in which a sample is injected into a continuous flow of a carrier solution that mixes with other continuously flowing solutions before reaching a detector. Precision is dramatically increased when FIA is used instead of manual injections and as a result very specific FIA systems have been developed for a wide array of analytical techniques. Community Standard Description: http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/L05/current/LAB36/</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmi:description>
        </gmi:MI_Instrument>
      </gmi:instrument>
      <gmi:instrument>
        <gmi:MI_Instrument>
          <gmi:identifier>
            <gmd:MD_Identifier>
              <gmd:code>
                <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/instrument/683.rdf" xlink:title="Flow injection lumogallion system with fluorometer" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Flow injection lumogallion system with fluorometer</gmx:Anchor>
              </gmd:code>
            </gmd:MD_Identifier>
          </gmi:identifier>
          <gmi:type>
            <gco:CharacterString>Flow injection lumogallion system with fluorometer</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmi:type>
          <gmi:description>
            <gco:CharacterString>PI Supplied Instrument Name: Flow injection lumogallion system with fluorometer PI Supplied Instrument Description:Dissolved Al was determined using a Flow Injection Analysis scheme with  fluorometeric detection. The scheme produces a complex between  lumogallion and dissolved Al. Major components of the scheme include a  Rabbit peristaltic pump, a Dynamax FL-1 fluorometer, a Rainin A/D board,  and a Macintosh G3 computer running Rainin MacIntegrator v 1.4.3 to log  and reduce data. Instrument Name: Flow injection lumogallion system with fluorometer Instrument Short Name:FIA with Fluorometer   Instrument Description: An analytical system used to determine concentrations of chemical species in a sample based on the fluorescence from the reaction between lumogallion and the species of interest. The system typically comprises individual components typically including pumps, injection and autosampler valves, preconcentration columns and a fluorometer. The system is normally uniquely assembled for each analysis.(From SeaDataNet) Community Standard Description: http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/L22/current/TOOL0513/</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmi:description>
        </gmi:MI_Instrument>
      </gmi:instrument>
      <gmi:operation>
          <gmi:MI_Operation>
            <gmi:description>
              <gco:CharacterString>Cruise: KN204-01</gco:CharacterString>
            </gmi:description>
            <gmi:identifier>
              <gmd:MD_Identifier>
                <gmd:code>
                  <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/deployment/58786.rdf" xlink:title="Cruise" xlink:actuate="onRequest">KN204-01</gmx:Anchor>
                </gmd:code>
              </gmd:MD_Identifier>
            </gmi:identifier>
            <gmi:status>
              <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="http://www.ngdc.noaa.gov/metadata/published/xsd/schema/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
            </gmi:status>
            <gmi:type>
              <gmi:MI_OperationTypeCode codeList="http://www.ngdc.noaa.gov/metadata/published/xsd/schema/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#MI_OperationTypeCode" codeListValue="real"/>
            </gmi:type>
            <gmi:parentOperation gco:nilReason="inapplicable"/>
            <gmi:platform>
              <gmi:MI_Platform>
                <gmi:citation>
                 <gmd:CI_Citation>
                   <gmd:title>
                     <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://www.whoi.edu/page.do?pid=8157" xlink:actuate="onRequest">R/V Knorr</gmx:Anchor>
                   </gmd:title>
                   <gmd:date gco:nilReason="unknown"/>
                 </gmd:CI_Citation>
                </gmi:citation>
                <gmi:citation>
                 <gmd:CI_Citation>
                   <gmd:title>
                     <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/C17/current/316N" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Community Standard Description</gmx:Anchor>
                   </gmd:title>
                   <gmd:date gco:nilReason="unknown"/>
                 </gmd:CI_Citation>
                </gmi:citation>
                <gmi:identifier>
                  <gmd:MD_Identifier>
                    <gmd:authority>
                      <gmd:CI_Citation>
                        <gmd:title>
                          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/authority/1.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">International Council for the Exploration of the Sea</gmx:Anchor>
                        </gmd:title>
                        <gmd:date gco:nilReason="unknown"/>
                      </gmd:CI_Citation>
                    </gmd:authority>
                    <gmd:code>
                      <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/platform/53994.rdf"
                       xlink:title="316N" xlink:actuate="onRequest">R/V Knorr</gmx:Anchor>
                    </gmd:code>
                  </gmd:MD_Identifier>
                </gmi:identifier>
                <gmi:description>
                  <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/platform/53994.rdf" xlink:title="R/V Knorr" xlink:actuate="onRequest">vessel</gmx:Anchor>
                </gmi:description>
                <gmi:instrument gco:nilReason="unknown"/>
              </gmi:MI_Platform>
            </gmi:platform>
            <gmi:plan>
              <gmi:MI_Plan>
                <gmi:status>
                  <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
                </gmi:status>
                <gmi:citation>
                  <gmd:CI_Citation>
                    <gmd:title>
                      <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/deployment/58786.rdf" xlink:title="Cruise" xlink:actuate="onRequest">KN204-01</gmx:Anchor>
                    </gmd:title>
                    <gmd:date gco:nilReason="unknown"/>
                    <gmd:citedResponsibleParty>
                      <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
                      <gmd:individualName>
                          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/person/50984.rdf" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Dr Edward  A. Boyle</gmx:Anchor>
                        </gmd:individualName>
                        <gmd:organisationName>
                          <gmx:Anchor xlink:href="http://lod.bco-dmo.org/id/affiliation/222.rdf" xlink:title="Affiliation" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</gmx:Anchor>
                        </gmd:organisationName>
                        <gmd:contactInfo>
                        <gmd:CI_Contact>
                          <gmd:onlineResource>
                            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
                              <gmd:linkage>
                                <gmd:URL>http://bcodata.whoi.edu/US_GEOTRACES/AtlanticSection/STS_Prelim_GT11_Doc.pdf</gmd:URL>
                              </gmd:linkage>
                              <gmd:description>
                                <gco:CharacterString>Report describing KN204-01</gco:CharacterString>
                              </gmd:description>
                            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
                          </gmd:onlineResource>
                        </gmd:CI_Contact>
                      </gmd:contactInfo>
                      <gmd:role>
                        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/resources/Codelist/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="principalInvestigator"/>
                      </gmd:role>
                      </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
                    </gmd:citedResponsibleParty>
                   </gmd:CI_Citation>
                </gmi:citation>
              </gmi:MI_Plan>
            </gmi:plan>
            </gmi:MI_Operation>
      </gmi:operation></gmi:MI_AcquisitionInformation>
  </gmi:acquisitionInformation>
</gmi:MI_Metadata>
