<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>P. Ryan Jackson</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Spatial distribution of depth-averaged velocity measured in the Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal, Chicago, IL (March 2-3, 2010)</title>
        <geoform>CSV file of time- and depth-averaged velocity data (5-second temporal average)</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7S180KR</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>These data were collected using a 600 kHz TRDI Rio Grande acoustic Doppler current profiler (ADCP) in mode 12 with 50 centimeter bins from a moving boat.  The data were georeferenced with a Trimble Ag132 differential Global Positioning System (GPS) receiver with submeter accuracy.  The data have been depth-averaged over the entire measured portion of the water column and temporally averaged over 5-second intervals to reduce noise.  These data were collected during water-quality surveys of the right bank of the Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal (CSSC) and include low-velocity regions of the canal such as barge slips in addition to the main channel. Data were processed using the Velocity Mapping Toolbox (Parsons and others, 2013). Any data assigned a value of "-9999" are bad or missing data and should not be used for analysis.&#xD;
&#xD;
Parsons, D. R., Jackson, P. R., Czuba, J. A., Engel, F. L., Rhoads, B. L., Oberg, K. A., Best, J. L., Mueller, D. S., Johnson, K. K. and Riley, J. D. (2013), Velocity Mapping Toolbox (VMT): a processing and visualization suite for moving-vessel ADCP measurements. Earth Surf. Process. Landforms, 38: 1244–1260. doi: 10.1002/esp.3367</abstract>
      <purpose>These data were collected to accompany water-quality surveys of the lower Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal targeting identification of potential inflows of Des Plaines River water through the fractured bedrock that separates the two water bodies.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Relevant information from field notes:&#xD;
3/3/2010 09:05 Central Standard Time (CST) Passing downstream-bound barge&#xD;
3/3/2010 11:17 CST Being passed by upstream-bound barge&#xD;
3/3/2010 11:24 CST In wake of upstream-bound barge</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20100302</begdate>
          <enddate>20100303</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>In work</progress>
      <update>Not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal, Chicago, IL</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-88.14331054695</westbc>
        <eastbc>-87.775268554777</eastbc>
        <northbc>41.791466470932</northbc>
        <southbc>41.606901063461</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Velocity</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal</placekey>
        <placekey>Illinois</placekey>
        <placekey>Cook County</placekey>
        <placekey>Will County</placekey>
        <placekey>DuPage County</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>P. Ryan Jackson</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Illinois Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>405 N. Goodwin Ave.</address>
          <city>Urbana</city>
          <state>IL</state>
          <postal>61801</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>2173289719</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pjackson@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>Great Lakes Restoration Initiative</datacred>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Dataset is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>n/a</methtype>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data processed per the Velocity Mapping Toolbox (VMT) v. 4.07 ASCII2GIS utility with full-depth averaging and 5-second temporal averaging.  &#xD;
For details on VMT and its utilities, see:  https://hydroacoustics.usgs.gov/movingboat/VMT/VMT.shtml&#xD;
NOTE: Any data assigned a value of "-9999" are bad or missing data and should not be used for analysis.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160321</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Point</direct>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <geograph>
        <latres>1.0E-6</latres>
        <longres>1.0E-6</longres>
        <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
      </geograph>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>World Geodetic System 1984</horizdn>
        <ellips>WGS84</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>NOTE: Any data assigned a value of "-9999" are bad or missing data and should not be used for analysis. &#xD;
NAME DESCRIPTION&#xD;
EnsNo Ensemble Number&#xD;
Year Year of sample&#xD;
Month Month of sample&#xD;
Day Day of sample&#xD;
Hour Hour of sample&#xD;
Min Minute of sample&#xD;
Sec Second of sample&#xD;
Lat_WGS84 Latitude in WGS84&#xD;
Lon_WGS84 Longitude in WGS84&#xD;
Heading_deg Heading reading at time of sample in degrees from true north&#xD;
Pitch_deg Pitch reading at time of sample in degrees&#xD;
Roll_deg Roll reading at time of sample in degrees&#xD;
Temp_C Temperature at time of sample in deg. C&#xD;
Depth_m Mean bed depth at time of sample in meters&#xD;
B1Depth_m Beam 1 bed depth at time of sample in meters&#xD;
B2Depth_m Beam 2 bed depth at time of sample in meters&#xD;
B3Depth_m Beam 3 bed depth at time of sample in meters&#xD;
B4Depth_m Beam 4 bed depth at time of sample in meters&#xD;
Backscatter_db Acoustic backscatter in dB&#xD;
DAVeast_cmps Depth- or Layer-averaged velocity (east component) in cm/s&#xD;
DAVnorth_cmps Depth- or Layer-averaged velocity (north component) in cm/s&#xD;
DAVmag_cmps Depth- or Layer-averaged velocity magnitude in cm/s&#xD;
DAVdir_deg Depth- or Layer-averaged velocity direction in degrees&#xD;
from true north&#xD;
DAVvert_cmps Depth- or Layer-averaged velocity (vertical) in cm/s (+ is up)</eaover>
      <eadetcit>https://hydroacoustics.usgs.gov/movingboat/VMT/VMT.shtml (see The Velocity Mapping Toolbox Users Guide, specifically the output file format for the ASCII2GIS utility).</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>U.S. Geological Survey – ScienceBase</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey – ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also may contain copyrighted materials if noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items must be secured from the copyright owner whenever applicable. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although the data have been subjected to rigorous review and are substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, the data are released on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from authorized or unauthorized use. Although the data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey or the U.S. Government shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Users of the data are advised to read all metadata and associated documentation thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>ZIP</formname>
          <formvern>none</formvern>
          <formcont>This WinZip file contains two CSV files (.csv), one with depth-averaged velocity data (with a 5-second temporal average applied) for the Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal for the days March 2, 2010 (20100302_DAV_5secAVG.csv)  and March 3, 2010 (20100303_DAV_5secAVG.csv) along with associated metadata.</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7S180KR</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160428</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>P. Ryan Jackson</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Illinois Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Hydrologist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>405 N. Goodwin Ave.</address>
          <city>Urbana</city>
          <state>IL</state>
          <postal>61801</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>2173289719</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pjackson@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>

