<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Frank L. Engel</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Survey of velocity at cross sections in the Des Plaines River near Brandon Road Lock and Dam, Joliet, Illinois (October 20, 2015)</title>
        <geoform>Microsoft Excel spreadsheet (*.xlsx)</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F76W986V</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>These data were collected using a 1200 kHz TRDI Rio Grande acoustic Doppler current profiler (ADCP) in mode 12 with 25 centimeter bins from a moving boat.  The data were georeferenced with a Hemisphere V102 differential Global Positioning System (GPS) receiver with submeter accuracy.  The data were processed in the Velocity Mapping Toolbox (Parsons and others, 2013) to obtain a mean velocity field for each cross section from individual transects at each cross section.  These data were collected in support of the US Army Corps of Engineers Great Lakes and Mississippi River Interbasin Study (GLMRIS), and were concurrent with a dye-tracing study.  NOTE: Any data assigned a value of "-9999" are invalid or missing data and should not be used for analysis. 
	  
	  Parsons, D. R., Jackson, P. R., Czuba, J. A., Engel, F. L., Rhoads, B. L., Oberg, K. A., Best, J. L., Mueller, D. S., Johnson, K. K. and Riley, J. D. (2013), Velocity Mapping Toolbox (VMT): a processing and visualization suite for moving-vessel ADCP measurements. Earth Surf. Process. Landforms, 38: 1244–1260. doi: 10.1002/esp.3367</abstract>
      <purpose>These data were collected in support of the US Army Corps of Engineers Great Lakes and Mississippi River Interbasin Study (GLMRIS), and were concurrent with a dye-tracing study.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Separate Excel spreadsheets are provided for each cross section and a description of the data within each spreadsheet are provided in the spreadsheet with the data.
	  
	  http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F76W986V</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20151020</begdate>
          <enddate>20151021</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Des Plaines River, Joliet, IL</descgeog>
      <bounding><westbc>-88.1292772293</westbc><eastbc>-88.1040859222</eastbc><northbc>41.5027601604</northbc><southbc>41.4862057787</southbc></bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Velocity</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>Des Plaines River</placekey>
        <placekey>Illinois</placekey>
        <placekey>Will County</placekey>
		<placekey>Brandon Road Lock and Dam</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Frank L. Engel</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Illinois Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>405 N. Goodwin Ave.</address>
          <city>Urbana</city>
          <state>IL</state>
          <postal>61801</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>2173289774</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>fengel@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>Great Lakes and Mississippi River Interbasin Study</datacred>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>n/a</methtype>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data processed per the Velocity Mapping Toolbox (VMT) v. 4.08.
		For details on VMT and its utilities, see:  https://hydroacoustics.usgs.gov/movingboat/VMT/VMT.shtml
		NOTE: Any data assigned a value of "-9999" are invalid or missing data and should not be used for analysis.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160510</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Point</direct>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>Transverse Mercator</mapprojn>
          <transmer>
            <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
            <longcm>-87.0</longcm>
            <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
            <feast>500000.0</feast>
            <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
          </transmer>
        </mapproj>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>World Geodetic System 1984</horizdn>
        <ellips>WGS 84</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>See The Velocity Mapping Toolbox Users Guide for the output file format for the Excel Files (accessed by downloading VMT from https://hydroacoustics.usgs.gov/movingboat/VMT/VMT.shtml. NOTE: Any data assigned a value of "-9999" are invalid or missing data and should not be used for analysis.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>https://hydroacoustics.usgs.gov/movingboat/VMT/VMT.shtml (see The Velocity Mapping Toolbox Users Guide, specifically the output file format for the Excel files).</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>U.S. Geological Survey – ScienceBase</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey – ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>ZIP</formname>
          <formvern>none</formvern>
          <formcont>This WinZip file contains 9 MS Excel files (.xlsx), each containing velocity data from a cross section of the Des Plaines River collected on October 20, 2015.  See The Velocity Mapping Toolbox Users Guide for the output file format for the Excel Files (accessed by downloading VMT from https://hydroacoustics.usgs.gov/movingboat/VMT/VMT.shtml). NOTE: Any data assigned a value of "-9999" are invalid or missing data and should not be used for analysis. File names are assigned a short text description of the spatial location of the measurement associated with the file (e.g. 20151020_VMTout_dsNorthOutfall.xlsx is the data file for a cross section dowstream of the North Outfall). This WinZip file also contains metadata.</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F76W986V</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160510</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Frank L. Engel</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Illinois Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>405 N. Goodwin Ave.</address>
          <city>Urbana</city>
          <state>IL</state>
          <postal>61801</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>2173289774</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>fengel@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>

