<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Paul D. Denning</origin>
        <origin>Gregory K. Lee</origin>
        <origin>Douglas B. Yager</origin>
        <origin>Jeffrey L. Mauk</origin>
        <origin>Matthew Granitto</origin>
        <origin>Bronwen Wang</origin>
        <origin>Melanie B. Werdon</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Data Supporting The Geochemical Atlas of Alaska, 2016</title>
        <geoform>ESRI Shapefiles</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7GF0RK5</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Paul D. Denning</origin>
            <origin>Gregory K. Lee</origin>
            <origin>Douglas B. Yager</origin>
            <origin>Jeffrey L. Mauk</origin>
            <origin>Matthew Granitto</origin>
            <origin>Bronwen Wang</origin>
            <origin>Melanie B. Werdon</origin>
            <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
            <title>The Geochemical Atlas of Alaska, 2016</title>
            <geoform>pdf pamphlet, 272 Digital Maps, Microsoft Excel Spreadsheet, ASCII</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey, Digital Data Series</sername>
              <issue>DS 908</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds908</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>A rich legacy of geochemical data produced since the early 1960s covers the great expanse of Alaska; careful treatment of such data may provide significant and revealing geochemical maps that may be used for landscape geochemistry, mineral resource exploration, and geoenvironmental investigations over large areas. To maximize the spatial density and extent of data coverage for statewide mapping of element distributions, we compiled and integrated analyses of more than 175,000 sediment and soil samples from three major, separate sources: the U.S. Geological Survey, the National Uranium Resource Evaluation program, and the Alaska Division of Geological &amp; Geophysical Surveys geochemical databases. Various types of heterogeneity and deficiencies in these data presented major challenges to our development of coherently integrated datasets for modeling and mapping of element distributions. Researchers from many different organizations and disparate scientific studies collected samples that were analyzed using highly variable methods throughout a time period of more than 50 years, during which many changes in analytical techniques were developed and applied. Despite these challenges, the U.S. Geological Survey has produced a new systematically integrated compilation of sediment and soil geochemical data with an average sample site density of approximately 1 locality per 10 square kilometers (km2) for the entire State of Alaska, although density varies considerably among different areas. From that compilation, we have modeled and mapped the distributions of 68 elements, thus creating an updated geochemical atlas for the State.</abstract>
      <purpose>
Geochemical data provide fundamental constraints on geological, biological, and environmental processes. Geochemical data reveal local enrichments that relate to rock types or point to mineral deposits, and may indicate areas of environmental concern. Geochemical data also show local depletions that may be important for human and wildlife health.
These data show the distribution of elements in sediments throughout Alaska. The data can be used for mineral exploration, environmental geochemistry, geologic mapping, and land use planning.
&gt;
&gt;    Description_of_Geographic_Extent: State of Alaska
&gt;
</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>1960</begdate>
          <enddate>2015</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>publication date</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>179.6546</westbc>
        <eastbc>-129.9939</eastbc>
        <northbc>71.6</northbc>
        <southbc>50.1834</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>geochemistry</themekey>
        <themekey>maps and atlases</themekey>
        <themekey>geochemical processes</themekey>
        <themekey>chemical analysis</themekey>
        <themekey>elements</themekey>
        <themekey>soils</themekey>
        <themekey>sediments</themekey>
        <themekey>geology</themekey>
        <themekey>mathematical modeling</themekey>
        <themekey>datasets</themekey>
        <themekey>data integration</themekey>
        <themekey>geographic information systems</themekey>
        <themekey>hydrologic unit code</themekey>
        <themekey>raster</themekey>
        <themekey>grid</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
        <themekey>geoscientific information</themekey>
        <themekey>economy</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>BLM state themes</themekt>
        <themekey>Alaska</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>BLM data themes</themekt>
        <themekey>geology</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS publication series</themekt>
        <themekey>Data Series</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Federal Agencies and Programs</themekt>
        <themekey>Data Processing</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Common geographic areas</placekt>
        <placekey>Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>United States</placekey>
        <placekey>North America</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Jeffrey L Mauk</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Southwest Region</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>Mail Stop 973, W 6th Ave Kipling St</address>
          <city>Lakewood</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>303-236-5605</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jmauk@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>Support for this study was provided by the USGS Central Mineral and Environmental Resources Science Center (CMERSC) under the leadership of Ian Ridley, the USGS Alaska Science Center (ASC), led by Marti Miller, and the Alaska Division of Geological &amp; Geophysical Surveys (ADGGS). In particular, the Central Region GIS &amp; Information Management Project under the leadership of Carma San Juan, and the Alaska Critical Minerals Cooperative Project, led by Timothy S. Hayes made this study possible. Early discussions with David B. Smith (CMERSC) were very helpful in preparation of our landscape-scale map sheets. Thoughtful, thorough, detailed, and constructive reviews by Steven M. Smith and John D. Horton greatly improved the final products of this study, and they are gratefully acknowledged by the authors. Lisa Binders guidance and assistance have been invaluable in the preparation of this atlas for publication and her involvement has been instrumental in its completion.</datacred>
    <native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft [Unknown] Version 6.2 (Build 9200) ; Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1 (Build 4959) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>
This dataset was derived from the Alaska Geochemical Database Version 2.0 (AGDB2), the National Uranium Resource Evaluation--Hydrogeochemical and Stream Sediment Reconnaissance (NURE-HSSR) database, and the Alaska Division of Geologic and Geophysical Surveys (ADGGS) geochemical database.
&gt;AGDB2: Includes analyses of 92,694 sediment samples and 6,869 soil samples that are contained in the Alaska Geochemical Database version 2.0 (http://pubs.usgs.gov/ds/759/) compiled by Granitto and others (2013). Seventy-three different analytical methods were used to produce the geochemical data for the USGS portion of the database. These samples were collected as part of numerous and diverse USGS studies and projects carried out between 1962 and 2009. The samples were prepared and analyzed according to various USGS standard methods cited in the Completeness Report of this metadata (Miesch and others, 1976; Arbogast, 1990, 1996; Taggart, 2002). Prior to the publication of the AGDB2, many analyses of geochemical samples were not readily accessible because those data were either stored on paper (hard copy) records, or in multiple and separate USGS legacy digital databases that were incomplete or that required recompilation or reformatting for input into GIS systems. Some historical hard copy data were physically recovered from storage facilities that were targeted for decommission and were subsequently digitized. Those data are now digitally archived as part of the AGDB2, thus highlighting the importance of preserving data at risk of being lost, destroyed, or discarded over time. Due to the long time span and the variety of scientific purposes for acquisition of the USGS data, many different field and laboratory methods were used. The 73 analytical methods used to determine geochemical concentrations include various forms of atomic absorption spectroscopy, colorimetry, emission spectrography, fire assay, gravimetry, inductively coupled plasma atomic emission and mass spectrometry, neutron activation analysis, and X-ray fluorescence spectrometry techniques. Granitto and others (2013) provide a complete list of analytical methods for the USGS data. Excepting aggregated best values, all data that are part of the AGDB2 are also archived in the USGS National Geochemical Database (http://mrdata.usgs.gov/geochem/), which stores geochemical data collected for water, sediment, soil, rock, and organic samples.
&gt;NURE-HSSR: The National Uranium Resources Evaluation (NURE) program was initiated in 1973 by the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission, now the Department of Energy, with a primary goal of identifying uranium resources in the United States. The Hydrogeochemical and Stream Sediment Reconnaissance (HSSR) program was one of nine components of NURE. Between 1976 and 1979, the Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory carried out systematic sampling and analyses of stream and lake sediments, and surface waters in Alaska. Four analytical methods were used: quantitative emission spectrography, neutron activation analysis, energy-dispersive X-ray fluorescence spectrometry, and delayed neutron counting. The NURE-HSSR sampling program ended prematurely in 1980 from lack of funding and no database compilation was produced from the 894 data files that had been created in 47 formats.
In 1985, the NURE-HSSR sample archive, original field maps, field notes, and data tapes became the responsibility of the USGS. In 1995, the USGS began a new effort to recompile the NURE-HSSR data by examining and reformatting the data from the original 894 files, and compiling these into an enhanced version of the data that are archived and maintained in the USGS National Geochemical Database (Smith, 1997). Our compilation includes chemical determinations from 65,397 Alaska sediment samples that were retrieved from this enhanced version of the NURE-HSSR data.
&gt;ADGGS: Includes analyses of 10,996 sediment samples collected as part of numerous ADGGS studies and projects between 1960 and 2007. Twenty-nine different analytical methods were used to produce the geochemical data in the ADGGS portion of the database, including seven that were not used by the USGS. These data were provided by the ADGGS and are also available for download at http://www.dggs.alaska.gov/webgeochem.
The following criteria were chosen for selecting data for the data set:
&gt;Each sample must have a valid and unique lab number.
&gt;Each sample must have a latitude and longitude.
&gt;Each sample must be identified as sediment or soil sample.
&gt;Each analytical determination must be linked to a valid and unique lab number.
&gt;Each analytical determination must be identified by analyte.
In addition, samples that could be identified as a processed derivative of sediment and soil samples were removed from the data set. This included heavy-mineral concentrates, single minerals, mineral separates, rock coatings, insoluble residues, weak partial digestions, and leachates.
The samples in this data set were collected for a variety of purposes. Not all samples were subject to the same sample preparation protocol or the same analytical protocol. The samples have been analyzed using documented techniques. For some elements, the methods of chemical analysis were the same throughout the study, while for others, the methods changed as analytical technology improved. Some of the methods used were specifically designed to give a concentration value based on a partial digestion or extraction of the sample. For these methods elements tightly bound in the structure of silicates in the sample are not measured. Therefore, the analytical results from these partial extraction techniques may not be comparable with results from methods designed to measure the total concentration of an element in a sample.
There are 2 renditions of "no data" in data provided in the
report: Because null (blank) values are not permitted in
shapefiles (they will automatically be substituted and shown as
0  a real value), it was necessary, in the shapefile versions of
the data, to create an identifiable value to denote no data. We
chose -9999. However, in the Excel spreadsheets, and in the
geodatabase feature datasets versions, nulls (blanks) are
permitted, so there they are.
</logic>
    <complete>
This data set provides chemical data for Ag, Al, As, Au, B, Ba, Be, Bi, C, Ca, Cd, Ce, Cl, Co, Cr, Cs, Cu, Dy, Er, Eu, F, Fe, Ga, Gd, Ge, Hf, Hg, Ho, In, K, La, Li, Lu, Mg, Mn, Mo, Na, Nb, Nd, Ni, P, Pb, Pd, Pr, Pt, Rb, S, Sb, Sc, Se, Si, Sm, Sn, Sr, Ta, Tb, Te, Th, Ti, Tl, Tm, U, V, W, Y, Yb, Zn, and Zr. In addition, the data set provides location and descriptive information for each sample. Not all the descriptive fields contain information for a particular sample because it was not recorded by the submitter or because it was never entered into the database. No sample will contain analyses for all possible elements. The analytical methods used were selected by the sample submitter based on the goals of the individual project and will vary throughout the data set. The analytical methods, sample preparation protocols, and quality control protocols used for various sample media by the USGS, ADGGS and NURE-HSSR are documented within the metadata records for the associated datasets: AK_geochem_data.xml and AK_wbd_means.xml
</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>
Consistent spatial reference among all samples was required to enable accurate spatial integration of the geochemical data. The USGS datasets contained geographic coordinates that were referenced to various geodetic datums, including the North American Datum of 1927 (NAD 27), the North American Datum of 1983 (NAD 83), and the World Geodetic System of 1984 (WGS 84) whereas the NUREHSSR and ADGGS data coordinates are all referenced to NAD 27. WGS 84, which is nearly identical to NAD 83, was chosen as the common datum for all data in this study because it has become the most widely used for online map information, new GIS data, and is the default datum for GPS instruments. The coordinate calculator function in ERDAS Imagine 2015 software (Hexagon Geospatial, 2014) was used to transform the geographic coordinates of all sample localities to WGS 84 and those new coordinates were added to the NUREHSSR, ADGGS, and USGS sediment and soil sample datasets.
All geographic coordinates of GIS-formatted (geodatabase and shapefile) sample data were also transformed into the Alaska Albers Equal Area Conic projection. This was done  to facilitate spatial distribution modeling of element concentrations and to improve interoperability with other data layers inasmuch as the Alaska Albers Equal Area Conic projection is the projection standard adopted by many State and Federal agencies in Alaska for ease of data integration.
</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>
This section not only describes the geochemical data that were compiled, processed, and integrated for the study, but also outlines the procedures that were used for spatial modeling of distributions those data. These element distribution models form the basis for the atlas map sheets that were produced in this study.
Data Compilation
The detail to which geochemical trends in Alaska could be mapped in prior investigations was limited by sampling density and inconsistent analytical methods (Smith and others, 2013b). To provide a more comprehensive and robust update to the geochemical atlas that was produced by Weaver and others (1983), we have combined analytical data from three major databasesUSGS, NURE-HSSR, and ADGGSfor 175,856 samples, nearly 114 thousand more than were used for the 1983 maps; and we have included distribution maps for 68 elements, 27 more than were provided in the earlier atlas compendium. These additional data have significantly improved the spatial density and extent of sample coverage across the state, and the determinations of additional elements have enhanced the scope of potential applications for this updated collection of map sheets and data compilation.
However, some difficulties arise when combining data of different sample media, with various geodetic datums, from different laboratories, and with different analytical methods. For more than 50 years, legacy data in our compilation were produced from samples that were collected for a wide variety of studies and that were analyzed using 80 different laboratory techniques. Therefore, the data have highly variable accuracy, precision, and associated limits of determination due to the steady and significant improvements in analytical methods during those years. For example, older geochemical data often have relatively high limits of analytical detection, so data for many elements are highly censored, with some having more than 90 percent of their values at levels that are less than the lower determination limit. Thus, the heterogeneous nature of the data in our compilation presents challenges for geochemical data integration and modeling.
USGS data
The USGS part of our compilation includes analyses of 92,694 sediment samples and of 6,869 soil samples that are part of the Alaska Geochemical Database version 2.0 (AGDB2) compiled by Granitto and others (2013). Seventy-three different analytical methods were used to produce the geochemical data for the USGS portion of the database. These samples were collected as part of numerous and diverse USGS studies and projects conducted between 1962 and 2009. The samples were prepared and analyzed according to various USGS standard methods (Arbogast, 1990, 1996; Miesch, 1976; Taggart, 2002). Prior to the AGDB2, many analyses of geochemical samples were not readily accessible because those data were either stored on paper (hard copy) records, or in multiple and separate USGS legacy digital databases that were incomplete or that required recompilation or reformatting for input into GIS systems. Some historical hard copy data were physically recovered from storage facilities that were targeted for decommission and were subsequently digitized. Those data are now digitally archived as part of the AGDB2, thus highlighting the importance of preserving data at risk of being lost, destroyed, or discarded over time. Due to the long time span and the variety of scientific purposes for acquisition of the USGS data, many different field and laboratory methods were utilized. The 73 analytical methods used to determine geochemical concentrations include various forms of atomic absorption spectroscopy, colorimetry, emission spectrography, fire assay, gravimetry, inductively coupled plasmaatomic emission and mass spectrometry, neutron activation analysis, and X-ray fluorescence spectrometry techniques. Granitto and others (2013) provide a complete list of analytical methods for the USGS data. Excepting aggregated best values, all data that are part of the AGDB2 are also archived in the USGS National Geochemical Database, which stores geochemical data collected for water, sediment, soil, rock, and organic samples.
NURE-HSSR data
The National Uranium Resources Evaluation (NURE) program was initiated in 1973 by the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission, which is now the Department of Energy, with a primary goal of identifying uranium resources in the United States. The Hydrogeochemical and Stream Sediment Reconnaissance (HSSR) program was one of nine components of NURE. Systematic sampling and analysis of stream and lake sediments and surface waters was conducted in Alaska by the Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory between 1976 and 1979. Four analytical methods were usedquantitative emission spectrography, neutron activation analysis, energy-dispersive X-ray fluorescence spectrometry, and delayed neutron counting. The NURE-HSSR sampling program ended prematurely in 1980 and no database compilation was produced from the 894 data files that had been created in 47 formats.
In 1985, the NURE-HSSR sample archive, original field maps, field notes, and data tapes became the responsibility of the USGS. In 1995, the USGS began a new effort to recompile the NURE-HSSR data by examining and reformatting the data from the original 894 files, and compiling these into an enhanced version of the data that are archived and maintained in the USGS National Geochemical Database (Smith, 1997). Our compilation includes chemical determinations from 65,397 Alaska sediment samples that were retrieved from this enhanced version of the NURE-HSSR data.
ADGGS data
The Alaska Division of Geological &amp; Geophysical Surveys (ADGGS) part of our compilation includes analyses of 10,996 sediment samples collected as part of numerous ADGGS studies and projects between 1960 and 2007. Twenty-nine different analytical methods were used to produce the geochemical data in the ADGGS portion of the database, including seven that were not used by the USGS. These data were provided by the ADGGS and are also available for download at http://www.dggs.alaska.gov/webgeochem.
</procdesc>
        <procdate>20150301</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>1. Alaska geochemical data for 175,856 samples were compiled from USGS, ADGGS, and NURE-HSSR databases. These data included best value distillations of analyses of 92,694 USGS sediment samples, 6,869 USGS soil samples, and 10,996 ADGGS sediment samples, plus analyses of 65,397 NURE sediment samples. Each of the 4 datasets was assembled in separate spreadsheets.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20150301</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>2. Consistent spatial reference among all samples was needed for accurate spatial integration of the geochemical data. The 4 geochemical datasets contain geographic coordinates (latitude-longitude) that are referenced to various datums; all were converted to the WGS 84 datum reference system. Subsequently, to facilitate spatial analyses, all geographic coordinates were transformed to the Alaska Albers Equal Area Conic projection.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20150301</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>3. All best value data for 68 elements in 175,856 samples were combined and have been provided as GIS shapefiles.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20150301</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Point</direct>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>Albers Conical Equal Area</mapprojn>
          <albers>
            <stdparll>55.0</stdparll>
            <stdparll>65.0</stdparll>
            <longcm>-154.0</longcm>
            <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
            <feast>0.0</feast>
            <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
          </albers>
        </mapproj>
        <planci>
          <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>0.001</absres>
            <ordres>0.001</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>METERS</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D_WGS_1984</horizdn>
        <ellips>WGS_1984</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>USGS Information Services</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225-0046</postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-ASK_USGS (1-888-275-8747)</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>U.S. Geological Survey Data Release for DS 908</resdesc>
    <distliab>
This database, identified as DS 908, has been approved for release
and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS).  Although this
database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially
complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant
to further analysis and review. Furthermore, it is released on
condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held
liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized
use.
Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer
system at the USGS, no warranty expressed or implied is made
regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system,
or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of
distribution constitute any such warranty.  The USGS shall not be
held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described
and/or contained herein.
Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive
purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.
Although this information product, for the most part, is in the
public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in
the text.  Permission to reproduce copyrighted items for other
than personal use must be secured from the copyright owner.
</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>ESRI ArcGIS Shapefiles</formname>
          <formvern>Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1 (Build 4959) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</formvern>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7GF0RK5</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S.Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
          <address>USGS Information Services</address>
          <address>Box 25286</address>
          <address>Denver Federal Center</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-ASK_USGS (1-888-275-8747)</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>http://answers.usgs.gov</cntemail>
        <cntemail>http://store.usgs.gov/</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 908</resdesc>
    <distliab>
This database, identified as DS 908, has been approved for release
and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS).  Although this
database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially
complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant
to further analysis and review. Furthermore, it is released on
condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held
liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized
use.
Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer
system at the USGS, no warranty expressed or implied is made
regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system,
or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of
distribution constitute any such warranty.  The USGS shall not be
held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described
and/or contained herein.
Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive
purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.
Although this information product, for the most part, is in the
public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in
the text.  Permission to reproduce copyrighted items for other
than personal use must be secured from the copyright owner.
</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <nondig>
Available as two dual layer DVDs.
Order from USGS at address above or see the USGS Store at
&lt;http://store.usgs.gov/mod/order.html&gt; for more ordering information.
</nondig>
      <fees>For current charges please see website http://store.usgs.gov/</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160511</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Paul Denning</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Southwest Region</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Physical Science Technician</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>Mail Stop 973, W 6th Ave Kipling St</address>
          <city>Lakewood</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>303-236-1222</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pdenning@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>