<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Neal J. Pastick</origin>
        <origin>Bruce K. Wylie</origin>
        <origin>M. Torre Jorgenson</origin>
        <origin>Shawn J. Nield</origin>
        <origin>Kristofer D. Johnson</origin>
        <origin>Andrew O. Finley</origin>
        <pubdate>20150731</pubdate>
        <title>Probabilistic estimates of the distribution of near-surface (within 1m) permafrost in Alaska.</title>
        <geoform>Raster Digital Data Set</geoform>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7C53HX6</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Neal J. Pastick</origin>
            <origin>M. Torre Jorgenson</origin>
            <origin>Bruce K. Wylie</origin>
            <origin>Shawn J. Nield</origin>
            <origin>Kristofer D. Johnson</origin>
            <origin>Andrew O. Finley</origin>
            <pubdate>20150731</pubdate>
            <title>Distribution of near-surface permafrost in Alaska: Estimates of present and future conditions</title>
            <geoform>Publication (Journal)</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>Remote Sensing of Environment</sername>
              <issue>168</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Tarmani, India</pubplace>
              <publish>Elsevier</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.rse.2015.07.019</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This medium resolution (i.e. 30-m pixels) spatial dataset provides an estimate of the occurrence of near-surface (within 1 m of the ground surface) permafrost in Alaska.  The dataset was developed using a decision-tree model that statistically and spatially extended late-season field observations (n ~ 17,000) using remotely sensed imagery, climatic data, and thematic maps of a wide range of surface and subsurface biophysical characteristics.  To circumvent the use of seasonal frost observations, only thaw-depth measurements taken during late-season months (late July to mid-September) or measurements designated to have no near-surface (within 1m) permafrost were used for model calibration and validation. Individual pixel values represent the probability of encountering near-surface permafrost (i.e. 0 to 100 %), as derived from a tree ensemble model, and pixel values greater than 100 correspond to masked land cover types (i.e. 101 = open water; 102 = perennial ice/snow; 103 = developed; 104 = barren, and; 105 = cultivated areas) as defined by the 2001 National Land Cover Database.  Decision tree models and resultant maps were tested using independent field observations and f-fold cross validations, which indicated that the map product has an overall accuracy of approximately 85 % when using a probability threshold of 50 % (i.e. less than 50 % = near-surface permafrost absent; greater than or equal to 50 % = near-surface permafrost present).</abstract>
      <purpose>High-latitude regions are experiencing rapid and extensive changes in ecosystem composition and function as the result of increases in average air temperature. Increasing air temperatures have led to widespread thawing and degradation of permafrost, which in turn has affected ecosystems, socioeconomics, and the carbon cycle of high latitudes. Research shows that the distribution of permafrost is heterogeneous in nature and that permafrost responds to a wide range of ecological factors. Here we overcome complex interactions between surface and subsurface conditions to map near-surface permafrost using decision-tree models, field observations, remotely sensed and derived data, and climatic indices. The resultant dataset was designed to provide a baseline estimate of the distribution of near-surface (within 1m) permafrost in Alaska which can be useful for regional land-use planning, environmental assessments, and a wide-array of geophysical studies. Temporal inconsistencies between masked land cover data and model input data (2001 vs. ~ 2010) may lead to differences between actual ground and estimated conditions. Subsequently, users may find it useful to mask out additional areas using more recent land cover datasets that were not available at the time of this study.  Study results indicate that more work is needed to better capture permafrost’s response to fire-induced change.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>2001</begdate>
          <enddate>2010</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>publication date</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Unknown</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-173.579902134</westbc>
        <eastbc>-117.451575503</eastbc>
        <northbc>71.354904854</northbc>
        <southbc>52.404332229</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Permafrost</themekey>
        <themekey>Spatial Modeling</themekey>
        <themekey>Pedometrics</themekey>
        <themekey>Remote Sensing</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Alaska</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None. Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</accconst>
    <useconst>Acknowledgement of the authors, their affiliations, and the funding agencies. Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The USGS or the U.S. Government shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, CLIMATE &amp; LAND-USE</cntorg>
          <cntper>Neal J Pastick</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>47914 252nd Street</address>
          <city>Sioux Falls</city>
          <state>SD</state>
          <postal>57198</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>605-594-2652</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>njpastick@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>Research was funded by the U.S. Geological Survey Land Change Science and LandCarbon Program. USGS contract G08PC91508 supported the work of Neal J. Pastick.</datacred>
    <native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows Server 2008 Version 6.0 (Build 6002) Service Pack 2; Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1 (Build 4959) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Independent (across space and time) field observations indicate that map accuracies are approximately 70% and 85% for sample burned and unburned areas, respectively. F-fold cross validation results indicate that the overall map accuracy for the entire map is ~ 85 %.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Spatial context is consistent with previously developed maps for the state. Spatial values are consistent with expected ranges or masked land cover types.</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Decision-tree models were developed to predict the presence-absence and probability of near-surface (within 1 m) permafrost distribution. Users of this product are referred to Pastick et al., (2015) for additional information on processing techniques used in this study. Select land cover types (i.e. open water, perennial ice/snow, developed, barren, cultivated), as defined by 2001 NLCD data, were masked using ERDAS IMAGINE 2011 model maker.</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Raster</direct>
    <rastinfo>
      <rasttype>Grid Cell</rasttype>
      <rowcount>61832</rowcount>
      <colcount>74332</colcount>
      <vrtcount>1</vrtcount>
    </rastinfo>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>Albers Conic Equal Area (ESRI Full Name: Albers_Conic_Equal_Area)</mapprojn>
          <albers>
            <stdparll>55.0</stdparll>
            <stdparll>65.0</stdparll>
            <longcm>-154.0</longcm>
            <latprjo>50.0</latprjo>
            <feast>0.0</feast>
            <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
          </albers>
        </mapproj>
        <planci>
          <plance>row and column</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>30.0</absres>
            <ordres>30.0</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>Meter</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D_WGS_1984</horizdn>
        <ellips>WGS_1984</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed Name="AK_ProbofPF_1m_clipped.img.vat">
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Value</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Probability of near-surface (within 1m of ground surface) permafrost estimates (i.e. 0 - 100 %) and masked land cover classes (i.e. 101 = Open Water; 102 = Perennial Ice/Snow; 103 = Developed; 104 = Barren Land; 105 = Cultivated) as defined by the 2001 National Land Cover Database (Homer et al., 2007).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>105</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Count</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Pixel Count</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>72</rdommin>
            <rdommax>299642127</rdommax>
            <attrunit>Individual 30-m pixels</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <overview>
      <eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes the tabular data associated with the data set. Please review the detailed descriptions that are provided (the individual attribute descriptions) for information on the values that appear as fields/table entries of the data set.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>The entity and attribute information was generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Please review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
    <distliab>Distributor assumes no liability for damage or losses resulting from the use or misuse of this data.</distliab>
    <custom>Data is provided online (http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7C53HX6).</custom>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150804</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, CLIMATE &amp; LAND-USE</cntorg>
          <cntper>Bruce K. Wylie</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>47914 252Nd Street</address>
          <city>Sioux Falls</city>
          <state>SD</state>
          <postal>57198</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>605-594-6078</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>wylie@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>