<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Gregory K. Lee</origin>
        <origin>Douglas B. Yager</origin>
        <origin>Jeffrey L. Mauk</origin>
        <origin>Matthew Granitto</origin>
        <origin>Paul D. Denning</origin>
        <origin>Bronwen Wang</origin>
        <origin>Melanie B. Werdon</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>The Geochemical Atlas of Alaska, 2016 - WBD Means</title>
        <geoform>Vector Digital Data Set (Polygon)</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>USGS Data Series, Data Release</sername>
          <issue>908</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7GF0RK5</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Gregory K. Lee</origin>
            <origin>Douglas B. Yager</origin>
            <origin>Jeffrey L. Mauk</origin>
            <origin>Matthew Granitto</origin>
            <origin>Paul D. Denning</origin>
            <origin>Bronwen Wang</origin>
            <origin>Melanie B. Werdon</origin>
            <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
            <title>The Geochemical Atlas of Alaska, 2016</title>
            <geoform>pdf pamphlet, 272 Digital Maps</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey, Digital Data Series</sername>
              <issue>DS 908</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds908</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>A rich legacy of geochemical data produced since the early 1960s covers the great expanse of Alaska; careful treatment of such data may provide significant and revealing geochemical maps that may be used for landscape geochemistry, mineral resource exploration, and geoenvironmental investigations over large areas. To maximize the spatial density and extent of data coverage for statewide mapping of element distributions, we compiled and integrated analyses of more than 175,000 sediment and soil samples from three major, separate sources: the U.S. Geological Survey, the National Uranium Resource Evaluation program, and the Alaska Division of Geological &amp; Geophysical Surveys geochemical databases. Various types of heterogeneity and deficiencies in these data presented major challenges to our development of coherently integrated datasets for modeling and mapping of element distributions. Researchers from many different organizations and disparate scientific studies collected samples that were analyzed using highly variable methods throughout a time period of more than 50 years, during which many changes in analytical techniques were developed and applied. Despite these challenges, the U.S. Geological Survey has produced a new systematically integrated compilation of sediment and soil geochemical data with an average sample site density of approximately 1 locality per 10 square kilometers (km2) for the entire State of Alaska, although density varies considerably among different areas. From that compilation, we have modeled and mapped the distributions of 68 elements, thus creating an updated geochemical atlas for the State.</abstract>
      <purpose>Geochemical data provide fundamental constraints on geological, biological, and environmental processes. Geochemical data reveal local enrichments that relate to rock types or point to mineral deposits, and may indicate areas of environmental concern. Geochemical data also show local depletions that may be important for human and wildlife health.
These data show the distribution of elements in sediments throughout Alaska. The data can be used for mineral exploration, environmental geochemistry, geologic mapping, and land use planning.
&gt;
&gt;    Description_of_Geographic_Extent: State of Alaska
&gt;</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>1960</begdate>
          <enddate>2015</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>publication date</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-180.0</westbc>
        <eastbc>180.0</eastbc>
        <northbc>67.886789699</northbc>
        <southbc>49.127593501</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>geochemistry</themekey>
        <themekey>maps and atlases</themekey>
        <themekey>geochemical processes</themekey>
        <themekey>chemical analysis</themekey>
        <themekey>elements</themekey>
        <themekey>soils</themekey>
        <themekey>sediments</themekey>
        <themekey>geology</themekey>
        <themekey>mathematical modeling</themekey>
        <themekey>datasets</themekey>
        <themekey>data integration</themekey>
        <themekey>geographic information systems</themekey>
        <themekey>hydrologic unit code</themekey>
        <themekey>raster</themekey>
        <themekey>grid</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
        <themekey>geoscientific information</themekey>
        <themekey>economy</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>BLM state themes</themekt>
        <themekey>Alaska</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>BLM data themes</themekt>
        <themekey>geology</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS publication series</themekt>
        <themekey>Data Series</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Federal Agencies and Programs</themekt>
        <themekey>Data Processing</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Common geographic areas</placekt>
        <placekey>Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>United States</placekey>
        <placekey>North America</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Jeffrey L Mauk</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Southwest Region</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Research Geologist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>Mail Stop 973, W 6th Ave and Kipling St</address>
          <city>Lakewood</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>303-236-5605</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jmauk@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>Support for this study was provided by the USGS Central Mineral and Environmental Resources Science Center (CMERSC) under the leadership of Ian Ridley, the USGS Alaska Science Center (ASC), led by Marti Miller, and the Alaska Division of Geological &amp; Geophysical Surveys (ADGGS). In particular, the Central Region GIS &amp; Information Management Project under the leadership of Carma San Juan, and the Alaska Critical Minerals Cooperative Project, led by Timothy S. Hayes made this study possible. Early discussions with David B. Smith (CMERSC) were very helpful in preparation of our landscape-scale map sheets. Thoughtful, thorough, detailed, and constructive reviews by Steven M. Smith and John D. Horton greatly improved the final products of this study, and they are gratefully acknowledged by the authors. Lisa Binders guidance and assistance have been invaluable in the preparation of this atlas for publication and her involvement has been instrumental in its completion.</datacred>
    <native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft [Unknown] Version 6.2 (Build 9200) ; Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1 (Build 4959) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>This dataset was derived from the Alaska Geochemical Database Version 2.0 (AGDB2), the National Uranium Resource Evaluation--Hydrogeochemical and Stream Sediment Reconnaissance (NURE-HSSR) database, and the Alaska Division of Geologic and Geophysical Surveys (ADGGS) geochemical database.
&gt;AGDB2: Includes analyses of 92,694 sediment samples and 6,869 soil samples that are contained in the Alaska Geochemical Database version 2.0 (http://pubs.usgs.gov/ds/759/) compiled by Granitto and others (2013). Seventy-three different analytical methods were used to produce the geochemical data for the USGS portion of the database. These samples were collected as part of numerous and diverse USGS studies and projects carried out between 1962 and 2009. The samples were prepared and analyzed according to various USGS standard methods cited in the Completeness Report of this metadata (Miesch and others, 1976; Arbogast, 1990, 1996; Taggart, 2002). Prior to the publication of the AGDB2, many analyses of geochemical samples were not readily accessible because those data were either stored on paper (hard copy) records, or in multiple and separate USGS legacy digital databases that were incomplete or that required recompilation or reformatting for input into GIS systems. Some historical hard copy data were physically recovered from storage facilities that were targeted for decommission and were subsequently digitized. Those data are now digitally archived as part of the AGDB2, thus highlighting the importance of preserving data at risk of being lost, destroyed, or discarded over time. Due to the long time span and the variety of scientific purposes for acquisition of the USGS data, many different field and laboratory methods were used. The 73 analytical methods used to determine geochemical concentrations include various forms of atomic absorption spectroscopy, colorimetry, emission spectrography, fire assay, gravimetry, inductively coupled plasma atomic emission and mass spectrometry, neutron activation analysis, and X-ray fluorescence spectrometry techniques. Granitto and others (2013) provide a complete list of analytical methods for the USGS data. Excepting aggregated best values, all data that are part of the AGDB2 are also archived in the USGS National Geochemical Database (http://mrdata.usgs.gov/geochem/), which stores geochemical data collected for water, sediment, soil, rock, and organic samples.
&gt;NURE-HSSR: The National Uranium Resources Evaluation (NURE) program was initiated in 1973 by the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission, now the Department of Energy, with a primary goal of identifying uranium resources in the United States. The Hydrogeochemical and Stream Sediment Reconnaissance (HSSR) program was one of nine components of NURE. Between 1976 and 1979, the Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory carried out systematic sampling and analyses of stream and lake sediments, and surface waters in Alaska. Four analytical methods were used: quantitative emission spectrography, neutron activation analysis, energy-dispersive X-ray fluorescence spectrometry, and delayed neutron counting. The NURE-HSSR sampling program ended prematurely in 1980 from lack of funding and no database compilation was produced from the 894 data files that had been created in 47 formats.
In 1985, the NURE-HSSR sample archive, original field maps, field notes, and data tapes became the responsibility of the USGS. In 1995, the USGS began a new effort to recompile the NURE-HSSR data by examining and reformatting the data from the original 894 files, and compiling these into an enhanced version of the data that are archived and maintained in the USGS National Geochemical Database (Smith, 1997). Our compilation includes chemical determinations from 65,397 Alaska sediment samples that were retrieved from this enhanced version of the NURE-HSSR data.
&gt;ADGGS: Includes analyses of 10,996 sediment samples collected as part of numerous ADGGS studies and projects between 1960 and 2007. Twenty-nine different analytical methods were used to produce the geochemical data in the ADGGS portion of the database, including seven that were not used by the USGS. These data were provided by the ADGGS and are also available for download at http://www.dggs.alaska.gov/webgeochem.
The following criteria were chosen for selecting data for the data set:
&gt;Each sample must have a valid and unique lab number.
&gt;Each sample must have a latitude and longitude.
&gt;Each sample must be identified as sediment or soil sample.
&gt;Each analytical determination must be linked to a valid and unique lab number.
&gt;Each analytical determination must be identified by analyte.
In addition, samples that could be identified as a processed derivative of sediment and soil samples were removed from the data set. This included heavy-mineral concentrates, single minerals, mineral separates, rock coatings, insoluble residues, weak partial digestions, and leachates.
The samples in this data set were collected for a variety of purposes. Not all samples were subject to the same sample preparation protocol or the same analytical protocol. The samples have been analyzed using documented techniques. For some elements, the methods of chemical analysis were the same throughout the study, while for others, the methods changed as analytical technology improved. Some of the methods used were specifically designed to give a concentration value based on a partial digestion or extraction of the sample. For these methods elements tightly bound in the structure of silicates in the sample are not measured. Therefore, the analytical results from these partial extraction techniques may not be comparable with results from methods designed to measure the total concentration of an element in a sample.
There are 2 renditions of "no data" in data provided in the
report: Because null (blank) values are not permitted in
shapefiles (they will automatically be substituted and shown as
0  a real value), it was necessary, in the shapefile versions of
the data, to create an identifiable value to denote no data. We
chose -9999. However, in the Excel spreadsheets, and in the
geodatabase feature datasets versions, nulls (blanks) are
permitted, so there they are.</logic>
    <complete>This data set provides chemical data for Ag, Al, As, Au, B, Ba, Be, Bi, C, Ca, Cd, Ce, Cl, Co, Cr, Cs, Cu, Dy, Er, Eu, F, Fe, Ga, Gd, Ge, Hf, Hg, Ho, In, K, La, Li, Lu, Mg, Mn, Mo, Na, Nb, Nd, Ni, P, Pb, Pd, Pr, Pt, Rb, S, Sb, Sc, Se, Si, Sm, Sn, Sr, Ta, Tb, Te, Th, Ti, Tl, Tm, U, V, W, Y, Yb, Zn, and Zr. In addition, the data set provides location and descriptive information for each sample. Not all the descriptive fields contain information for a particular sample because it was not recorded by the submitter or because it was never entered into the database. No sample will contain analyses for all possible elements. The analytical methods used were selected by the sample submitter based on the goals of the individual project and will vary throughout the data set. The analytical methods, sample preparation protocols, and quality control protocols used for various sample media by the USGS, ADGGS and NURE-HSSR are documented in the following publications:
Adrian, B.M., Arbogast, B.F., Detra, D.E., and Mays, R.E., 1990, Direct-current arc emission spectrographic method for the semiquantitative analysis of rock, stream-sediment, soil, and heavy-mineral concentrate samples, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 100-106, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Adrian, B.M., Arbogast, B.F., Detra, D.E., and Mays, R.E., 1996, Direct-current arc emission spectrographic method for semiquantitative analysis of geologic materials, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 130-143, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Allcott, G.H., and Lakin, H.W., 1974, Statistical summary of geochemical data furnished by 85 laboratories for for six geochemical exploration reference samples: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 74-1003, 103 p.
Allcott, G.H., and Lakin, H.W., 1978, Tabulation of geochemical data furnished by 109 laboratories for six geochemical exploration reference samples: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 78-163, 199 p.
Almond, Hy, 1952, A field method for the determination of traces of cobalt in soils: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 52-5, 6 p.
Almond, Hy, 1953, A field method for the determination of manganese in soils, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Almond, Hy, Bloom, Harold, Crowe, H.E., and Marranzino, A.P., eds., Additional field methods used in geochemical prospecting by the U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 53-278, p. 32-34, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr53278.
Almond, Hy, 1953, A field method for the determination of traces of arsenic in soils, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Almond, Hy, Bloom, Harold, Crowe, H.E., and Marranzino, A.P., eds., Additional field methods used in geochemical prospecting by the U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 53-278, p. 8-13, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr53278.
Almond, Hy, 1953, Field methods for the determination of traces of arsenic in soils--Confined-spot procedure using a modified Gutzeit apparatus: Analytical Chemistry, v. 25, no. 11, p. 1766-1767, accessed March 25, 2016 at DOI: 10.1021/ac60083a056.
Almond, Hy, 1955, Rapid field and laboratory method for the determination of copper in soil and rock, in Contributions to Geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1036-A, p. A1-A8, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1036A.
Almond, Hy, and Bloom, Harold, 1951, A semimicro method for the determination of cobalt in soils and rocks-: a field test using the chromograph: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 125, 6 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir125.
Almond, Hy, Crowe, H.E., and Thompson, C.E., 1955, Rapid determination of germanium in coal, soil and rock, in Contributions to Geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1036-B, p. 9-17, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1036B.
Almond, Hy, Stevens, R.E., and Lakin, H.W., 1953, A confined-spot method for the determination of traces of silver in soils and rocks, in Brannock, W.W. and others, Contributions to geochemistry, 1949: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 992, p. 71-83, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b992.
Annell, C.S., 1956, Controlled atmospheres for spectrochemical analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 653, 28 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei653.
Annell, C.S., 1964, A spectrographic method for the determination of cesium, rubidium and lithium in tektites, in Geological Survey Research 1964, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 501-B, p. B148-B151, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp501B.
Annell, C.S., 1967, Spectrographic determination of volatile elements in silicates and carbonates of geologic interest using an argon d-c arc, in Geological Survey Research 1967, chap. C: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 575-C, p. C132-C136, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp575C.
Annell, C.S., and Helz, A.W., 1960, Spectrochemical analysis using controlled atmospheres with a simple gas jet, in Geological Survey Research 1960, Short papers in the geological sciences: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 400-B, p. B497-B499, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp400B.
Annell, C.S., and Helz, A.W., 1961, A constant-feed direct-current arc: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1084-J; in Contributions to Geochemistry, p. 231-251, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1084J.
Arbogast, B.F., ed., 1990, Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, 184 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Arbogast, B.F., Detra, D.E., and VanTrump, George, Jr., 1987, Statistical summary of geochemical data furnished by 146 laboratories for six geochemical exploration reference samples: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 87-436, 136 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Arbogast, B.F., ed., 1996, Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, 248 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Aruscavage, P.J., 1972, A neutron activation analysis procedure for the determination of mercury in soil and rock samples, in Geological Survey Research, 1972, chap. C: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 800-C, p. C209-C214, accessed March 21, 2016 at https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp800C.
Aruscavage, P.J., 1977, Determination of arsenic, antimony, and selenium in coal by atomic absorption spectrometry with a graphite tube analyzer: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 5, no. 4, p. 405-408-, accessed March 21, 2016 at  https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007421
Aruscavage, P.J., 1979, The determination of lead in 13 USGS standard rocks: Talanta, v. 26, iss. 11, p. 1052-1054, accessed March 28, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0039-9140(79)80018-1.
Aruscavage, P.J., 1990, Determination of chloride in geologic materials by ion-selective electrode following KMN04-H2SO4-HF dissolution, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 119-122, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Aruscavage, P.J., 1993, Analysis of Se by chemical separation/GFAA, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Aruscavage, P.J., 1993, Atomic absorption spectrometry analysis, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Aruscavage, P.J., 1996, Choride by ion-selective electrode following KMnO4-H2SO4-HF dissolution, in Arbogast, B.F., ed.,- Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 191-194, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Aruscavage, P.J., and Campbell, E.Y., 1978, Spectrophotometric determination of tungsten in rocks using zinc dithiol: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 6, p. 697-699, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007429.
Aruscavage, P.J., and Campbell, E.Y., 1979, The determination of silver in silicate rocks by electrothermal atomic absorption spectrometry: Analytica Chimica Acta, v. 109, p. 171-175, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0003-2670(01)84242-2.
Aruscavage, P.J., and Campbell, E.Y., 1981, Molybdenum content of 16 US Geological Survey standard rocks: Geostandards Newsletter, v. 5, p. 171-173, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1751-908X.1981.tb00323.x.
Aruscavage, P.J., and Campbell, E.Y., 1983, An ion-selective electrode method for the determination of chlorine in geological materials: Talanta, v. 30, iss. 10, p. 745-749, accessed March 28, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0039-9140(83)80171-4.
Aruscavage, P.J., and Crock, J.G., 1987, Atomic absorption methods, in Baedecker, P.A., ed., Methods for geochemical analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1770-C, C1-C6, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1770.
Aruscavage, P.J., and Hakim, A.O., 1992, DGMR/USGS chemistry laboratory analytical procedures, 1991: U.S. Geological Survey interagency report 845, Technical report (Saudia Arabia. Deputy Ministry for Mineral Resources), various pagings.
Baedecker, P.A., 1977, SPECTRA: Computer reduction of gamma-ray spectroscopic data for neutron activation analysis, in Taylor, R. E., ed., Advances in Obsidian Glass Studies: New Jersey, Noyes Press, p. 334-349.
Baedecker, P.A., and Grossman, J.N., 1989, The computer analysis of high resolution gamma-ray spectra from instrumental activation analysis experiments: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 89-454, 98 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr89454.
Baedecker, P.A., and Grossman, J.N., 1994, The SPECTRA program library: a PC based system for gamma-ray spectra analysis and INAA data reduction: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 94-168, 52 p., accessed March 21, 2016- at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr94168.
Baedecker, P.A., and McKown, D.M., 1987, Instrumental neutron activation analysis of geochemical samples, in Baedecker, P.A., ed., Methods for geochemical analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1770-H, H1-H14, accessed March 21, 2016  at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1770.
Baedecker, P.A., ed., 1987, Methods for geochemical analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1770, 132 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1770.
Baedecker, P.A., Grossman, J.N., and Buttleman, Kim, 1998, National geochemical data base, PLUTO geochemical data base for the United States: U.S. Geological Survey Digital Data Series DDS-47, 1 CD-ROM.
Baedecker, P.A., Grossman, J.N., and Wandless, G.A., 1993, "Long count" INAA package, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Barnett, P.R., 1961, An evaluation of whole-order, 1/2-order, and 1/3-order reporting in semiquantitative spectrochemical analysis, in Contributions to Geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1084-H, p. 183-206, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1084H.
Barnett, P.R., Huleatt, W.P., Rader, L.F., Jr., and Myers, A.T., 1954, Spectrographic determination of contamination of rock samples after grinding with alumina ceramic: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 417, 6 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei417.
Barnett, P.R., Skinner, D.L., and Huffman, Claude, Jr., 1968, Determination of gold, platinum, and palladium by a combined fire-assay, ion-exchange and spectrochemical technique, in Geological Survey Research 1968, Chapter C: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 600-C, p. C161-C163, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp600C.
Bartel, A.J., and Millard, H.T., Jr., 1976, Analysis of rocks and soils for iodine by radioisotope dilution-neutron activation, in Miesch, A.T., Barnett, P.R., Bartel, A.J, Dinnin, J.I., Feder, G.L., Harms, T.F., Huffman, Claude, Jr., Janzer, V.J., Millard, H.T., Jr., Neiman, H.G., Skougstad, M.W., and Wahlberg, J.S., Methods of sampling, laboratory analysis, and statistical reduction of data, in Geochemical survey of Missouri: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 954-A, p. A15-A17, accessed October 28, 2015 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp954A.
Barton, H.N., 1986, Emission spectrographic determination of volatile trace elements in geologic materials by a carrier distillation technique: Journal of Geochemical Exploration, v. 25, p. 367-378, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0375-6742(86)90084-1.
Bastron, Harry, Barnett, P.R., and Murata, K.J., 1960, Method for the quantitative spectrographic analysis of rocks, minerals, ores, and other materials by a powder d-c arc technique, in Contributions to Geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1084-G, p. G1-G182, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1084G.
Berman, Sol, 1967, The photoelectric determination of lithium, in Geological Survey Research 1967, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 575-B, p. B161-B163, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp575B.
Bigelow, R.C., 1982, Interfacing an ARL plasma spectrometer to an HP1000 minicomputer: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 82-963, various foliations, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr82963.
Bigelow, R.C., Vaughn, R.B., and Church, S.E., 1999, MASSPEC: a PC program to control and to process data from an automated mass-spectrometer: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 99-161, 34 p., accessed August 13, 2012 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr99161.
Bloom, Harold, 1953, A field method for the determination of ammonium citrate-soluble heavy metals in soils and sediments as a guide to ore, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Almond, Hy, Bloom, Harold, Crowe, H.E., and Marranzino, A.P., eds., Additional field methods used in geochemical prospecting by the U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 53-278, p. 16-25, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr53278.
Bloom, Harold, 1955, A field method for the determination of ammonium citrate-soluble heavy metals in soils and alluvium: Economic Geology, v. 50, no. 5, p. 533-541, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.2113/gsecongeo.50.5.533.
Bloom, Harold, and Crowe, H.E., 1953, Determination of readily soluble copper, zinc, and lead in soils and rocks: nitric acid digestion, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Almond, Hy, Bloom, Harold, Crowe, H.E., and Marranzino, A.P., eds., Additional field methods used in geochemical prospecting by the U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 53-278, p. 16-25, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr53278.
Bloom, Harold, and Crowe, H.E., 1954, Determination of readily soluble copper, zinc, and lead in soils and rocks: nitric acid extraction: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 53-287, 24 p.
Brandt, E.L., Aruscavage, P.J., and Papp, C.S.E., 1990, Determination of carbonate carbon in geologic materials by coulometric titration, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 68-72, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Brannock, W.W., and Bethold, S.M., 1953, The determination of sodium and potassium in silicate rocks by flame photometer, in Brannock, W.W. and others, Contributions to geochemistry, 1949: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 992, p. 1-15, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b992.
Brannock, W.W., and others, 1953, Contributions to geochemistry, 1949: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 992, 94 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b992.
Briggs, P.H., 1990, Elemental analysis of geologic material by inductively coupled plasma-atomic emission spectrometry, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 83-91, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Briggs, P.H., 1993, ICP multielement package, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Briggs, P.H., 1996, Forty elements by inductively coupled plasma-atomic emission spectrometry, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., -Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 77-94, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Briggs, P.H., 2002, The determination of forty elements in geological and botanical samples by inductively coupled plasma-atomic emission spectrometry, in Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, p. G1-G18, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-0223/G01fortyelementICP-AESsolid_M.pdf.
Briggs, P.H., and Crock, J.G., 1986, Automated determination of total selenium in rocks, soils, and plants: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 86-40, 20 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr8640.
Briggs, P.H., and Meier, A.L., 1999, The determination of forty two elements in geological materials by inductively coupled plasma - mass spectrometry: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 99-166, 15 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr99166.
Briggs, P.H., and Meier, A.L., 2002, The determination of forty-two elements in geological materials by inductively coupled plasma-mass spectrometry for NAWQA, in Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, p. J1-J14, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-0223/J22NAWQAMethod_M.pdf.
Briggs, P.H., and Meier, A.L., 2002, The determination of forty-two elements in geological materials by inductively coupled plasma-mass spectrometry, in Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, p. I1-I14, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-0223/I20NAWQAPlus_M.pdf.
Brookes, A.E., Leary, J.J., and Golightly, D.W., 1981, Selection of operating conditions for multiple-element analysis by inductively coupled plasma-atomic emission spectrometry : an application of optimization methodology in analytical chemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 81-1211, 80 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr811211.
Brown, F.M., Simon, F.O., and Greenland, L.P., 1975, Spectrophotometric-isotope dilution determination of arsenic in soils and rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 3, no. 2, p. 187-190, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007407.
Brown, Zoe Ann, and Curry, K.J., 2002, Total carbon by combustion, in Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, p. R1-R4, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-0223/R10TotalCarbon_M.pdf.
Brown, Zoe Ann, and Curry, K.J., 2002, Total sulfur by combustion, in Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, p. Q1-Q4, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-0223/Q25TotS_M.pdf.
Brown, Zoe Ann, O'Leary, R.M., Hageman, P.L., and Crock, J.G., 2002, Mercury in water, geologic, and plant materials by continuous flow-cold vapor-atomic absorption spectrometry, in Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, p. M1-M9, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-0223/M12HgCV_M.pdf.
Brown, Zoe Ann, Papp, C.S.E., Brandt, E.L., and Aruscavage, P.J., 2002, Carbonate carbon by coulometric titration, in Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, p. S1-S6, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-0223/S08CarbonateCarbon_S.pdf.
Budahn, J.R., and Wandless, G.A., 2002, Instrumental neutron activation by abbreviated count, in Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, p. Y1-Y9, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-0223/Y15INAA-SHORT_M.pdf.
Budahn, J.R., and Wandless, G.A., 2002, Instrumental neutron activation by long count, in Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, p. X1-X13, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-0223/X14INAALong_M.pdf.
Campbell, E.Y., and Aruscavage, P.J., 1982, Molybdenum and tungsten contents of five CRPG and ANRT geochemical reference materials: Geostandards Newsletter, v. 6, p. 229-2311, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1751-908X.1982.tb00357.x.
Campbell, E.Y., and Greenland, L.P., 1976, Homogeneity of niobium content of eight USGS standard rocks, in Flanagan, F.J., ed., 1976, Descriptions and analyses of eight new USGS rock standards: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 840, p. 87-89, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp840.
Campbell, E.Y., and Simon, F.O., 1978, Atomic absorption determination of beryllium in geological materials by use of electrothermal atomization: Talanta, v. 25, iss. 5, p. 251-255, accessed March 28, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0039-9140(78)80050-2.
Campbell, W.L., 1981, Manganese dioxide causes spurious gold values in flame atomic absorption readings from HBr-Br2 digestions, in Rose, A.W., and Gundlach, H., eds., Geochemical exploration 1980: Journal of Geochemical Exploration, v. 15, p. 613-616, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0375-6742(81)90090-X.
Canney, F.C., and Hawkins, D.B., 1958, Cold acid extraction of copper from soils and sediments-a proposed field method: Economic Geology, v. 53, no. 7, p. 877-886, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.2113/gsecongeo.53.7.877.
Canney, F.C., and Nowlan, G.A., 1964, Determination of ammonium citrate-soluble cobalt in soils and sediments: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 64-30, 15 p.
Carron, M.K., and Cuttitta, Frank, 1962, Determination of silica in tektites and similar glasses by volatilization, in Geological Survey research 1962, Short papers in geology, hydrology and topography, Articles 180-239: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 450-B, p. B78--B79, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp450B.
Carron, M.K., Naeser, C.R., Rose, H.J., Jr., and Hildebrand, F.A., 1958, Fractional precipitation of rare earths with phosphoric acid, in Contributions to Geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1036-N, p. 253-275, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1036N.
Chaffee, M.A., 1970, Determination of acid-soluble and total manganese in geological and botanical materials by atomic absorption, in Geological Survey Research 1970, chap. D: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 700-D, p. D217-D221, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp700D.
Chao, T.T., 1984, Use of partial dissolution techniques in geochemical exploration: Journal of Geochemical Exploration, v. 20, p. 101-135, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0375-6742(84)90078-5.
Chao, T.T., and Zhou, Liyi, 1983, Extraction techniques for selective dissolution of amorphous iron oxides from soils and sed1ments: Soil Science Society of America Journal, v. 47, p. 225-232, accessed March 28, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.2136/sssaj1983.03615995004700020010x.
Chao, T.T., and Sanzolone, R.F., 1973, Atomic absorption spectrophotometric determination of microgram levels of Co, Ni, Cu, Pb, and Zn in soil and sediment extracts containing large amounts of Mn and Fe: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 1, no. 6, p. 681-685, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007399.
Chao, T.T., and Sanzolone, R.F., 1977, Chemical dissolution of sufide minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 5, no. 4, p. 409-412, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007422.
Chao, T.T., and Sanzolone, R.F., 1992, Decomposition techniques, in Hall, G.E.M., ed., Geoanalysis: Journal of Geochemical Exploration, v. 44, p. 65-106, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0375-6742(92)90048-D.
Chao, T.T., Sanzolone, R.F., and Hubert, A.E., 1978, Flame and flameless atomic-absorption determination of tellurium in geological materials: Analytica Chimica Acta, V. 96, p. 251-257, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0003-2670(01)83660-6.
Church, S.E., 1981, Multi-element analysis of fifty-four geochemical reference samples using inductively coupled plasma-atomic emission spectrometry: Geostandards Newsletter, v. 5, p. 133-160, accessedMarch 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1751-908X.1981.tb00320.x.
Clark, J.R., and Viets, J.G., 1981, Multielement extraction system for the determination of 18 Trace Elements in geochemical samples: Analytical Chemistry, v. 53, p. 61-65, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/ac00224a017.
Clarke, F.W., and Hillebrand, W.F., 1897, Analyses of rocks, with a chapter on analytical methods, laboratory of the United States Geological survey 1880 to 1896: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 148, 306 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b148.
Clarke, R.S., Jr., and Cuttitta, Frank, 1957, Determination of thallium by a dithizone mixed-color method: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 667, 20 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei667.
Clifton, H.E., Hubert, A.E., and Phillips, R.L., 1967, Marine sediment sample preparation for analysis for low concentrations of fine detrital gold: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 545, 11 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir545.
Cooley, E.F., Curry, K.J., and Carlson, R.R., 1976, Analysis for the platinum group metals and gold by fire-assay emission spectrography: Applied Spectroscopy, v. 30, iss. 1, p. 52-56, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://www.s-a-s.org/4DCGI/sas/journal/abstract.html?WebTopic_w=550.
Cremer, M.J., 1984, Acid decomposition for atomic absorption analysis, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 90-91, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Cremer, M.J., 1984, An extraction - colorometric procedure for molybdenum, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 137-138, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Cremer, M.J., 1984, Chlorine, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 11-12, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Cremer, M.J., 1984, Classical analysis, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 50-78, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Cremer, M.J., 1984, Colorometric Al2O3, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 7-10, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Cremer, M.J., 1984, Colorometric determination of phosphorus, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 16-17, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Cremer, M.J., 1984, Colorometric determination of total iron, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 13-15, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Cremer, M.J., 1984, Colorometric TiO2, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 20-22, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Cremer, M.J., 1984, Determination of boron in silicates, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 92-95, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Cremer, M.J., 1984, Digestion method for fluorine in silicates and phosphates, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 92-95, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Cremer, M.J., 1984, K2O and Na2O analysis, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 139-143, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Cremer, M.J., 1984, Mercury in rocks and minerals, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 131-136, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Cremer, M.J., 1984, Total sulfur, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 79-83, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, 153 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Crenshaw, G.L., and Lakin, H.W., 1974, A sensitive and rapid method for the determination of trace amounts of selenium in geologic materials: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 2, no. 4, p. 483-487, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007403.
Crenshaw, G.L., and Ward, F.N., 1975, Determination of fluorine in soils and rocks by known-increment addition and selective-ion electrode detection, in Ward, F.N., ed., New and refined methods of trace analysis useful in geochemical exploration: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1408, p. 77-84., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1408.
Crock, J.G., 1986, The determination of bismuth in geological reference materials by automated hydride generation-atomic absorption spectroscopy: Analytical Letters, v. 19, p. 1367-1385, accessed March 25, 2016 at DOI:10.1080/00032718608069113.
Crock, J.G., 1993, Analysis of Au by chemical separation/GFAA, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Crock, J.G., 2005, Determination of total mercury in biological and geological samples a presentation for the 2004 Teledyne Leeman Labs "Seminar on Low-Level Mercury Data and Analyses": U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 2005-1030, v. 1.0, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2005/1030/.
Crock, J.G., and Lichte, F.E., 1981, The determination of trace-level antimony in geological materials by semi-automated hydride generation-atomic absorption spectroscopy: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 81-671, 24 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr81671.
Crock, J.G., and Lichte, F.E., 1981, The determination of trace-level arsenic in geological materials by semi-automated hydride generation-atomic absorption spectroscopy: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 81-672, 20 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr81672.
Crock, J.G., and Lichte, F.E., 1982, An improved method for the determination of arsenic and antimony in geologic materials by automated hydride generation-atomic absorption spectroscopy: Analytica Chimica Acta, v. 144, p. 223-233, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0003-2670(01)95536-9.
Crock, J.G., and Lichte, F.E., 1982, The determination of rare-earth elements in geological materials by inductively argon coupled plasma-optical emission spectroscopy: Analytical Chemistry, v. 54, p. 1329-1333, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/ac00245a018.
Crock, J.G., and Severson, R.C., 1980, Four reference soil and rock samples for measuring element availability in the western energy regions: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 841, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir841.
Crock, J.G., Briggs, P.H., Jackson, L.L., and Lichte, F.E., 1987, Analytical methods for the analysis of stream sediments and rocks from Wilderness Study Areas: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 87-84, 35 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr8784.
Crock, J.G., Lichte, F.E., and Briggs, P.H., 1983, Determination of elements in National Bureau of Standards geological reference materials SRM278 obsidian and SRM 688 basalt by inductively coupled plasma-atomic emission spectroscopy: Geostandards Newsletter, v. 7, p. 335-340, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1751-908X.
Curry, K.J., 1990, Determination of total carbon in geologic materials by combustion, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 114-118, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Curry, K.J., 1990, Determination of total sulfur in geologic materials by combustion, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 131-135, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Curry, K.J., 1996, Total carbon by combustion, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 173-176, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Curry, K.J., 1996, Total sulfur by combustion, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 177-181, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Curry, K.J., and Papp, C.S.E., 1996, Acid-soluble sulfate, sulfide, and organic sulfur, in Arbogast, B.F., ed.,  -Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 182-185, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Cuttitta, Frank, 1952, The colorimetric determination of total iron with o-phenanthroline: a spectrophotometric study: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 223, 25 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei223.
Cuttitta, Frank, 1957, Annotated bibliography of the analytical chemistry of niobium and tantalum, January 1935-June 1953, in Selected Bibliographies of Analytical Chemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1029-A, 73 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1029A.
Cuttitta, Frank, 1961, Dithizone mixed-color method for determining small amounts of thallium in manganese ores, in Geological Survey Research 1961, Short papers in the geologic and hydrologic sciences, Articles 147-292: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 424-C, p. C384-C385, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp424C.
Cuttitta, Frank, and Brittin, Edward, 1954, Retention of uranium during oxidative ashing of selected naturally occurring carbonaceous substances: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 461, 8 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei461.
Cuttitta, Frank, and Warr, J.J., Jr., 1957, Retention of lead during oxidative ashing of selected naturally occurring carbonaceous substances: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 683, 9 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei683.
Cuttitta, Frank, and Warr, J.J., Jr., 1960, Preparation of lead iodide for mass spectrometry, in Geological Survey Research 1960, Short papers in the geological sciences: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 400-B, p. B487-B488, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp400B.
d'Angelo, W.M., 1993, Analysis of F and Cl anions by ion chromatography, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
d'Angelo, W.M., 1993, Analysis of Sb by chemical separation/GFAA, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Delevaux, M.H., Smith, R.K., and Grimaldi, F.S., 1954, The photometric determination of aluminum in phosphate materials with ferron: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 450, 19 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei450.
Detra, D.E., 1993, Analysis of sulfur by combustion/IR spectroscopy, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Dietrich, J.A., Cooley, E.F., and Curry, K.J., 1977, A device for automatic photoelectric control of the analytical gap for emission spectrographs: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 748, 5 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir748.
Dinnin, J.I., 1959, Rapid analysis of chromite and chrome ore, in Contributions to Geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1084-B, p. 31-68, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1084B.
Dinnin, J.I., 1960, Determination of total iron in chromite and chrome ore, in Geological Survey Research 1960, Short papers in the geological sciences: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 400-B, p. B476-B477, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp400B.
Dinnin, J.I., 1961, Flame photometric determination of strontium with the use of releasing agents, in Geological Survey Research 1961, Short papers in the geologic and hydrologic sciences, Articles 293-435: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 424-D, p. D392-D394, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp424D.
Dinnin, J.I., 1961, Gravimetric determination of silica in chromite and chrome ore, in Geological Survey Research 1961, Short papers in the geologic and hydrologic sciences, Articles 293-435: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 424-D, p. D397-D399, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp424D.
Dinnin, J.I., 1961, Use of releasing agents in the flame photometric determination of magnesium and barium, in Geological Survey Research 1961, Short papers in the geologic and hydrologic sciences, Articles 293-435: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 424-D, p. D391-D392, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp424D.
Dinnin, J.I., and Kinser, C.A., 1961, Indirect semiautomatic determination of alumina with EDTA, in Geological Survey Research 1961, Short papers in the geologic and hydrologic sciences, Articles 1-146: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 424-B, p. B329-B331, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp424B.
Dinnin, J.I., and Williams, E.G., 1961, Chemical aid for distinguishing chromite, ilmenite, and magnetite, in Geological Survey Research 1961, Short papers in the geologic and hydrologic sciences, Articles 293-435: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 424-D, p. D394, accessed August 13, 2012 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp424D.
Dinnin, J.I., and Worthing, H.W., 1966, Determination of microquantities of mercury in sulfide ores by penfield tube-dithizone and semiquantitative spectrographic methods, in Geological Survey Research 1966, Chapter C: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 550-C, p. C220-C223, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp550C.
Doering, W.P., 1968, A rapid method for measuring the Rb/Sr ratio in silicate rocks, in Geological Survey Research 1968, Chapter C: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 600-C, p. C164-C168, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp600C.
Domenico, J.A., and Viets, J.G., 1980, The design of mobile laboratories used in geochemical exploration: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 80-301, 25 p.
Dorrzapf, A.F., Jr., 1967, Spectrographic detection limits of the noble metals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 67-83, 76 p.
Dorrzapf, A.F., Jr., 1973, Spectrochemical computer analyses, argon-oxygen d-c arc method for silicate rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 1, no. 5, p. 559-562, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007398.
Dorrzapf, A.F., Jr., 1993, ICP multielement analysis, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Dorrzapf, A.F., Jr., and Brown, F.W., 1970, Direct spectrographic analysis for platinum, palladium and rhodium in gold beads from fire assay: Applied Spectroscopy, v. 24, iss. 4, p. 415-418, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://www.s-a-s.org/4DCGI/sas/journal/abstract.html?WebTopic_w=2477.
Doughten, M.W., 1993, Analysis of As and Sn by chemical separation/GFAA, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Doughten, M.W., 1993, Analysis of Ge by chemical separation/GFAA, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Doughten, M.W., 1993, Analysis of Mo, Nb and W by ion exchange separation/ICP-AES, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Doughten, M.W., 1993, Analysis of Te by ion exchange separation/GFAA, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Doughten, M.W., and Aruscavage, P.J., 1996, Niobium, tungsten, and molybdenum by ion exchange/inductively coupled plasma-atomic emission spectrometry, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 126-129, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Elsheimer, H.N., 1987, Application of an ion-selective electrode method to the determination of chloride in 41 international geochemical reference materials: Geostandards Newsletter, v. 11, p. 115-122, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1751-908X.1987.tb00014.x.
Elsheimer, H.N., 1987, X-ray spectrometric analysis of major and selected minor elements in silicate rocks utilizing an automatic fusion technique: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 87-71, 37 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr8771.
Engleman, E.E., Jackson, L.L. and Norton, D.R., 1985. Determination of carbonate carbon in geological materials by coulometric titration: Chemical Geology, v. 53, p. 125-128, accessed  March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0009-2541(85)90025-7.
Evans, J.R., and Sellers, G.A., 1993, Analysis of Cr, Ni, Zu, Zn, Rb, Sr, Y, Zr, Nb, Ba, La and Ce by energy-dispersive XRF, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Fabbi, B.P., 1970, A die for pelletizing samples for X-ray fluorescence analysis, in Geological Survey Research 1970, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 700-B, p. B187-B189, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp700B.
Fabbi, B.P., and Espos, L.F., 1972, X-ray fluorescence of arsenic, antimony, nickel, rubidium, scandium, vanadium, and zinc in rock standards and other rock samples, in Geological Survey research, 1972, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 800-B, p. B147-B150., accessed March 21, 2016 at https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp800B.
Fabbi, B.P., and Espos, L.F., 1976, X-ray fluorescence analysis of 21 selected major, minor, and Trace Elements in eight new USGS standard rocks, in Flanagan, F.J., ed., 1976, Descriptions and analyses of eight new USGS rock standards: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 840, p. 89-95, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp840.
Fahey, J.J., and Foster, M.D., 1945, Preliminary report on a method for the determination of small quantities of thorium: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 16, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei16.
Fey, D.L., 1993, Analysis of water-extractable boron by ICP-AES, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Ficklin, W.H., 1970, A rapid method for the determination of fluoride in rocks and soils, using an ion-selective electrode, in Geological Survey Research 1970, Chapter C: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 700-C, p. C186-C188, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp700C.
Ficklin, W.H., 1975, Ion-selective electrode determination of iodine in rocks and soils: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 3, no. 6, p. 753-755, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007411.
Ficklin, W.H., and Mosier, E.L., 1999, Field methods for sampling and analysis of environmental samples for unstable and selected stable constituents, in Plumlee, G.S., and Logsdon, M.J., The environmental geochemistry of mineral deposits: Society of Economic Geologists, Reviews in Economic Geology, v. 6A, p. 249-264, accessed March 28, 2016 at  -http://www.segweb.org/store_info/REV/REV-06-Additional-Product-Info.pdf.
Ficklin, W.H., and Ward, F.N., 1976, Flameless atomic absorption determination of bismuth in soils and rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 4, no. 2, p. 217-220, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007413.
Filipek, L.H., 1993, Analysis of carbon by combustion/IR spectroscopy, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Flanagan, F.J., 1956, Semiquantitative spectrographic analysis and rank correlation in geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 628, 17 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei628.
Flanagan, F.J., 1961, Fatigue in scintillation counting, in Geological Survey Research 1961, Short papers in the geologic and hydrologic sciences, Articles 1-146: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 424-B, p. B324-B326, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp424B.
Flanagan, F.J., 1964, Judging the analytical ability of rock analysts by chi-squared, in Geological Survey Research 1964, Chapter C: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 501-C, p. C157-C159, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp501C.
Flanagan, F.J., 1984, Three USGS mafic rock references samples, W-2, DNC-1, and BIR-1: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1623, 54 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1623.
Flanagan, F.J., 1986, Additions and corrections for USGS bulletin 1623, three USGS mafic rock reference samples, W-2, DNC-1, and BIR-1: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 86-220, 13 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr86220.
Flanagan, F.J., 1986, Reference samples in geology and geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1582, 70 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1582.
Flanagan, F.J., and Gottfried, David-, 1980, USGS rock standards, III : manganese nodule reference samples, USGS-Nod-A-1 and USGS-Nod-P-1: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 1155, 39 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp1155.
Flanagan, F.J., and Kellagher, R.C., 1955, A comparison of sample splitting methods: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 505, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei505.
Flanagan, F.J., and McCall, B.A., 1955, An improved glass sample holder for assaying low radioactivity samples: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 568, 7 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei568.
Flanagan, F.J., Chandler, J.C., Breger, I.A., Moore, C.B., and Lewis, C.F., 1976, The carbon contents of USGS volcanic rock standards, in Flanagan, F.J., ed., 1976, Descriptions and analyses of eight new USGS rock standards: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 840, p. 123-127, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp840.
Flanagan, F.J., ed., 1976, Descriptions and analyses of eight new USGS rock standards: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 840, 192 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp840.
Flanagan, F.J., Kellagher, R.C., and Smith, W.L., 1958, The slotted cone splitter: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 720, 18 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei720.
Fletcher, M.H., 1950, A study of critical factors in the "direct" fluorimetric determination of uranium: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 130, 40 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei130.
Fletcher, M.H., and May, Irving, 1950, An improved fluorimeter for the determination of uranium in fluoride melts: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 50-33, 10 p.
Fletcher, M.H., and May, Irving, 1950, An improved fluorimeter for the determination of uranium in fluoride melts: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 120, 10 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei120.
Fletcher, M.H., and Milkey, R.G., 1954, A spectrophotometric study of the thorium-morin mixed-color system: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 460, 40 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei460.
Fletcher, M.H., and Warner, E.R., 1951, A fluorimeter for solutions: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 51-66, 6 p.
Fletcher, M.H., and Warner, E.R., 1953, A fluorimeter for solutions: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 311, 8 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir311.
Fletcher, M.H., Grimaldi, F.S., and Jenkins, L.B., 1956, The thoron-mesotartaric acid system for the determination of thorium: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 350, 24 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei350.
Fletcher, M.H., May, Irving, and Anderson, J.W., 1951, The design of the model V transmission fluorimeter: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 51-65, 5 p.
Fletcher, M.H., May, Irving, and Anderson, J.W., 1950, The design of the Model V transmission fluorimeter: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 133, 5 p., accessed March 21, 2016 a https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei133.
Fletcher, M.H., May, Irving, and Slavin, Morris, 1949, A transmission fluorimeter for use in the fluorimetric method of analysis for uranium: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 104, 14 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei104.
Fletcher, M.H., May, Irving, and Slavin, Morris, 1950, A transmission fluorimeter for use in the fluorimetric method of analysis for uranium: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 50-34, 14 p.
Foster, M.D., Grimaldi, F.S., and Stevens, R.E., 1945, Preliminary report on methods of analysis for very small percentages of uranium: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 2, 25 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei2.
Fries, T.L., 1993, Analysis of F by selective ion electrode, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Fries, T.L., 1993, Analysis of Na2O and K2O by flame photometry, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Fries, T.L., Christie, J.H., and Pribble, S.T., 1990, Flame photometric determination of K2O and Na2O in rocks and mineral separates, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 107-110, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Fries, T.L., Christie, J.H., and Pribble, S.T., 1996, Flame photometric determination of K2O and Na2O, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey open-file report 96-525, p. 144-148, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Fries, T.L., Christie, J.H., Pribble, S.T., and Siems, D.F., 2002, Flame photometric determination of K2O, in Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, p. P1-P5, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-0223/P29K2O_M.pdf.
Fries, T.L., Lamothe, P.J., and Pesek, J.J., 1984, Determination of rare-earth elements in manganese nodules by inductively coupled argon-plasma emission spectroscopy: Analytica Chimica Acta, v. 159, p. 326-336, accessed March 25, 2016 at doi:10.1016/S0003-2670(00)84307-X.
Frost, I.C., 1960, Comparison of three methods for the determination of total and organic carbon in geochemical studies, in Geological Survey Research 1960, Short papers in the geological sciences: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 400-B, p. B480-B483, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp400B.
Frost, I.C., 1961, Evaluation of the use of dichromate oxidation to estimate the organic carbon content of rocks, in Geological Survey Research 1961, Short papers in the geologic and hydrologic sciences, Articles 147-292: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 424-C, p. C376-C377, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp424C.
Gent, C.A., and Wilson, S.A., 1985, The determination of sulfur and chlorine in coals and oil shales using ion chromatography: Analytical Letters, v. 18, p. 729-740, accessed March 25, 2016 at DOI:10.1080/00032718508066171.
Gillison, J.R., 1993, Analysis of Au by chemical separation/GFAA, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Gillison, J.R., 1993, Analysis of F by selective ion electrode, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Gillison, J.R., 1993, Analysis of Hg by cold vapor AA, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Gillison, J.R., 1993, Analysis of major element oxides by "rapid rock", in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Golightly, D.W., 1978, Recent geochemical applications of the inductively coupled argon-plasma: "Applications of inductively coupled plasmas to emission spectroscopy", Eastern Analytical Symposium, p. 107-119.
Golightly, D.W., Dorrzapf, A.F., Jr., and Berman, Sol, 1987, Trace boron concentrations in geologic standard materials determined by fluoride-volatilization arc spectrography: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 87-150, 10 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr87150.
Golightly, D.W., Dorrzapf, A.F., Jr., and Thomas, C.P., 1977, Sets of spectral lines for spectrographic thermometry and manometry in d-c arcs of geologic materials: Spectrochimica Acta, v. 32B, iss. 7, p. 313-325, accessed march 28, 2016 at 10.1016/0584-8547(77)80033-5.
Golightly, D.W., Dorrzapf, A.F., Jr., Mays, R.E., Fries, T.L., and Conklin, N.M., 1987, Analysis of geologic materials by direct-current arc emission spectrography and spectrometry, in Baedecker, P.A., ed., Methods for geochemical analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1770-A, p. A1-A13, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1770.
Gough, L.P., 1993, Analysis of F by selective ion electrode, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Greenland, L.P., 1967, Determination of phosphorus in silicate rocks by neutron activation, in Geological Survey Research 1967, Chapter C: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 575-C, p. C137-C139, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp575C.
Greenland, L.P., and Campbell, E.Y., 1971, Substoichiometric determination of tantalum by neutron activation, in Geological Survey Research 1971, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 750-B, p. B191-B193, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp750B.
Greenland, L.P., and Campbell, E.Y., 1972, Determination of nanogram amounts of bismuth in rocks by substoichiometric isotope dilution analysis: Analytica Chimica Acta, v. 60, p. 159-165, accessed March 25, 2016 at doi:10.1016/S0003-2670(01)81895-X.
Greenland, L.P., and Campbell, E.Y., 1974, Spectrophotometric determination of niobium in rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 2, no. 3, p. 353-355, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007402.
Greenland, L.P., and Campbell, E.Y., 1976, Rapid determination of nanogram amounts of tellurium in silicate rocks: Analytica Chimica Acta, v. 87, p. 323-328, accessed March 25, 2016 at dx.doi.org/doi:10.1016/S0003-2670(01)82261-3.
Greenland, L.P., and Campbell, E.Y., 1977, Application of selenium hydride-atomic absorption technique to test for homogeneity of USGS standard rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 5, no. 4, p. 403-404, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007421.
Greenland, L.P., and Campbell, E.Y., and Flanagan, F.J., 1976, The bismuth content of six new USGS standard rocks. in Flanagan, F.J., ed., 1976, Descriptions and analyses of eight new USGS rock standards: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 840,  p. 45-47, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp840.
Greenland, L.P., and McLane, J.E., 1969, Determination of germanium in silicates by neutron activation analysis, in Geological Survey Research 1969, Chapter C: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 650-C, p. C152-C154, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp650C.
Greenland, L.P., Rowe, J.J., and Dinnin, J.I., 1971, Application of triple coincidence counting and of fire-assay separation to the neutron activation determination of iridium, in Geological Survey Research 1971, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 750-B, p. B175-B179, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp750B.
Griffitts, W.R., and Patten, L.E., 1961, Determining the distribution of beryllium in rocks by a contact-print method, in Geological Survey Research 1961, Short papers in the geologic and hydrologic sciences, Articles 147-292: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 424-C, p. C378, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp424C.
Grimaldi, F.S., 1946, Elimination of interference by nickel in the determination of uranium by means of zinc amalgam reductors: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 23, 5 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei23.
Grimaldi, F.S., 1953, Quercetin as a colorimetric reagent for zirconium: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 53-81, 93 p.
Grimaldi, F.S., 1960, Dilution-addition method for flame photometry, in Geological Survey Research 1960, Short papers in the geological sciences: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 400-B, p. B494-B495, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp400B.
Grimaldi, F.S., and Fairchild, J.G., 1945, Preliminary report on methods of analysis for very small percentages of thorium, part 1: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 15, 25 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei15.
Grimaldi, F.S., and Fletcher, M.H., 1955, The thoron-tartaric acid systems for the spectrophotometric determination of thorium: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 571, 25 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei571.
Grimaldi, F.S., and Guttag, N.S., 1950, Short routine direct method for the fluorimetric determination of uranium in phosphate rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 134, 7 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei134.
Grimaldi, F.S., and Helz, A.W., 1961, Trace element sensitivities, in Geological Survey Research 1961, Short papers in the geologic and hydrologic sciences, Articles 293-435: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 424-D, p. D388-D391, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp424D.
Grimaldi, F.S., and Levine, Harry, 1948, The rapid fluorimetric determination of uranium in low-grade ores: a preliminary report: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 47, 7 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei47.
Grimaldi, F.S., and Levine, Harry, 1948, The rapid fluorimetric determination of uranium in low-grade ores: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 50-35, 13 p.
Grimaldi, F.S., and Levine, Harry, 1950, The fluorimetric determination of aluminum in phosphate rock with 8-hydroxyquinoline: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 60, 13 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei60.
Grimaldi, F.S., and Levine, Harry, 1953, The fluorimetric determination of aluminum in phosphate rock with 8-hydroxyquinoline, in Brannock, W.W. and others, Contributions to geochemistry, 1949: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 992, p. 39-49, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b992.
Grimaldi, F.S., and March, C.A., 1947, The determination of thorium in high grade and low grade ores: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 44, 20 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei44.
Grimaldi, F.S., and Schnepfe, M.M., 1967, Determination of palladium in the parts-per-billion range in rocks, in Geological Survey Research 1967, Chapter C: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 575-C, p. C141-C144, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp575C.
Grimaldi, F.S., and Schnepfe, M.M., 1968, Determination of palladium and platinum in rocks, in Geological Survey Research 1968, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 600-B, p. B99-B103, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp600B.
Grimaldi, F.S., and Simon, F.O., 1963, Determination of traces of boron in halite and anhydritic halite rocks, in Geological Survey Research 1963, Short papers in geology and hydrology, Articles 1-59: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 475-B, p. B166-B168, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp475B.
Grimaldi, F.S., Cuttitta, Frank, and Ingram, B.L., 1954, The determination of small and large amounts of fluorine in rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 492, 19 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei492.
Grimaldi, F.S., Jenkins, L.B., and Fletcher, M.H., 1956, The selective precipitation of thorium iodate from a tartaric acid-hydrogen peroxide medium : application to the rapid spectrophotometric determination of thorium in silicate rocks and in ores: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 489, 23 P., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei489.
Grimaldi, F.S., May, Irving, and Fletcher, M.H., 1952, U.S. Geological Survey fluorimetric methods of uranium analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 199; also U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 219, 53 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei219.
Grimaldi, F.S., May, Irving, Fletcher, M.H., and Titcomb, Jane, 1954, Collected papers on methods of analysis for uranium and thorium: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1006, 184 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1006.
Grimaldi, F.S., Shapiro, Leonard, and Schnepfe, M.M., 1966, Determination of carbon dioxide in limestone and dolomite by acid-base titration, in Geological Survey Research 1966, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 550-B, p. B186-B188, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp550B.
Grimaldi, F.S., Ward, F.N., and Kreher, Ruth, 1949, A direct quantitative fluorimetric method for the determination of small amounts of uranium in the field and laboratory: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements investigations report 98, 13 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei98.
Grimes, D.J., and Marranzino, A.P., 1968, Direct-current arc and alternating-current spark emission spectrographic field methods for the semiquantitative analysis of geologic materials: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 591, 6 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir591.
Grimes, J.G., 1984, NURE HSSR geochemical sample archives transfer report - geochemical analysis: Martin Marietta Energy Systems, Inc., Oak Ridge Gaseous Diffusion Plant, Oak Ridge, Tenn., K/UR-500, Part 3, 150 p.
Grossman, J.N., 1993, REPORT, a program for generating method descriptions and bibliographies of routine work performed in analytical chemistry laboratories: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-A, 8 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931A.
Grossman, J.N., 1998, National Geochemical Atlas: The geochemical landscape of the conterminous United States derived from stream sediment and other solid sample media analyzed by the National Uranium Evaluation (NURE) Program: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 98-622, 1 CD-ROM, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://ngmdb.usgs.gov/Prodesc/proddesc_13041.htm.
Grossman, J.N., 2004, The National Geochemical Survey, database and documentation: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 2004-1001, Internet, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2004/1001/.
Grossman, J.N., and Doughten, M.W., 1993, A program for generating method descriptions and bibliographies of routine work performed in analytical chemistry laboratories computer file: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-C, 1 computer disk, 3 1/2 in., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931C.
Guttag, N.S., and Grimaldi, F.S., 1951, Fluorimetric determination of uranium in shales, lignites, and monazites after alkali carbonate separation: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 153-A, 18 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei153A.
Haffty, Joseph, Haubert, A.W., and Page, N.J., 1979, Determination of iridium and ruthenium in geological samples by fire assay and emission spectrography, in Shorter Contributions to Geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 1129-G, p. G1-G4, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp1129AI.
Haffty, Joseph, Riley, L.B., and Goss, W.D., 1977, A manual on fire assaying and determination of the noble metals in geological materials: detailed description of techniques and methods of analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1445, 58 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1445.
Hageman, P.L., 2007, U.S. Geological Survey field leach test for assessing water reactivity and leaching potential of mine wastes, soils, and other geologic and environmental materials: Techniques of water resources investigations of the United States Geological Survey bk. 5, D-3, 14 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/tm/2007/05D03/.
Hageman, P.L., and Briggs, P.H., 2000, A simple field leach test for rapid screening and qualitative characterization of mine waste dump material on abandoned mine lands: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 2000-15, 13 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr0015.
Hageman, P.L., and Welsch, E.P., 1996, Arsenic, antimony, and selenium by flow injection or continuous flow-hydride generation-atomic absorption spectrophometry, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 24-30, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Hageman, P.L., Brown, Zoe Ann, and Welsch, E.P., 2002, Arsenic and selenium by flow injection or continuous flow-hydride generation-atomic absorption spectrophotometry, in Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, p. L1-L7, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-0223/L06AS24Se_M.pdf.
Helz, A.W., 1956, Rapid-scanning microphotometry: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 579, 12 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei579.
Helz, A.W., 1964, A gas jet for d-c arc spectroscopy, in Geological Survey Research 1963, Short papers in geology and hydrology, Articles 122-172: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 475-D, p. D176-D178, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp475D.
Helz, A.W., 1965, The problem of automatic plate reading and computer interpretation for spectrochemical analysis, in Geological Survey Research 1965, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 525-B, p. B160-B164, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp525B.
Helz, A.W., 1973, Spectrochemical computer analysis - Instrumentation: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 1, no. 4, p. 475-482, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007397.
Helz, A.W., and Annell, C.S., 1961, Determination of beryllium with a direct-reading spectrograph, in Geological Survey Research 1961, Short papers in the geologic and hydrologic sciences, Articles 147-292: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 424-C, p. C380-C382, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp424C.
Helz, A.W., Walthall, F.G., and Berman, Sol, 1969, Computer analysis of photographed optical emission spectra: Applied Spectroscopy, v. 23, iss. 5, p. 508-518, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://www.s-a-s.org/4DCGI/sas/journal/abstract.html?WebTopic_w=8782.
Heropoulos, Chris, Seeley, J.L., and Radtke, A.S., 1984, Spectrographic determination of selenium in stibnite: Applied Spectroscopy, v. 38, iss. 3, p. 451-454.
Hillebrand, W.F., 1900, Some principles and methods of rock analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 176, 114 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b176.
Hillebrand, W.F., 1907, The analysis of silicate and carbonate rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 305, 200 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b305.
Hillebrand, W.F., 1910, The analysis of silicate and carbonate rocks: a revision of Bulletin 305: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 422, 239 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b422.
Hillebrand, W.F., 1919, The analysis of silicate and carbonate rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 700, 285 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b700.
Hillebrand, W.F., and Allen, E.T., 1905, Comparison of a wet and crucible-fire methods for the assay of gold telluride ores, with notes on the errors occurring in the operations of fire assay and parting: U.S. Geological Survey bulletin 253, 31 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b253.
Hinkle, M.E., Leong, K.W., and Ward, F.N., 1965, Field determination of nanogram quantities of mercury in soils and rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 808, 14 p.
Hinkle, M.E., Leong, K.W., and Ward, F.N., 1966, Field determination of nanogram quantities of mercury in soils and rocks, in Geological Survey Research 1966, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 550-B, p. B135-B137, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp550B.
Hoover, D.B., Smith, D.B., and Leinz, R.W., 1997, CHIM, an electrogeochemical partial extraction method: an historical overview: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 97-92, 27 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr9792.
Hopkins, D.M., 1977, An improved ion-selective electrode method for the rapid determination of fluorine in rocks and soils: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 5, no. 5, p. 589-593, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007422.
Hopkins, Delmont M., 1990, Determination of uranium in geologic materials by UV-f luorescence, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 111-113, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Hoyte, A.F., 1957, A gamma-ray absorption method for the determination of uranium in ores: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 57-55, 16 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr5755.
Hoyte, A.F., 1960, A gamma-ray absorption method for the determination of uranium in ores, in Geological Survey Research 1960, Short papers in the geological sciences: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 400-B, p. B504-B507, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp400B.
Hubert, A.E., 1971, Determination of tellurium in geologic materials in the parts-per-billion range, in Geological Survey Research 1971, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 750-B, p. B188-B190, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp750B.
Hubert, A.E., and Chao, T.T., 1977, X-ray fluorescence determination of titanium in geological materials: Analytica Chimica Acta, v. 92, p. 197-200, accessed March 25, 2016 at doi:10.1016/S0003-2670(01)84587-6.
Hubert, A.E., and Chao, T.T., 1985, Determination of gold, indium, tellurium and thallium in the same sample digest of geological materials by atomic-absorption spectroscopy and two-step solvent extraction: Talanta, v. 32, iss. 7, p. 568-570, accessed March 28, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0039-9140(85)80145-4.
Hubert, A.E., and Lakin, H.W., 1972, Atomic absorption determination of thallium and indium in geologic materials: Geochemical exploration 1972, Amsterdam, Elsevier, p. 389-387.
Huffman, Claude, Jr., 1962, Ion-exchange separation and spectrophotometric determination of cadmium, in Geological Survey Research 1962, Short papers in geology, hydrology, and topography, Articles 180-239: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 450-E, p. E126-E128, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp450E.
Huffman, Claude, Jr., 1968, Copper, strontium, and zinc content of U.S. Geological Survey silicate rock standards, in Geological Survey research 1968, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 600-B, p. B110-B111, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp600B.
Huffman, Claude, Jr., 1975, Analysis of rocks and soils for total content of sodium, magnesium, lithium, rubidium, zinc, cadmium, mercury, fluorine and carbon, in U.S. Geological Survey, 1975, Geochemical survey of the western coal regions second annual progress report, July 1975: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 75-436, p. 71-73, accessed October 30, 2015 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr75436.
Huffman, Claude, Jr., and Bartel, A.J., 1964, Ion-exchange separation of tin from silicate rocks, in Geological Survey Research 1964, Chapter D: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 501-D, p. D131-D133, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp501D.
Huffman, Claude, Jr., and Dinnin, J.I., 1976, Analysis of rocks and soils by atomic absorption spectrometry and other methods, in Miesch, A.T., Barnett, P.R., Bartel, A.J., Dinnin, J.I., Feder, G.L., Harms, T.F., Huffman, Claude, Jr., Janzer, V.J., Millard, H.T., Jr., Neiman, H.G., Skougstad, M.W., and Wahlberg, J.S., Methods of sampling, laboratory analysis, and statistical reduction of data, in Geochemical survey of Missouri: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 954-A, p. A12-A14, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp954A.
Huffman, Claude, Jr., Mensik, J.D., and Rader, L.F., Jr., 1966, Determination of silver in mineralized rocks by atomic-absorption spectrophotometry, in Geological Survey Research 1966, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 550-B, p. B189-B191, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp550B.
Huffman, Claude, Jr., Mensik, J.D., and Riley, L.B., 1967, Determination of gold in geologic materials by solvent extraction and atomic-absorption spectrometry: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 544, 6 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir544.
Huffman, Claude, Jr., Rahill, R.L., Shaw, V.E., and Norton, D.R., 1972, Determination of mercury in geologic materials by flameless atomic absorption spectrometry, in Geological Survey research, 1972, Chapter C: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 800-C, p. C203-C207, accessed March 21, 2016 at https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp800C.
Ingerson, Earl, 1954, Geochemical work of the Geochemistry and Petrology Branch U.S. Geological Survey: Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta, v. 5, p. 20-39, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0016-7037(54)90059-9.
Ingram, B.L., 1962, Spectrophotometric determination of fluorine with thoron, in Geological Survey Research 1962, Short papers in geology, hydrology, and topography, Articles 180-239: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 450-E, p. E130, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp450E.
Ingram, B.L., and May, Irving, 1971, Determining fluoride in rocks with a specific ion electrode, in Geological Survey Research 1971, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 750-B, p. B180-B184, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp750B.
Jackson, L.L., Brown, F.W., and Neil, S.T., 1987, Major and minor elements requiring individual determination, classical whole rock analysis, and rapid rock analysis, in Baedecker, P.A., ed., Methods for geochemical analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1770-G, p. G1-G23, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1770.
Jenkins, L.B., 1954, The determination of potassium and sodium in siliceous, argillaceous, and phosphatic rocks by the flame photometer: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 453, 17 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei453.
Jenkins, L.B., 1983, A review of classical silicate-rock analysis and recommended modifications of classical methods of analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 864, 34 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir864.
Jenkins, L.B., and Moore, Roosevelt, 1970, Determination of lead in rocks and minerals after extraction with diethylammonium diethyldithiocarbamate, in Geological Survey Research 1970, Chapter D: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 700-D, p. D222-D224, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp700D.
Johnson, R.G., 1984, Trace element analysis of silicates by means of energy-dispersive X-ray spectrometry: X-Ray Spectrometry, v. 13, iss. 2, p. 64-68, accessed March 28, 2016 at DOI: 10.1002/xrs.1300130206.
Johnson, R.G., and King, B.L., 1987, Energy-dispersive X-ray fluorescence spectrometry, in Baedecker, P.A., ed., Methods for geochemical analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1770-F, F1-F5, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1770.
Johnson, R.G., and Wandless, G.A., 1983, Determination of carrier yields for neutron activation analysis using energy dispersive X-ray spectrometry: Journal of Radioanalytical and Nuclear Chemistry, v. 81, p. 21-28, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF02132917.
Kane, J.S., 1979, Determination of nanogram amounts of bismuth in rocks by atomic absorption spectrometry with electrothermal atomization: Analytica Chimica Acta, v. 106, p. 325-331, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0003-2670(01)85016-9.
Kane, J.S., 1979, DEV1, a Fortran program for one-way analysis of variance of analytical data: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 79-282, 19 p., accessed March 22, 106 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr79282.
Kane, J.S., 1985, The inductively coupled plasma spectrometric method for the determination of six indicator elements for mineralization processes in granites: Geostandards Newsletter, v. 9, iss. 2, p. 181-190, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1751-908X.1985.tb00446.x.
Kane, J.S., 1987, The U.S. Geological Survey instrument for simultaneous multi-element atomic absorption spectrometry: description of the hardware and of the system control and data aquisition software: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 87-604, 54 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr87604.
Kane, J.S., 1993, The USGS reference sample Devonian Ohio Shale SDO-1: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 2046, 65 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b2046.
Kellagher, R.C., 1953, A multiple cone splitter for rapid sampling in the laboratory: U.S. Geological Survey trace elements Investigations Report 371, 14 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei371.
Kennedy, K.R., and Crock, J.G., 1987, Determination of mercury in geological materials by continuous-flow, cold-vapor, atomic spectrophotometry: Analytical Letters, v. 20, p. 899-908, accessed March 25, 2016 at DOI:10.1080/00032718708062939.
Kent, Judy., and King, B.L., 1993, Analysis of Cr, Ni, Zu, Zn, Rb, Sr, Y, Zr, Nb, Ba, La and Ce by energy-dispersive XRF, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Kepferle, R.C., De Witt, Wallace, and Flanagan, F.J., 1985, Ohio shale (Devonian), SDO-1 from Rowan County, Kentucky: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 85-145, 14 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr85145.
King, B.L., 1996, Twelve selected Trace Elements by energy-dispersive X-ray fluorescence spectrometry, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 228-235, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
King, B.L., and Lindsay, J.R., 1990, Determination of 12 selected trace elements in geologic materials by energy-dispersive X-ray fluorescence spectrometry, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 161-165, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Kinser, C.A., 1953, The Model VI transmission fluorimeter for the determination of uranium: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 2370, 20 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei370.
Kinser, C.A., 1954, The Model VI transmission fluorimeter for the determination of uranium: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 330, 9 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir330.
Kirschenbaum, Herbert, 1981, A manual of modified analytical procedures for conventional rock analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 81-359, 83 p.
Kirschenbaum, Herbert, 1983, The classical chemical analysis of silicate rocks - The old and the new: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1547, 55 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1547.
Kirschenbaum, Herbert, 1988, The determination of fluoride in silicate rocks by ion-selective electrode: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 88-588, 5 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr88588.
Kirschenbaum, Herbert, and Doughten, M.W., 1990, Determination of fluoride in silicates and sediments by ion-selective electrode following a sodium carbonate-zinc oxide fusion, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 173-176, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Klock, P.R., 1984, Carbonate carbon in silicates, carbonates, and phosphates, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 96-101, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Klock, P.R., 1984, Total carbon content of geologic materials, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 102-107, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Klock, P.R., and Cremer, M.J., 1984, FeO in silicates, carbonates, and phosphates using the Metrohm titrator, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 121-126, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Klock, P.R., and Lamothe, P.J., 1984, Modification of a carbon-hydrogen-nitrogen analyzer for reduction of instrument background: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-489, 6 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84489.
Knight, R.J., and McKown, D.M., 1996, Uranium and thorium by delayed neutron counting, in Arbogast, B.F., ed.,  Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 206-210, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Knight, R.J., and McKown, D.M., 2002, Uranium and thorium by delayed neutron counting, in Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, p. Z1-Z5, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-0223/Z26UThDN_M.pdf.
Lakin, H.W., 1959, A field test for selenium: International Geological Congress, 20th, Mexico 1956, Symposium de Exploracion Geoquimica, v. 2, p. 453-459 [1961].
Lakin, H.W., Almond, Hy, and Ward, F.N., 1951, Compilation of field tests used in geochemical prospecting by the U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84, 83 p.
Lakin, H.W., Almond, Hy, and Ward, F.N., 1952, Compilation of field tests used in geochemical prospecting by the U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 161, 34 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir161.
Lakin, H.W., and Nakagawa, H.N., 1965, A spectrophotometric method for the determination of gold useful in mineral exploration: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 65-181, 12 p.
Lakin, H.W., and Nakagawa, H.N., 1965, A spectrophotometric method for the determination of gold useful in mineral exploration, in Geological Survey Research 1965, Chapter C: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 525-C, p. C168-C171, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp525C.
Lakin, H.W., and Thompson, C.E., 1963, Effect of copper on the precipitation of tellurium with hypophosphorus acid using selenium or gold as a collector, in Geological Survey Research 1962, Short papers in geology, hydrology, and topography, Articles 180-239: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 450-E, p. E128-E129, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp450E.
Lakin, H.W., Curtin, G.C., Hubert, A.E., Shacklette, H.T., and Doxtader, K.G., 1974, Geochemistry of gold in the weathering cycle: a study of the solubilization of gold by the formation of chloride, bromide, iodide, thiosulfate, thiocyanide, and cyanide gold complexes and related topics: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1330, 80 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1330.
Lakin, H.W., Stevens, R.E., and Almond, Hy, 1949, Field methods for the determination of zinc in soils: Economic Geology, v. 44, no. 4, p. 296-306, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.2113/gsecongeo.44.4.296.
Lamothe, P.J., 1993, Analysis of boron by emission spectrography, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Lamothe, P.J., Fries, T.L., and Consul, J.J., 1986, A microwave-oven system for the dissolution of geologic samples: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 86-189, 19 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr86189.
Layman, L.R., and Lichte, F.E., 1982, Design and implementation of an auto-profiling system for spectrometers using ICP excitation: ICP Newsletter, v. 7, iss. 11, p. 565, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://www.speciation.net/Database/Journals/ICP-Information-Newsletter-;i33.
Leary, J.J., Brookes, A.E., Dorrzapf, A.F., Jr., and Golightly, D.W., 1982, An objective function for optimization techniques in simultaneous multiple-element analysis by inductively plasma spectrometry: Applied Spectroscopy, v. 36, iss. 1, p. 37-40, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://www.s-a-s.org/4DCGI/sas/journal/abstract.html?WebTopic_w=8864.
Leinz, R.W., 1993, Analysis of Cl by selective ion electrode, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Leinz, R.W., and Grimes, D.J., 1978, Spectrochemical determination of submicrogram amounts of tungsten in geologic materials: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 6, no. 2, p. 259-262, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007425.
Leventhal, J.S., Crock, J.G., Mountjoy, Wayne, Thomas, J.A., Shale, V.E., Briggs, P.H., Wahlberg, J.S., and Malcolm, M.J., 1978, Preliminary analytical results for a new U.S. Geological Survey Devonian Ohio Shale Standard SDO-1: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 78-447, 13 p.
Levine, Harry, and Grimaldi, F.S., 1949, Application of mesityl oxide to the determination of thorium: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 105, 36 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei105.
Levine, Harry, and Grimaldi, F.S., 1957, Determination of thorium in the parts per million range in rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 692, 11 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei692.
Lichte, F.E., Golightly, D.W., and Lamothe, P.J., 1987, Inductively coupled plasma-atomic emission spectrometry, in Baedecker, P.A., ed., Methods for geochemical analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1770-B, p. B1-B10, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1770.
Lichte, F.E., Meier, A.L., and Crock, J.G., 1987, Determination of the rare earth elements in geological materials by inductively coupled plasma-mass spectrometry: Analytical Chemistry, v. 59, iss. 8, p. 1150-1157, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/ac00135a018.
Lillie, E.G., and Greenland, L.P., 1973, Spectrophotometric determination of tungsten in rocks by an isotope dilution procedure: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 1, no. 5, p. 555-558, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007398.
Lillie, E.G., and Greenland, L.P., 1976, Molybdenum in USGS standard rocks, in Flanagan, F.J., ed., 1976, Descriptions and analyses of eight new USGS rock standards: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 840,  p. 47-49, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp840.
Marinenko, John, and May, Irving, 1970, Gas chromatographic determination of carbonate carbon in rocks and minerals, in Geological Survey Research 1970, Chapter D: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 700-D, p. D103-D105, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp700D.
Marinenko, John, May, Irving, and Dinnin, J.I., 1972, Determination of mercury in geologic materials by flameless atomic absorption spectrometry, in Geological Survey research, 1972, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 800-B, p. B151-B155., accessed March 21, 2016 at https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp800B.
Marinenko, John, and Mei, Leung, 1974, Spectrophotometric determination of vanadium in rutile and in mafic rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 2, no. 6, p. 701-704, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007405.
May, Irving, and Cuttitta, Frank, 1961, Completeness of precipitation of selenium as the element, in Geological Survey Research 1961, Short papers in the geologic and hydrologic sciences, Articles 293-435: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 424-D, p. D394-D395, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp424D.
May, Irving, and Fletcher, M.H., 1948, A preliminary report on a transmission fluorimeter: U.S. Geological Survey trace elements Investigations Report 91, 7 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei91.
May, Irving, and Fletcher, M.H., 1950, A battery-powered fluorimeter for the determination of uranium: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 135, 9 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei135.
May, Irving, and Jenkins, L.B., 1965, Use of arsenazo III in determination of thorium in rocks and minerals, in Geological Survey Research 1965, Chapter D: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 525-D, p. D192-D195, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp525D.
May, Irving, Dinnin, J.I., and Rosenbaum, Fred, 1964, A simple oxygen sheath for flame photometry, in Geological Survey Research 1964, Chapter C: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 501-C, p. C152-C153, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp501C.
May, Irving, Rowe, J.J., and Letner, Raymond, 1965, A platinum-lined bomb for the high temperature decomposition of refractory minerals, in Geological Survey Research 1965, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 525-B, p. B165-B166, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp525B.
Mays, R.E., Czamanske, G.K., and Heropoulos, Chris, 1974, Synthetic sulfide standards for quantitative emission spectrographic analysis: Applied Spectroscopy, v. 28, no. 5, p. 462-465, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://www.s-a-s.org/4DCGI/sas/journal/abstract.html?WebTopic_w=8568.
McHugh, J.B., and Welsch, E.P., 1975, Atomic absorption determination of antimony in geologic materials, in Ward, F.N., ed., New and refined methods of trace analysis useful in geochemical exploration: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1408, p. 5-12., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1408.
McKown, D.M., and Knight, R.J., 1990, Determination of uranium and thorium in geologic materials by delayed neutron counting, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 146-150, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
McKown, D.M., and Millard, H.T., Jr., 1987, Determination of uranium and thorium by delayed neutron counting, in Baedecker, P.A., ed., Methods for geochemical analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1770-I, I1-I12, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1770.
Mee, J.S., Siems, D.F., and Taggart, J.E., Jr., 1993, Analysis of major elements by XRF, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Mee, J.S., Siems, D.F., and Taggart, J.E., Jr., 1996, Major element analysis by wavelength dispersive X-ray fluorescence spectrometry, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 236-242, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Meier, A.L., 1976, Analytical methods and problems of lithium determination in rocks, sediments and brines, in Vine, J.D., ed., Lithium resources and requirements by the year 2000: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 1005, p. 161-162, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp1005.
Meier, A.L., 1979, A technique for decomposition and dissolution of rocks for the determination of lithium, calcium and magnesium by atomic absorption, in Shorter Contributions to Geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 1129-I, p. I1-I5, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp1129AI.
Meier, A.L., 1980, Flameless atomic-absorption-  determination of gold in geological materials: Journal of Geochemical Exploration, v. 13, p. 77-85, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0375-6742(80)90022-9.
Meier, A.L., and Bigelow, R.C., 1984, AFS DETECTION LIMITS: listing and explanation of a computer program for the Baird Plasma/AFS and Apple II computer to determine detection limits: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-698, 23 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84698.
Meier, A.L., and Lichte, F.E., 1996, Rare earth elements by inductively coupled plasma-mass spectrometry, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 166-172, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Meier, A.L., and Slowik, Tara, 2002, Rare earth elements by inductively coupled plasma-mass spectrometry, in Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, p. K1-K8, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-0223/K19NewREE_M.pdf.
Meier, A.L., Carlson, R.R., Lichte, F.E., and Bullock, J.H., Jr., 1996, Platinum group elements by nickel sulfide fire assay separation and inductively coupled plasma-mass spectrometry, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 158-165, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Meyrowitz, Robert, and Massoni, C.J., 1954, An automatic micromuffle for the determination of ash in carbonaceous material: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 412, 7 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei412.
Miesch, A.T., Barnett, P.R., Bartel, A.J., Dinnin, J.I., Feder, G.L., Harms, T.F., Huffman, Claude, Jr., Janzer, V.J., Millard, H.T., Jr., Neiman, H.G., Skougstad, M.W., and Wahlberg, J.S., Methods of sampling, laboratory analysis, and statistical reduction of data, in Geochemical survey of Missouri: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 954-A, 38 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp954A.
Milkey, R.G., 1952, A theoretical treatment of the absorption characteristics of the dithizone mixed-color system: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 236, 12 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei236.
Milkey, R.G., and Fletcher, M.H., 1956, A fluorimetric study of the thorium-morin system: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 589, 56 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei589.
Millard, H.T., Jr., 1975, Determination of uranium and thorium in rocks and soils by the delayed neutron technique, in U.S. Geological Survey, 1975, Geochemical survey of the western coal regions second annual progress report, July 1975: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 75-436, p. 79-81, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr75436.
Millard, H.T., Jr., 1976, Determination of uranium and thorium in U.S.G.S. standard rocks by the delayed neutron technique, in Flanagan, F. J., ed., Descriptions and analysis of eight new USGS rock standards: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 840, p. 61-70., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp840.
Millard, H.T., Jr., and Bartel, A.J., 1971, A neutron activation analysis procedure for the determination of the noble metals in geological samples, in Brunfelt, A.O., and Steinnes, Eiliv. eds., Activation analysis in geochemistry and cosmochemistry: Proceedings of the NATO Advanced Study Institute, Oslo, Norway, Universitetsforlaget, p. 353-358.
Millard, H.T., Jr., and Keaten, B.A., 1982, Precision of uranium and thorium determinatons by delayed neutron counting: Journal of Radioanalytical Chemistry, v. 72, iss. 1-2, p. 489-500.
Millard, H.T., Jr., Marinenko, John, and McLane, J.E., 1969, Establishment of gold-quartz standard GQS-1: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 598, 6 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir598.
Moreland, John and Myers, A.T., 1973, Notes on use and maintenance of vertical pulverizers for geologic materials: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 73-194, 6 p.
Mosier, E.L., 1975, Use or emission spectroscopy for the semiquantitative analysis of trace elements and silver in native gold, in Ward, F.N., ed., New and refined methods of trace analysis useful in geochemical exploration: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1408, p. 97-105., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1408.
Mosier, E.L., Antweiler, J.C., and Nishi, J.M., 1975, Spectrochemical determination of trace elements in galena:  U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 3, no. 5, p. 625-630, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007410.
Mossotti, V.G., and King, B.L., 1982, The determination of total volatiles in rocks by loss-on-fusion: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 82-587, 23 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr82587.
Motooka, J.M., 1988, An exploration geochemical technique for the determination of preconcentrated organometallic halides by ICP-AES: Applied Spectroscopy, v. 42, iss. 7, p. 1293-1296, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://www.s-a-s.org/4DCGI/sas/journal/abstract.html?WebTopic_w=1654.
Motooka, J.M., 1990, Organometallic halide extraction applied to the analysis of geologic materials for 10 elements by inductively coupled plasma-atomic emission spectrometry, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 92-96, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Motooka, J.M., 1993, Analysis of Ag, As, Au, Bi, Cd, Cu, Mo, Pb, Sb and Zn by solvent extraction ICP-AES, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Motooka, J.M., 1996, Organometallic halide extraction for 10 elements by inductively coupled plasma-atomic emission spectrometry, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 102-108, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Motooka, J.M., and Grimes, D.J., 1976, Analytical precision of one-sixth order semiquantitative spectrographic analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 738, 25 p., accessed march 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir738.
Motooka, J.M., Mosier, E.L., Sutley, S.J., and Viets, J.G., 1979, Induction-coupled plasma determination of Ag, Au, Bi, Cd, Cu, Pb, and Zn in geologic materials using a selective extraction technique--preliminary investigation: Applied Spectroscopy, v. 33, iss. 5, p. 456-460, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://www.s-a-s.org/4DCGI/sas/journal/abstract.html?WebTopic_w=1216.
Mountjoy, Wayne, 1970, Determination of cobalt in geologic materials by solvent extraction and atomic absorption spectrometry, in Geological Survey Research 1970, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 700-B, p. B174-B176, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp700B.
Mountjoy, Wayne, and Lipp, H.H., 1961, Some factors affecting the determination of beryllium by the gamma-ray activation method, in Geological Survey Research 1961, Short papers in the geologic and hydrologic sciences, Articles 147-292: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 424-C, p. C379-C380, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp424C.
Mountjoy, Wayne, and Wahlberg, J.S., 1968, Determination of micro amounts of cesium in geologic materials, in Geological Survey Research 1968, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 600-B, p. B119-B122, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp600B.
Myers, A.T., and Barnett, P.R., 1952, Contamination of rock samples during grinding as determined spectrographically: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 179, 31 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei179.
Myers, A.T., Havens, R.G. and Dunton, P.J., 1961, A spectrochemical method for the semiquantitative analysis of rocks, minerals, and ores, in Contributions to Geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1084-I, p. 207-229, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1084I.
Myers, A.T., Havens, R.G., Connor, J.J., Conklin, N.M. and Rose, H.J., Jr., 1976, Glass reference standards for the trace-element analysis of geological materials; compilation of interlaboratory data: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 1013, 29 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp1013.
Nakagawa, H.N., 1975, Atomic absorption determination of silver, bismuth, cadmium, cobalt, copper, nickel, lead, and zinc in calcium- and iron-rich geologic materials, in Ward, F.N., ed., New and refined methods of trace analysis useful in geochemical exploration: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1408, p. 85-96., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1408.
Nakagawa, H.N., and Harms, T.F., 1968, Atomic absorption determination of cadmium in geologic materials, in Geological Survey Research 1968, Chapter D: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 600-D, p. D207-D209, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp600D.
Nakagawa, H.N., and Lakin, H.W., 1965, A field method for the determination of silver in soils and rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 65-182, 13 p.
Nakagawa, H.N., and Lakin, H.W., 1965, A field method for the determination of silver in soils and rocks, in Geological Survey Research 1965, Chapter C: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 525-C, p. C172-C175, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp525C.
Nakagawa, H.N., and Thompson, C.E., 1968, Atomic absorption determination of tellurium, in Geological Survey Research 1968, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 600-B, p. B123-B125, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp600B.
Neil, S.T., 1984, Colorometric determination of silica, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 18-19, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Neil, S.T., 1984, Determination of total Mn with NaBiO3, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 127-130, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Neil, S.T., 1984, Extended analysis of the ammonia group precipitate, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 44-48, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Neil, S.T., 1984, Gravimetric determination of phosphorus, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 30-35, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Neil, S.T., 1984, Main portion on phosphate rocks and minerals, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 36-43, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Neiman, H.G., 1976, Analysis of rocks, soils, and plant ashes by emission spectroscopy, in Miesch, A.T., Barnett, P.R., Bartel, A.J., Dinnin, J.I., Feder, G.L., Harms, T.F., Huffman, Claude, Jr., Janzer, V.J., Millard, H.T., Jr., Neiman, H.G., Skougstad, M.W., and Wahlberg, J.S., Methods of sampling, laboratory analysis, and statistical reduction of data, in Geochemical survey of Missouri: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 954-A, p. A14-A15, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp954A.
Niles, W.W., 1964, Determination of total iron in hematitic iron ores by X-ray fluorescence spectrometry, in Geological Survey Research 1963, Short papers in geology and hydrology, Articles 122-172: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 475-D, p. D174-D175, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp475D.
Norton, D.R., and Papp, C.S.E., 1990, Determination of moisture and total water in silicate rocks, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 73-82, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Norton, D.R., and Papp, C.S.E., 1996, Moisture and total water in silicate rocks, in Arbogast, B.F., ed.,  Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 67-76, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Nowlan, G.A., 1965, Use of bathocuproine in the quantitative determination of copper in soils, sediments and rocks, in Geological Survey Research 1965, Chapter D: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 525-D, p. D189-D191, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp525D.
Nowlan, G.A., 1970, A field method for the determination of cold-extractable nickel in stream sediments and soils, in Geological Survey Research 1970, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 700-B, p. B177-B180, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp700B.
Oda, Uteana, Myers, A.T., and Cooley, E.F., 1959, A field method of spectrographic analysis for use in geochemical exploration work: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 59-91, 8 p.
O'Leary, R.M., 1990, Determination of sulfur in geologic materials by iodometric titration, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 136-138, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
O'Leary, R.M., 1993, Analysis of As, Sb and Se by hydride generation AA, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
O'Leary, R.M., 1996, Cadmium and silver by flame atomic absorption spectrometry, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 56-59, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
O'Leary, R.M., 1996, Tellurium and thallium by flame atomic absorption spectrometry, in Arbogast, B.F., ed.,  -Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 37-41, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
O'Leary, R.M., and Chao, T.T., 1990, Determination of gold, tellurium, and thallium, in rock, stream-sediment, and soil samples by flame, and gold by graphite furnace, atomic absorption spectrophotometry following dissolution by HF, aqua regia, and HBR-Br2, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 52-59, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
O'Leary, R.M., and Hopkins, D.M., 1990, Determination of fluoride in rock, soil, and stream-sediment samples by ion-selective electrode following Na2CO3-K2CO3-KNO3 fusion and dissolution with citric acid, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 127-130, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, 48 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Antimony, atomic absorption method, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p. 4-6, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Arsenic, confined-spot method, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p. 6-8, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Arsenic, spectrophotometric method, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p. 8-11, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Bismuth, cadmium, copper, lead, silver, and zinc, organic extraction method, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p.11-14, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Calcium, lithium, magnesium, potassium, and sodium, atomic absorption method, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p.14-17, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Cobalt, copper, lead, nickel, and zinc, atomic absorption method, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p.17-19, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Copper, acid-extractable method, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p.19-21, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Fluorine, ion-selective electrode method, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p.21-23, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Gold, flame atomic absorption method, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p.23-25, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Gold, flameless atomic absorption method, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p.25-27, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Heavy metals, ammonium citrate-extractable method, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p.27-29, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Indium and thallium, atomic absorption method, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p.29-31, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Molybdenum, atomic absorption method, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p.31-33, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Selenium, nameless atomic absorption method, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p.33-36, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Tellurium, flame and flameless atomic absorption methods, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p.36-39, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Tin, atomic absorption method, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p.39-41, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Tungsten, visible spectrophotometric method, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p.41-42, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Uranium, ultraviolet fluorescence method, in O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, p.42-45, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir948.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1990, Determination of gold in samples of rock, soil, stream-sediment and heavy-mineral concentrate by flame and graphite furnace atomic absorption spectrophotometry following dissolution in HBR-Br2, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 46-51, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1996, Gold by flame or graphite furnace atomic absorption spectrometry, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey open-file report 96-525, p. 31-36, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
O'Leary, R.M., and Viets, J.G., 1986, Determination of antimony, arsenic, bismuth, cadmium, copper, lead, molybdenum, silver, and zinc in geological materials by atomic absorption spectrometry using a hydrochloric acid-hydrogen peroxide digestion: Atomic Spectroscopy, v. 7, p. 4-8, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://www.speciation.net/Database/Journals/Atomic-Spectroscopy-;i19.
O'Leary, R.M., and Welsch, E.P., 1990, Determination of tungsten in rock, soil, and stream-sediment samples by visible absorption spectrophotometry, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 157-160, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
O'Leary, R.M., Crock, J.G., and Kennedy, K.R., 1990, Determination of mercury in geologic materials by continuous flow-cold vapor-atomic absorption spectrophotometry, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 60-67, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
O'Leary, R.M., Hageman, P.L., and Crock, J.G., 1996, Mercury in water, geologic, and plant materials by continuous flow-cold vapor-atomic absorption spectrometry, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 42-50, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Palmer, C.A., and Pickering, M.J., 1993, "Short count" INAA package, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Palmer, C.A., Kolker, Allan, Willett, J.C., Mroczkowski, S.J., Finkelman, R.B., Taylor, K.C., Dulong, F.T., and Bullock, J.H., Jr., 1999, Preliminary report on the International Energy Agency mode of occurrence inter-laboratory comparison, phase I: USGS results: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 99-160, 48 p., accessed march 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr99160.
Papp, C.S.E.,  1993, "X-ray support" package for FeO, CO2, H2O+, and H2O-, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Papp, C.S.E., Aruscavage, P.J., and Brandt, E.L., 1990, Determination of ferrous oxide in geologic materials by potentiometric titration, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 139-145, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Papp, C.S.E., Aruscavage, P.J., and Brandt, E.L., 1996, Ferrous oxide by potentiometric titration, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 200-205, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Papp, C.S.E., Brandt, E.L., and Aruscavage, P.J., 1996, Carbonate carbon by coulometric titration, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 60-66, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Papp, C.S.E., Filipek, L.H., and Smith, K.S., 1991, Selectivity and effectiveness of extractants used to release metals associated with organic matter: Applied Geochemistry, v. 6, p. 349-353, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0883-2927(91)90010-M.
Parshall, E.E., and Rader, L.F., Jr., 1955, Diagrams for construction of model '54 transmission and reflection fluorimeter: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 55-130, 3 p., accessed March 22, 2015 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr55130.
Parshall, E.E., and Rader, L.F., Jr., 1955, The model '54 transmission and reflection fluorimeter for the determination of uranium, with adaptation to field use: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 520, 48 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei520.
Parshall, E.E., and Rader, L.F., Jr., 1957, Model '54 transmission and reflection fluorimeter for determination of uranium with adaptation to field use, in Contributions to Geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1036-M, p. 221-251, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1036M.
Patten, L.E., and Ward, F.N., 1962, Geochemical field method for beryllium prospecting, in Geological Survey Research 1962, Short papers in geology, hydrology, and topography, Articles 60-119: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 450-C, p. C103-C104, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp450C.
Peacock, T.R., 1990, Physical preparation of soil samples, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 29-32, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Peacock, T.R., 1996, Soil sample preparation, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 11-14, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Peacock, T.R., and Taylor, C.D., 1990, Physical preparation of stream-sediment samples, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 26-28, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Peacock, T.R., Taylor, C.D., and Theodorakos, P.M., 1996, Stream-sediment sample preparation, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 7-10, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Peck, L.C., 1964, Systematic analysis of silicates: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1170, 89 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1170.
Peck, L.C., and Smith, V.C., 1961, Removal of manganese from solutions prior to determination of calcium and magnesium, in Geological Survey Research 1961, Short papers in the geologic and hydrologic sciences, Articles 293-435: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 424-D, p. D401-D402, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp424D.
Peterman, Z.E., Doe, B.R., and Bartel, A.J., 1967, Data on the rock GSP-1 (granodiorite) and the isotope-dilution method of analysis for Rb and Sr, in Geological Survey Research 1967, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 575-B, p. B181-B185, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp575B.
Phair, George, and Levine, Harry, 1952, Notes on the differential leaching of uranium, radium, and lead from pitchblende in H2SO4 solutions: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 262, 23 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei262.
Philpotts, J.A., 1987, Isotope-dilution mass spectrometry, in Baedecker, P.A., ed., Methods for geochemical analysis: U.S. Geological Survey bulletin 1770-K, p. K1-K5, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1770.
Powell, R.A. and Kinser, C.A., 1956, A dithizone method for the determination of lead in monazite: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 630, 18 p., accessed march 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei630.
Pribble, S.T., 1990, Determination of fluoride in silicates by ion-selective electrode following LiBO2 fusion and HNO3 dissolution, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 123-126, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Pribble, S.T., 1996, Fluoride in silicates by ion-selective electrode following LiBO2 fusion and HNO3 dissolution, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 195-199, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Prosser, C.L., 1993, "X-ray support" package for FeO, CO2, H2O+, and H2O-, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Rader, L.F., Jr., and Grimaldi, F.S., 1961, Chemical analyses for selected minor elements in Pierre Shale, in Analytical Methods in Geochemical Investigations of the Pierre Shale: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 391-A, 45 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp391A.
Rader, L.F., Jr., Swadley, W.C., Lipp, H.H., and Huffman, Claude, Jr., 1960, Determination of zinc in basalts and other rocks, in Geological Survey Research 1960, Short papers in the geological sciences: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 400-B, p. B477-B480, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp400B.
Rait, Norma, 1993, Analysis of silver by chemical separation/GFAA, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Rait, Norma, Walthall, F.G., and Philpotts, J.A., 1993, Abundances of Li, Rb, and Sr in W-2, BCR-1, and AC-E determined by isotope dilution mass spectroscopy: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-267, 6 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr93267.
Randolph, R.B., and Grimaldi, F.S., 1949, The determination of phosphorus in rocks containing vanadium: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 99, 12 p., accessed march 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei99.
Randolph, R.B., and Grimaldi, F.S., 1953, The determination of phosphorus in rocks containing vanadium, in Brannock, W.W. and others, Contributions to geochemistry, 1949: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 992, p. 49-57, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b992.
Randolph, R.B., and Grimaldi, F.S., 1953, The probable error of chemical analysis, in Brannock, W.W. and others, Contributions to geochemistry, 1949: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 992, p. 57-71, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b992.
Reichen, L.E., 1971, Determination of sulfur in pyritic rocks by a single precipitation of barium sulfate after nitrate fusion, in Geological Survey Research 1971, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 750-B, p. B163-B164, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp750B.
Reichen, L.E., and Fahey, J.J., 1962, An improved method for the determination of FeO in rocks and minerals including garnet, in Contributions to geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1144-B, p. B1-B5, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1144B.
Riddle, G.O., 1993, Analysis of platinum group elements by ICP-MS, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Riviello, J.M., 1984, Total water--Penfield method, in Cremer, M.J., Klock, P.R., Neil, S.T., and Riviello, J.M., 1984, Chemical methods for analysis of rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 84-565, p. 87-89, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr84565.
Rose, H.J., Jr., Adler, Isidore, and Flanagan, F.J., 1962, Use of La2O3 as a heavy absorber in the X-ray fluorescence analysis of silicate rocks, in Geological Survey Research 1962, Short papers in geology, hydrology, and topography, Articles 1-59: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 450-B, p. B80-B82, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp450B.
Rose, H.J., Jr., Adler, Isidore, and Flanagan, F.J., 1963, X-ray fluorescence analysis of the light elements in rocks and minerals: Applied Spectroscopy, v. 17, iss. 4, p. 81-85, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://www.s-a-s.org/4DCGI/sas/journal/abstract.html?WebTopic_w=2180.
Rose, H.J., Jr., and Flanagan, F.J., 1962, X-ray fluorescence determination of thallium in manganese ores, in Geological Survey Research 1962, Short papers in geology, hydrology, and topography, Articles 1-59: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 450-B, p. B82-B83, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp450B.
Rose, H.J., Jr., Adler, Isidore, and Flanagan, F.J., 1963, X-ray fluorescence analysis of the light elements in rocks and minerals: Applied Spectroscopy, v. 17, p. 81-85, accessed October 28, 2015 at http://www.s-a-s.org/images/page.html#765.
Rose, H.J., Jr., Cuttitta, Frank, and Larson, R.R., 1965, Use of X-ray fluorescence in determination of selected major constituents in silicates, in Geological Survey Research 1965, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 525-B, p. B155-B159, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp525B.
Rose, H.J., Jr., Cuttitta, Frank, Carron, M.K., and Brown, Robena, 1964, Semimicro X-ray fluorescence analysis of tektites using 50-milligram samples, in Geological Survey Research 1963, Short papers in geology and hydrology, Articles 122-172: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 475-D, p. D171-D173, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp475D.
Rosholt, J.N., 1953, A quantitative radiochemical method for the determination of the major sources of natural radioactivity in ores and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 318, 35 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei318.
Rosholt, J.N., 1956, Quantitative radiochemical methods for the determination of the sources of natural radioactivity. Part II: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 484, 36 p., accessed march 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei484.
Rowe, J.J., 1951, Noninterference of arsenate ion in the volumetric determination of uranium using the Jones reductor: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 316, 9 p.
Rowe, J.J., 1973, Determination of gold in phosphates by activation analysis using epithermal neutrons: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 1, no. 1, p. 79-80, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007394.
Rowe, J.J. and Simon, F.O., 1968, The determination of gold in geologic materials by neutron activation analysis using fire assay for the radiochemical separations: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 599, 4 p., accessed August 13, 2012 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir599.
Rowe, J.J., and Steinnes, Eiliv, 1977, Determination of 22 minor and Trace Elements in 8 new USGS standard rocks by instrumental activation analysis with epithermal neutrons: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 5, no. 3, p. 397-402, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007420.
Sanford, R.F., and Seeley, J.L., 1987, A new method of analysis for trace elements in gold-silver deposits: comparison with Lake City data: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 87-67, 39 p., accessed march 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr8767.
Sanzolone, R.F., and Chao, T.T., 1976, Atomic absorption spectrometric determinations of copper, zinc and lead in geological materials: Analytica Chimica Acta, v. 86, p. 163-168, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0003-2670(01)83030-0.
Sanzolone, R.F., and Chao, T.T., 1981, Determination of submicrogram amounts of selenium in geological materials by electrothermal atomic-absorption spectrophotometry after solvent extraction: The Analyst, v. 106, iss. 1263, p. 647-652, accessed on March 25, 2016 at http://pubs.rsc.org/en/content/articlelanding/1981/an/an9810600647#!divAbstract.
Sanzolone, R.F., and Chao, T.T., 1983, Atomic-absorption determination of mercury in geological materials by flame and carbon-rod atomisation after solvent extraction and using co-extracted silver as a matrix modifier: Analyst, v. 108, p. 56-63, accessed  March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/AN9830800058.
Sanzolone, R.F., Chao, T.T., and Welsch, E.P., 1979, Determination of arsenic in geological materials by electrothermal atomic-absorption spectrometry after hydride generation: Analytica Chimica Acta, v. 108, P. 357-361, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0003-2670(01)93076-4.
Schnepfe, M.M., 1958, A study of cation exchange with vermiculite: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 512, 40 p., accessed August 13, 2012 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr60122.
Schnepfe, M.M., 1974, Spectrofluorimetric procedure using 2,3-napthalenediamine for determining selenium in rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 2, no. 5, p. 631-636, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007404.
Schnepfe, M.M., and Grimaldi, F.S., 1968, Determination of rhodium in rocks, in Geological Survey Research 1968, Chapter D: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 600-D, p. D210-D213, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp600D.
Schnepfe, M.M., and Grimaldi, F.S., 1969, Atomic absorption determination of rhodium in chromite concentrates: Talanta, v. 16, iss. 11, P. 1461-1465, accessed March 28, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0039-9140(69)80197-9.
Schwarz, L.J., and Barker, J.L., 1976, Gold content of USGS standard rocks, in Flanagan, F.J., ed., 1976, Descriptions and analyses of eight new USGS rock standards: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 840, p. 71-73, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp840.
Schwarz, L.J., and Rowe, J.J., 1976, The determination of antimony, hafnium, and tantalum in the new USGS standard rocks, in Flanagan, F.J., ed., 1976, Descriptions and analyses of eight new USGS rock standards: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 840, p. 67-71, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp840.
Senftle, F.E., 1976, Possible methods of measuring uranium and its radioactive products in solutions: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 76-305, 7 p.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, 10 element ICP-AES DIBK extraction, SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 2: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2015, 10 element ICP-MS, multi-acid digestion (ICP-10), SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 2: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, 40 element ICP-AES multi-acid, total, SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 1: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, 42 element ICP-AES-MS multi-acid, total, SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 19: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, 55 element ICP-AES-MS sodium peroxide sinter,  SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 22: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, Arsenic (As)and antimony (Sb), SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Methods 9 &amp; 11: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, Carbonate carbon, SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 3-B: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, Chloride (Cl), SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 18: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, Essential and non-essential water, SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 5: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, Ferrous oxide, SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 4: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, Fluoride (F), SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 16: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2009, Gold (Au), SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 7: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, Gold (Au), SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 7: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2009, Gold, platinum, and palladium, SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 20: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, Gold, platinum, and palladium: SGS Analytical ontract Laboratory Method 20: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, ICP major element analysis using a lithium metaborate fusion, SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 17: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, Mercury (Hg), SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 8: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, High concentration rare earth elements, ICP-MS sodium peroxide fusion: SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 17: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, Selenium (Se), SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 10: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, Tellurium (Te), SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 13: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, Thallium (Tl), SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 14: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2014, Thallium (Tl), SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 14: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, Titanium (Ti), SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 21: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services,  2011, Total carbon, SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 3-A: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, Total sulfur, SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 6: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, Tungsten (W), SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 12: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
SGS Minerals Services, 2011, XRF major element analysis, SGS Analytical Contract Laboratory Method 15: SGS Minerals Services, 1885 Leslie Street, Toronto, ON M3B 2M3, Canada.
Shapiro, Leonard, 1960, A spectrophotometric method for the determination of FeO in rocks, in Geological Survey Research 1960, Short papers in the geological sciences: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 400-B, p. B496-B497, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp400B.
Shapiro, Leonard, 1967, A simple and rapid indirect determination of fluorine in minerals and rocks, in Geological Survey Research 1967, Chapter D: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 575-D, p. D232-D235, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp575D.
Shapiro, Leonard, 1967, Rapid analysis of rocks and minerals by a single-solution method, in Geological Survey Research 1967, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 575-B, p. B187-B191, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp575B.
Shapiro, Leonard, 1971, Rapid scanning technique for low levels of CO2 in silicate rocks, in Geological Survey Research 1971, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 750-B, p. B161-B162, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp750B.
Shapiro, Leonard, 1973, Rapid determination of sulfur in rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 1, no. 1, p. 81-84, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007394.
Shapiro, Leonard, 1974, Spectrophotometric determination of silica at high concentrations using fluoride as a depolymerizer: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 2, no. 3, p. 357-360, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007402.
Shapiro, Leonard, 1975, Rapid analysis of silicate, carbonate and phosphatic rocks [revised edition]: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1401, 76 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1401.
Shapiro, Leonard, and Brannock, W.W., 1952, A field test for titanium in rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 157, 3 p.
Shapiro, Leonard, and Brannock, W.W., 1952, Rapid analysis of silicate rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 165, 17 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir165.
Shapiro, Leonard, and Brannock, W.W., 1954, Field method for the determination of titanium in rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 54-283, 7 p.
Shapiro, Leonard, and Brannock, W.W., 1956, Rapid analysis of silicate rocks, in Contributions to Geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1036-C, p. 19-49, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1036C.
Shapiro, Leonard, and Brannock, W.W., 1957, A field method for the determination of calcium and magnesium in limestone and dolomite: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 57-99, 8 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr5799.
Shapiro, Leonard, and Brannock, W.W., 1962, Rapid analysis of silicate, carbonate and phosphate rocks, in Contributions to Geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1144-A, 56 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1144A.
Shapiro, Leonard, and Curtis, E.L., 1963, Percent-constituent printing accessory and flow-through cell for a spectrophotometer, in Geological Survey Research 1963, Short papers in geology and hydrology, Articles 60-121: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 475-C, p. C171-C174, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp475C.
Shapiro, Leonard, and Massoni, C.J., 1965, Automatic sample changer and controller for an X-ray quantometer, in Geological Survey Research 1965, Chapter D: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 525-D, p. D178-D183, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp525D.
Shapiro, Leonard, and Massoni, C.J., 1968, Automatic sample changer for atomic absorption spectrophotometry, in Geological Survey Research 1968, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 600-B, p. B126-B129, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp600B.
Shapiro, Leonard, and Massoni, C.J., 1972, An automated spectrophotometer, in Geological Survey Research, 1972, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 800-B, p. B137-B140., accessed March 21, 2016 at https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp800B.
Shapiro, Leonard, and Rosenbaum, Fred, 1962, A sequential heating device for FeO determinations, in Geological Survey Research 1962, Short papers in geology, hydrology, and topography, Articles 60-119: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 450-C, p. C102-C103, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp450C.
Shapiro, Leonard, and Toulmin, M.S., 1961, Colorometric determination of iron in small samples of sphalerite, in Geological Survey Research 1961, Short papers in the geologic and hydrologic sciences, Articles 1-146: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 424-B, p. B328-B329, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp424B.
Siems, D.F., 2000, The determination of 30 elements in geological materials by energy-dispersive X-ray fluorescence spectrometry: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 00-475, 13 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr00475.
Siems, D.F., 2002, The determination of 30 elements in geological materials by energy-dispersive X-ray fluorescence spectrometry, in Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, p. U1-U11, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-0223/U27edsfinal_U.pdf.
Simon, F.O., 1962, Spectrophotometric catalytic determination of small amounts of rhenium in mineralized rocks and molybdenite: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 62-126, 60 p.
Simon, F.O., and Rollinson, C.L., 1975, Determination of tungsten in geologic materials by neutron activation analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 3, no. 4, p. 475-478, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007409.
Simon, F.O., Campbell, E.Y., and Aruscavage, P.J., 1977, Thallium contents of 16 USGS standard rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 5, no. 5, p. 579-581, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007422.
Skeen, C.J., 1993, Analysis of Bi by chemical separation/GFAA, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Skeen, C.J., 1993, Analysis of carbon, hydrogen, and nitrogen, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Skeen, C.J., 1993, Analysis of Cl by selective ion electrode, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Skeen, C.J., 1993, Analysis of Tl by chemical separation/GFAA, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Skeen, C.J., 1996, Carbon, hydrogen, and nitrogen by a CHN elemental analyzer, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 186-190, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Skeen, C.J., and Crandell, W.B., 1989, Computerized spectrographic data for two new USGS rocks, AMH-1 and DTS-2: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 89-183, 15 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr89183.
Smith, D.B., 1993, Analysis of U by UV_fluorescence, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Smith, Hezekiah, 1993, Analysis of major elements by ICP, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Smith, Hezekiah, 1993, Analysis of platinum group elements by fire assay/GFAA, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Smith, Hezekiah, 1993, Analysis of S by combustion/IR spectroscopy, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Smith, R.L., and Pietrzyk, D.J., 1984, Liquid chromatographic separation of metal ions on a silica column: Analytical Chemistry, v. 56, iss. 4, p. 610-614, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/ac00268a005.
Starkey, H.C., Mountjoy, Wayne, and Gardner, J.M., 1977, Removal of fluorine and lithium from hectorite by solutions spanning a wide range of pH: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 5, no. 2, p. 235-237, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007419.
Stevens, R.E., 1934, Studies on the alkalinity of some silicate minerals, in Shorter contributions to general geology: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 185-A, p. 1-13, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp185A.
Stevens, R.E., and Lakin, H.W., 1949, The chromograph, a new analytical tool for laboratory and field use: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 63, 11 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir63.
Stevens, R.E., Chodos, A.A., Havens, R.G., Godijn, Elisabeth, and Neil, S.T., 1960, Combination of gravimetric and spectrographic methods in the analysis of silicates, in Geological Survey Research 1960, Short papers in the geological sciences: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 400-B, p. B499-B501, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp400B.
Stevens, R.E., Fleischer, Michael, Niles, W.W., Chodos, A.A., Filby, R.H., Leininger, R.K., Ahrens, L.H., and Flanagan, F.J.et al, 1960, Second report on a cooperative investigation of the composition of two silicate rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1113, 126 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1113.
Stevens, R.E., Wood, W. H., Goetz, K. G, and Horr, C.A., 1956, Machine for preparing phosphors for the fluorimetric determination of uranium: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 578, 22 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei578.
Stewart, K.C., 1990, Determination of water extractable boron in soil and stream-sediment samples by inductively coupled plasma-atomic emission spectroscopy, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 97-99, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Stuckless, J.S., Millard, H.T., Jr., Bunker, C.M., Nkomo, I.T., Rosholt, J.N., Bush, C.A., Huffman, Claude, Jr., and Keil, R.L., 1977, A comparison of some analytical techniques for determining uranium, thorium and potassium in granitic rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 5, no. 1, p. 83-91, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007418.
Sutton, A.L., and Christie, J.H., 1992, Organization and design of an automated laboratory information management system for the Branch of Geochemistry Research and Operational Laboratory: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 92-392, 20 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr92392.
Sutton, A.L., Havens, R.G., and Sainsbury, C.L., 1973, A spectrochemical method for determining the composition of native gold: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 1, no. 3, p. 301-308, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007396.
Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., 2002, Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-0223/.
Taggart, J.E., Jr., and Siems, D.F., 2002, Major element analysis by wavelength dispersive X-ray fluorescence spectrometry, in Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, p. T1-T9, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-223/T16WDXRF_M.pdf.
Taggart, J.E., Jr., and Wahlberg, J.S., 1980, New mold design for casting fused samples: Advances In X-ray Analysis, v. 23, p. 257-261.
Taggart, J.E., Jr., Bartel, A.J., and Siems, D.F., 1990, High precision major element analysis of rocks and minerals by wavelength dispersive X-ray fluorescence spectroscopy, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 166-172, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Taggart, J.E., Jr., Lichte, F.E., and Wahlberg, J.S., 1981, Methods of analysis of samples using X-ray fluorescence and induction coupled plasma spectroscopy, in The 1980 Eruption of Mount St. Helens, Washington: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 1250, p. 683-687, accessed August 13, 2012 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp1250.
Taggart, J.E., Jr., Lindsay, J.R., Scott, B.A., Vivit, D.V., Bartel, A.J., and Stewart, K.C., 1987, Analysis of geologic materials by wavelength-dispersive X-ray fluorescence spectrometry, in Baedecker, P.A., ed., Methods for geochemical analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1770-E, E1-E19, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1770.
Taggart, J.E., Jr., Wahlberg, J.S., and Taylor, H.E., 1980, X-ray spectrometric major-element analyses of tephra samples from the May 18, 1980 eruption of Mt. St. Helens: samples collected from Washington, Idaho, and Montana: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 80-1130, 13 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr801130.
Taylor, C.D., Theodorakos, P.M., and Peacock, T.R., 2002, Sample Preparation, in Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, p. A2-1 - A3-4, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-0223/A1RxSampPrep_M.pdf.
Taylor, H.E., 1987, Atomic spectroscopy advances: inductively coupled plasma-mass spectrometry, an introduction: Spectroscopy v. 1, no. 11, p. 20-22.
Theobald, P.K., Jr., and Thompson, C.E., 1959, Geochemical prospecting with heavy-mineral concentrates used to locate a tungsten deposit: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 411, 13 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir411.
Theobald, P.K., Jr., and Thompson, C.E., 1968, Experimental error in sample preparation and spectrographic analysis in the Jiddah laboratory, Saudi Arabia: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 68-267, 6 p.
Thomas, C.P., 1978, A minicomputer based emission spectrographic analysis system: the program: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 78-982, 427 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr78982.
Thomas, C.P., 1975, An integrated-intensity method for emission spectrographic computer analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 3, no. 2, p. 181-186, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007407.
Thomas, J.A., Mountjoy, Wayne, and Huffman, Claude, Jr., 1976, Copper, lithium, manganese, strontium, zinc, sodium, potassium, and magnesium contents of eight new USGS standard rock samples, in Flanagan, F.J., ed., 1976, Descriptions and analyses of eight new USGS rock standards: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 840, p. 119-123, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp840.
Thompson, C.E., 1967, A spectrophotometric method for the determination of traces of platinum and palladium in geologic materials, in Geological Survey Research 1967, Chapter D: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 575-D, p. D236-D238, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp575D.
Thompson, C.E., and Lakin, H.W., 1957, A field chromatographic method for determination of uranium in soils and rocks, in Contributions to Geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1036-L, p. 209-220, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1036L.
Thompson, C.E., and Lakin, H.W., 1963, Separation of tellurium from iron and gold using tributyl phosphate and ether, in Geological Survey Research 1963, Short papers in geology and hydrology, Articles 1-59: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 475-B, p. B28-B29, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp475B.
Thompson, C.E., and Nakagawa, H.N., 1960, Spectrophotometric determination of traces of lead in igneous rocks, in Contributions to Geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1084-F, p. 151-164, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1084F.
Thompson, C.E., Nakagawa, H.N., and VanSickle, G.H., 1968, Rapid analysis for gold in geologic materials, in Geological Survey Research 1968, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 600-B, p. B130-132, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp600B.
Tillman, J.H., 1977, A combustimetric method for determining the total carbon content of geologic materials: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 5, no. 5, p. 583-587, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007422.
Truesdell, A.H., and Christ, C.L., 1964, Use of sodium-sensitive glass electrodes for solubility determinations, in Geological Survey Research 1963, Short papers in geology and hydrology, Articles 122-172:  U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 475-D, p. D167-D171, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp475D.
Truesdell, A.H., Carroll, Dorothy, and Schnepfe, M.M., 1967, Bibliography of ion exchange in selectivity: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 67-221, 90 p.
U.S. Geological Survey, 1975, Geochemical survey of the western coal regions second annual progress report, July 1975: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 75-436, 132 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr75436.
VanSickle, G.H., and Lakin, H.W., 1968, An atomic-absorption method for the determination of gold in large samples of geologic materials: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 561, 4 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir561.
Vaughn, W.W., 1967, A simple mercury vapor detector for geochemical prospecting: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 540, 8 p., accessed August 13, 2012 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir540.
Vaughn, W.W., and McCarthy, J.H., Jr., 1964, An instrumental technique for the determination of submicrogram concentrations of mercury in soils, rocks and gas, in Geological Survey Research 1964, Chapter D: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 501-D, p. D123-D127, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp501D.
Vaughn, W.W., Cramer, W.G., and Sharp, W.N., 1965, Gamma activation device for low-level beryllium analysis, in Geological Survey Research 1965, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 525-B, p. B151-B154, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp525B.
Viets, J.G., 1978, Determination of silver, bismuth, cadmium, copper, lead, and zinc in geologic materials by atomic absorption spectrometry with tricaprylmethylammonium chloride: Analytical Chemistry, v. 50, iss. 8, p. 1097-1101, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/ac50030a023.
Viets, J.G., and O'Leary, R.M., 1992, The role of atomic absorption spectrometry in geochemical exploration, in Hall, G.E.M., ed., Geoanalysis: Journal of Geochemical Exploration, v. 44, p. 107-138, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0375-6742(92)90049-E.
Viets, J.G., Clark, J.R., and Campbell, W.L., 1984, A rapid, partial leach and organic separation for the sensitive determination of Ag, Bi, Cd, Cu, Mo, Pb, Sb, and Zn in surface geologic materials by flame atomic absorption: Journal of Geochemical Exploration, v. 20, p. 355-366, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0375-6742(84)90076-1.
Viets, J.G., O'Leary, R.M., and Clark, J.R., 1984, Determination of arsenic, antimony, bismuth, cadmium, copper, lead, molybdenum, silver and zinc in geological materials by atomic-absorption spectrometry: Analyst, v. 109, p. 1589-1592, accessed-  March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/AN9840901589.
Vivit, D.V., and Lindsay, J.R., 1987, X-ray spectrometric determinations of arsenic sorbed onto cellulose after solvent extraction from fused silicate rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 87-183, 9 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr87183.
Wahlberg, J.S., 1975, Analysis of rocks and soils by X-ray fluorescence, in U.S. Geological Survey, 1975, Geochemical survey of the western coal regions second annual progress report, July 1975: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 75-436, p. 69-70, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr75436.
Wahlberg, J.S., 1976, Analysis of rocks and soils by X-ray fluorescence, in Miesch, A.T., Barnett, P.R., Bartel, A.J., Dinnin, J.I., Feder, G.L., Harms, T.F., Huffman, Claude, Jr., Janzer, V.J., Millard, H.T., Jr., Neiman, H.G., Skougstad, M.W., and Wahlberg, J.S., Methods of sampling, laboratory analysis, and statistical reduction of data, in Geochemical survey of Missouri: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 954-A, p. A11-A12, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp954A.
Wahlberg, J.S., and Myers, A.T., 1968, Determination of bromine and iodine by X-ray fluorescence, in Geological Survey Research 1968, Chapter D: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 600-D, p. D214-D216, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp600D.
Wahlberg, J.S., Skinner, D.L., and Rader, L.F., Jr., 1956, Volumetric determination of uranium using titanous sulfate as reductant before oxidimetric titration: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 614, 20 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei614.
Walthall, F.G., 1974, Spectrochemical computer analysis - program description: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 2, no. 1, p. 61-71, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007400.
Walthall, F.G., and Fleming, S.L., II, 1989, Preparation of coal for analysis, in Golightly, D.W., and Simon, F.O., eds., Methods for sampling and inorganic analysis of coal: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1823, p. 15-20, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1823.
Walthall, F.G., Dorrzapf, A.F., Jr., and Flanagan,F.J., 1976, Computerized spectrographic data for USGS standards, in Flanagan, F.J., ed., 1976, Descriptions and analyses of eight new USGS rock standards: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 840, p. 99-117, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp840.
Wandless, G.A., 1987, Radiochemical neutron activation analysis of geologic materials, in Baedecker, P.A., ed., Methods for geochemical analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1770-J, J1-J8, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1770.
Wandless, G.A., 1996, Instrumental neutron activation by abbreviated count, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 211-217, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Wandless, G.A., 1996, Instrumental neutron activation by long count, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Analytical methods manual for the Mineral Resource Surveys Program, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-525, p. 218-227, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr96525.
Wandless, G.A., and Knight, R.J., 1990, Instrumental neutron activation of geologic materials by abbreviated count method, in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 151-156, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Wandless, G.A., and Morgan, J.W., 1985, Analysis of low levels of rare earths by radiochemical neutron activation analysis, I: Journal of Radioanalytical and Nuclear Chemistry, v. 92, p. 273-282, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF02219757.
Ward, F.N., 1951, Determination of molybdenum in soils and rocks: Analytical Chemistry, v. 23, no. 5, p. 788-791, accessed March 25, 2016 at DOI: 10.1021/ac60053a031.
Ward, F.N., 1951, Field method for the determination of tungsten in soils: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 119, 4 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/cir119.
Ward, F.N., 1970, Analytical methods for determination of mercury in rocks and soils, in Mercury in the Environment: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 713, p. 46-49, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp713.
Ward, F.N., and Bailey, E.H., 1960, Camp- and sample-site determination of traces of mercury in soils and rocks: American Institute of Mining Engineers Transactions, v. 217, p. 343-350.
Ward, F.N., and Crowe, H.E., 1956, Colorimetric determinations of traces of bismuth in rocks, in Contributions to Geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1036-I, p. 173-179, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1036I.
Ward, F.N., and Fishman, M.J., 1976, Determination of lead in soils and rocks, in Lead in the Environment: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 957, p. 81-84, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp957.
Ward, F.N., and Lakin, H.W., 1953, Determination of microgram quantities of antimony in soils and rocks, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Almond, Hy, Bloom, Harold, Crowe, H.E., and Marranzino, A.P., eds., Additional field methods used in geochemical prospecting by the U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 53-278, p. 3-8, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr53278.
Ward, F.N., and Lakin, H.W., 1954, Determination of traces of antimony in soils and rocks: Analytical Chemistry, v. 26, no. 7, p. 1168-1173, accessed March 25, 2016 at DOI: 10.1021/ac60091a020.
Ward, F.N., and Marranzino, A.P., 1953, Determination of microgram quantities of niobium in rocks, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Almond, Hy, Bloom, Harold, Crowe, H.E., and Marranzino, A.P., eds., Additional field methods used in geochemical prospecting by the U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 53-278, p. 34-39, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr53278.
Ward, F.N., and Marranzino, A.P., 1953, The field determination of small amounts of vanadium in rocks, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Almond, Hy, Bloom, Harold, Crowe, H.E., and Marranzino, A.P., eds., Additional field methods used in geochemical prospecting by the U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 53-278, p. 39-42, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr53278.
Ward, F.N., and Marranzino, A.P., 1955, Field determination of microgram quantities of niobium in rocks: Analytical Chemistry, v. 27, no. 8, p. 1325-1328, accessed March 25, 2016 at DOI: 10.1021/ac60104a034.
Ward, F.N., and Nakagawa, H.N., 1967, Atomic absorption determination of bismuth in altered rocks, in Geological Survey Research 1967, Chapter D: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 575-D, p. D239-D241, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp575D.
Ward, F.N., ed., 1975, New and refined methods of trace analysis useful in geochemical exploration: a collection of methods additional to those presented earlier in U.S. Geological Survey Bulletins 1152 and 1289: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1408, 105 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1408.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Almond, Hy, Bloom, Harold, Crowe, H.E., and Marranzino, A.P., eds., Additional field methods used in geochemical prospecting by the U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 53-278, 42 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr53278.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, 100 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Acid-extractable copper in soils and sediments, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 25-27, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Ammonium citrate-soluble heavy metals in soils and sediments, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 27-29, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Antimony in soils and rocks, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 38-40, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Arsenic in soils, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 40-44, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Barium in soils and rocks, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 44-45, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Chromium in soils and rocks, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 47-48, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Cobalt in soils, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 34-35, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Copper, lead, and zinc in soils and rocks, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, Hubert. W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 19-25, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Germanium in coal and rocks, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 48-51, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Iron in soils, dichromate titration method, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 54-55, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Iron in soils, orthophenanthroline method, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 52-54, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Manganese in soils and rocks, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 55-57, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Molybdenum in soils and rocks, acid digestion method, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 61-63, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Molybdenum in soils and rocks, carbonate fusion method, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 59-61, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Nickel in soils, rocks, and plants, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 37-38, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Niobium in rocks, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 65-66, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Paper-chromatographic method for traces of copper, cobalt, and nickel in soils, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 31-34, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Phosphorus in soils and rocks, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 66-68, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Selenium in highly seleniferous materials, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 68-72, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Small quantities of tin in soils and rock, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 74-76, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Spectrographic analysis for use in geochemical exploration, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 91-94, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Titanium in rocks, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 76-78, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Traces of bismuth in rocks, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 45-47, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Traces of mercury in soils and rocks--camp- and sample-site determination, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 57-59, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Tungsten in soils, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 78-79, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Uranium in soils and rocks, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 79-82, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Vanadium in rocks, thiocyanate method, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, Hubert. W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 89-91, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., Thompson, C.E., Oda, Uteana, McCarthy, J.H., Jr., Marranzino, A.P., and Markward, E.L., 1963, Vanadium in soils and rocks, phosphotungstate method, in Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., et al, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: a compilation of trace and semimicroanalytical methods of yielding semiquantitative data on geologic materials useful in geochemical prospecting for ore deposits: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, p. 87-89, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1152.
Ward, F.N., Nakagawa, H.N., Harms, T.F., and VanSickle, G.H., 1969, Atomic-absorption methods of analysis useful in geochemical exploration: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1289, 45 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1289.
Ward, F.N., Nakagawa, H.N., Harms, T.F., and VanSickle, G.H., 1969, Atomic-absorption determinations of the constituents--calcium in rocks, soils, and plant ash, and lithium, potassium, and sodium in rocks and soils, in Ward, F.N., Nakagawa, H.N., Harms, T.F., and VanSickle, G.H., 1969, Atomic-absorption methods of analysis useful in geochemical exploration: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1289, p. 25-33, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1289.
Ward, F.N., Nakagawa, H.N., Harms, T.F., and VanSickle, G.H., 1969, Atomic-absorption determinations of the constituents--gold and tellurium in rocks and soils, in Ward, F.N., Nakagawa, H.N., Harms, T.F., and VanSickle, G.H., 1969, Atomic-absorption methods of analysis useful in geochemical exploration: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1289, p. 33-41, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1289.
Ward, F.N., Nakagawa, H.N., Harms, T.F., and VanSickle, G.H., 1969, Atomic-absorption determinations of the constituents--mercury in rocks and soils, in Ward, F.N., Nakagawa, H.N., Harms, T.F., and VanSickle, G.H., 1969, Atomic-absorption methods of analysis useful in geochemical exploration: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1289, p. 41-42, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1289.
Ward, F.N., Nakagawa, H.N., Harms, T.F., and VanSickle, G.H., 1969, Atomic-absorption determinations of the constituents--silver, bismuth, cadmium, lead, copper, zinc, cobalt, and nickel in rocks and soils, in Ward, F.N., Nakagawa, H.N., Harms, T.F., and VanSickle, G.H., 1969, Atomic-absorption methods of analysis useful in geochemical exploration: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1289, p. 9-25, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1289.
Waring, C.L., 1964, Determination of hafnium content and Hf/Zr ratios in zircon with the direct-reading emission spectrometer, in Geological Survey Research 1964, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 501-B, p. B146-B147, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp501B.
Waring, C.L., and Annell, C.S., 1951, A semiquantitative spectrographic method for the analysis of minerals, rocks, and ores: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 143, 23 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei143.
Waring, C.L., and Annell, C.S., 1952, A semiquantitative spectrographic method for the analysis of minerals, rocks, and ores, II: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 215, 32 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei215.
Waring, C.L., and Conklin, N.M., 1966, Quantitative spectrochemical determination of minor elements in apatite, in Geological Survey Research 1966, Chapter C: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 550-C, p. C228-C230, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp550C.
Waring, C.L., and Mela, Henry, Jr., 1952, The determination of small amounts of rare earths in phosphate rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 239, 20 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei239.
Waring, C.L., and Worthing, H.W., 1952, A spectrographic method for determining trace amounts of lead in zircon and other minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 216, 15 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei216.
Waring, C.L., and Worthing, H.W., 1955, A spectrographic method for determining the hafnium-zirconium ratio in zircon: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 502, 15 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei502.
Waring, C.L., and Worthing, H.W., 1956, A spectrographic method for determining the hafnium-zirconium ratio in zircon, in Contributions to Geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1036-F, p. 81-90, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1036F.
Waring, C.L., Franck, M.L. and Sherwood, A.M., 1954, An application of spectrographic microphotometric scanning: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 444, 29 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei444.
Waring, C.L., Franck, M.L., and Sherwood, A.M., 1956, An application of spectrographic microphotometric scanning, in Contributions to Geochemistry: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1036-E, p. 69-80, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1036E.
Waring, C.L., Worthing, H.W., and Hazel, K.V., 1957, A spectrochemical method for the determination of selenium: U.S. Geological Survey Trace Elements Investigations Report 687, 16 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tei687.
Warr, J.J., Jr., and Cuttitta, Frank, 1960, The determination of lead in iron-bearing materials, in Geological Survey Research 1960 Short papers in the geological sciences: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 400-B, p. B483-B484, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp400B.
Watterson, J.R., 1976, Determination of tellurium and gold in rocks to 1 part per billion: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 76-531, 3 p.
Watterson, J.R., and Neuerburg, G.J., 1975, Analysis for tellurium in rocks to 5 parts per billion: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 3, no. 2, p. 191-195, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007407.
Watterson, J.R., Ficklin, W.H., and Turner, J.H., 1976, A modification of Shapiro's technique for determining low levels of CO2 in silicate rocks: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 76-530, 5 p.
Welsch, E.P., 1979, Determination of arsenic in geologic materials using silver diethyldithiocarbamate: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 79-1442, 10 p.
Welsch, E.P., 1983, A rapid geochemical spectrophotometric determination of tungsten with dithiol: Talanta, v. 30, iss. 11, p. 876-878, accessed March 28, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0039-9140(83)80203-3.
Welsch, E.P., 1993, Analysis of Au, Te and Tl by chemical separation/FAA, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Welsch, E.P., 1993, Analysis of W by UV-Vis spectrophometry, in Doughten, M.W., and Grossman, J.N., eds., Method descriptions and bibliography of routine work performed by the Branch of Geochemistry analytical laboratories, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-1-B, 16 p., accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr931B.
Welsch, E.P., and Chao, T.T., 1975, Determination of trace amounts of antimony in geological materials by atomic absorption spectrometry: Analytica Chimica Acta, v. 76, p. 65-69, accessed March 25, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0003-2670(01)81985-1.
Welsch, E.P., and Chao, T.T., 1976, Determination of trace amounts of tin in geological materials by atomic-absorption spectrometry: Analytica Chimica Acta, v. 82, p. 337-342, accessed March 25, 2016 at doi:10.1016/S0003-2670(01)84611-0.
Welsch, E.P., Crock, J.G., and Sanzolone, R.F., 1990, Trace-level determination of arsenic and selenium using continuous-flow hydride generation atomic absorption spectrophotometry (HG-AAS), in Arbogast, B.F., ed., Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 38-45, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr90668.
Wilson, E.E., and Stacey, J.S., 1969, A transistorized emission regulator for gas-source mass spectrometry, in Geological Survey Research 1969, Chapter B: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 650-B, p. B143-B146, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp650B.
Wilson, S.A., 1993, Assessment of chemical variability in three independently prepared batches of National Institute for Standards and Technology SRM 2704, Buffalo River Sediment: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 93-692, 23 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr93692.
Wilson, S.A., and Herron, Matt, 2002, Dry moist samples to constant weight under ambient conditions, calculate % moisture, in Taggart, J.E., Jr., ed., Analytical methods for chemical analysis of geologic and other materials, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 02-223, p. C1-C3, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-0223/C18QCMoist_M.pdf.
Wilson, S.A., Briggs, P.H., Mee, J.S., Hageman, P.L., Siems, D.F., Malcolm, M.J., and Curry, K.J., 1995, The Physical preparation and chemical analysis of NIST SRMs 2786 and 2787, lead paint in soil: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 95-486, 24 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr95486.
Wilson, S.A., Briggs, P.H., Brown, Zoe Ann, Taggart, J.E., Jr., and Knight, R.J., 1999, Collection, preparation and testing of NIST hard rock mine waste reference material SRM 2780: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 99-370, 15 p., accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr99370.
Wilson, S.A., Kane, J.S., Crock, J.G., and Hatfield, D.B., 1987, Chemical methods of separation for optical emission, atomic absorption spectrometry, and colorimetry, in Baedecker, P.A., ed., Methods for geochemical analysis: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1770-D, D1-D14, accessed March 21, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1770.
Zhou, Liyi, Chao, T.T., and Meier, A.L., 1984, Determination of total tin in geological materials by electrothermal atomic-absorption spectrophotometry using a tungsten-impregnated graphite furnace: Talanta, v. 31, iss. 1, p. 73-76, accessed March 28, 2016 at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0039-9140(84)80014-4.
Zielinski, R.A., 1975, Radiochemical determination of very low concentrations of nickel in rocks and minerals: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 3, no. 4, p. 467-474, accessed March 22, 2016 at http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/70007409.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Consistent spatial reference among all samples was required to enable accurate spatial integration of the geochemical data. The USGS datasets contained geographic coordinates that were referenced to various geodetic datums, including the North American Datum of 1927 (NAD 27), the North American Datum of 1983 (NAD 83), and the World Geodetic System of 1984 (WGS 84) whereas the NURE-HSSR and ADGGS data coordinates are all referenced to NAD 27. WGS 84, which is nearly identical to NAD 83, was chosen as the common datum for all data in this study because it has become the most widely used for online map information, new GIS data, and is the default datum for GPS instruments. The coordinate calculator function in ERDAS Imagine 2015 software (Hexagon Geospatial, 2014) was used to transform the geographic coordinates of all sample localities to WGS 84 and those new coordinates were added to the NURE-HSSR, ADGGS, and USGS sediment and soil sample datasets.
All geographic coordinates of GIS-formatted (geodatabase and shapefile) sample data were also transformed into the Alaska Albers Equal Area Conic projection. This was done-  to facilitate spatial distribution modeling of element concentrations and to improve interoperability with other data layers inasmuch as the Alaska Albers Equal Area Conic projection is the projection standard adopted by many State and Federal agencies in Alaska for ease of data integration.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>1. Alaska geochemical data for 175,856 samples were compiled from USGS, ADGGS, and NURE-HSSR databases. These data included best value distillations of analyses of 92,694 USGS sediment samples, 6,869 USGS soil samples, and 10,996 ADGGS sediment samples, plus analyses of 65,397 NURE sediment samples. Each of the 4 datasets was assembled in separate spreadsheets.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20150301</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>2. Consistent spatial reference among all samples was needed for accurate spatial integration of the geochemical data. The 4 geochemical datasets contain geographic coordinates (latitude-longitude) that are referenced to various datums; all were converted to the WGS 84 datum reference system. Subsequently, to facilitate spatial analyses, all geographic coordinates were transformed to the Alaska Albers Equal Area Conic projection.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20150301</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>3. All best value data for 68 elements in 175,856 samples were combined and have been provided as (1) Excel spreadsheet, (2) GIS shapefile, and (3) ESRI geodatabase.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20150301</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>4. The ArcGIS Spatial Join tool was used to create HUC-based
element distribution models. The join operation was performed
for the overlay of the 12-digit HUC (subwatershed) polygons
and the combined sediment data that had had censored values
replaced by estimates. The optional merge rule of mean was
used to calculate and associate (as attributes) mean
concentrations of all sediment sample determinations that were
found within the subwatershed boundaries.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20150301</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>G-polygon</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>13988</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>AK Albers WGS84 (ESRI Full Name: AK_Albers_WGS84)</mapprojn>
          <albers>
            <stdparll>55.0</stdparll>
            <stdparll>65.0</stdparll>
            <longcm>-154.0</longcm>
            <latprjo>50.0</latprjo>
            <feast>0.0</feast>
            <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
          </albers>
        </mapproj>
        <planci>
          <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>0.6096</absres>
            <ordres>0.6096</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>Meter</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D_WGS_1984</horizdn>
        <ellips>WGS_1984</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>1</rdommin>
            <rdommax>13988</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>sample_sit</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Number of sample sites found within a unique 12-digit HUC boundary.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1709</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>AreaAcres</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The area of each hydrologic unit including non-contributing areas stored in acres AreaAcres is common to all polygon feature classes and is calculated at the 12-digit hydrologic unit from the intrinsic area value maintained by the GIS software; therefore, acreage values may vary from user calculations, depending on the projection of the data. North American Albers Equal Area Conic, North American Datum 1983 is the required projection to use for calculation. If the units of the area field are stored in square meters, then use the conversion factor 0.0002471. For example, 40,469,446 square meters multiplied by 0.0002471 =10,000 acres</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Federal Standards and Procedures for the National Watershed Boundary Dataset (WBD)</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>386.40140649</rdommin>
            <rdommax>6230451.2563</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>AreaSqKm</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The area of each hydrologic unit including non-contributing areas stored in square kilometers. AreaSqKm is calculated at the 12-digit hydrologic unit from the intrinsic area value maintained by the GIS software; therefore, the square kilometer values may vary from user calculations, depending on the projection of the data. North American Albers Equal Area Conic, North American Datum 1983 is the default projection.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Federal Standards and Procedures for the National Watershed Boundary Dataset (WBD)</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>1.56371101</rdommin>
            <rdommax>25213.741681</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>HUC12</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The HUC12 field is a unique 12-digit hydrologic unit code. HUC12 represents the 12-digit hydrologic unit boundaries (previously referred to as Subwatersheds).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Federal Standards and Procedures for the National Watershed Boundary Dataset (WBD)</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>The HUC12 field is a unique 12-digit hydrologic unit code. HUC12 represents the 12-digit hydrologic unit boundaries (previously referred to as Subwatersheds). For Example: 10190020904</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Name</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Name refers to the GNIS name for the geographic area in which the hydrologic unit is located. Populated using GNIS names and guidelines as outlined in the WBD Standards.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Federal Standards and Procedures for the National Watershed Boundary Dataset (WBD)</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Name refers to the GNIS name for the geographic area in which the hydrologic unit is located. Populated using GNIS names and guidelines as outlined in the WBD Standards. For Example: Upper Blue River</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Ag_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Silver in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>162.731664286</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Al_pc</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Aluminum in mass percent for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>15.28</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in mass percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_As_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Arsenic in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>5000</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Au_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Gold in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>911.197491648</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_B_ppm</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Boron in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2000</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Ba_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Barium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>139789.638553</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Be_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Beryllium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>31.3350366667</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Bi_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Bismuth in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>116.8425</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_C_pct</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Carbon in mass percent for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>19.8235294118</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in mass percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Ca_pc</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Calcium in mass percent for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>33.17</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in mass percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Cd_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Cadmium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>230.452480786</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Ce_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Cerium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2475.37837838</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Cl_pc</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Chlorine in mass percent for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1.56197625</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in mass percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Co_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Cobalt in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>134.6</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Cr_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Chromium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>5000.11111</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Cs_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Caesium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>52.5625</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Cu_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Copper in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>5000</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Dy_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Dysprosium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>98.6</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Er_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Erbium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>40.5</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Eu_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Europium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>43</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_F_pct</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Fluorine in mass percent for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>0.515</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in mass percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Fe_pc</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Iron in mass percent for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>21.680555</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in mass percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Ga_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Gallium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>138.857142857</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Gd_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Gadolinium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>126</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Ge_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Germanium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>15</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Hf_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Hafnium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>104.317117117</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Hg_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Mercury in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>502.297732055</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Ho_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Holmium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>25</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_In_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Indium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>0.9175</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_K_pct</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Potassium in mass percent for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>6.8273</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in mass percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_La_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Lanthanum in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2104.50490142</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Li_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Lithium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>159</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Lu_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Lutetium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>13.2504504505</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Mg_pc</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Magnesiumin mass percent for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>12.3166666667</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in mass percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Mn_pc</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Manganese in mass percent for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1.3028</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in mass percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Mo_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Molybdenum in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>300.44055</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Na_pc</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Sodium in mass percent for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>4.8456</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in mass percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Nb_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Niobium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>450</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Nd_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Neodymium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1010</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Ni_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Nickel in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1884.125</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_P_pct</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Phosphorus in mass percent for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1.745</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in mass percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Pb_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Lead in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>4970.73015857</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Pd_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Palladium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>7.64810352941</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Pr_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Praseodymium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>179</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Pt_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Platinum in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>0.2652555</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Rb_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Rubidium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>337</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_S_pct</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Sulfur in mass percent for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>19.35</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in mass percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Sb_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Antimony in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1893.1746</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Sc_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Scandium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>116.242105263</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Se_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Selenium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>39.65</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Si_pc</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Silicon in mass percent for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>35.9</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in mass percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Sm_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Samarium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>185.441000901</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Sn_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Tin in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>13636.5701923</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Sr_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Strontium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Ta_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Tantalum in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>85.1334367816</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Tb_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Terbium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>21</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Te_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Tellurium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>111.215944444</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Th_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Thorium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>954.599432624</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Ti_pc</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Titanium in mass percent for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1.94285714286</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in mass percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Tl_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Thallium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>5.05419315385</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Tm_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Thullium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>4.13</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_U_ppm</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Uranium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>172.1</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_V_ppm</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Vanadium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>3742</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_W_ppm</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Tungsten in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1086.27870504</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Y_ppm</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Yttrium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>300</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Yb_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Ytterbium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>76.0774774775</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Zn_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Zinc in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>5080.05793</rdommax>
            <attrunit>concentration mean in parts per million by mass</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mean_Zr_pp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Concentration means of Zirconium in parts per million by mass for Watershed Boundary Dataset 12 Digit hydrologic units.  Where no data are available, a value of -9999 is provided.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Metadata author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2372.75</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape_Leng</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Unknown</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>139.544466094</rdommin>
            <rdommax>3567042.00657</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape_Area</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Unknown</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.000247968716502</rdommin>
            <rdommax>3.30784550678</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <overview>
      <eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes the tabular data associated with the data set. Please review the detailed descriptions that are provided (the individual attribute descriptions) for information on the values that appear as fields/table entries of the data set.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>The entity and attribute information was generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Please review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>USGS Information Services</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <address>USGS Information Services</address>
          <address>Box 25286</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225-0046</postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-ASK_USGS (1-888-275-8747)</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>U.S. Geological Survey Data Release for DS 908</resdesc>
    <distliab>This database, identified as DS 908, has been approved for release
and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS).  Although this
database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially
complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant
to further analysis and review. Furthermore, it is released on
condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held
liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized
use.
Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer
system at the USGS, no warranty expressed or implied is made
regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system,
or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of
distribution constitute any such warranty.  The USGS shall not be
held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described
and/or contained herein.
Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive
purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.
Although this information product, for the most part, is in the
public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in
the text.  Permission to reproduce copyrighted items for other
than personal use must be secured from the copyright owner.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Vector Digital Data Set (Polygon)</formname>
          <formvern>Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1 (Build 4959) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</formvern>
          <formspec>ESRI Point Shapefile, ESRI Polygon Shapefile</formspec>
          <formcont>ESRI Point Shapefile:Seven files (AK_geochem_data.dbf, AK_geochem_data.prj, AK_geochem_data.sbn, AK_geochem_data.sbx, AK_geochem_data.shp, AK_geochem_data.xml, AK_geochem_data.shx) comprise the AK_geochem_data shapefile.  ESRI Polygon Shapefile: Seven files (AK_WBD_means.dbf, AK_WBD_means.prj, AK_WBD_means.sbn, AK_WBD_means.sbx, AK_WBD_means.shp, AK_WBD_means.xml, AK_WBD_means.shx) comprise the AK_WBD_means shapefile.</formcont>
          <transize>131.5</transize>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7GF0RK5</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
            <accinstr>The digitial files can be accessed from USGS ScienceBase at the URL above.</accinstr>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S.Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
          <address>USGS Information Services</address>
          <address>Box 25286</address>
          <address>Denver Federal Center</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-ASK_USGS (1-888-275-8747)</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>http://answers.usgs.gov</cntemail>
        <cntemail>http://store.usgs.gov/</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 908</resdesc>
    <distliab>This database, identified as DS 908, has been approved for release
and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS).  Although this
database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially
complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant
to further analysis and review. Furthermore, it is released on
condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held
liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized
use.
Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer
system at the USGS, no warranty expressed or implied is made
regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system,
or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of
distribution constitute any such warranty.  The USGS shall not be
held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described
and/or contained herein.
Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive
purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.
Although this information product, for the most part, is in the
public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in
the text.  Permission to reproduce copyrighted items for other
than personal use must be secured from the copyright owner.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <nondig>Available as two dual layer DVDs.
Order from USGS at address above or see the USGS Store at
&lt;http://store.usgs.gov/mod/order.html&gt; for more ordering information.</nondig>
      <fees>For current charges please see website http://store.usgs.gov/</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160615</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Paul Denning</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Southwest Region</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Physical Science Technician</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>Mail Stop 973, W 6th Ave Kipling St</address>
          <city>Lakewood</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>303-236-1222</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pdenning@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>