<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Deborah Bergfeld</origin>
        <origin>Tina Neal</origin>
        <origin>Game McGimsey</origin>
        <origin>Cindy Werner</origin>
        <origin>Chris Waythomas</origin>
        <origin>Jen Lewicki</origin>
        <origin>Taryn Lopez</origin>
        <origin>Maggie Mangan</origin>
        <origin>Tom Miller</origin>
        <origin>Angie Diefenbach</origin>
        <origin>Janet Schaefer</origin>
        <origin>Michelle Coombs</origin>
        <origin>Bronwen Wang</origin>
        <origin>Kirsten Nicolaysen</origin>
        <origin>Pavel Izbekov</origin>
        <origin>Zebulon Maharrey</origin>
        <origin>Mark Huebner</origin>
        <origin>Andy Hunt</origin>
        <origin>John Fitzpatrick</origin>
        <origin>Gary Freeburg</origin>
        <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
        <title>Aleutian Arc geothermal fluids: chemical analyses of waters and gases (2015)</title>
        <geoform>Excel Table</geoform>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F74X55VB</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This report contains the chemical and isotopic data from thermal waters and gases collected from the Aleutian Arc over the past 20 years, where such data remain unpublished or only published in part.</abstract>
      <purpose>The data were collected for purposes such as constraining the strength of magmatic degassing, evaluating geothermal resources, or simply establishing baseline hydrologic conditions at remote volcanoes that are seldom visited.</purpose>
      <supplinfo>It is likely that most location information is referenced to WGS 84, but we cannot verify this.</supplinfo>    
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>1995</begdate>
          <enddate>present</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>publication date</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>In work</progress>
      <update>as needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Aleutian Arc AK</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>177.0</westbc>
        <eastbc>-152.0</eastbc>
        <northbc>61.4</northbc>
        <southbc>51.4</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Geochemistry</themekey>
        <themekey>Volcanology</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>Aleutian Islands</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None.</accconst>
    <useconst>Please recognize the U.S. Geological Survey as the source of this information.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Deborah Bergfeld</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>345 Middlefield Rd.</address>
          <city>Menlo Park</city>
          <state>California</state>
          <postal>94025</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>650-329-4657</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>dbergfel@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>State of Alaska Division of Geological and Geophysical Surveys, University of Alaska Geophysical Institute, National Science Foundation, Whitman College</datacred>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Bergfeld, D.</origin>
            <origin>Lewicki, J.L.</origin>
            <origin>Evans, W.C.</origin>
            <origin>Hunt, A.G.</origin>
            <origin>Revesz, K.</origin>
            <origin>Huebner, M.</origin>
            <pubdate>2013</pubdate>
            <title>Geochemical investigation of the hydrothermal system on Akutan Island, Alaska, July 2012</title>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Report</sername>
              <issue>2013-5231</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sir/2013/5231/pdf/sir2013-5231.pdf</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>online</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
              <caldate>2013</caldate>
            </sngdate>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Bergfeld, 2013</srccitea>
        <srccontr>collection and analytical protocols</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Hunt, A.G.</origin>
            <origin>Stern, L.</origin>
            <origin>Pohlman, J.W.</origin>
            <origin>Ruppel, C.</origin>
            <origin>Moscati, R.J.</origin>
            <origin>Landis, G.P.</origin>
            <pubdate>2013</pubdate>
            <title>Mass fractionation of noble gases in synthetic methane hydrate: Implications for naturally occurring gas hydrate dissociation</title>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>Chemical Geology</sername>
              <issue>339</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>unknown</pubplace>
              <publish>Elsevier</publish>
            </pubinfo>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>paper</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
              <caldate>2013</caldate>
            </sngdate>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Hunt, 2013</srccitea>
        <srccontr>collection and analytical protocols</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Lamothe, P.J.</origin>
            <origin>Meier, A.L.</origin>
            <origin>Wilson, S.</origin>
            <pubdate>1999</pubdate>
            <title>The determination of forty four elements in aqueous samples by inductively coupled plasma - mass spectrometry</title>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
              <issue>99-151</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>paper</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
              <caldate>1999</caldate>
            </sngdate>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Lamothe, 1999</srccitea>
        <srccontr>collection and analytical protocols</srccontr>
      </srcinfo> 
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Revesz, K.</origin>
            <origin>Coplen, T. B.</origin>
            <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of the delta (2H/1H) of water: RSIL lab code 1574</title>
            <onlink>http://pubs.water.usgs.gov/tm10C1/</onlink>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <lworkcit>
              <citeinfo>
                <origin>Revesz, K.</origin>
                <origin>Coplen, T.B.</origin>
                <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                <title>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods 10-C1</title>
                <pubinfo>
                  <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
                  <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                </pubinfo>
              </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>paper</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
              <caldate>2008</caldate>
            </sngdate>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Revesz, 2008a</srccitea>
        <srccontr>collection and analytical protocols</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Revesz, K.</origin>
            <origin>Coplen, T. B.</origin>
            <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of the delta (18O/16O) of water: RSIL lab code 489</title>
            <onlink>http://pubs.water.usgs.gov/tm10C2</onlink>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <lworkcit>
              <citeinfo>
                <origin>Revesz, K.</origin>
                <origin>Coplen, T.B.</origin>
                <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                <title>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods 10-C1</title>
                <pubinfo>
                  <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
                  <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                </pubinfo>
              </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>paper</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
              <caldate>2008</caldate>
            </sngdate>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Revesz, 2008b</srccitea>
        <srccontr>collection and analytical protocols</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Gas samples discussed herein were collected in evacuated glass sample bottles without added caustic.  Bubbling gases were collected from springs using an inverted funnel and water displacement.  Fumarole gases were collected through a metal tube into a T-handle glass bottle with a downstream pinch clamp.  Samples for dissolved inorganic carbon (DIC) and its isotopes were collected by injecting water into a septum-equipped evacuated glass bottle using a syringe.  Helium isotope samples were collected in copper tubes sealed with refrigeration clamps.</procdesc>
        <srcused>Bergfeld, 2013</srcused>
        <procdate>unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Some water samples were collected according to established field protocols, including: on-site measurement of pH; filtration of water for chemical analysis through 0.45 mu-m membrane filters; acidification of cation samples; collection of isotope and alkalinity samples in tightly sealed glass bottles.  However, for many of the water samples, field measurements were minimal and consist of temperature and location, and only raw (unfiltered) water samples were collected.  Unless otherwise specified, the pH, specific conductance, and alkalinity values presented in the tables are laboratory measurements, and filtration as needed prior to chemical analysis was performed in the laboratory.  Lack of field processing probably has minimal negative impact on conservative species like Na, Cl and most major ions, but trace and redox-sensitive species like Fe or nutrients like NO3 and PO4 may have large uncertainties.  A few raw, acidified samples were collected, which can greatly influence the concentrations of many of the metal species.</procdesc>
        <srcused>Bergfeld, 2013</srcused>
        <procdate>unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Chemical analyses of gas and water samples were carried out at USGS laboratories in Menlo Park, California. Gases were analyzed by using gas chromatographs equipped with a thermal-conductivity detector. Water samples were analyzed for anions by ion chromatography except for HCO3, which was analyzed by titration and should be considered as total alkalinity as HCO3 in all tables attached to this report.  Cations were analyzed by argon plasma optical-emission spectrometry, and the results given in mg/L and g/L. </procdesc>
        <srcused>Bergfeld, 2013</srcused>
        <procdate>unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>For some samples, major cation and trace element concentrations were determined at the USGS Minerals Program laboratories in Denver, Colorado, by inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry (ICP-MS).  These results are usually given in ppm and ppb.  Analytical results presented herein preserve the units of the reporting laboratory. </procdesc>
        <srcused>Lamothe, 1999</srcused>
        <procdate>unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>For low salinity waters, mg/L nearly equals ppm, and g/L nearly equals ppb.  Stable isotope analyses of waters, steam, DIC, CO2, and CH4 were performed by mass spectrometry at the USGS Stable Isotope Laboratory in Reston, Virginia.</procdesc>
        <srcused>Revesz, 2008a</srcused>
        <srcused>Revesz, 2008b</srcused>
        <procdate>unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Noble-gas ratios were determined by mass spectrometry at the USGS Noble Gas Laboratory in Denver, Colorado. Reported 3He/4He ratios are corrected for air contamination and are given as RC/RA values, where RA is the 3He/4He ratio in air.</procdesc>
        <srcused>Hunt, 2013</srcused>
        <procdate>unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>GNIS placenames</indspref>
    <direct>Point</direct>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Explanation of data entries by individual column (9999 means no data; 8888 means that result was below detection limit):&#xD;
Name of volcano, volcanic center, or island where sampling occurred&#xD;
Sample number assigned by collector&#xD;
Brief description of feature sampled&#xD;
Type of fluid sampled; water, gas, or both&#xD;
Date of sampling&#xD;
Latitude in decimal degrees (WGS 84 datum for samples collected after 1990)&#xD;
Longitude in decimal degrees (WGS 84 datum for samples collected after 1990)&#xD;
Elevation of sample site in meters above sea level&#xD;
Temperature of feature in degrees Celsius&#xD;
Specific conductance of water in microSeimens/cm referenced to 25 degrees Celsius&#xD;
pH of water&#xD;
Location of pH measurement: in the field (on-site); in the lab (stored sample); or at a location described in the reference (for published values)&#xD;
Location of USGS laboratory performing anion analysis: Menlo (Park); Denver; or at a location described in the reference (for published values)&#xD;
F concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Cl concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
SO4 concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Br concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
NO3 concentration in water in milligrams per liter as N&#xD;
PO4 concentration in water in milligrams per liter as P&#xD;
Alkalinity concentration in water in milligrams per liter HCO3&#xD;
Cation sample type: FA is filtered acidified; RA is raw acidified; or as described in the reference (for published values)&#xD;
Location of USGS laboratory performing cation analysis: Menlo (Park); Denver; or at a location described in the reference (for published values)&#xD;
Al concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
As concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
B concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Ba concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Ca concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Cd concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Co concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Cr concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Cs concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Cu concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Fe concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
K concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Li concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Mg concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Mn concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Mo concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Na concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
NH3 concentration in water in milligrams per liter as N&#xD;
Ni concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Pb concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Rb concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Se concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
SiO2 concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Sr concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Ti concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
U concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
V concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Zn concentration in water in milligrams per liter&#xD;
Ag concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Be concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Bi concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Ce concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Dy concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Er concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Eu concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Ga concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Gd concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Ge concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Ho concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
La concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Lu concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Nb concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Nd concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Pr concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Sb concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Sc concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Sm concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Ta concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Tb concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Th concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Tl concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Tm concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
W concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Y concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Yb concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Zr concentration in water in micrograms per liter&#xD;
Dissolved inorganic carbon concentration in water in millimoles/kilogram&#xD;
Ratio of oxygen-18 to oxygen-16 isotopes of water (or fumarolic steam) in standard delta notation&#xD;
Ratio of deuterium to protium isotopes of water (or fumarolic steam) in standard delta notation&#xD;
Ratio of carbon-13 to carbon-12 isotopes of DIC in water in standard delta notation&#xD;
Carbon-14 concentration in DIC in fraction modern carbon&#xD;
He concentration in gas (exclusive of water vapor) in volume-percent&#xD;
H2 concentration in gas (exclusive of water vapor) in volume-percent&#xD;
Ar concentration in gas (exclusive of water vapor) in volume-percent&#xD;
O2 concentration in gas (exclusive of water vapor) in volume-percent&#xD;
N2 concentration in gas (exclusive of water vapor) in volume-percent&#xD;
CH4 concentration in gas (exclusive of water vapor) in volume-percent&#xD;
CO2 concentration in gas (exclusive of water vapor) in volume-percent&#xD;
C2H6 concentration in gas (exclusive of water vapor) in volume-percent&#xD;
H2S concentration in gas (exclusive of water vapor) in volume-percent&#xD;
CO concentration in gas (exclusive of water vapor) in volume-percent&#xD;
C3H8 concentration in gas (exclusive of water vapor) in volume-percent&#xD;
C4H10 concentration in gas (exclusive of water vapor) in volume-percent&#xD;
SO2 concentration in gas (exclusive of water vapor) in volume-percent&#xD;
Sum of measured gas concentrations (exclusive of water vapor) in volume-percent&#xD;
Molar ratio of gas/steam in fumarole samples&#xD;
Molar N2/Ar ratio in gas&#xD;
Molar N2/Ar ratio in gas after correcting for air contamination&#xD;
Molar N2/O2 ratio in gas&#xD;
Ratio of carbon-13 to carbon-12 isotopes of CO2 in gas in standard delta notation&#xD;
Ratio of carbon-13 to carbon-12 isotopes of CH4 in gas in standard delta notation&#xD;
Carbon-14 concentration in CO2 gas in fraction modern carbon&#xD;
Ratio of helium-3 to helium-4 isotopes in gas or water corrected for air contamination and presented in standard Rc/Ra notation&#xD;
Ratio of Argon-40 to Argon-36 isotopes in gas or water&#xD;
Reference citation for published values and methods</eaover>
      <eadetcit>Hem, J. D., 1985, Study and interpretation of the chemical characteristics of natural water: U.S. Geological Survey Water Supply Paper 2254, 263 p.</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150624</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>William Evans</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Chemist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>345 Middlefield Rd.</address>
          <city>Menlo Park</city>
          <state>California</state>
          <postal>94025</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>650-329-4514</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>wcevans@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>

