<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Jeffrey W. Riley</origin>
        <pubdate>20160630</pubdate>
        <title>All sites shorelines</title>
        <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7Z60M4M</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This dataset represents the shoreline positions that were surveyed at the beginning and end of a one year study of erosion along the back barrier (western shoreline) of Cumberland Island National Seashore (CUIS). Additionally, this dataset also contains projected shoreline positions for the year 2050 and 2100 derived from erosion rates observed in this study and the R package - Analysis of Moving Boundaries Using R (AMBUR). To determine shoreline positions, points were surveyed along the edge of the margin scarp using either a Trimble R8 Real-Time Kinematic Global Positioning System (RTK GPS) unit, a Trimble S6 total station, or both. Points were then converted to a polyline feature to represent the position and configuration of the selected sites shoreline. The goal of this exercise was to estimate the net amount of retreat which could be compared to other methods that were being used in this study.</abstract>
      <purpose>Much research has been conducted to better understand erosion and accretion processes for the seaward zones of coastal barrier islands; however, at Cumberland Island National Seashore, Georgia, the greater management concern is the effect that erosion is having on the resources of the island’s western shoreline, or the back barrier.  Catastrophic slumping and regular rates of erosion greater than 1 meter per year threaten important habitat, historical and pre-historical resources, and modern infrastructure on the island.  Prior research has helped National Park Service (NPS) staff identify the most severe and vulnerable areas, but in order to develop effective management actions, information is needed on what forces and conditions cause erosion. To this end, the U.S. Geological Survey, in cooperation with the NPS, conducted two longitudinal surveys, one each at the beginning and end of the approximately year-long monitoring period from late 2011 to early 2013, along five selected segments of the back barrier of the Cumberland Island National Seashore. Monitoring stations were constructed at four of these locations that had previously been identified as erosional hotspots. The magnitude of erosion at each location was quantified to determine the relative influence of causative agents. Results indicate that erosion is, in general, highly variable within and among these segments of the Cumberland Island National Seashore’s back barrier. Observed erosion ranged from a maximum of 2.5 meters of bluff-line retreat to some areas that exhibited no net erosion over the 1-year study period. In terms of timing of erosion, three of the four sites were primarily affected by punctuated erosional events that were coincident with above-average high tides and elevated wind speeds. The fourth site exhibited steady, low-magnitude retreat throughout the study period. While it is difficult to precisely subscribe certain amounts of erosion to specific agents, this study provides insight into the mode of erosion among sites and the interaction among factors that set up conditions that may be leading to punctuated events. 
Estimates of sea-level rise were incorporated into the results of this study to project conditions that could be in place by the end of the 21st century. When using the erosion rates observed in this study to extrapolate future shoreline position, results indicate an average retreat (across all monitored locations) of 15 meters by 2050 and approximately 37 meters by 2100.
</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20111207</begdate>
          <enddate>20130213</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Data represent the shoreline positions at the beginning and end of an approximately one year study. Rates observed over that period were then used to project future shorelines to the year 2050 and 2100.</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Cumberland Island National Seashore</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-81.482936</westbc>
        <eastbc>-81.443104</eastbc>
        <northbc>30.930110</northbc>
        <southbc>30.736775</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Coastal erosion</themekey>
        <themekey>shoreline retreat</themekey>
        <themekey>barrier island</themekey>
        <themekey>Cumberland Island National Seashore</themekey>
        <themekey>AMBUR</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>There is no guarantee or warranty concerning the accuracy of the data. Users should not use these data for critical applications without a full awareness of the data limitations. Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the U.S. Geological Survey or data originators regarding the utility of the data on any other system, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. No responsibility is assumed by the U.S. Geological Survey or data originators in the use of these data.</useconst>
    <native>Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.2.2.3552</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <logic>Data are complete for the intended purposes. No updates are planned</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>To determine shoreline positions, points were surveyed along the edge of the margin scarp using either a Trimble R8 Real-Time Kinematic Global Positioning System (RTK GPS) unit, a Trimble S6 total station, or both. Points were then converted to a polyline feature to represent the position and configuration of the selected sites shoreline. The goal of this exercise was to estimate the net amount of retreat which could be compared to other methods that were being used in this study.</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>String</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>20</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>NAD 1983 UTM Zone 17N</mapprojn>
          <transmer>
            <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
            <longcm>-81.0</longcm>
            <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
            <feast>500000.0</feast>
            <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
          </transmer>
        </mapproj>
        <planci>
          <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>0.000000002220024164500956</absres>
            <ordres>0.000000002220024164500956</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>meter</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D North American 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS 1980</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>ALL_sites_shorelines</enttypl>
        <enttypd>This dataset contains shoreline position information for the dates listed in the attribute table</enttypd>
        <enttypds>data originator</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>FID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DATE_</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The date that the survey was conducted or the year that the shoreline was projected out to.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>data originator </attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>The date that the survey was conducted or the year that the shoreline was projected out to.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GROUP_</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Two letter abbreviation for the site location</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>data originator </attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Two letter abbreviation for the site location</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape_Leng</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>shape length</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>data originator </attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>shape length</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Creator</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Identifies shorelines that were surveyed or projected using AMBUR. </attrdef>
        <attrdefs>data originator </attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Identifies shorelines that were surveyed or projected using AMBUR. </udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>ScienceBase</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>There is no guarantee concerning the accuracy of the data. No warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. Users should not use this data for critical applications without a full awareness of the limitations. Acknowledgement of originating agencies would be appreciated in products derived from this data.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160711</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jeffrey W. Riley</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>Ecologist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1770 Corporate Dr Suite 500</address>
          <city>Norcross</city>
          <state>GA</state>
          <postal>30093</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>6789246682</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jriley@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>