<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>P. Ryan Jackson</origin>
        <origin>Frank Engel</origin>
        <origin>Elizabeth Murphy</origin>
        <origin>Jessica Zinger</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Hydroacoustic measurements of velocities in and near the rake-to-box junction gap of a moving, fully-loaded commercial barge tow</title>
        <geoform>Microsoft Excel Spreadsheets</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7445JMT</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Jeremiah J. Davis</origin>
            <origin>P. Ryan Jackson</origin>
            <origin>Frank L. Engel</origin>
            <origin>Jessica A. Zinger</origin>
            <origin>Rebecca N. Neeley</origin>
            <origin>Samuel T. Finney</origin>
            <origin>Elizabeth A. Murphy</origin>
            <title>Entrainment, retention, and transport of freely swimming fish in junction gaps between commercial barges operating on the Illinois Waterway</title>
            <geoform>Journal Article</geoform>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>In August 2015, water velocities around a fully-loaded commercial barge tow were measured as the barge tow traveled upstream through the Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal from a starting position in Lockport Pool, and passed through the Electric Dispersal Barrier System at RM 296 near Romeoville, IL. Velocity measurements were made in and alongside the gap formed by the junction between the boxed stern of a rake hopper barge and the raked bow of a rake tanker barge (herein referred to as the rake-to-box junction gap) using two SonTek Argonaut SW 3kHz acoustic Doppler velocity meters (ADVM). &#xD;
&#xD;
One ADVM was mounted 0.091 meters below the water surface, facing downward in the center of the rake-to-box junction gap, rotated 35 degrees clockwise to the box side of the gap (Downlooking ADVM). The other ADVM was mounted 1.37 meters below the water surface at the edge of the rake-to-box junction gap, facing outward from the barge tow at an angle of 23 degrees measured counter-clockwise from a line perpendicular to the barge (Side-looking ADVM). Differential GPS (dGPS) receivers were mounted directly above both ADVMs and their output was logged in HYPACK (more information available at http://www.hypack.com). The dGPS mounted above the Downlooking ADVM also logged GPS Doppler-based heading information with an accuracy of ± 0.75°. &#xD;
&#xD;
The water velocity data are reported in a stationary, course-oriented reference frame (i.e. corrected for the movement of the barge tow), such that positive course-parallel velocities point in the direction of barge travel (upstream, for this dataset), and positive course-normal velocities point into the gap (toward the right, when facing in the direction of barge travel). Profiles of mean course-parallel velocity and mean course-normal velocity are reported for several ranges of barge tow speed. The distance from the barge (Side-looking ADVM) and the distance below the water surface (Downlooking ADVM) are given for the center of each ADVM measurement cell.</abstract>
      <purpose>Velocity data were collected concurrently with a series of mark and recapture trials conducted by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, designed to quantify the likelihood of fish retention and transport within the rake-to-box junction gap. The velocity data was collected to identify the hydrodynamic mechanisms responsible for fish entrainment and retention in barge junction gaps.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20150821</begdate>
          <enddate>20150822</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>observed</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-88.065249</westbc>
        <eastbc>-88.057298</eastbc>
        <northbc>41.651615</northbc>
        <southbc>41.608047</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>streamflow</themekey>
        <themekey>surface water (non-marine)</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal</placekey>
        <placekey>Illinois</placekey>
        <placekey>Romeoville</placekey>
        <placekey>Will County</placekey>
        <placekey>Lockport Locks</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>P. Ryan Jackson</cntper>
          <cntorg>USGS Illinois Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>405 N. Goodwin Ave</address>
          <city>Urbana</city>
          <state>Illinois</state>
          <postal>61820</postal>
          <country>IL</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>217-328-9719</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pjackson@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>Great Lakes Restoration Initiative</datacred>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>n/a</methtype>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>SonTek Argonaut SW Data was opened in ViewArgonaut and the multicell data was exported as ascii files. In the case of the ADVM mounted facing outward from the barge at 23 degrees, the velocity components were rotated to be perpendicular and parallel to the barge tow prior to exporting the data as ascii files.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20150831</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Matlab scripts were used to match the velocity data exported from ViewArgonaut with the GPS data by timestamp</procdesc>
        <procdate>20151106</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Matlab scripts were used to transform the velocities into a stationary, course-oriented reference frame</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160422</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal, Lockport Pool, Electric Dispersal Barrier System</indspref>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>SidelookingADVM.xlsx</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Velocities measured by the side-looking ADVM facing outward from the rake-to-box junction gap, in a course-orientated stationary reference frame</enttypd>
        <enttypds>SonTek Argonaut SW 3kHz acoustic Doppler velocity meter</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Mean Course-Parallel Velocity Tab</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Positive course-parallel velocity is in the direction of barge travel (upstream)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Profiles of mean course-parallel velocity are reported for several ranges of barge tow speed. The distance from the barge are given for the center of each ADVM measurement cell.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Mean Course-Normal Velocity Tab</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Positive course-normal velocity is to the right, when facing in the direction of barge travel (i.e. into the gap)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Profiles of mean course-normal velocity are reported for several ranges of barge tow speed. The distance from the barge are given for the center of each ADVM measurement cell.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>DownlookingADVM.xlsx</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Velocities measured by the downlooking ADVM in the rake-to-box junction gap, in a course-orientated stationary reference frame</enttypd>
        <enttypds>SonTek Argonaut SW 3kHz acoustic Doppler velocity meter</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Mean Course-Parallel Velocity Tab</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Positive course-parallel velocity is in the direction of barge travel (upstream)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Profiles of mean course-parallel velocity are reported for several ranges of barge tow speed. The distance below the water surface are given for the center of each ADVM measurement cell.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Mean Course-Normal Velocity Tab</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Positive course-normal velocity is to the right, when facing in the direction of barge travel (i.e. into the gap)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Profiles of mean course-normal velocity are reported for several ranges of barge tow speed. The distance below the water surface are given for the center of each ADVM measurement cell.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Mean Vertical Velocity Tab</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Positive vertical velocity is up, away from the channel bed</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Profiles of mean vertical velocity are reported for several ranges of barge tow speed. The distance below the water surface are given for the center of each ADVM measurement cell.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-­888-­275-­8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items must be secured from the copyright owner whenever applicable. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although the data have been subjected to rigorous review and are substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, the data are released on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from authorized or unauthorized use. Although the data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Users of the data are advised to read all metadata and associated documentation thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</distliab>
    <techpreq>The user must have Microsoft Excel to read this data.</techpreq>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160504</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Jessica Zinger</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Illinois Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>405 N. Goodwin Ave.</address>
          <city>Urbana</city>
          <state>IL</state>
          <postal>61801</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>2173289765</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jzinger@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>

