<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>P. Ryan Jackson</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Spatial distribution of Rhodamine WT dye concentration measured in the Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal, Chicago, IL (November 15-18, 2011)</title>
        <geoform>ArcGIS Layer package and Excel spreadsheet with raw data</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7HH6H55</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>A boat equipped with a differential Global Positioning System (GPS) receiver (Hemisphere Crescent A100 Smart Antenna) and a Turner Designs C3 submersible fluorometer was used to survey the spatial distribution of the Rhodamine WT dye in the Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal (CSSC) throughout the study area. The fluorometer was installed in a fixed, downlooking orientation approximately 1 foot below the water surface. Fluorometer readings were taken at a frequency of 1 per second. Data were acquired on a personal computer running the Turner Designs C-FINS software extension for ArcGIS 10. This data acquisition software allows the C3 data to be georeferenced and plotted in real time as color-coded concentrations on a user-supplied base map. The data were logged in the CFINS program and stored as shapefiles, and raw (not georeferenced) data were stored internally on the boat-mounted C3 and downloaded at the end of each shift (every 12 hours). Survey techniques were restricted to streamwise transects along the bank of the CSSC nearest the Des Plaines River in both the upstream and downstream direction. The boat survey crew followed the wall of the canal as closely as possible, including data collection in barge slips. Mooring of barges and active barge traffic restricted surveys in some locations and led to some contamination of fluorometer data by increasing local turbidity concentrations near the active vessels. The C3 turbidity sensor was not calibrated and therefore reported only relative changes in background turbidity and not absolute turbidity values (in relative Nephelometric turbidity units (NTU)). Several vertical profiles were also made in target areas to ensure dye was not being transported near the bed without any surface detection.</abstract>
      <purpose>These data were collected during dye tracing surveys of the lower Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal targeting identification of potential inflows of Des Plaines River water through the fractured bedrock that separates the two water bodies. Dye was injected into the Des Plaines River at 422481 m E, 4617942 m N (UTM WGS84 Zone 16N).  The dye was injected at three locations in the cross section to help ensure even distribution of the tracer in the river. Injection began at 1050 hours on November 15, 2011, and ended at 1200 hours on November 16. A total of approximately 57 gallons of Rhodamine WT in a 20 percent solution was used in the study. The target dye concentration in the Des Plaines River throughout the reach of interest was 20 parts per billion. All times are in Central Standard Time.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Turbidity created by barges led to apparent increases in dye concentration. After reviewing the data and accounting for turbidity-induced spikes (the C3 fluorometer includes a turbidity sensor ), no dye was detected in the Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal. All Rhodamine WT concentrations remained below 1 part per billion after accounting for turbidity-induced spikes.&#xD;
&#xD;
http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7HH6H55</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20111115</begdate>
          <enddate>20111118</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal, Chicago, IL</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-88.059758</westbc>
        <eastbc>-87.929801</eastbc>
        <northbc>41.70729</northbc>
        <southbc>41.646426</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Dye</themekey>
        <themekey>Tracer</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal</placekey>
        <placekey>Illinois</placekey>
        <placekey>DuPage County</placekey>
        <placekey>Cook County</placekey>
        <placekey>Will County</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>P. Ryan Jackson</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Illinois Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>405 N. Goodwin Ave.</address>
          <city>Urbana</city>
          <state>IL</state>
          <postal>61801</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>2173289719</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pjackson@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>Great Lakes Restoration Initiative</datacred>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Dataset is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>n/a</methtype>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data were exported from ArcGIS as a layer package.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160321</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Point</direct>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <geograph>
        <latres>1.0E-6</latres>
        <longres>1.0E-6</longres>
        <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
      </geograph>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>World Geodetic System 1984</horizdn>
        <ellips>WGS84</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>A description of the C-FINS logged data file can be found at:&#xD;
http://www.turnerdesigns.com/t2/doc/instructions/998-2382.pdf&#xD;
&#xD;
Attributes in the ArcGIS Layer Package (Boat-MountedC3_All_edited_data.lpk)&#xD;
FID: ArcGIS point feature identifier&#xD;
Shape: ArcGIS feature type (point)&#xD;
C3_Date: Sample date (MM/DD/YY)&#xD;
C3_Time: Sample time (CST)&#xD;
C3_DepthM: Depth of the C3 sensors, in meters&#xD;
C3_DegC: Water temperature, in degrees Celsius&#xD;
Chan1_Val: Value of channel 1 parameter (rhodamine concentration) &#xD;
Chan1_Unit: Units of channel 1 parameter (ppb: parts per billion)&#xD;
Chan1_Type: Channel 1 sensor type (Rhodamine WT) &#xD;
Lat_DD: Sample latitude, in decimal degrees (WGS84)&#xD;
Long_DD: Sample longitude, in decimal degrees (WGS84)&#xD;
COG_True: Course over ground, degrees relative to true north&#xD;
SOG: Speed over ground&#xD;
SOG_Unit: Speed over ground units &#xD;
A description of the Turner Designs C3 fluorometer including a description of how raw data files can be handled can be found at:&#xD;
http://www.turnerdesigns.com/t2/doc/manuals/998-2300.pdf&#xD;
Attributes of Boat-MountedC3_All_raw_data.xlsx include:&#xD;
All Raw Data worksheet includes a 7-line header including calibration information &#xD;
Date_Time: Date and time&#xD;
Rhodamine: Rhodamine WT concentration in parts per billion (ppb)&#xD;
Turbidity: Relative Turbidity values (uncalibrated) in Nephelometic turbidity units (NTU)&#xD;
Temp: Water temperature in degrees Celsius</eaover>
      <eadetcit>C-FINS extension download: &#xD;
http://www.turnerdesigns.com/inline-monitoring?page=shop.product_details&amp;category_id=100&amp;flypage=flypage_default.tpl&amp;product_id=218&#xD;
&#xD;
ESRI ArcGIS Layer Package:&#xD;
http://webhelp.esri.com/arcgisexplorer/900/en/add_arcgis_layers.htm</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>U.S. Geological Survey – ScienceBase</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey – ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items must be secured from the copyright owner whenever applicable. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although the data have been subjected to rigorous review and are substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, the data are released on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from authorized or unauthorized use. Although the data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Users of the data are advised to read all metadata and associated documentation thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>ZIP</formname>
          <formvern>none</formvern>
          <formcont>This WinZip file contains an ArcGIS Layer Package (.lpk) with the moving-boat fluorometer data from the Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal (Boat-MountedC3_All_edited_data.lpk). Also included in this WinZip file is an Microsoft Excel spreadsheet (.xlsx) with the raw fluorometer data from the boat-mounted fluorometer (Boat-MountedC3_All_raw_data.xlsx).  Finally, the WinZip file contains also contains metadata.</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7HH6H55</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160429</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>P. Ryan Jackson</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Illinois Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Hydrologist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>405 N. Goodwin Ave.</address>
          <city>Urbana</city>
          <state>IL</state>
          <postal>61801</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>2173289719</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pjackson@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>

