<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Kathleen Longshore</origin>
        <origin>Todd Esque</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Golden Eagle Food Habits in the Mojave Desert:  Remote nest camera data</title>
        <geoform>Tabular Digital Data</geoform>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Expansion of renewable energy development is rapidly transforming the Mojave Desert landscape and has the potential to impact Golden Eagles through loss of foraging habitat and reduced prey base.  Regional information on Golden Eagle food habits is limited and little is known of how dietary variability influences eagle productivity.  We examined diet using motion activated trail cameras and collection of prey remains at 18 nests during two seasons (2014 and 2015).</abstract>
      <purpose>To provide baseline diet information to inform regional conservation strategies.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Nest Cameras:
We used historical geospatial nest information compiled from interagency databases (USFWS, BLM, CDFW, and NDOW) to target known breeding areas within the Mojave Desert eco-regions of Nevada and California during two nesting seasons (2014 and 2015).  For nests determined to be active, we installed cameras when nestlings reached greater than or equal to 3.5 weeks of age.  The timing of camera installation was intended to minimize disturbance of breeding activities (in accordance with USFWS permit #MB27836B-0).  Adults are most susceptible to disturbance during the earliest stages of nesting and chicks, which cannot thermoregulate prior to 3 weeks of age, are at risk of mortality if exposed to prolonged cold or heat.
We used trail cameras manufactured by Bushnell (Trophy Cam, 8 megapixel) and Reconyx (HC500, 3.1 megapixel). Each camera was equipped with lithium ion AA batteries and a 32 gigabyte SD memory card.  Cameras were programed to take one picture when movement was detected at minimum intervals of 60 seconds.
For each prey delivery captured by nest cameras, we recorded the date and time the photograph was taken, as well as the prey species and the estimated percent of the item delivered.  For example, the lower half of a black-tailed jackrabbit would be estimated as 50% of the whole individual. When possible, we recorded the age of individuals to increase the accuracy of biomass calculations.
We calculated frequency of occurrence (percent composition) of prey in the diet by dividing the number of individuals for each species or category (i.e., leporids, birds, reptiles, mesocarnivores, and rodents) by the total number of individuals in the sample.  To calculate biomass, we multiplied the number of individuals by the estimated weight of each species,</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20140423</begdate>
          <enddate>20150825</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>observed</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>In work</progress>
      <update>None planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-118.382</westbc>
        <eastbc>-113.014</eastbc>
        <northbc>37.349</northbc>
        <southbc>33.704</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>golden eagle</themekey>
        <themekey>diet</themekey>
        <themekey>prey selection</themekey>
        <themekey>renewable energy</themekey>
        <themekey>nest camera</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Mojave Desert</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None. Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</accconst>
    <useconst>The authors of these data require that users direct any questions pertaining to appropriate use or assistance with understanding limitations and interpretation of the data to the individuals/organization listed in the Point of Contact section.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, PACIFIC REGION</cntorg>
          <cntper>Kathleen Longshore</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>Research Wildlife Biologist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>160 Stephanie Boulevard</address>
          <city>Henderson</city>
          <state>NV</state>
          <postal>89074</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>702-564-4505</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>702-564-4600</cntfax>
        <cntemail>longshore@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>Diego Johnson, Justin Streit, Matt Simes, USGS,</datacred>
    <native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.2.2 (Build 3552) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Quality control was performed by multiple researchers.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Development of the data set by the agency / individuals identified in the 'Originator' element in the Identification Info section of the record.</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Prey_type</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Common name of prey</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unknown</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Taxa_Group</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Larger group to which the animal belongs</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Birds</edomv>
            <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Leporids </edomv>
            <edomvd>The Leporidae are a family of mammals that include rabbits and hares, over 60 species in all.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Mesocarnivores</edomv>
            <edomvd>A mesocarnivore is an animal whose diet consists of 50–70% meat with the balance consisting of non-vertebrate foods which may include fungi, fruits, and other plant material. Mesocarnivores are seen today among the Canidae (coyotes, many foxes), Viverridae (civets), Mustelidae (martens, tayra), Procyonidae (ring-tailed cat), Mephitidae (skunks), and Herpestidae (some mongooses).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Reptiles</edomv>
            <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Rodents</edomv>
            <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Scientific_name</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>genus and species name</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unknown</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Number_2014</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>frequency of prey species detected</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>70</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Percent_2014</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The percent of the total diet for each prey species.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>0.443</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Number_2015</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>frequency of prey species detected</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>331</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Percent_2015</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>the percent of the total diet for each prey species</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>0.596</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Number_2014_2015</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The frequency of prey species detected for both years compined.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>1</rdommin>
            <rdommax>401</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Percent_2014_2015</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The precent of the total diet for each prey species for both years combined.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.001</rdommin>
            <rdommax>0.562</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <overview>
      <eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes the tabular data associated with the data set. Please review the detailed descriptions that are provided (the individual attribute descriptions) for information on the values that appear as fields/table entries of the data set.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>The entity and attribute information was generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Please review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center</address>
          <address>Building 810</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Tabular Digital Data</formname>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://www.sciencebase.gov</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160314</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Kathleen Longshore</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, PACIFIC REGION</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Research Wildlife Biologist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>160 Stephanie Boulevard</address>
          <city>Henderson</city>
          <state>NV</state>
          <postal>89074</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>702-564-4505</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>702-564-4600</cntfax>
        <cntemail>longshore@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>