<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Sarah M Elliott</origin>
        <origin>Kathy E Lee</origin>
        <origin>Sue Langer</origin>
        <origin>Molly M Trombley</origin>
        <origin>Michael A Menheer</origin>
        <origin>Mark E Brigham</origin>
        <origin>Edward T Furlong</origin>
        <origin>William T Foreman</origin>
        <origin>Zachary Jorgenson</origin>
        <origin>Steven Choy</origin>
        <origin>Jeremy Moore</origin>
        <origin>JoAnn Banda</origin>
        <origin>Daniel J Gefell</origin>
        <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
        <title>Chemicals of Emerging Concern in Water and Bottom Sediment in Great Lakes Areas of Concern, 2013 - Field and Laboratory Quality Assurance</title>
        <geoform>Tabular data</geoform>
        <onlink>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/54733ba1e4b0b935bc76cec0</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), in cooperation with the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS) and the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), identified the occurrence of contaminants of emerging concern (CECs) in water and bottom sediments collected in 2013 at 57 sites throughout the Great Lakes Basin. The 2013 effort is part of a long-term study that began in 2010. Included in this directory are collection methods, references to or descriptions of analytical methods used, data for samples collected in 2013, and associated quality-assurance data.   

Samples were collected from April through October 2013 by USGS, USFWS, and/or EPA personnel. Study sites include tributaries to the Great Lakes located near Duluth, Minnesota; Kewaunee, Wisconsin; Appleton, Wisconsin; Detroit, Michigan; Grand Rapids, Michigan; St Clair, Michigan; Cleveland, Ohio; Wanakena, New York; and Potsdam, New York (see "2013 Site List"). During this study, 93 environmental samples and 6 field replicate sample pairs of surface water, 3 field blank water samples, and 3 laboratory-matrix spike water samples were collected or prepared. Additionally, 49 environmental samples, 4 field replicate sample pairs, and two laboratory-matrix spike samples of bottom sediment were collected or prepared.&amp;nbsp;Water and bottom-sediment samples were analyzed at the USGS National Water Quality Laboratory in Denver, Colorado, for a broad suite of CECs.

The Field and Laboratory Quality Assurance provides seven tables that support the analytical results for wastewater compounds, steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A, and pharmaceuticals in water and wastewater compounds, steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A, pharmaceuticals, and antidepressants in bottom-sediment samples collected during 2013.</abstract>
      <purpose>The Fish and Wildlife Service initiated the study through the Great Lakes Restoration Initiative as an early warning program to detect and identify emerging contaminants and to evaluate the effects of these contaminants on fish and wildlife.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Suggested citation (USE THIS): Elliott, S.M., Lee, K.E., Brigham, M.E., Langer, S.K., Trombley, M.M., Menheer, M.A., Furlong, E.T., Foreman, W.T., Jorgenson, Z.G., Choy, S.J., Moore, J.N., Banda, J.B., and Gefell, D.J., 2015, Chemicals of emerging concern in water and bottom sediment in the Great Lakes Basin 2013 - Analytical methods, Collection methods, Environmental Data, and Quality Assurance: U.S. Geological Survey Data Release, http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7DF6P9D.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>201304</begdate>
          <enddate>201310</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Great Lakes Basin</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-93.2231979370117</westbc>
        <eastbc>-73.6395492553711</eastbc>
        <northbc>48.3042488098145</northbc>
        <southbc>40.4067077636719</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Area of Concern</themekey>
        <themekey>Emerging Contaminants</themekey>
        <themekey>Toxicology</themekey>
        <themekey>Great Lakes Restoration Initiative</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Great Lakes</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Sarah Elliott</cntper>
          <cntorg>U. S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <address>2280 Woodale Drive</address>
          <city>Mounds View</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55112</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>763-783-3130</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>selliott@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>U.S. Geological Survey, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</datacred>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Lee, K.E.</origin>
        <origin>Langer, S.K.</origin>
        <origin>Menheer, M.A.</origin>
        <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
        <origin>Furlong, E.T.</origin>
        <origin>Smith, S.G.</origin>
        <pubdate>2012</pubdate>
        <title>Chemicals of emerging concern in water and bottom sediment in Great Lakes areas of concern, 2010-2011—Collection methods, analyses methods, quality assurance, and data</title>
        <geoform>Publication</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series</sername>
          <issue>Data Series 723, 26 p.</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/ds/723/</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Lee, K.E. </origin>
        <origin>Langer, S.K.</origin>
        <origin>Menheer, M.A.</origin>
        <origin>Hansen, D.S.</origin>
        <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
        <origin>Furlong, E.T.</origin>
        <origin>Jorgenson, Z.G.</origin>
        <origin>Choy, S.J.</origin>
        <origin>Moore, J.N.</origin>
        <origin>Banda, JoAnn</origin>
        <origin>Gefell, D.J.</origin>
        <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
        <title>Chemicals of emerging concern in water and bottom sediment in the Great Lakes Basin, 2012—Collection methods, analytical methods, quality assurance, and study data</title>
        <geoform>Publication</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series</sername>
          <issue>Data Series 910, 14 p.</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds910</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Several quality-control measures were implemented both in the field and at the laboratory to evaluate the integrity of the data being generated. Sample replicates and blank samples were collected in the field. Surrogate standards, isotope dilution standards, matrix spikes, reagent blank-water spikes, and reagent blank-sediment samples were prepared in the laboratory. Quality control measures used in 2013 were similar to those used in previous years of the study. Detailed descriptions and how the quality-assurance data are used can be found in Lee and others (2012) for data collected in 2010-11 and in Lee and others (2015) for data collected in 2012 for the same study. The following calculations were used to analyze the quality assurance samples: relative percent difference between field replicates, detections in field and lab-blank samples, and percent recovery of surrogate standards, isotope dilution standards, matrix spikes, and laboratory-blank spikes.

Field Quality Assurance:   

Field blank water samples were collected to assess potential contamination sources introduced during sample collection and processing. Three field blank water samples were collected in 2013; analytical results are included in "2013WaterData" in the   'Environmental Data' section of this directory. Seven pharmaceuticals were detected in one of the field blank samples; no compounds were detected in the other two field blank samples. Environmental concentrations less than three times the highest field blank concentration were considered to be affected by blank-related contamination and assigned a 'Cf' qualifier, which is located immediately after the value in "2013WaterData" and "2013Data_by_Result"  in the 'Environmental Data' section of this directory. For the seven compounds detected in field blank samples, 12 samples were considered affected by blank-related contamination for 1,7-dimethylxanthine; 42 samples for caffeine; 2 samples for glipizide; 37 samples for lidocaine; 19 samples for metformin; 0 samples for sulfadimethoxine; and 14 samples for sulfamethoxazole.    

Field replicate samples (see spreadsheet file) were collected to assess variability in results from point of sample collection through analysis. Variability was characterized by calculating the relative percent difference for each compound between each replicate pair. A summary of relative percent difference and detection consistency for water and sediment field replicate samples is provided in Table 4. Relative percent difference is calculated by dividing the absolute difference in environmental concentrations between the environmental and replicate samples by the mean concentration of the two samples and multiplying by 100.     

Five water replicate sample pairs were collected for analysis of wastewater compounds (schedule 4433) and pharmaceuticals in filtered water (schedule 2440), 1 replicate sample pair for analysis of pharmaceuticals in unfiltered water (schedule 8244), and 6 replicate sample pairs for analysis of steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A (schedule 4434) during 2013 ("2013WaterData"). Mean relative percent differences ranged from 0 to 66.7 for wastewater compounds (schedule 4433) in unfiltered water, 3.4 to 19 for steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A (schedule 4434) in unfiltered water, and 7 to 74 for pharmaceuticals (schedule 2440) in filtered water. Only one replicate sample pair was analyzed by research method 8244 for pharmaceuticals in unfiltered water, relative percent difference ranged from 25 to 121 for all compounds.    

Four bottom-sediment replicate sample pairs were collected during 2013 ("2013SedimentData"). Mean relative percent differences ranged from 6 to 73 for wastewater compounds (schedule 5433) and 12 to 128 for steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A (research method 6434). Seventeen replicate sample pairs were analyzed for human-use pharmaceuticals and antidepressants (research method 9008). Mean relative percent differences ranged from 20 to 94 for human-use pharmaceuticals and 20 to 43 for antidepressants.    

Laboratory Quality Assurance:  

This directory also includes summaries of percent recovery of laboratory matrix-spike samples, compound detections in laboratory-blank samples, percent recovery of laboratory reagent-matrix spike samples, surrogate standards, and isotope dilution standard (IDS) compounds that were analyzed with environmental samples.   

Laboratory-matrix spike samples for water and bottom sediment were prepared to evaluate recovery performance of compounds in samples collected at specific sites. Recovery of target analytes and statistics for laboratory-matrix spike samples are provided in Table 5 (water) and Table 6 (bottom sediment) in this directory.   

Three laboratory-matrix spike water samples were collected during 2013 (Table 5). Mean percent recovery for wastewater compounds (schedule4433) in unfiltered water ranged from 33 to 195. Mean percent recovery for steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A (schedule 4434) in unfiltered water ranged from 74 to 111. Mean percent recovery for pharmaceuticals (schedule 2440) in filtered water ranged from 53 to 394. No field-matrix spike water samples were analyzed for schedule 8244. Mean recoveries for most compounds in these methods were within the range (60-120) of what is typically deemed to be acceptable recovery rates (W.T. Foreman and R.B. Green, U.S. Geological Survey National Water Quality Laboratory, written communication, 2014).  

Two laboratory-matrix spike bottom-sediment samples were prepared during 2013 to evaluate recovery of compounds using laboratory schedules 5433 and 6434 (Table 6). Mean percent recovery of wastewater compounds (schedule 5433) ranged from 15 to 157. Mean percent recovery of steroid hormones. sterols, and bisphenol A (research method 6434) ranged from 38 to 117. Fourteen laboratory-matrix spike bottom-sediment samples were prepared during 2013 to evaluate recovery of human-use pharmacetuicals and antidepressants (research method 9008) (Table 6). Mean percent recovery of pharmaceuticals in bottom sediment ranged from 3 to 24. Mean percent recovery of antidepressants in bottom sediment ranged from 3 to 31. Pharmaceutical recoveries of laboratory-matrix spike bottom-sediment samples were substantially lower than anticipated; experiments to identify the reason for this drop in performance are underway (E.T. Furlong, U.S. Geological Survey National Water Quality Laboratory, written communication, 2015). 

Laboratory blank-water samples are reagent-water samples or baked reagent-sand matrix simultaneously analyzed with environmental samples that provide information about potential contamination introduced during sample preparation and analysis at the laboratory. Table 7 provides a summary of compounds detected in laboratory blank-water and blank-sediment samples analyzed with environmental samples collected during 2013. Thirty compounds were detected in at least one laboratory blank-water sample analyzed for wastewater compounds in unfiltered water (schedule 4433), several of which were detected at concentrations that may have affected some environmental sample results. The only compound detected in laboratory blank-water samples analyzed for steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A (schedule 4434) was cholesterol, which was detected in two laboratory blank-water samples. Detected concentrations of cholesterol in the laboratory blank-water samples were substantially lower than environmental concentrations ("2013WaterData") and were assumed to not have affected environmental sample results. Thirty-eight compounds were detected in at least one laboratory blank-water sample analyzed for pharmaceuticals in filtered water (schedule 2440), several of which were detected at concentrations that may have affected some environmental sample results. Thirty-three compounds were detected in at least one laboratory blank-sediment sample analyzed for wastewater compounds (schedule 5433), several of which were detected at concentrations that may have affected some environmental results. No compounds were detected in laboratory blank-sediment samples analyzed for steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A (schedule 6434) or human-use pharmaceuticals and antidepressants (research method 9008).  

Laboratory reagent-spike samples are reagent-water and ashed sand-matrix samples spiked with a known concentration of select chemicals that provide information about method performance with time, in the absence of sample matrix. Summaries of recoveries in laboratory reagent-water and reagent-sediment spikes are provided in Tables 8 and 9, respectively. In water, mean percent recovery of waste water compounds (schedule 4433) ranged from 32 to 143. Mean percent recovery of steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A (schedule 4434) ranged from 80 to 112. Mean percent recovery of pharmaceuticals (schedule 2044) ranged from 50 to 104. In bottom-sediment samples, mean percent recovery of wastewater compounds (schedule 5433) ranged from 15 to 114. Mean percent recovery of 18 wastewater compounds (schedule 5433) was less than 60 percent, and environmental sample results associated with those compounds should be interpreted with caution. Mean percent recovery of steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A (research method 6434) ranged from 83 to 108; all within acceptable range of recovery. Mean percent recovery of human-use pharmaceuticals and antidepressants (research method 9008) ranged from 8 to 22 and 6 to 20, respectively. Pharmaceutical recoveries of laboratory reagent-spike ashed sand matrix samples were substantially lower than anticipated; experiments to identify the reason for this drop in performance are underway (E.T. Furlong, U.S. Geological Survey National Water Quality Laboratory, written communication, 2015).  

Surrogate standards and IDS compounds are similar in structure to several of the target method compounds and are used to monitor sample-specific laboratory procedural performance. Additionally, IDS compounds are used to correct chemical concentrations of steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A in unfiltered water (schedule 4434) and bottom sediment (schedule 6434). Mean recoveries, standard deviations, and relative standard deviations (absolute value of the coefficient of variation) for surrogate standards and IDS compounds are provided in Table 10. Mean percent recovery of surrogate compounds analyzed for wastewater compounds in unfiltered water (schedule 4433) ranged from 47 to 92. Decafluorobiphenyl was the only surrogate standard with a mean percent recovery less than 60. Mean percent recovery of IDS compounds analyzed for steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A in unfiltered water (schedule 4434) ranged from 26 to 84. Progesterone-2,3,4-13C3 was the only IDS compound with a mean percent recovery less than 60. Mean percent recovery of surrogate standards analyzed for pharmaceuticals in filtered water (schedule 2440) ranged from 75 to 119; all within the acceptable range of recovery. In bottom-sediment samples, mean percent recovery of surrogate standard analyzed for wastewater compounds (schedule 5433) ranged from 23 to 73. Mean percent recoveries for bisphenol A-d3 and decafluorobiphenyl were below 60. Mean percent recovery of IDS compounds analyzed for steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A (schedule 6434) ranged from 8 to 63. All compounds except bisphenol A-d16 and mestranol-2,4,16,16-d4 had mean percent recoveries less than 60. Mean percent recovery of surrogate standards analyzed for human-use pharmaceuticals and antidepressants (research method 9008) were all less than 40. Pharmaceutical recoveries of surrogate compounds in bottom-sediment samples were substantially lower than anticipated; experiments to identify the reason for this drop in performance are underway (E.T. Furlong, U.S. Geological Survey National Water Quality Laboratory, written communication, 2015).</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. All sites that were sampled during 2013 are represented in the data set.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>both</methtype>
        <methdesc>Collection Methods:
Methods used to collect environmental samples in 2013 followed methods used in previous years of the study and are provided in detail in Lee and others (2012) for data collected in 2010/11 and in Lee and others (2015) for data collected in 2012 for the same study. Briefly, water samples were collected from streams and lakes using a modified depth-integrated sampling method with a weighted bottle sampler fitted with a 1-liter, glass bottle. Bottom-sediment samples were collected to include the most recently deposited bottom-sediment deposition (top 10 centimeters) using a stainless steel Ekman dredge. All samples were collected with inert materials and sampling personnel avoided the use of personal-care items such as insect repellent, cologne, aftershave, and perfume.   

Analytical methods:
Water samples were analyzed for more than 200 chemicals at the USGS National Water Quality Laboratory (NWQL) using methods for wastewater compounds in unfiltered water (schedule 4433; Zaugg and others, 2006), steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A in unfiltered water (schedule 4434; Foreman and others, 2012), pharmaceuticals in unfiltered water (research method 8244; Phillips and others, 2010), and pharmaceuticals in filtered water (schedule 2440; Furlong and others, 2014). Bottom-sediment samples were analyzed for more than 100 chemicals at the NWQL using methods for wastewater compounds (schedule 5433; Burkhardt and others, 2006), steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A  (research method 6434; described in Fischer and others, 2015), and pharmaceuticals and antidepressants (research method 9008; described in Lee and others, 2012; 2015).   

Research method 8244 for pharmaceuticals in unfiltered water follows the method of schedule 4433 for wastewater compounds in unfiltered water; a more detailed method description, along with method performance in wastewater effluent is contained in Zaugg and others (2006).    

For more information on the Collection and Analytical Methods, see https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/546cf046e4b0fc7976bf1d39.</methdesc>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Burkhardt, M.R.</origin>
            <origin>Zaugg, S.D.</origin>
            <origin>Smith, S.G.</origin>
            <origin>ReVello, R.C.</origin>
            <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of wastewater compounds in sediment and soil by pressurized solvent extraction, solid-phase extraction, and capillary-column gas chromatography/mass spectrometry</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods</sername>
              <issue>book 5, chap. B2, 40 p.</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/tm/2006/tm5b2/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Fischer, J.M.</origin>
            <origin>Phillips, P.J.</origin>
            <origin>Reilly, T.J.</origin>
            <origin>Focazio, M.J.</origin>
            <origin>Loftin, K.A.</origin>
            <origin>Benzel, W.M.</origin>
            <origin>Jones, D.K.</origin>
            <origin>Smalling, K.L.</origin>
            <origin>Fisher, S.C.</origin>
            <origin>Fisher, I.J.</origin>
            <origin>Iwanowicz, L.R.</origin>
            <origin>Romanok, K.M.</origin>
            <origin>Jenkins, D.</origin>
            <origin>Bowers, L.</origin>
            <origin>Boehlke, A.</origin>
            <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
            <origin>Deetz, A.C.</origin>
            <origin>Carper, L.G.</origin>
            <origin>Imbrigiotta, T.E.</origin>
            <origin>Birdwell, J.</origin>
            <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
            <title>Estuarine bed-sediment-quality data collected in New Jersey and New York after Hurricane Sandy, 2013</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series</sername>
              <issue>Data Series 905, 42 p.</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds905</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
            <origin>Gray, J.L.</origin>
            <origin>ReVello, R.C.</origin>
            <origin>Lindley, C.E.</origin>
            <origin>Losche, S.A.</origin>
            <origin>Barber, L.B.</origin>
            <pubdate>2012</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of steroid hormones and related compounds in filtered and unfiltered water by solid-phase extraction, derivatization, and gas chromatography with tandem mass spectrometry</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods</sername>
              <issue>book 5, chap. B9, 118 p.</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/tm/5b9/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Furlong, E.T.</origin>
            <origin>Noriega, M.C.</origin>
            <origin>Kanagy, C.J.</origin>
            <origin>Kanagy, L.K.</origin>
            <origin>Coffey, L.J.</origin>
            <origin>Burkhardt, M.R.</origin>
            <pubdate>2014</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of human-use pharmaceuticals in filtered water by direct aqueous injection–high-performance liquid chromatography/tandem mass spectrometry</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods</sername>
              <issue>book 5, chap. B10, 49 p.</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/tm5B10</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Phillips, P.J.</origin>
            <origin>Smith, S.G.</origin>
            <origin>Kolpin, D.W.</origin>
            <origin>Zaugg, S.D.</origin>
            <origin>Buston, H.T.</origin>
            <origin>Furlong, E.T.</origin>
            <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
            <title>Method description, quality assurance, environmental data, and other information for analysis of 
pharmaceuticals in wastewater-treatment-plant effluents, streamwater, and reservoirs, 2004-2009
</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report </sername>
              <issue>OFR 2010-1102, 36 p</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2010/1102/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Zaugg, S.D.</origin>
            <origin>Smith, S.G.</origin>
            <origin>Schroeder, M.P.</origin>
            <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of wastewater compounds in 
whole water by continuous liquid–liquid extraction and capillary-column gas 
chromatography/mass spectrometry</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods</sername>
              <issue>book 5, chap. B4, 30 p.
</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/tm/2006/05B04/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
            <title>National Field Manual for the Collection of Water-Quality Data</title>
            <edition>book 9, chaps. A1–A9</edition>
            <geoform>None</geoform>
            <onlink>http://pubs.water.usgs.gov/twri9A</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Downloaded data from the USGS National Water Information System.
Verified all samples were accounted for and had all the appropriate data associated with them.</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>The Field and Laboratory Quality Assurance provides data related to the analytical results (Environmental Data) for wastewater compounds, steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A, and pharmaceuticals in water and wastewater compounds, steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A, pharmaceuticals, and antidepressants in bottom-sediment samples collected during 2013. The Collection and Analysis methods (indicated by their number) can be found at ttps://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/546cf046e4b0fc7976bf1d39.

There are seven files here including Field Replicate Samples, and summaries of percent recovery of laboratory matrix-spike samples, compound detections in laboratory-blank samples, percent recovery of laboratory reagent-matrix spike samples, surrogate standards, and isotope dilution standard (IDS) compounds that were analyzed with environmental samples.   </eaover>
      <eadetcit>None</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. The data has been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although this database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, it is released on condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized use. Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Project level information</formname>
          <formcont>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), in cooperation with the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS) and the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), identified the occurrence of contaminants of emerging concern (CECs) in water and bottom sediment collected in 2013 at 57 sites throughout the Great Lakes Basin. The 2013 effort is part of a long-term study that began in 2010. Included in this directory are references to or descriptions of analytical methods used, collection methods, environmental data, and associated quality-assurance data for samples collected in 2013.    </formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7DF6P9D</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150722</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Sarah Elliott</cntper>
          <cntorg>U. S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>2280 Woodale Drive</address>
          <city>Mounds View</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55112</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>763-783-3130</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>selliott@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>