<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Sarah M. Elliott, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Kathy E. Lee, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Sue K. Langer, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Molly M. McCool, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Michael A. Menheer, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Mark E. Brigham, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Edward T. Furlong, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>William T. Foreman, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Zachary G. Jorgenson, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
        <origin>Steven J. Choy, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
        <origin>Jeremy N. Moore, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
        <origin>Jo A. Banda, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
        <origin>Daniel J. Gefell, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
        <origin>Heiko L. Schoenfuss, St. Cloud State University</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Chemicals of Emerging Concern in Water and Bottom Sediment in the Great Lakes Basin, 2014 - Environmental Data</title>
        <geoform>Tabular data</geoform>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7TH8JS6</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), in cooperation with the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS) and St. Cloud State University (SCSU), identified the occurrence of chemicals of emerging concern (CECs) in water and bottom sediment collected in 2014 at 65 sites throughout the Great Lakes Basin. The 2014 effort is part of a long-term study that began in 2010. Included in this directory are collection methods, references to or descriptions of analytical methods used, data for samples collected in 2014, and associated quality-assurance data. Samples were collected during the periods of April to May and August to September by USGS, USFWS, and (or) SCSU personnel. Study sites include tributaries to the Great Lakes located near Green Bay, Wisconsin; Chicago, Illinois; Detroit, Michigan; Grand Rapids, Michigan; Cleveland, Ohio; and Wanakena, New York. During this study, 204 environmental samples and 6 field replicate sample pairs of surface water, 6 field blank water samples, and 4 laboratory-matrix spike water samples were collected or prepared. Additionally, 21 environmental samples, 3 field replicate sample pairs, and 2 laboratory-matrix spike samples of bottom sediments were collected or prepared. At 22 select water-quality sites, polar organic chemical integrative samplers (POCIS) were deployed in water and analyzed for a similar suite of CECs as were measured in water and bottom-sediment samples. A total of 22 environmental samples, 4 field-blank samples (exposed to ambient air), and 4 field replicate sample pairs were collected or prepared. Water and bottom-sediment samples were prepared and analyzed at the USGS National Water Quality Laboratory (NWQL) in Denver, Colorado. All POCIS samples were extracted at the Environmental Sampling Technologies Laboratory in St. Joseph, Missouri. Extracts were sent to NWQL where final preparation steps and analyses were completed.</abstract>
      <purpose>The U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service initiated the study through the Great Lakes Restoration Initiative as an early warning program to detect and identify emerging contaminants and to evaluate the effects of these contaminants on fish and wildlife.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Suggested citation: Elliott, S.M., Lee, K.E., Brigham, M.E., Langer, S.K., McCool, M.M., Menheer, M.A., Furlong, E.T., Foreman, W.T., Jorgenson, Z.G., Choy, S.J., Moore, J.N., Banda, J.A., Gefell, D.J., and Schoenfuss, H.L., 2016, Chemicals of Emerging Concern in Water and Bottom Sediment in the Great Lakes Basin, 2014 - Analytical Methods, Collection Methods, Quality-Assurance Analyses, and Data: U.S. Geological Survey Data Release, http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7TH8JS6.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>201404</begdate>
          <enddate>201409</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Great Lakes Basin</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-93.2231979370117</westbc>
        <eastbc>-73.6395492553711</eastbc>
        <northbc>48.3042488098145</northbc>
        <southbc>40.4067077636719</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Area of Concern</themekey>
        <themekey>Emerging Contaminants</themekey>
        <themekey>Toxicology</themekey>
        <themekey>Great Lakes Restoration Initiative</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Great Lakes</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>Use of the data provided herein should proceed only after the Field and Laboratory Quality Assurance (https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/547dfe57e4b09357f05f6c14) data have been reviewed and taken into consideration.   </useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Sarah Elliott</cntper>
          <cntorg>U. S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <address>2280 Woodale Drive</address>
          <city>Mounds View</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55112</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>763-783-3130</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>selliott@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>U.S. Geological Survey, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, and St. Cloud State University</datacred>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Lee, K.E.</origin>
        <origin>Langer, S.K.</origin>
        <origin>Menheer, M.A.</origin>
        <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
        <origin>Furlong, E.T.</origin>
        <origin>Smith, S.G.</origin>
        <pubdate>2012</pubdate>
        <title>Chemicals of emerging concern in water and bottom sediment in Great Lakes areas of concern, 2010-2011—Collection methods, analyses methods, quality assurance, and data</title>
        <geoform>Publication</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series</sername>
          <issue>Data Series 723, 26 p.</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/ds/723/</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Lee, K.E. </origin>
        <origin>Langer, S.K.</origin>
        <origin>Menheer, M.A.</origin>
        <origin>Hansen, D.S.</origin>
        <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
        <origin>Furlong, E.T.</origin>
        <origin>Jorgenson, Z.G.</origin>
        <origin>Choy, S.J.</origin>
        <origin>Moore, J.N.</origin>
        <origin>Banda, JoAnn</origin>
        <origin>Gefell, D.J.</origin>
        <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
        <title>Chemicals of emerging concern in water and bottom sediment in the Great Lakes Basin, 2012—Collection methods, analytical methods, quality assurance, and study data</title>
        <geoform>Publication</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series</sername>
          <issue>Data Series 910, 14 p.</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds910</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Several quality-control measures were implemented in the field and at the Environmental Sampling Technologies Laboratory and the National Water Quality Laboratory to evaluate the integrity of the data being generated. Sample replicates and blank samples were collected in the field. Surrogate standards, isotope dilution standards, matrix spikes, reagent blank-water spikes, reagent blank-sand samples, POCIS method blank samples, and POCIS method spikes were prepared in the laboratory. Quality-control measures used in 2014 were similar to those used in previous years of the study. Detailed descriptions and how the quality-assurance data are used can be found in Lee and others (2012) for data collected in 2010-11 and in Lee and others (2015) for data collected in 2012 for the same study. The following calculations were used to analyze the quality-assurance samples: relative percent difference between field replicates, detections in field and laboratory-blank samples, and percent recovery of surrogate standards, isotope dilution standards, and matrix spikes.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Dataset is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. All sites that were sampled during 2014 are represented in the dataset.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>both</methtype>
        <methdesc>Collection Methods:
Methods used to collect environmental samples in 2014 followed methods used in previous years of the study and are provided in detail in Lee and others (2012) for data collected in 2010-11 and in Lee and others (2015) for data collected in 2012 for the same study. Briefly, water samples were collected from streams and lakes using a modified depth-integrated sampling method with a weighted bottle sampler fitted with a 1-liter, glass bottle. Bottom-sediment samples were collected to include the most recently deposited bottom-sediment deposition (top 10 centimeters) using a stainless steel Ekman dredge. All samples were collected with inert materials and sampling personnel avoided the use of personal-care items (with the exception of sunscreen) such as insect repellent, cologne, aftershave, and perfume.  
POCIS samplers were deployed at select sites for a period of 14 days. The samplers were stored in sealed storage containers at less than 5 degrees Celsius until deployment. Upon arriving at the site, POCIS samplers were removed from their storage containers and placed into a deployment canister. As soon as possible after placing the sampler in the deployment canister, the canister was placed in a 1.25-meter long metal tube and submerged under water. The tube was fastened to an attachment structure above the sediment surface with metal ties. When field blanks were collected, the storage container containing the field blank was opened before deployment of the environmental POCIS sampler and closed after the deployed sampler was securely anchored in the water. The field blank procedure was repeated upon retrieval of the associated POCIS samplers. 

</methdesc>
        <methdesc>Analytical methods:
Water samples were analyzed for more than 200 chemicals at the USGS National Water Quality Laboratory (NWQL) using methods for wastewater compounds in unfiltered water (schedule 4433; Zaugg and others, 2006), steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A (referred to as hormones throughout) in unfiltered water (schedule 4434; Foreman and others, 2012), and pharmaceuticals in filtered water (schedule 2440; Furlong and others, 2014). Bottom-sediment samples were analyzed for more than 100 chemicals at the NWQL using methods for wastewater compounds (schedule 5433; Burkhardt and others, 2006), steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A (referred to as hormones throughout; research method 6434; described in Fischer and others, 2015), and pharmaceuticals (research method 9008; described in Lee and others, 2012; 2015). 

Wastewater compounds, hormones, and pharmaceuticals were eluted from POCIS discs at Environmental Sampling Technologies Laboratory in St. Joseph, Missouri. Wastewater compounds were extracted from the two discs separately using 20-25 milliliters (mL) 20% methyl tertiary butyl ether/dichloromethane mixture per disc. Hormones and pharmaceuticals were extracted using 20-25 mL methanol per disc that was pooled after extraction for blowdown and filtration. Two discs for each analytical method were deployed, so eluent from both discs was combined in a single vial for a given schedule. Eluents were then sent to the USGS National Water Quality Laboratory for final processing and analyses. The POCIS extracts were analyzed for more than 200 chemicals at the NWQL using methods based on those established for wastewater compounds in unfiltered water (Zaugg and others, 2006), hormones in unfiltered water (Foreman and others, 2012), and pharmaceuticals in filtered water (Furlong, 2014). Ten chemicals included in the wastewater compound schedule [polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons and pentabromodiphenyl ether (PBDE-47)] were omitted from reporting (as indicated with a 'NR' in 2014POCISData.xlsx) because they are poorly sampled by POCIS and no data are available to support the use of POCIS for those chemicals (D.A. Alvarez, USGS Columbia Environmental Research Center, written communication, 2015). Any discussion regarding environmental and quality-assurance data does not include those compounds.</methdesc>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Burkhardt, M.R.</origin>
            <origin>Zaugg, S.D.</origin>
            <origin>Smith, S.G.</origin>
            <origin>ReVello, R.C.</origin>
            <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of wastewater compounds in sediment and soil by pressurized solvent extraction, solid-phase extraction, and capillary-column gas chromatography/mass spectrometry</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods</sername>
              <issue>book 5, chap. B2, 40 p.</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/tm/2006/tm5b2/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Fischer, J.M.</origin>
            <origin>Phillips, P.J.</origin>
            <origin>Reilly, T.J.</origin>
            <origin>Focazio, M.J.</origin>
            <origin>Loftin, K.A.</origin>
            <origin>Benzel, W.M.</origin>
            <origin>Jones, D.K.</origin>
            <origin>Smalling, K.L.</origin>
            <origin>Fisher, S.C.</origin>
            <origin>Fisher, I.J.</origin>
            <origin>Iwanowicz, L.R.</origin>
            <origin>Romanok, K.M.</origin>
            <origin>Jenkins, D.</origin>
            <origin>Bowers, L.</origin>
            <origin>Boehlke, A.</origin>
            <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
            <origin>Deetz, A.C.</origin>
            <origin>Carper, L.G.</origin>
            <origin>Imbrigiotta, T.E.</origin>
            <origin>Birdwell, J.</origin>
            <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
            <title>Estuarine bed-sediment-quality data collected in New Jersey and New York after Hurricane Sandy, 2013</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series</sername>
              <issue>Data Series 905, 42 p.</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds905</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
            <origin>Gray, J.L.</origin>
            <origin>ReVello, R.C.</origin>
            <origin>Lindley, C.E.</origin>
            <origin>Losche, S.A.</origin>
            <origin>Barber, L.B.</origin>
            <pubdate>2012</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of steroid hormones and related compounds in filtered and unfiltered water by solid-phase extraction, derivatization, and gas chromatography with tandem mass spectrometry</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods</sername>
              <issue>book 5, chap. B9, 118 p.</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/tm/5b9/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Furlong, E.T.</origin>
            <origin>Noriega, M.C.</origin>
            <origin>Kanagy, C.J.</origin>
            <origin>Kanagy, L.K.</origin>
            <origin>Coffey, L.J.</origin>
            <origin>Burkhardt, M.R.</origin>
            <pubdate>2014</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of human-use pharmaceuticals in filtered water by direct aqueous injection–high-performance liquid chromatography/tandem mass spectrometry</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods</sername>
              <issue>book 5, chap. B10, 49 p.</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/tm5B10</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Zaugg, S.D.</origin>
            <origin>Smith, S.G.</origin>
            <origin>Schroeder, M.P.</origin>
            <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of wastewater compounds in 
whole water by continuous liquid–liquid extraction and capillary-column gas 
chromatography/mass spectrometry</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods</sername>
              <issue>book 5, chap. B4, 30 p.
</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/tm/2006/05B04/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
            <title>National Field Manual for the Collection of Water-Quality Data</title>
            <edition>book 9, chaps. A1–A9</edition>
            <geoform>None</geoform>
            <onlink>http://pubs.water.usgs.gov/twri9A</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Downloaded data from the USGS National Water Information System.
Verified all samples were accounted for and had all the appropriate data associated with them.</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>The environmental data provides analytical results for wastewater compounds, hormones, and pharmaceuticals in water, bottom-sediment and POCIS samples collected during 2014. The water, sediment, and POCIS data provided are as reported by the laboratory, unless otherwise noted. Discussion of number of detections that follows does not include results that were 'v', 'Cf', or ‘Cl’ coded (potentially affected by field or laboratory blank contamination). Although it is ultimately up to the data analyst how to use the data, for the purposes of this data release, results determined to be affected by contamination were treated as non-detects. Use of the data provided herein should proceed only after the Field and Laboratory Quality Assurance (https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/547dfe57e4b09357f05f6c14) data have been reviewed and taken into consideration. In unfiltered water samples, 54 of the 69 wastewater compounds analyzed with laboratory schedule 4433 were detected in at least one sample with concentrations ranging from 0.002 to 14.4 micrograms per liter (μg/L). Eighty-three of the 110 pharmaceuticals analyzed by laboratory schedule 2440 were detected in at least one filtered water sample with concentrations ranging from 0.042 to 10,200 nanograms per liter (ng/L). Fifteen of the 20 compounds analyzed by laboratory schedule 4434 were detected in at least one unfiltered water sample with concentrations ranging from 0.23 to 80,500 ng/L. In bottom-sediment samples, 49 of the 57 wastewater compounds analyzed by laboratory schedule 5433 were detected in at least one sample with concentrations ranging from 1.2 to 9,330 micrograms per kilogram (μg/kg). Twenty of the 29 compounds analyzed by research method 9008 were detected in at least one sample with concentrations ranging from 1.6 to 466 μg/kg. Fifteen of the 20 compounds analyzed by custom method 6434 were detected in at least one sample with concentrations ranging from 0.06 to 32,000 μg/kg. In POCIS, 35 of the 69 wastewater compounds analyzed with research method 8068 were detected in at least one sample with concentrations ranging from 1.5 to 438,000 nanograms per POCIS (ng/POCIS). Seventy-nine of the 109 pharmaceuticals analyzed with research method 8240 were detected in at least one sample with concentrations ranging from 53 to 1,620,000 ng/POCIS. Seventeen of the 20 hormones analyzed with research method 8092 were detected in at least one sample at concentrations ranging from 0.08 to 2,360 ng/POCIS.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>None</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although this database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, it is released on condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized use. Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Project level information</formname>
          <formcont>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), in cooperation with the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS) and St. Cloud State University (SCSU), identified the occurrence of contaminants of emerging concern (CECs) in water and bottom sediment colleted in 2014 at 65 sites throughout the Great Lakes Basin. The 2014 effort is part of a long-term study that began in 2010.   </formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7TH8JS6</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160408</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Sarah Elliott</cntper>
          <cntorg>U. S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>2280 Woodale Drive</address>
          <city>Mounds View</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55112</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>763-783-3130</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>selliott@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>