<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Sarah M. Elliott, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Kathy E. Lee, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Sue K. Langer, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Molly M. McCool, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Michael A. Menheer, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Mark E. Brigham, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Edward T. Furlong, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>William T. Foreman, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Zachary G. Jorgenson, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
        <origin>Steven J. Choy, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
        <origin>Jeremy N. Moore, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
        <origin>Jo A. Banda, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
        <origin>Daniel J. Gefell, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
        <origin>Heiko L, Schoenfuss, St. Cloud State University</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Chemicals of Emerging Concern in Water and Bottom Sediment in the Great Lakes Basin, 2014 - Field and Laboratory Quality Assurance</title>
        <geoform>Tabular data</geoform>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7TH8JS6</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), in cooperation with the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS) and St. Cloud State University (SCSU), identified the occurrence of chemicals of emerging concern (CECs) in water and bottom sediment collected in 2014 at 65 sites throughout the Great Lakes Basin. The 2014 effort is part of a long-term study that began in 2010. Included in this directory are collection methods, references to or descriptions of analytical methods used, data for samples collected in 2014, and associated quality-assurance data. Samples were collected during the periods of April to May and August to September by USGS, USFWS, and (or) SCSU personnel. Study sites include tributaries to the Great Lakes located near Green Bay, Wisconsin; Chicago, Illinois; Detroit, Michigan; Grand Rapids, Michigan; Cleveland, Ohio; and Wanakena, New York. During this study, 204 environmental samples and 6 field replicate sample pairs of surface water, 6 field blank-water samples, and 4 laboratory-matrix spike water samples were collected or prepared. Additionally, 21 environmental samples, 3 field replicate sample pairs, and 2 laboratory-matrix spike samples of bottom sediments were collected or prepared. At 22 select water-quality sites, polar organic chemical integrative samplers (POCIS) were deployed in water and analyzed for a similar suite of CECs as were measured in water and bottom-sediment samples. A total of 22 environmental samples, 4 field-blank samples (exposed to ambient air), and 4 field replicate sample pairs were collected or prepared. Water and bottom-sediment samples were prepared and analyzed at the USGS National Water Quality Laboratory (NWQL) in Denver, Colorado. All POCIS samples were extracted at the Environmental Sampling Technologies Laboratory in St. Joseph, Missouri. Extracts were sent to NWQL where final preparation steps and analyses were completed. The Field and Laboratory Quality Assurance provides eight tables that support the analytical results for wastewater compounds, steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A, and pharmaceuticals in water, sediment, and POCIS samples collected during 2014.</abstract>
      <purpose>The U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service initiated the study through the Great Lakes Restoration Initiative as an early warning program to detect and identify emerging contaminants and to evaluate the effects of these contaminants on fish and wildlife.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Suggested citation: Elliott, S.M., Lee, K.E., Brigham, M.E., Langer, S.K., McCool, M.M., Menheer, M.A., Furlong, E.T., Foreman, W.T., Jorgenson, Z.G., Choy, S.J., Moore, J.N., Banda, J.A., Gefell, D.J., and Schoenfuss, H.L., 2016, Chemicals of Emerging Concern in Water and Bottom Sediment in the Great Lakes Basin, 2014 - Analytical Methods, Collection Methods, Quality-Assruance Analyses, and Data: U.S. Geological Survey Data Release, http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7TH8JS6.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>201404</begdate>
          <enddate>201409</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Great Lakes Basin</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-93.2231979370117</westbc>
        <eastbc>-73.6395492553711</eastbc>
        <northbc>48.3042488098145</northbc>
        <southbc>40.4067077636719</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Area of Concern</themekey>
        <themekey>Emerging Contaminants</themekey>
        <themekey>Toxicology</themekey>
        <themekey>Great Lakes Restoration Initiative</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Great Lakes</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Sarah Elliott</cntper>
          <cntorg>U. S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <address>2280 Woodale Drive</address>
          <city>Mounds View</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55112</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>763-783-3130</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>selliott@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>U.S. Geological Survey, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, and St. Cloud State University</datacred>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Lee, K.E.</origin>
        <origin>Langer, S.K.</origin>
        <origin>Menheer, M.A.</origin>
        <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
        <origin>Furlong, E.T.</origin>
        <origin>Smith, S.G.</origin>
        <pubdate>2012</pubdate>
        <title>Chemicals of emerging concern in water and bottom sediment in Great Lakes areas of concern, 2010-2011—Collection methods, analyses methods, quality assurance, and data</title>
        <geoform>Publication</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series</sername>
          <issue>Data Series 723, 26 p.</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/ds/723/</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Lee, K.E. </origin>
        <origin>Langer, S.K.</origin>
        <origin>Menheer, M.A.</origin>
        <origin>Hansen, D.S.</origin>
        <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
        <origin>Furlong, E.T.</origin>
        <origin>Jorgenson, Z.G.</origin>
        <origin>Choy, S.J.</origin>
        <origin>Moore, J.N.</origin>
        <origin>Banda, JoAnn</origin>
        <origin>Gefell, D.J.</origin>
        <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
        <title>Chemicals of emerging concern in water and bottom sediment in the Great Lakes Basin, 2012—Collection methods, analytical methods, quality assurance, and study data</title>
        <geoform>Publication</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series</sername>
          <issue>Data Series 910, 14 p.</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds910</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Several quality-control measures were implemented in the field and at the Environmental Sampling Technologies Laboratory and the USGS National Water Quality Laboratory to evaluate the integrity of the data being generated. Sample replicates and blank samples were collected in the field. Surrogate standards, isotope dilution standards, matrix spikes, reagent blank-water spikes, reagent blank-sand samples, POCIS method blank samples, and POCIS method spikes were prepared in the laboratory. Quality-control measures used in 2014 were similar to those used in previous years of the study. Detailed descriptions and how the quality-assurance data are used can be found in Lee and others (2012) for data collected in 2010-11 and in Lee and others (2015) for data collected in 2012 for the same study.                                                             
</attraccr>
      <attraccr>Field Quality Assurance:   
Field blank-water samples were collected to assess potential contamination sources introduced during sample collection and processing. Six field blank-water samples were collected in 2014; analytical results are included in '2014WaterData' at https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/547dfe43e4b09357f05f6c0c. At least one compound was detected in three of the field blank-water samples. Three wastewater compounds were detected in one field blank-water sample and one sterol was detected in the other two field blank-water samples. Environmental concentrations less than three times the highest field blank concentration were considered to be affected by blank-related contamination and assigned a ‘Cf’ qualifier, which is located immediately after the analytical result in '2014WaterData'. A total of 106 water samples were considered affected by blank-related contamination for cholesterol analyzed using methods for schedule 4433; 42 samples for cholesterol analyzed using methods for schedule 4434; 141 samples for DEET; 74 samples for triphenyl phosphate; and 8 samples for tris (2-butoxyethyl) phosphate.                                                                                        
Field blank-POCIS samples were collected to assess potential contamination sources introduced during sampler deployment, retrieval, and processing. Four field blank-POCIS samples were collected in 2014; analytical results are included in '2014POCISData' at https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/547dfe43e4b09357f05f6c0c. At least one compound was detected in every field blank-POCIS sample. Nineteen to twenty-one wastewater compounds were detected in each field blank-POCIS sample. Acetophenone, benzophenone, cholesterol, cumene, d-limonene, diethyl phthalate, diethylhexylphthalate, methyl salicylate, tetrachloroethene, triclosan, and triphenyl phosphate all had detections in field blank-POCIS samples at or above environmental concentrations and therefore, all results were considered affected by blank contamination and reported as non-detects. One sterol (cholesterol) analyzed by research method 8092 (hormones) was detected in all field blank-POCIS samples. Cholesterol detections in the field blank-POCIS samples were all less than detections in the extraction blank-POCIS samples, and therefore environmental concentrations were flagged for potential contamination according to extraction blank-POCIS concentrations. 
Field replicate samples were collected to assess variability in results from point of sample collection through analysis. Variability was characterized by calculating the relative percent difference for each compound between each replicate pair. A summary of relative percent difference and detection consistency for water and sediment field replicate samples is provided in '2014ReplicateSamples'. Relative percent difference is calculated by dividing the absolute difference in environmental concentrations between the environmental and replicate samples by the mean concentration of the two samples and multiplying by 100.  Six water replicate sample pairs were collected during 2014; analytical results are included in ‘2014WaterData’ at https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/547dfe43e4b09357f05f6c0c. Mean relative percent differences ranged from 0 to 100 for wastewater compounds (schedule 4433) in unfiltered water, 5.7 to 60 for pharmaceuticals (schedule 2440) in filtered water, and 5.4 to 8.2 for steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A (schedule 4434) in unfiltered water. Three bottom-sediment replicate sample pairs were collected during 2014. Mean relative percent differences ranged from 0 to 109 for wastewater compounds (schedule 5433) and 15 to 170 for hormones (research method 6434). Six replicate sample pairs were analyzed for pharmaceuticals (research method 9008); mean relative percent differences ranged from 4.8 to 97 for pharmaceuticals. Four POCIS replicate sample pairs were collected during 2014; analytical results are included in ‘2014POCISData’ at https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/547dfe43e4b09357f05f6c0c. Mean relative percent differences ranged from 2.4 to 63 for wastewater compounds (research method 8068), 16 to 69 for hormones (research method 8092), and 7.2 to 141 for pharmaceuticals (research method 8240).</attraccr>
      <attraccr>Laboratory Quality Assurance:  
This directory includes summaries of compound detections in laboratory-blank samples, percent recovery of laboratory reagent-matrix spike samples, surrogate standards, isotope dilution standard (IDS) compounds and laboratory-matrix spike samples that were analyzed with environmental samples.  
Laboratory blank samples are reagent-water (blank-water samples) or baked reagent-sand samples (blank-sediment samples) simultaneously analyzed with environmental samples that provide information about potential contamination introduced during sample preparation and analysis at the laboratory. '2014WaterSedLabBlankDetections' provides a summary of compounds detected in laboratory blank-water and blank-sediment samples analyzed with environmental samples collected during 2014. One wastewater compound analyzed with schedule 4433, 35 pharmaceuticals analyzed with schedule 2440, and 6 hormones analyzed with schedule 4434, were detected in at least one laboratory blank-water sample; several chemicals within each analytical schedule were detected at concentrations that may have affected results of the environmental samples (denoted with a ‘v’ in ‘2014WaterData’). One compound was detected in at least one laboratory blank-sediment sample analyzed with schedule 5433. Fourteen compounds were detected in laboratory blank-sediment samples analyzed with research method 9008; however, concentrations were not determined to affect environmental results. One compound was detected in laboratory blank-sediment samples analyzed with schedule 6434.
Laboratory blank-POCIS method samples were prepared during both the extraction step at Environmental Sampling Technologies Laboratory (EST) and the final preparation and analyses steps at the USGS National Water Quality Laboratory (NWQL). '2014POCISLaboratoryBlankDetections' provides a summary of compounds detected in laboratory blank-POCIS samples prepared during 2014. Two wastewater compounds analyzed with research method 8068 were detected in at least one EST laboratory blank-POCIS sample. Concentrations of wastewater compounds in the EST laboratory blank-POCIS samples commonly were not substantially greater than concentrations in environmental samples; thus, environmental samples were coded with a ‘Cl’ to indicate potential contamination from laboratory methods. No wastewater compounds were detected in the NWQL laboratory blank-POCIS sample. One pharmaceutical was detected in at least one EST laboratory blank-POCIS sample. Cholesterol was the only compound detected in EST laboratory blank-POCIS samples for compounds analyzed using research method 8092. All but four environmental samples were considered to be affected by blank-related contamination and flagged with a ‘Cl’. 
Laboratory reagent-spike samples are reagent-water (for reagent-water spikes) and ashed sand (for reagent-sediment spikes) matrix samples spiked with a known concentration of select chemicals that provide information about method performance with time, in the absence of sample matrix. Summaries of recoveries in laboratory reagent-water and reagent-sediment spikes are provided in ‘2014LaboratoryReagentSpikes’. In water, mean percent recovery of wastewater compounds (schedule 4433) ranged from 31 to 102, excluding bis(2-ethylhexyl)phthalate which had a mean percent recovery of 306. Five wastewater compounds (3-tert-butyl-4-hydroxyanisole; 3,4-dichlorophenyl isocyanate; 5-methyl-1H-benzotriazole; cotinine; and d-limonene) had mean percent recoveries less than 60; thus, environmental sample results associated with these compounds should be interpreted with caution. Mean percent recovery of pharmaceuticals (schedule 2440) ranged from 40 to 115. Mean percent recoveries for promethazine and tamoxifen were less than 60; thus, environmental sample results associated with those compounds should be interpreted with caution. Mean percent recovery of hormones (schedule 4434) ranged from 76 to 112; all within the acceptable range of recovery (W.T. Foreman and R.B. Green, U.S. Geological Survey National Water Quality Laboratory, written communication, 2014).  In bottom-sediment samples, mean percent recovery of wastewater compounds (schedule 5433) ranged from 11 to 127. Mean percent recovery of 19 wastewater compounds (schedule 5433) was less than 60; thus, environmental sample results associated with those compounds should be interpreted with caution. Mean percent recovery of pharmaceuticals (research method 9008) ranged from 4.3 to 220. Mean percent recovery for 27 compounds was less than 60; thus, environmental sample results associated with those compounds should be interpreted with caution. Furthermore, mean percent recovery for six compounds (buproprion, cimetidine, erythromycin, miconazole, ranitidine, and sulfamethoxazole) was less than 20 indicating very poor recovery of those pharmaceuticals was achieved with research method 9008. Mean percent recovery of steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A (custom method 6434) ranged from 63 to 120; all within the acceptable range of recovery.
Surrogate standards and IDS compounds are similar in structure to several of the target method compounds and are used to monitor sample-specific laboratory procedural performance. Additionally, IDS compounds are used to correct chemical concentrations of environmental samples in methods 4434 and 6434. Mean recoveries, standard deviations, and relative standard deviations (absolute value of the coefficient of variation) for surrogate standards and IDS compounds are provided in '2014SurrogateRecoveries'. Mean percent recovery of surrogate compounds analyzed with laboratory schedule 4433 ranged from 49 to 81. Caffeine-13C6 and decafluorobiphenyl had percent recoveries less than 60. Mean percent recovery of IDS compounds analyzed with laboratory schedule 2440 ranged from 82 to 128; all within the acceptable range of recovery. Mean percent recovery of IDS compounds analyzed with laboratory schedule 4434 ranged from 23 to 81. Medroxyprogesterone-d3, progesterone-2,3,4-13C3, and trans-diethyl-1,1,1’,1’-d4-stilbesterol-3,3,5’,5’-d4 had mean percent recoveries less than 60. In bottom-sediment samples, mean percent recovery of surrogate compounds analyzed with schedule 5433 ranged from 14 to 81. Mean percent recovery of decafluorobiphenyl was less than 20. Mean percent recovery of surrogate compounds analyzed with research method 9008 ranged from 0.02 to 2, indicating poor recovery of the method compounds.  Mean percent recovery of IDS compounds analyzed with schedule 6434 ranged from 9 to 51; all surrogate compounds analyzed with schedule 6434 had mean percent recoveries less than 60. In POCIS samples, mean percent recovery of surrogate compounds analyzed with research method 8068 ranged from 100 to 128; all within the acceptable range of recovery. Mean percent recovery of surrogate compounds analyzed with research method 8240 ranged from 61 to 192; 11 of the surrogate compounds for this method had mean percent recoveries greater than 120. Additionally, several individual surrogate recoveries were greater than 200; thus, analytical data obtained from reasearch method 8240 should be interpreted with caution. Mean percent recovery of IDS compounds analyzed with research method 8092 ranged from 56 to 89; progesterone-2,3,4-13C3 had a mean percent recovery less than 60. 
Laboratory-matrix spike samples for water and bottom sediment were prepared to evaluate recovery performance of compounds in samples collected at specific sites. Recovery of method chemicals and statistics for laboratory-matrix spike samples are provided in '2014WaterMatrixSpikeRecovery' and '2014SedimentMatrixSpikeRecovery'. Three laboratory-matrix spike water samples were collected during 2014. Mean percent recovery for wastewater compounds (schedule4433) in unfiltered water ranged from 23 to 108. Mean percent recovery for pharmaceuticals (schedule 2440) ranged from 25 to 160. Mean percent recovery for hormones (schedule 4434) in unfiltered water ranged from 69 to 119. Mean recoveries for most compounds in these methods were within the range (60-120) of what is typically deemed to be acceptable. Two laboratory-matrix spike bottom-sediment samples were prepared during 2014. Mean percent recovery of wastewater compounds (schedule 5433) ranged from 50 to 253. Several compounds had mean percent recoveries greater than 150. Environmental sample results should be analyzed with caution and after consideration of matrix spike recoveries. Four laboratory matrix spike bottom-sediment samples were prepared during 2014 to evaluate recovery of compounds using research method 9008. Excluding buproprion and sulfamethoxazole, mean percent recovery of pharmaceuticals (research method 9008) in bottom-sediment samples ranged from 0.6 to 7.9. Buproprion was not recovered from any of the laboratory matrix spike samples. Recovery of sulfamethoxazole in one of the laboratory matrix spike samples was negative, indicating substantial matrix interference from that sample. Mean percent recovery of hormones (research method 6434) ranged from 73 to 279; 12 of these compounds had mean recoveries greater than 150.                                                                                                              
Four laboratory-matrix spike POCIS samples were prepared at EST labs during sample extraction for analyses of wastewater compounds, hormones, and pharmaceuticals (research methods 8068, 8092, and 8240, respectively). One laboratory-matrix spike was prepared at NWQL during final sample preparation for analyses of wastewater compounds (research method 8068) and pharmaceuticals (research method 8240), and three laboratory-matrix spikes were prepared at NWQL for analyses of hormones (research method 8092) ('2014POCISMethodSpikeRecovery'). Mean percent recovery of wastewater compounds in EST method spikes ranged from 20 to 229. Five compounds had mean percent recoveries less than 60 and eight compounds had mean percent recoveries greater than 120. Percent recovery of wastewater compounds in the NWQL method spike ranged from 79 to 120, all within the range of acceptable recoveries. Excluding four pharmaceuticals, mean percent recovery of pharmaceuticals in EST method spikes ranged from 0.53 to 482. Desmethyldiltiazem, ezetimibe, tiotropium, and valacyclovir were not recovered in any of the EST laboratory-matrix spikes. Additionally, 1,7-dimethylxanthine, diltiazem, famotidine, hydrocortisone, lamivudine, methotrexate, prednisolone, prednisone, and ranitidine were not detected in at least one of the EST laboratory-matrix spikes and generally had low recoveries. Forty-five pharmaceuticals had mean percent recoveries less than 60 and 25 had mean percent recoveries less than 20. Caffeine and sulfamethoxazole had mean percent recoveries greater than 200. Mean percent recovery of pharmaceuticals in NWQL method spikes ranged from 6.3 to 145. Twenty-eight pharmaceuticals had mean percent recoveries less than 60 for the NWQL method spikes; tamoxifen was the only pharmaceutical with a mean percent recovery less than 20. Acyclovir was the only pharmaceutical with a mean percent recovery greater than 120. Mean percent recovery of hormones in EST method spikes ranged from 55 to 150. Norethindrone was the only compound with a mean percent recovery less than 60, whereas three compounds (cholesterol, dihydrotestosterone, and epitestosterone) had mean percent recoveries greater than 120. Mean percent recovery of hormones in NWQL method spikes ranged from 75 to 120; all within the range of acceptable recoveries.
</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. All sites that were sampled during 2014 are represented in the data set.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>both</methtype>
        <methdesc>Collection Methods:
Methods used to collect environmental samples in 2014 followed methods used in previous years of the study and are provided in detail in Lee and others (2012) for data collected in 2010-11 and in Lee and others (2015) for data collected in 2012 for the same study. Briefly, water samples were collected from streams and lakes using a modified depth-integrated sampling method with a weighted bottle sampler fitted with a 1-liter, glass bottle. Bottom-sediment samples were collected to include the most recently deposited bottom-sediment deposition (top 10 centimeters) using a stainless steel Ekman dredge. All samples were collected with inert materials and sampling personnel avoided the use of personal-care items (with the exception of sun screen) such as insect repellent, cologne, aftershave, and perfume. POCIS samplers were deployed at select sites for a period of 14 days. The samplers were stored in sealed storage containers at less than 5 degrees Celsius until deployment. Upon arriving at the site, POCIS samplers were removed from their storage containers and placed into a deployment canister. As soon as possible after placing the sampler in the deployment canister, the canister was placed in a 1.25-meter long metal tube and submerged under water. The tube was fastened to an attachment structure above the sediment surface with metal ties. When field blanks were collected, the storage container containing the field blank was opened before deployment of the environmental POCIS sampler and closed after the deployed sampler was securely anchored in the water. The field blank procedure was repeated upon retrieval of the associated POCIS samplers. 

Analytical methods:
Water samples were analyzed for more than 200 chemicals at the USGS National Water Quality Laboratory (NWQL) using methods for wastewater compounds in unfiltered water (schedule 4433; Zaugg and others, 2006), steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A (referred to as hormones throughout) in unfiltered water (schedule 4434; Foreman and others, 2012), and pharmaceuticals in filtered water (schedule 2440; Furlong and others, 2014). Bottom-sediment samples were analyzed for more than 100 chemicals at the NWQL using methods for wastewater compounds (schedule 5433; Burkhardt and others, 2006), steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A (referred to as hormones throughout) (research method 6434; described in Fischer and others, 2015), and pharmaceuticals and antidepressants (research method 9008; described in Lee and others, 2012; 2015). 

Wastewater compounds, hormones, and pharmaceuticals were eluted from POCIS discs at the Environmental Sampling Technologies Laboratory (EST) in St. Joseph, Missouri. Wastewater compounds were extracted from the two discs separately using 20-25 milliliters (mL) 20% methyl tertiary butyl ether/dichloromethane mixture per disc. Hormones and pharmaceuticals were extracted using 20-25 mL methanol per disc that was pooled after extraction for blowdown and filtration. Two discs for each analytical method were deployed, so eluent from both discs was combined in a single vial for a given schedule. Eluents were then sent to the USGS National Water Quality Laboratory for final processing and analyses. POCIS extracts were analyzed for more than 200 chemicals at the NWQL using methods based on those established for wastewater compounds in unfiltered water (Zaugg and others, 2006), hormones in unfiltered water (Foreman and others, 2012), and pharmaceuticals in filtered water (Furlong, 2014). Ten chemicals included in the wastewater compound schedule [polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons and pentbromodiphenyl ether (PBDE-47)] were omitted from reporting (as indicated with a 'NR' in 2014POCISData.xlsx) because they are poorly sampled by POCIS and no data are available to support the use of POCIS for those chemicals (D.A. Alvarez, USGS Columbia Environmental Research Center, written communication, 2015). Any discussion regarding environmental and quality-assurance data does not include those compounds.</methdesc>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Burkhardt, M.R.</origin>
            <origin>Zaugg, S.D.</origin>
            <origin>Smith, S.G.</origin>
            <origin>ReVello, R.C.</origin>
            <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of wastewater compounds in sediment and soil by pressurized solvent extraction, solid-phase extraction, and capillary-column gas chromatography/mass spectrometry</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods</sername>
              <issue>book 5, chap. B2, 40 p.</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/tm/2006/tm5b2/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Fischer, J.M.</origin>
            <origin>Phillips, P.J.</origin>
            <origin>Reilly, T.J.</origin>
            <origin>Focazio, M.J.</origin>
            <origin>Loftin, K.A.</origin>
            <origin>Benzel, W.M.</origin>
            <origin>Jones, D.K.</origin>
            <origin>Smalling, K.L.</origin>
            <origin>Fisher, S.C.</origin>
            <origin>Fisher, I.J.</origin>
            <origin>Iwanowicz, L.R.</origin>
            <origin>Romanok, K.M.</origin>
            <origin>Jenkins, D.</origin>
            <origin>Bowers, L.</origin>
            <origin>Boehlke, A.</origin>
            <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
            <origin>Deetz, A.C.</origin>
            <origin>Carper, L.G.</origin>
            <origin>Imbrigiotta, T.E.</origin>
            <origin>Birdwell, J.</origin>
            <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
            <title>Estuarine bed-sediment-quality data collected in New Jersey and New York after Hurricane Sandy, 2013</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series</sername>
              <issue>Data Series 905, 42 p.</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds905</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
            <origin>Gray, J.L.</origin>
            <origin>ReVello, R.C.</origin>
            <origin>Lindley, C.E.</origin>
            <origin>Losche, S.A.</origin>
            <origin>Barber, L.B.</origin>
            <pubdate>2012</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of steroid hormones and related compounds in filtered and unfiltered water by solid-phase extraction, derivatization, and gas chromatography with tandem mass spectrometry</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods</sername>
              <issue>book 5, chap. B9, 118 p.</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/tm/5b9/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Furlong, E.T.</origin>
            <origin>Noriega, M.C.</origin>
            <origin>Kanagy, C.J.</origin>
            <origin>Kanagy, L.K.</origin>
            <origin>Coffey, L.J.</origin>
            <origin>Burkhardt, M.R.</origin>
            <pubdate>2014</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of human-use pharmaceuticals in filtered water by direct aqueous injection–high-performance liquid chromatography/tandem mass spectrometry</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods</sername>
              <issue>book 5, chap. B10, 49 p.</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/tm5B10</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Zaugg, S.D.</origin>
            <origin>Smith, S.G.</origin>
            <origin>Schroeder, M.P.</origin>
            <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of wastewater compounds in 
whole water by continuous liquid–liquid extraction and capillary-column gas 
chromatography/mass spectrometry</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods</sername>
              <issue>book 5, chap. B4, 30 p.
</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/tm/2006/05B04/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
            <title>National Field Manual for the Collection of Water-Quality Data</title>
            <edition>book 9, chaps. A1–A9</edition>
            <geoform>None</geoform>
            <onlink>http://pubs.water.usgs.gov/twri9A</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Downloaded data from the USGS National Water Information System.
Verified all samples were accounted for and had all the appropriate data associated with them.</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>The Field and Laboratory Quality Assurance provides data related to the analytical results (Environmental Data) for wastewater compounds, steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A, and pharmaceuticals in water, sediment, and POCIS samples collected during 2014. 
Eight files are included in this directory that summarize quality-assurance results including those associated with laboratory blank samples, laboratory reagent- and matrix-spike recoveries, replicate samples, and surrogate recoveries.   </eaover>
      <eadetcit>None</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although this database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, it is released on condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized use. Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Project level information</formname>
          <formcont>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), in cooperation with the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS) and St. Cloud State University (SCSU), identified the occurrence of contaminants of emerging concern (CECs) in water and bottom sediment collected in 2014 at 65 sites throughout the Great Lakes Basin. The 2014 effort is part of a long-term study that began in 2010.   </formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7TH8JS6</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160408</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Sarah Elliott</cntper>
          <cntorg>U. S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>2280 Woodale Drive</address>
          <city>Mounds View</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55112</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>763-783-3130</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>selliott@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>