<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Sarah M Elliott</origin>
        <origin>Kathy E Lee</origin>
        <origin>Sue Langer</origin>
        <origin>Molly M Trombley</origin>
        <origin>Michael A Menheer</origin>
        <origin>Mark E Brigham</origin>
        <origin>Edward T Furlong</origin>
        <origin>William T Foreman</origin>
        <origin>Zachary Jorgenson</origin>
        <origin>Steven Choy</origin>
        <origin>Jeremy Moore</origin>
        <origin>JoAnn Banda</origin>
        <origin>Daniel J Gefell</origin>
        <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
        <title>Chemicals of Emerging Concern in Water and Bottom Sediment in Great Lakes Areas of Concern, 2013 - Environmental Data</title>
        <geoform>Tabular data</geoform>
        <onlink>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/547368c7e4b0b935bc76d0a0</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), in cooperation with the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS) and the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), identified the occurrence of contaminants of emerging concern (CECs) in water and bottom sediments collected in 2013 at 57 sites throughout the Great Lakes Basin. The 2013 effort is part of a long-term study that began in 2010. Included in this directory are collection methods, references to or descriptions of analytical methods used, data for samples collected in 2013, and associated quality-assurance data.   

Samples were collected from April through October 2013 by USGS, USFWS, and/or EPA personnel. Study sites include tributaries to the Great Lakes located near Duluth, Minnesota; Kewaunee, Wisconsin; Appleton, Wisconsin; Detroit, Michigan; Grand Rapids, Michigan; St Clair, Michigan; Cleveland, Ohio; Wanakena, New York; and Potsdam, New York (see "2013 Site List"). During this study, 93 environmental samples and 6 field replicate sample pairs of surface water, 3 field blank water samples, and 3 laboratory-matrix spike water samples were collected or prepared. Additionally, 49 environmental samples, 4 field replicate sample pairs, and two laboratory-matrix spike samples of bottom sediment were collected or prepared. Water and bottom-sediment samples were analyzed at the USGS National Water Quality Laboratory in Denver, Colorado, for a broad suite of CECs.

The Environmental Data provides 4 tables that describes the analytical results for wastewater compounds, steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A, and pharmaceuticals in water and wastewater compounds, steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A, pharmaceuticals, and antidepressants in bottom-sediment samples collected during 2013.</abstract>
      <purpose>The Fish and Wildlife Service initiated the study through the Great Lakes Restoration Initiative as an early warning program to detect and identify emerging contaminants and to evaluate the effects of these contaminants on fish and wildlife.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Suggested citation (USE THIS): Elliott, S.M., Lee, K.E., Brigham, M.E., Langer, S.K., Trombley, M.M., Menheer, M.A., Furlong, E.T., Foreman, W.T., Jorgenson, Z.G., Choy, S.J., Moore, J.N., Banda, J.B., and Gefell, D.J., 2015, Chemicals of emerging concern in water and bottom sediment in the Great Lakes Basin 2013 - Analytical methods, Collection methods, Environmental Data, and Quality Assurance: U.S. Geological Survey Data Release, http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7DF6P9D.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>201304</begdate>
          <enddate>201310</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Great Lakes Basin</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-93.2231979370117</westbc>
        <eastbc>-73.6395492553711</eastbc>
        <northbc>48.3042488098145</northbc>
        <southbc>40.4067077636719</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Area of Concern</themekey>
        <themekey>Emerging Contaminants</themekey>
        <themekey>Toxicology</themekey>
        <themekey>Great Lakes Restoration Initiative</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Great Lakes</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>Use of the data provided herein should proceed only after the Field and Laboratory Quality Assurance (https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/54733f7fe4b0b935bc76cecd) data have been reviewed and taken into consideration.   </useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Sarah Elliott</cntper>
          <cntorg>U. S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <address>2280 Woodale Drive</address>
          <city>Mounds View</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55112</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>763-783-3130</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>selliott@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>U.S. Geological Survey, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, and U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</datacred>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Lee, K.E.</origin>
        <origin>Langer, S.K.</origin>
        <origin>Menheer, M.A.</origin>
        <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
        <origin>Furlong, E.T.</origin>
        <origin>Smith, S.G.</origin>
        <pubdate>2012</pubdate>
        <title>Chemicals of emerging concern in water and bottom sediment in Great Lakes areas of concern, 2010-2011—Collection methods, analyses methods, quality assurance, and data</title>
        <geoform>Publication</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series</sername>
          <issue>Data Series 723, 26 p.</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/ds/723/</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Lee, K.E. </origin>
        <origin>Langer, S.K.</origin>
        <origin>Menheer, M.A.</origin>
        <origin>Hansen, D.S.</origin>
        <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
        <origin>Furlong, E.T.</origin>
        <origin>Jorgenson, Z.G.</origin>
        <origin>Choy, S.J.</origin>
        <origin>Moore, J.N.</origin>
        <origin>Banda, JoAnn</origin>
        <origin>Gefell, D.J.</origin>
        <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
        <title>Chemicals of emerging concern in water and bottom sediment in the Great Lakes Basin, 2012—Collection methods, analytical methods, quality assurance, and study data</title>
        <geoform>Publication</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series</sername>
          <issue>Data Series 910, 14 p.</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds910</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Several quality-control measures were implemented both in the field and at the laboratory to evaluate the integrity of the data being generated. Sample replicates and blank samples were collected in the field. Surrogate standards, isotope dilution standards, matrix spikes, reagent blank-water spikes, and reagent blank-sediment samples were prepared in the laboratory. Quality control measures used in 2013 were similar to those used in previous years of the study. Detailed descriptions and how the quality-assurance data are used can be found in Lee and others (2012) for data collected in 2010-11 and in Lee and others (2015) for data collected in 2012 for the same study. The following calculations were used to analyze the quality assurance samples: relative percent difference between field replicates, detections in field and lab-blank samples, and percent recovery of surrogate standards, isotope dilution standards, matrix spikes, and laboratory-blank spikes.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. All sites that were sampled during 2013 are represented in the data set.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>both</methtype>
        <methdesc>Collection Methods:
Methods used to collect environmental samples in 2013 followed methods used in previous years of the study and are provided in detail in Lee and others (2012) for data collected in 2010/11 and in Lee and others (2015) for data collected in 2012 for the same study. Briefly, water samples were collected from streams and lakes using a modified depth-integrated sampling method with a weighted bottle sampler fitted with a 1-liter, glass bottle. Bottom-sediment samples were collected to include the most recently deposited bottom-sediment deposition (top 10 centimeters) using a stainless steel Ekman dredge. All samples were collected with inert materials and sampling personnel avoided the use of personal-care items such as insect repellent, cologne, aftershave, and perfume.   

Analytical methods:
Water samples were analyzed for more than 200 chemicals (see 2013 Chemicals Analyzed) at the USGS National Water Quality Laboratory (NWQL) using methods for wastewater compounds in unfiltered water (schedule 4433; Zaugg and others, 2006), steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A in unfiltered water (schedule 4434; Foreman and others, 2012), pharmaceuticals in unfiltered water (research method 8244; Phillips and others, 2010), and pharmaceuticals in filtered water (schedule 2440; Furlong and others, 2014). Bottom-sediment samples were analyzed for more than 100 chemicals at the NWQL using methods for wastewater compounds (schedule 5433; Burkhardt and others, 2006), steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A  (research method 6434; described in Fischer and others, 2015), and pharmaceuticals and antidepressants (research method 9008; described in Lee and others, 2012; 2015).   

Research method 8244 for pharmaceuticals in unfiltered water follows the method of schedule 4433 for wastewater compounds in unfiltered water; a more detailed method description, along with method performance in wastewater effluent is contained in Zaugg and others (2006).    

For more information on the Collection and Analytical Methods, see https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/546cf046e4b0fc7976bf1d39.</methdesc>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Burkhardt, M.R.</origin>
            <origin>Zaugg, S.D.</origin>
            <origin>Smith, S.G.</origin>
            <origin>ReVello, R.C.</origin>
            <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of wastewater compounds in sediment and soil by pressurized solvent extraction, solid-phase extraction, and capillary-column gas chromatography/mass spectrometry</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods</sername>
              <issue>book 5, chap. B2, 40 p.</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/tm/2006/tm5b2/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Fischer, J.M.</origin>
            <origin>Phillips, P.J.</origin>
            <origin>Reilly, T.J.</origin>
            <origin>Focazio, M.J.</origin>
            <origin>Loftin, K.A.</origin>
            <origin>Benzel, W.M.</origin>
            <origin>Jones, D.K.</origin>
            <origin>Smalling, K.L.</origin>
            <origin>Fisher, S.C.</origin>
            <origin>Fisher, I.J.</origin>
            <origin>Iwanowicz, L.R.</origin>
            <origin>Romanok, K.M.</origin>
            <origin>Jenkins, D.</origin>
            <origin>Bowers, L.</origin>
            <origin>Boehlke, A.</origin>
            <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
            <origin>Deetz, A.C.</origin>
            <origin>Carper, L.G.</origin>
            <origin>Imbrigiotta, T.E.</origin>
            <origin>Birdwell, J.</origin>
            <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
            <title>Estuarine bed-sediment-quality data collected in New Jersey and New York after Hurricane Sandy, 2013</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series</sername>
              <issue>Data Series 905, 42 p.</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds905</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
            <origin>Gray, J.L.</origin>
            <origin>ReVello, R.C.</origin>
            <origin>Lindley, C.E.</origin>
            <origin>Losche, S.A.</origin>
            <origin>Barber, L.B.</origin>
            <pubdate>2012</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of steroid hormones and related compounds in filtered and unfiltered water by solid-phase extraction, derivatization, and gas chromatography with tandem mass spectrometry</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods</sername>
              <issue>book 5, chap. B9, 118 p.</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/tm/5b9/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Furlong, E.T.</origin>
            <origin>Noriega, M.C.</origin>
            <origin>Kanagy, C.J.</origin>
            <origin>Kanagy, L.K.</origin>
            <origin>Coffey, L.J.</origin>
            <origin>Burkhardt, M.R.</origin>
            <pubdate>2014</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of human-use pharmaceuticals in filtered water by direct aqueous injection–high-performance liquid chromatography/tandem mass spectrometry</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods</sername>
              <issue>book 5, chap. B10, 49 p.</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/tm5B10</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Phillips, P.J.</origin>
            <origin>Smith, S.G.</origin>
            <origin>Kolpin, D.W.</origin>
            <origin>Zaugg, S.D.</origin>
            <origin>Buston, H.T.</origin>
            <origin>Furlong, E.T.</origin>
            <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
            <title>Method description, quality assurance, environmental data, and other information for analysis of 
pharmaceuticals in wastewater-treatment-plant effluents, streamwater, and reservoirs, 2004-2009
</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report </sername>
              <issue>OFR 2010-1102, 36 p</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2010/1102/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Zaugg, S.D.</origin>
            <origin>Smith, S.G.</origin>
            <origin>Schroeder, M.P.</origin>
            <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
            <title>Determination of wastewater compounds in 
whole water by continuous liquid–liquid extraction and capillary-column gas 
chromatography/mass spectrometry</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods</sername>
              <issue>book 5, chap. B4, 30 p.
</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/tm/2006/05B04/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
            <title>National Field Manual for the Collection of Water-Quality Data</title>
            <edition>book 9, chaps. A1–A9</edition>
            <geoform>None</geoform>
            <onlink>http://pubs.water.usgs.gov/twri9A</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Downloaded data from the USGS National Water Information System.
Verified all samples were accounted for and had all the appropriate data associated with them.</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>The Environmental Data provides analytical results for wastewater compounds, steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A, and pharmaceuticals in water and wastewater compounds, steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A, pharmaceuticals, and antidepressants in bottom-sediment samples collected during 2013. The Collection and Analysis methods (indicated by their number) can be found at ttps://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/546cf046e4b0fc7976bf1d39.

There are four files here including a comparison of data obtained for compounds determined by two pharmaceutical methods (methods 8244 and 2440). The Water Data and Sediment Data provided are as reported by the laboratory, unless otherwise noted, and listed by sample. Data by Result provides all environmental data included in the Water and Sediment Data, listed by compound.

Discussion of number of detections does not include results that were 'v' or 'Cf' coded (potentially affected by lab or field blank contamination). Although it is ultimately up to the data analyst how to use the data, for the purposes of this report, results determined to be affected by contamination were treated as non-detects. Use of the data provided herein should proceed only after the Field and Laboratory Quality Assurance (https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/54733f7fe4b0b935bc76cecd) data have been reviewed and taken into consideration.   

Only a subset of samples were analyzed using both pharmaceutical methods 8244 and 2440 in unfiltered and filtered water, respectively. More pharmaceuticals were detected using the filtered method (schedule 2440) than using the unfiltered method (research method 8244). Sixty percent of the compounds analyzed were either detected by both methods or not detected by either method. The relative percent difference between detected concentrations of any given pharmaceutical using both analytical methods was calculated by dividing the absolute difference in concentrations between the two methods by the mean concentration from the two methods and multiplying by 100. Relative percent difference between detected concentrations of any given pharmaceutical using both analytical methods ranged from 1 to 189 for all samples.  

In unfiltered water samples, 55 of the 69 wastewater compounds analyzed with laboratory schedule 4433 were detected in at least one sample with concentrations ranging from 0.002 to 13.5 micrograms per liter (ug/L). Eleven of the 20 compounds (steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A) analyzed by laboratory schedule 4434 were detected in at least one unfiltered water sample with concentrations ranging from 0.16 to 14,900 nanograms per liter (ng/L). Thirty-three of the 48 pharmaceuticals analyzed by research method 8244 were detected in at least one unfiltered water sample with concentrations ranging from 0.006 to 0.827 ug/L. Eighty-two of the 110 pharmaceuticals analyzed by laboratory schedule 2440 were detected in at least one filtered water sample with concentrations ranging from 0.14 to 27,900 ng/L.  

In bottom-sediment samples, 38 of the 57 wastewater compounds analyzed by laboratory schedule 5433 were detected in at least one sample with concentrations ranging from 1 to 26,200 micrograms per kilogram (ug/kg). Thirteen of the 20 compounds (steroid hormones, sterols, and bisphenol A) analyzed by research method 6434 were detected in at least one sample with concentrations ranging from 0.04 to 11,400 ug/kg. Eighteen of the 20 human-use pharmaceuticals analyzed by research method 9008 were detected in at least one sample with concentrations ranging from 0.02 to 11.2 ug/kg. Five of the 11 antidepressants analyzed by research method 9008 were detected in at least one sample with concentrations ranging from 0.01 to 10.3 ug/kg.


</eaover>
      <eadetcit>None</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. The data has been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although this database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, it is released on condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized use. Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Project level information</formname>
          <formcont>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), in cooperation with the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS) and the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), identified the occurrence of contaminants of emerging concern (CECs) in water and bottom sediment collected in 2013 at 57 sites throughout the Great Lakes Basin. The 2013 effort is part of a long-term study that began in 2010. Included in this directory are references to or descriptions of analytical methods used, collection methods, environmental data, and associated quality-assurance data for samples collected in 2013.    </formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7DF6P9D</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150727</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Sarah Elliott</cntper>
          <cntorg>U. S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>2280 Woodale Drive</address>
          <city>Mounds View</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55112</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>763-783-3130</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>selliott@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>