<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Sarah M. Elliott, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Kathy E. Lee, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Sue K. Langer, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Molly M. McCool, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Michael A. Menheer, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Mark E. Brigham, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Edward T. Furlong, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>William T. Foreman, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <origin>Zachary G. Jorgenson, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
        <origin>Steven J. Choy, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
        <origin>Jeremy N. Moore, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
        <origin>Jo A. Banda, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
        <origin>Daniel J. Gefell, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
        <origin>Heiko L. Schoenfuss, St. Cloud State University</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Chemicals of Emerging Concern in Water and Bottom Sediment in the Great Lakes Basin, 2014 - Analytical Methods, Collection Methods, Quality-Assurance Analyses, and Data</title>
        <geoform>Tabular data</geoform>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7TH8JS6</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), in cooperation with the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS) and St. Cloud State University (SCSU), identified the occurrence of chemicals of emerging concern (CECs) in water and bottom sediment collected in 2014 at 65 sites throughout the Great Lakes Basin. The 2014 effort is part of a long-term study that began in 2010. Included in this directory are collection methods, references to or descriptions of analytical methods used, data for samples collected in 2014, and associated quality-assurance data. Samples were collected during the periods of April to May and August to September by USGS, USFWS, and (or) SCSU personnel. Study sites include tributaries to the Great Lakes located near Green Bay, Wisconsin; Chicago, Illinois; Detroit, Michigan; Grand Rapids, Michigan; Cleveland, Ohio; and Wanakena, New York. During this study, 204 environmental samples and 6 field replicate sample pairs of surface water, 6 field blank-water samples, and 4 laboratory-matrix spike water samples were collected or prepared. Additionally, 21 environmental samples, 3 field replicate sample pairs, and 2 laboratory-matrix spike samples of bottom sediments were collected or prepared. At 22 select water-quality sites, polar organic chemical integrative samplers (POCIS) were deployed in surface waters and analyzed for a similar suite of CECs as were measured in water and bottom-sediment samples. A total of 22 environmental samples, 4 field-blank samples (exposed to ambient air), and 4 field replicate sample pairs were collected or prepared. Water and bottom-sediment samples were prepared and analyzed at the USGS National Water Quality Laboratory (NWQL) in Denver, Colorado. All POCIS samples were extracted at the Environmental Sampling Technologies Laboratory in St. Joseph, Missouri. Extracts were sent to NWQL where final preparation steps and analyses were completed. 
</abstract>
      <purpose>The U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service initiated the study through the Great Lakes Restoration Initiative as an early warning program to detect and identify emerging contaminants and to evaluate the effects of these contaminants on fish and wildlife.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Suggested citation: Elliott, S.M., Lee, K.E., Brigham, M.E., Langer, S.K., McCool, M.M., Menheer, M.A., Furlong, E.T., Foreman, W.T., Jorgenson, Z.G., Choy, S.J., Moore, J.N., Banda, J.A., Gefell, D.J., and Schoenfuss, H.L., 2016, Chemicals of Emerging Concern in Water and Bottom Sediment in the Great Lakes Basin, 2014 - Analytical Methods, Collection Methods, Quality-Assurance Analyses, and Data: U.S. Geological Survey Data Release, http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7TH8JS6.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>201404</begdate>
          <enddate>201409</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Great Lakes Basin</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-93.2231979370117</westbc>
        <eastbc>-73.6395492553711</eastbc>
        <northbc>48.3042488098145</northbc>
        <southbc>40.4067077636719</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Area of Concern</themekey>
        <themekey>Emerging Contaminants</themekey>
        <themekey>Toxicology</themekey>
        <themekey>Great Lakes Restoration Initiative</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Great Lakes</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Sarah Elliott</cntper>
          <cntorg>U. S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <address>2280 Woodale Drive</address>
          <city>Mounds View</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55112</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>763-783-3130</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>selliott@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>U.S. Geological Survey, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, and St. Cloud State University</datacred>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Lee, K.E.</origin>
        <origin>Langer, S.K.</origin>
        <origin>Menheer, M.A.</origin>
        <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
        <origin>Furlong, E.T.</origin>
        <origin>Smith, S.G.</origin>
        <pubdate>2012</pubdate>
        <title>Chemicals of emerging concern in water and bottom sediment in Great Lakes areas of concern, 2010-2011—Collection methods, analyses methods, quality assurance, and data</title>
        <geoform>Publication</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series</sername>
          <issue>Data Series 723, 26 p.</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/ds/723/</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Lee, K.E. </origin>
        <origin>Langer, S.K.</origin>
        <origin>Menheer, M.A.</origin>
        <origin>Hansen, D.S.</origin>
        <origin>Foreman, W.T.</origin>
        <origin>Furlong, E.T.</origin>
        <origin>Jorgenson, Z.G.</origin>
        <origin>Choy, S.J.</origin>
        <origin>Moore, J.N.</origin>
        <origin>Banda, JoAnn</origin>
        <origin>Gefell, D.J.</origin>
        <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
        <title>Chemicals of emerging concern in water and bottom sediment in the Great Lakes Basin, 2012—Collection methods, analytical methods, quality assurance, and study data</title>
        <geoform>Publication</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series</sername>
          <issue>Data Series 910, 14 p.</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds910</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
  </idinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>This is a Project level record. Please see entity and attribute information from the metadata records of each dataset.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>None</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although this database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, it is released on condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized use. Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Environmental Data</formname>
          <formcont>Analytical results for wastewater compounds, hormones, and pharmaceuticals in water, bottom-sediment, and polar organic chemical integrative samplers (POCIS) samples collected during 2014.</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7TH8JS6</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160408</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Sarah Elliott</cntper>
          <cntorg>U. S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>2280 Woodale Drive</address>
          <city>Mounds View</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55112</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>763-783-3130</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>selliott@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>