<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="MetadataWizardStylesheet.xsl"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Jennifer L. Graham</origin>
        <origin>Theodore D. Harris</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Phytoplankton data for Cheney Reservoir near Cheney, Kansas, June 2001 through November 2015</title>
        <geoform>Excel Spreadsheet and Comma Separated Values (CSV) file  </geoform>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F71N7Z7V</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) Data Release provides phytoplankton data collected from Cheney Reservoir, Kansas, during June 2001 through November 2015. All data are reported as raw calculated values and are not rounded to USGS significant figures. This data release was produced in compliance with the open data requirements as a way to make scientific products associated with USGS research efforts and publications available to the public. The dataset includes all routine and quality assurance/quality control samples collected at the long-term sampling site on Cheney Reservoir located near the dam (USGS station identification number 07144790). Phytoplankton were identified to the lowest possible taxonomic level and abundance (density) and biovolume are reported.</abstract>
      <purpose> The data were collected by the USGS Kansas Water Science Center, in cooperation with the City of Wichita, as part of the Cheney Reservoir and Watershed water-quality study. For more information on other datasets collected at this long-term site, see the "Cheney Reservoir and Watershed Water-Quality Studies" webpage at the USGS Kansas Water Science Center website (http://ks.water.usgs.gov/).</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20010622</begdate>
          <enddate>20151109</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Publication Date</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>In work</progress>
      <update>Annually</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>
		Data were collected at the USGS Station Cheney Reservoir nr Cheney, KS (USGS Station Identification Number 07144790). The sampling station is located near the reservoir dam.  
	</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-97.9097</westbc>
        <eastbc>-97.7589</eastbc>
        <northbc>37.8297</northbc>
        <southbc>37.7056</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Freshwater</themekey>
        <themekey>Phytoplankton</themekey>
        <themekey>Algae</themekey>
        <themekey>Taxonomy</themekey>
        <themekey>Taxa</themekey>
	<themekey>Division</themekey>
        <themekey>Genus</themekey>
        <themekey>Species</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Cheney Reservoir</placekey>
        <placekey>Kansas</placekey>
        <placekey>USGS Station ID 07144790</placekey>
        <placekey>United States</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <taxonomy>
      <keywtax>
        <taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
        <taxonkey>Ochrophyta</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>Bacillariophyta</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>Chlorophyta</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>Chrysophyta</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>Cryptophycophyta</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>Cryptophyta</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>Euglenophycota</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>Euglenophyta</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>Cyanophyta</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>Pyrrophycophyta</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>Pyrrophyta</taxonkey>
      </keywtax>
      <taxonsys>
        <ider>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>John Beaver</cntper>
              <cntorg>BSA environmental Services, Inc.</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
              <address>23400 Mercantile Rd, Suite 8</address>
              <city>Beachwood</city>
              <state>OH</state>
              <postal>44122</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>2167650582</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>info@bsaenv.com</cntemail>
          </cntinfo>
        </ider>
        <classsys>
          <classcit>
            <citeinfo>
              <origin>BSA Environmental Services, Inc. BSA has an extensive hard copy and digital reference library, which includes thousands of taxonomic references and keys. Their literature collection is continually expanding as new sources of information become available. In addition, BSA's location allows immediate access to several university libraries. Every effort is made to use the most current taxa names, and any recent changes in nomenclature are noted.</origin>
              <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
              <title>None</title>
              <geoform>None</geoform>
              <pubinfo>
                <pubplace>None</pubplace>
                <publish>None</publish>
              </pubinfo>
              <onlink>None</onlink>
            </citeinfo>
          </classcit>
        </classsys>
	<idref>
		<citeinfo>
        	<origin>Burkholder, J.M. and Wetzel, R.G.</origin>
        	<pubdate>1989</pubdate>
        	<title>Epiphytic microalgae on natural substrata in a hardwater lake: seasonal dynamics of community structure, biomass, and ATP content</title>
        	<geoform>document</geoform>
		<serinfo>
          		<sername>Archiv fur Hydrobiologie. Supplementband</sername>
          		<issue>Volume 83, pages 1-56</issue>
        	</serinfo>
      		</citeinfo>
	</idref>      
	<idref>
		<citeinfo>
        	<origin>Hillenbrand, H., Durselen, C.D., Kirschtel, D., Pollingher, U., and Zohary, T.</origin>
        	<pubdate>1999</pubdate>
        	<title>Biovolume calculation for pelagic and benthic microalgae</title>
        	<geoform>document</geoform>
		<serinfo>
          		<sername>Journal of Phycology</sername>
          		<issue>Volume 35, pages 403-424</issue>
        	</serinfo>
		</citeinfo>
      
	</idref>
	<idref>
		<citeinfo>
        	<origin>Lund, J.W.G., Kipling, C., and LeCren, E.D.</origin>
        	<pubdate>1958</pubdate>
        	<title>The inverted microscope method of estimating algal numbers and the statistical basis of estimates by counting</title>
        	<geoform>document</geoform>
		<serinfo>
          		<sername>Hydrobiologia</sername>
          		<issue>Volume 11, pages 143-170</issue>
        	</serinfo>
      		</citeinfo>
	</idref>
	<idref>      
		<citeinfo>
        	<origin>McNabb, C.D.</origin>
        	<pubdate>1960</pubdate>
        	<title>Enumeration of freshwater phytoplankton concentrated on the membrane filter</title>
        	<geoform>document</geoform>
		<serinfo>
          		<sername>Limnology and Oceanography</sername>
          		<issue>Volume 5, pages 57-61</issue>
        	</serinfo>
      		</citeinfo>
	</idref>
        <taxonpro>Phytoplankton were enumerated to the lowest possible taxonomic level using membrane-filtered slides (McNabb, 1960). A minimum of 400 natural units (colonies, filaments, and unicells) were counted from each sample; in accordance with Lund and others (1958), counting 400 natural units provides accuracy within 90-percent confidence limits. In addition, an entire strip of the filter was counted at high magnification (usually 630 X) along with one-half of the filter at a lower magnification (usually 400 X) to ensure complete species reporting. Cell biovolumes of all identified phytoplankton taxa were quantified. Biovolumes were estimated using formulae for solid geometric shapes that most closely match the cell shape (Hillenbrand et al., 1999). Biovolume calculations were based on measurements of 10 organisms per taxon for each sample, where possible. For taxa with substantial size variation (such as diatoms), size classes were designated arbitrarily to determine average cell size (biovolume). For each taxon, 25 cells were measured from each size class (assuming that sufficient numbers were available). Mean biovolumes within each size class were used to calculate the total biovolume contributed by the taxon to its representative sample (Burkholder and Wetzel, 1989). </taxonpro>
        <taxoncom>Phytoplankton were enumerated to the lowest possible taxonomic level, which was at least to genus for most organisms. Because taxonomy is constantly evolving, and nomenclature changes are common, the historic (circa 2001) phytoplankton nomenclature was used for the Cheney Reservoir data to retain taxonomic continuity. The phytoplankton data collected from Cheney Reservoir during June 2001 through November 2015 contained 151 unique genera in 7 Divisions (Classes). Taxonomic citations are included for the 7 Divisions in the dataset.</taxoncom>
      </taxonsys>
      <taxoncl>
        <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
        <taxonrv>Chromista</taxonrv>
        <taxoncl>
          <taxonrn>Subkingdom</taxonrn>
          <taxonrv>Harosa</taxonrv>
          <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Infrakingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Halvaria</taxonrv>
            <taxoncl>
              <taxonrn>Superdivision</taxonrn>
              <taxonrv>Heterokonta</taxonrv>
              <taxoncl>
                <taxonrn>Division</taxonrn>
                <taxonrv>Ochrophyta</taxonrv>
                <taxoncl>
                  <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
                  <taxonrv>Bacillariophyceae</taxonrv>
                </taxoncl>
              </taxoncl>
            </taxoncl>
          </taxoncl>
        </taxoncl>
        <taxoncl>
          <taxonrn>Subkingdom</taxonrn>
          <taxonrv>Viridiplantae</taxonrv>
          <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Infrakingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Chlorophyta</taxonrv>
            <common>green algae</common>
          </taxoncl>
        </taxoncl>
        <taxoncl>
          <taxonrn>Subkingdom</taxonrn>
          <taxonrv>Chromista</taxonrv>
          <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Division</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Chrysophyta</taxonrv>
            <common>golden-brown algae</common>
            <common>chrysophycophytes</common>
            <taxoncl>
              <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
              <taxonrv>Chrysophyceae</taxonrv>
            </taxoncl>
          </taxoncl>
        </taxoncl>
        <taxoncl>
          <taxonrn>Subkingdom</taxonrn>
          <taxonrv>Chromista</taxonrv>
          <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Division</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Cryptophycophyta</taxonrv>
            <taxoncl>
              <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
              <taxonrv>Cryptophyceae</taxonrv>
            </taxoncl>
          </taxoncl>
        </taxoncl>
        <taxoncl>
          <taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
          <taxonrv>Euglenophycota</taxonrv>
          <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Euglenophyceae</taxonrv>
          </taxoncl>
        </taxoncl>
        <taxoncl>
          <taxonrn>Subkingdom</taxonrn>
          <taxonrv>Negibacteria</taxonrv>
          <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Cyanobacteria</taxonrv>
            <taxoncl>
              <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
              <taxonrv>Cyanophyceae</taxonrv>
            </taxoncl>
          </taxoncl>
        </taxoncl>
        <taxoncl>
          <taxonrn>Subkingdom</taxonrn>
          <taxonrv>Chromista</taxonrv>
          <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Division</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Pyrrophycophyta</taxonrv>
            <taxoncl>
              <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
              <taxonrv>Dinophyceae</taxonrv>
            </taxoncl>
          </taxoncl>
        </taxoncl>
      </taxoncl>
    </taxonomy>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>Users are advised to read the data set's metadata thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Kansas Water Science Center</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jennifer Graham</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>4821 Quail Crest Place</address>
          <city>Lawrence</city>
          <state>KS</state>
          <postal>66049</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(785)832-3511</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jlgraham@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>This study was conducted by the U.S. Geological Survey in cooperation with the City of Wichita, Kansas.</datacred>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Data were analyzed by a certified aquatic laboratory (BSA Environmental Services, Inc.) that does its own quality assurance and quality control procedures. All data were broadly checked for accuracy; no obvious outliers were present in the data. Replicate samples were regularly collected, and also are included in the dataset. Replicate samples can be identified as those having timestamps 5 minutes after the routine sample collected on any given date.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted, but data were checked for naming consistency and numerical errors.</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>Discrete field data collection.</methtype>
        <methdesc>Phytoplankton samples were collected at monthly or bi-monthly intervals from June 2001 through November 2014. Phytoplankton samples collected during June 2001 through July 2004 were collected near the surface using a Teflon Kemmerer bottle or a weighted bottle sampler with a 1-liter Teflon bottle following USGS methods; these samples were not depth integrated. Starting in August 2004 phytoplankton samples were collected as integrated photic-zone (the bottom of which is the depth where light is approximately 1 percent of that at the surface) samples using a double check-valve bailer; these samples were depth integrated. Vertical profiles collected in Cheney Reservoir indicate that thermal stratification rarely occurs and water-quality conditions typically are uniform throughout the water column. Water-quality results collected before and after the sampling procedure change in summer 2004 were similar. More detailed information about sample collection is available in Stone and others (2013).
	</methdesc>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Stone, M.L, Graham, J.L., and Gatotho, J.W.</origin>
            <pubdate>2013</pubdate>
            <title>Model documentation for relations between continuous real-time and discrete water-quality constituents in Cheney Reservoir near Cheney, Kansas 2001-2009</title>
            <geoform>document</geoform>
	    <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
              <issue>USGS Open-File Report 2013-1123</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2013/1123/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
      </method>
	<procstep>
	<procdesc>Routinely collected phytoplankton data were compiled into one spreadsheet for this data release. Data were evaluated to ensure consistency in naming conventions and presentation of dates and times.</procdesc>
	<procdate>20160122</procdate>
	</procstep>    
</lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>Cheney Reservoir Near Cheney, Kansas (07144790)
Long= -97.794218
Lat= 37.726123</indspref>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Cheney_Phytoplankton_Data.xls</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Taxonomic identification, abundance, and biovolume data for phytoplankton samples collected from Cheney Reservoir, Kansas, during June 2001 through November 2015</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Not Specified</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Cheney_Phytoplankton_Data.csv</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Taxonomic identification, abundance, and biovolume data for phytoplankton samples collected from Cheney Reservoir, Kansas, during June 2001 through November 2015</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Not Specified</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SITE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Location where samples were collected. In this case, all samples were collected at the long-term monitoring site on Cheney Reservoir located near the dam.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Not Specified</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Cheney Reservoir</edomv>
            <edomvd>All samples were collected at the long-term monitoring site on Cheney Reservoir located near the dam.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Not Specified</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>STATION ID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>USGS station identification number. In this case, all samples have the station identification number 07144790.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Not Specified</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>07144790</edomv>
            <edomvd>All samples have the station identification number 07144790.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Not Specified</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SAMPLE DATE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Date sample was collected</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Not Specified</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>MM-DD-YYYY</edomv>
            <edomvd>Month-Day-Year</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Not Specified</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SAMPLE TIME</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Time sample was collected</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Not Specified</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>HH:MM</edomv>
            <edomvd>Hours:Minutes</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Not Specified</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SAMPVOL</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Subsample volume examined by analysts</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Not Specified</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.1</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>milliliters, mL</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>FIELDAREA</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Area of each microscopic field examined (refers indirectly to magnification); data are calculated raw values and are not rounded to USGS significant figures</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Not Specified</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.01</rdommin>
            <rdommax>200</rdommax>
            <attrunit>square micrometers, um^2</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>FIELDS</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Number of microscopic fields examined</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Not Specified</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>1</rdommin>
            <rdommax>300</rdommax>
            <attrunit>Unitless</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>AREACOUNTED</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Area of microscopic field examined (field area multiplied by fields); data are calculated raw values and are not rounded to USGS significant figures</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Not Specified</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.01</rdommin>
            <rdommax>200</rdommax>
            <attrunit>square micrometers, um^2</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>FACTOR1</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Proportional multiplier to achieve density and biovolume per liter; data are calculated raw values and are not rounded to USGS significant figures</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Not Specified</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.01</rdommin>
            <rdommax>300</rdommax>
            <attrunit>Unitless</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TAXA</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Phytoplankton taxonomy genus and species name</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Not Specified</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Text</edomv>
            <edomvd>Presented as Genus species. Distinct unknown species are indicated as sp. Variants are indicated as var. Compare with is indicated as cf.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Not Specified</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GENUS</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Phytoplankton taxonomy genus name</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Not Specified</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Text</edomv>
            <edomvd>Organism genus</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Not Specified</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DIVISION</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Phytoplankton taxonomy division name</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Not Specified</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Text</edomv>
            <edomvd>One of seven phytoplankton divisions: Bacillariophyta, Chlorophyta, Chrysophyta, Cryptophyta, Cyanophyta, Euglenophyta, or Pyrrophyta.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Not Specified</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TALLY</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The number of cells of a specific taxa counted in a sample.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Not Specified</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>1</rdommin>
            <rdommax>20,000</rdommax>
            <attrunit>cells</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DENSITY (CELLS/L)</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The number of cells per volume; data are calculated raw values and are not rounded to USGS significant figures</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Not Specified</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>1</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100,000,000</rdommax>
            <attrunit>cells per liter</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>BIOVOLUME FACTOR</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Multiplier used to compute the biovolume of each species; data are calculated raw values and are not rounded to USGS significant figures</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Not Specified</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>150,000</rdommax>
            <attrunit>Unitless</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>BIOVOLUME (UM3/L)</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The biovolume of a specific taxa in a sample; data are calculated raw values and are not rounded to USGS significant figures.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Not Specified</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>50,000,000,000</rdommax>
            <attrunit>cubic micrometers per liter, um^3/L</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160404</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Jennifer Graham</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S.Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>4821 Quail Crest Pl.</address>
          <city>Lawrence</city>
          <state>KS</state>
          <postal>66049</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(785)832-3511</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jlgraham@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>