<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Prinos, Scott, T.</origin><origin>Johnson, Carole, D.</origin><origin>White, Eric, A.</origin><pubdate>2016</pubdate><title>Raw Data from Continuous Resistivity Profiles Collected May 24-25, and July 28, 2011 in Biscayne Bay and a Cooling Canal System, Miami-Dade County</title><geoform>Raw output files from Advanced Geosciences, Inc. SuperSting R8-IP Resistivity meter, Scans of field notes as PDFs</geoform><onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7DZ06DV</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>The salinity of groundwater at the Florida Power &amp; Light Company (FPL) Turkey Point Nuclear Plant in southeastern Florida is being evaluated. The power plant contains a large cooling canal system with warm water; which has salinities elevated above typical, natural surface water in southeastern Florida, circulating within the canals in the uppermost part the highly permeable karst carbonate Biscayne aquifer. The canal system is a closed system that does not discharge directly to fresh or marine surface water bodies. However, exchange between the canal system and groundwater has been postulated based on existing hydrologic information. 
A pilot study was conducted to determine if Continuous resistivity profiles could be used to determine the vertical and horizontal extent of the hypersaline water from the cooling canal system. Continuous resistivity profiles were collected May 24-25, and July 28, 2011 in some of the cooling canals of the Florida Power and Light Company Turkey Point power plant and in Biscayne Bay near the power plant.</abstract><purpose>This data was collected as part of a pilot study to determine the vertical and horizontal extent of the hypersaline water from the cooling canal system in Miami-Dade County.</purpose><supplinf>Software used to process the preliminary results was from  Advanced Geosciences, Inc (AGI). The contact Information is
http://www.agiusa.com/
AGI USA +1 512.335.3338
Advanced Geosciences, Inc
2121 Geoscience Drive
Austin, Texas 78726
The data files included in this release are the *.crs, *.cmd, *.gps, and *.stg, these files are raw output from a meter designed by AGI and intended to be read directly into a software package by AGI.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><mdattim><sngdate><caldate>20110524</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20110525</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20110728</caldate></sngdate></mdattim></timeinfo><current>observed</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Not planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-80.33825</westbc><eastbc>-80.287133</eastbc><northbc>25.40146</northbc><southbc>25.337408</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>none</themekt><themekey>Continous Resistivity Profiling</themekey><themekey>CRP</themekey><themekey>Geophysical</themekey><themekey>Survey</themekey><themekey>Salinity</themekey></theme><place><placekt>None</placekt><placekey>Florida</placekey><placekey>Miami-Dade County</placekey><placekey>Biscayne Bay</placekey><placekey>Turkey Point</placekey><placekey>Cooling Canal System</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>These data are preliminary or provisional and are subject to revision. They are being provided to meet the need for timely best science. The data have not received final approval by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and are provided on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government shall be held liable for any damages resulting from the authorized or unauthorized use of the data</useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Scott T. Prinos</cntper><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg></cntperp><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>Center for Collaborative Research, Nova Southeast University, 3321 College Avenue</address><city>Davie</city><state>FL</state><postal>33314</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>954-377-5944</cntvoice><cntemail>stprinos@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac><datacred>Florida Power and Light Company who provided access, and funded the effort.</datacred><native>SuperSting R8 IP Resistivity Meter Firmware version: 01.03.12E, Software used to process the preliminary results was AGI Earth Imager 2D 2.4.0.0617, AGISAdmin-MLM1.3.4.217</native></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>The provided files are raw unedited data that have not been quality assured. These data are preliminary or provisional and are subject to revision. They are being provided to meet the need for timely best science. The data have not received final approval by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and are provided on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government shall be held liable for any damages resulting from the authorized or unauthorized use of the data.</attraccr></attracc><logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic><complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>Data were collected using Advanced Geosciences, Inc. SuperSting R8 IP Resistivity Meter  Firmware version: 01.03.12E. These files are raw unprocessed files. Details concerning the collection of these data are included in the field notes. Software used to process the preliminary results was AGI Earth Imager 2D 2.4.0.0617, AGISAdmin-MLM1.3.4.217, however, these preliminary results are not published, and there are no plans to publish them at the current time.</procdesc><procdate>2011</procdate></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>Southeastern Miami-Dade County, Florida, about 10 miles east of Florida City, including southwestern Biscayne Bay.</indspref><direct>Point</direct></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><geograph><latres>0.001</latres><longres>0.001</longres><geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit></geograph><geodetic><horizdn>WGS84</horizdn><ellips>WGS_1984</ellips><semiaxis xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:nil="true">6378137.000000</semiaxis><denflat xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:nil="true">298.257224</denflat></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>PDF files</enttypl><enttypd>Scanned Field Notes</enttypd><enttypds>USGS</enttypds></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>Field Notes</attrlabl><attrdef>Form</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Text</udom></attrdomv></attr></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Raw data files</enttypl><enttypd>Advanced Geosciences, Inc. SuperSting R8 IP Resistivity raw output files  Firmware version: 01.03.12E</enttypd><enttypds>USGS</enttypds></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>Raw output files</attrlabl><attrdef>Raw output files</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Integer</udom></attrdomv></attr></detailed></eainfo><distinfo><distrib><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg></cntorgp><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address><city>Denver</city><state>CO</state><postal>80225</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice><cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib><distliab>These data are preliminary or provisional and are subject to revision. They are being provided to meet the need for timely best science. The data have not received final approval by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and are provided on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government shall be held liable for any damages resulting from the authorized or unauthorized use of the data.
Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items must be secured from the copyright owner whenever applicable. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS).  Although the data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Users of the data are advised to read all metadata and associated documentation thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</distliab><techpreq>Processing of these data requires geophysical expertise, skills in modeling of resistivity data, and specialized software such as AGI Earth Imager 2D 2.4.0.0617, AGISAdmin-MLM1.3.4.217. The user must have software capable of reading the AGI format in order to process these data.</techpreq></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20160614</metd><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Scott Prinos</cntper><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Hydrologist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>Center for Collaborative Research, Nova Southeast University,  3321 College Avenue, Davie, FL 33314</address><city>Davie</city><state>FL</state><postal>33314</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>954-377-5944</cntvoice><cntemail>stprinos@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></metc><metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv></metainfo></metadata>