<metadata><Esri><DataProperties><itemProps><itemName Sync="TRUE">Cumberland_Plateau_streamflow_and_fish_data</itemName><nativeExtBox><westBL Sync="TRUE">-85.131100</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">-84.128784</eastBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">35.690000</southBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">36.918800</northBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></nativeExtBox><itemSize Sync="TRUE">0.004</itemSize><itemLocation><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\NWISTN\landeco\ifm\publications\Cumberland_Plateau\Data_Release\FINAL data release files for ScienceBase\Cumberland_Plateau_streamflow_and_fish_data.shp</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></itemLocation><imsContentType Sync="TRUE">002</imsContentType></itemProps><coordRef><type Sync="TRUE">Geographic</type><geogcsn Sync="TRUE">GCS_North_American_1983</geogcsn><csUnits Sync="TRUE">Angular Unit: Degree (0.017453)</csUnits><peXml Sync="TRUE">&lt;GeographicCoordinateSystem xsi:type='typens:GeographicCoordinateSystem' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns:xs='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema' xmlns:typens='http://www.esri.com/schemas/ArcGIS/10.1'&gt;&lt;WKT&gt;GEOGCS[&amp;quot;GCS_North_American_1983&amp;quot;,DATUM[&amp;quot;D_North_American_1983&amp;quot;,SPHEROID[&amp;quot;GRS_1980&amp;quot;,6378137.0,298.257222101]],PRIMEM[&amp;quot;Greenwich&amp;quot;,0.0],UNIT[&amp;quot;Degree&amp;quot;,0.0174532925199433],AUTHORITY[&amp;quot;EPSG&amp;quot;,4269]]&lt;/WKT&gt;&lt;XOrigin&gt;-400&lt;/XOrigin&gt;&lt;YOrigin&gt;-400&lt;/YOrigin&gt;&lt;XYScale&gt;11258999068426.238&lt;/XYScale&gt;&lt;ZOrigin&gt;-100000&lt;/ZOrigin&gt;&lt;ZScale&gt;10000&lt;/ZScale&gt;&lt;MOrigin&gt;-100000&lt;/MOrigin&gt;&lt;MScale&gt;10000&lt;/MScale&gt;&lt;XYTolerance&gt;8.9831528411952133e-009&lt;/XYTolerance&gt;&lt;ZTolerance&gt;0.001&lt;/ZTolerance&gt;&lt;MTolerance&gt;0.001&lt;/MTolerance&gt;&lt;HighPrecision&gt;true&lt;/HighPrecision&gt;&lt;LeftLongitude&gt;-180&lt;/LeftLongitude&gt;&lt;WKID&gt;4269&lt;/WKID&gt;&lt;LatestWKID&gt;4269&lt;/LatestWKID&gt;&lt;/GeographicCoordinateSystem&gt;</peXml></coordRef></DataProperties><SyncDate>20160107</SyncDate><SyncTime>15374600</SyncTime><ModDate>20160107</ModDate><ModTime>15374600</ModTime><ArcGISFormat>1.0</ArcGISFormat><scaleRange><minScale>24000</minScale><maxScale>24000</maxScale></scaleRange></Esri><mdLang><languageCode value="eng"/><countryCode value="USA" Sync="TRUE"></countryCode></mdLang><mdChar><CharSetCd value="004"/></mdChar><mdHrLv><ScopeCd value="005"/></mdHrLv><mdContact><rpIndName>Rodney R Knight</rpIndName><rpOrgName>U.S. Geological Survey, Lower Mississippi-Gulf Water Science Center</rpOrgName><rpPosName>Hydrologist</rpPosName><rpCntInfo><cntPhone><voiceNum>615-837-4731</voiceNum><faxNum>615-837-4799</faxNum></cntPhone><cntAddress addressType="postal"><delPoint>640 Grassmere Park</delPoint><delPoint>Suite 100</delPoint><city>Nashville</city><adminArea>TN</adminArea><postCode>37211</postCode><country>US</country><eMailAdd>rrknight@usgs.gov</eMailAdd></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="007"/></role></mdContact><mdDateSt>20160115</mdDateSt><mdStanName>ArcGIS Metadata</mdStanName><mdStanVer>1.0</mdStanVer><distInfo><distributor><distorCont><rpIndName>Rodney R Knight</rpIndName><rpOrgName>U.S. Geological Survey, Lower Mississippi-Gulf Water Science Center</rpOrgName><rpPosName>Hydrologist</rpPosName><rpCntInfo><cntPhone><voiceNum>615-837-4731</voiceNum><faxNum>615-837-4799</faxNum></cntPhone><cntAddress addressType="postal"><delPoint>Suite 100</delPoint><delPoint>640 Grassmere Park</delPoint><city>Nashville</city><adminArea>TN</adminArea><postCode>37211</postCode><country>US</country><eMailAdd>rrknight@usgs.gov</eMailAdd></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="005"/></role></distorCont><distorOrdPrc><resFees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</resFees></distorOrdPrc><distorFormat><formatName>Vector Digital Data Set (Point)</formatName></distorFormat><distorTran><onLineSrc><linkage>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7JH3J83</linkage></onLineSrc></distorTran></distributor><distTranOps><onLineSrc><linkage>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7JH3J83</linkage></onLineSrc><transSize Sync="TRUE">0.004</transSize></distTranOps><distFormat><formatName Sync="TRUE">Shapefile</formatName></distFormat></distInfo><dataIdInfo><idCitation><resTitle>Streamflow and fish community diversity data for use in developing ecological limit functions for the Cumberland Plateau, northeastern Middle Tennessee and southwestern Kentucky, 2016</resTitle><date><pubDate>2016-01-15</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Rodney R Knight</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Jennifer M. Cartwright</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>David E. Ladd</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>U.S. Geological Survey, ScienceBase</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>https://www.sciencebase.gov</delPoint></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="010"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><fgdcGeoform>Vector Digital Data Set (Point)</fgdcGeoform><PresFormCd value="005" Sync="TRUE"></PresFormCd></presForm></idCitation><idAbs>This geospatial dataset includes one point feature class file and associated FGDC-compliant metadata representing datasets to support development of ecological limit functions for the Cumberland Plateau in northeastern Middle Tennessee and southeastern Kentucky. Knight and others (2012, 2014) developed a methodology of relating fish species richness to changes in hydrologic conditions for sites within the Tennessee River Basin; this dataset applies this methodology to 138 sites within the the Cumberland Plateau. Information contained within this dataset represents values of basin characteristics (see Table II in Knight and others, 2012), estimates of streamflow characteristics (see Table I in Knight and others, 2012), measures of individual and cumulative departure of streamflow characteristics from reference hydrologic conditions, and fish species richness for 138 sites in the study area. Characteristics describing each basin were estimated and standardized (see Table III in Knight and others, 2012) and include: percent forest, percent agriculture, percent of basin in the Interior Plateau Level 3 Ecoregion, percent of basin in Blue Ridge Level 3 Ecoregion, mean basin elevation, index of Hortonian overland flow, soil factor, geologic factor, monthly mean precipitation, January precipitation deviation, August temperature deviation, temperature range, and rock depth as well as the interaction of soil factor, geologic factor, and rock depth with monthly mean precipitation. Basin characteristics were used as independent variables to estimate streamflow characteristics, also in standardized form, following Knight and others (2012). Estimated streamflow characteristics include measures of the magnitude, duration, frequency, timing, and rate of change of the annual hydrograph (Knight and others, 2012). Departure values for individual streamflow characteristics were determined by calculating the numerical distance (difference) outside the reference range for each streamflow characteristic. Reference hydrologic conditions for the study area were determined using methods presented in Knight and others (2012; 2014). Reference ranges are included in the metadata in the entity and attribute descriptions for the fields representing individual hydrologic departure values. Cumulative hydrologic departures represent the sum of individual departure values that were identified as statistically significant (p &lt; 0.05) in quantile regression analysis based on Knight and others (2014), stratified by fish group. Fish species richness for 11 fish groups is presented for each site and represents trophic, taxonomic, reproductive, and habitat preferences (see Table I in Knight and others, 2014) as well as fishes that are considered as rare, threatened, or endangered by Withers (2009). Knight, R.R., Gain, W.S., and Wolfe, W.J., 2012, Modelling ecological flow regime: an example from the Tennessee and Cumberland River basins: Ecohydrology, v. 5, p. 613–627, http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/eco.246 Knight, R.R., Murphy, J.C., Wolfe, W.J., Saylor, C.F., and Wales, A.K., 2014, Ecological limit functions relating fish community response to hydrologic departures of the ecological flow regime in the Tennessee River basin, United States: Ecohydrology, v. 7, p. 1262–1280, http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/eco.1460 Withers, D., 2009, Tennessee Natural Heritage Program rare animals list: Division of Natural Areas, Tennessee Department of Environment and Conservation, Nashville, TN, 61 p, last accessed November 19, 2015, at https://www.tn.gov/assets/entities/environment/attachments/na_animal-list.pdf</idAbs><idPurp>The purpose of this data release is to present data (basin characteristics, estimates of streamflow characteristics, measures of individual and cumulative departure of streamflow characteristics from reference hydrologic conditions, and fish species richness) that were used to support development of ecological limit functions for the Cumberland Plateau in northeastern Middle Tennessee and southeastern Kentucky. Although this data set has been used by the U.S. Geological Survey, U.S. Department of the Interior, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the U.S. Geological Survey as to the accuracy of the data and related materials. The act of distribution shall not constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumed by the U.S. Geological Survey in the use of this data, software, or related materials. Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</idPurp><idStatus><ProgCd value="001"/></idStatus><idPoC><rpIndName>Rodney R Knight</rpIndName><rpOrgName>U.S. Geological Survey, Lower Mississippi-Gulf Water Science Center</rpOrgName><rpPosName>Hydrologist</rpPosName><rpCntInfo><cntPhone><voiceNum>615-837-4731</voiceNum><faxNum>615-837-4799</faxNum></cntPhone><cntAddress addressType="postal"><delPoint>640 Grassmere Park</delPoint><delPoint>Suite 100</delPoint><city>Nashville</city><adminArea>TN</adminArea><postCode>37211</postCode><country>US</country><eMailAdd>rrknight@usgs.gov</eMailAdd></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="007"/></role></idPoC><resMaint><maintFreq><MaintFreqCd value="011"/></maintFreq></resMaint><placeKeys><keyword>Cumberland Plateau physiographic section; Appalachian Plateaus physiographic province</keyword></placeKeys><themeKeys><keyword>ecological flow regime; streamflow characteristics; hydrologic departure; fish species richness</keyword></themeKeys><searchKeys><keyword>ecological flow regime; streamflow characteristics; hydrologic departure; fish species richness</keyword><keyword>Cumberland Plateau physiographic section; Appalachian Plateaus physiographic province</keyword></searchKeys><resConst><LegConsts><useLimit>Although this data set has been used by the U.S. Geological Survey, U.S. Department of the Interior, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the U.S. Geological Survey as to the accuracy of the data and related materials. The act of distribution shall not constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumed by the U.S. Geological Survey in the use of this data, software, or related materials. Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</useLimit><othConsts>None. Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</othConsts></LegConsts></resConst><resConst><Consts><useLimit>Although this data set has been used by the U.S. Geological Survey, U.S. Department of the Interior, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the U.S. Geological Survey as to the accuracy of the data and related materials. The act of distribution shall not constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumed by the U.S. Geological Survey in the use of this data, software, or related materials. Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</useLimit></Consts></resConst><spatRpType><SpatRepTypCd value="001"/></spatRpType><dataLang><languageCode value="eng"/><countryCode value="USA" Sync="TRUE"></countryCode></dataLang><envirDesc>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.2.1 (Build 3497) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</envirDesc><dataExt><exDesc>publication date</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Instant><tmPosition>2016-01-15</tmPosition></TM_Instant></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle><geoEle/></dataExt><dataExt><geoEle><GeoBndBox><westBL>-85.1311</westBL><eastBL>-84.12878418</eastBL><southBL>35.69</southBL><northBL>36.9188</northBL></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt><suppInfo>Please consult the references below for detailed methodology and data descriptions relating to basin characteristics, estimates of streamflow characteristics, measures of individual and cumulative departure of streamflow characteristics from reference hydrologic conditions, and fish species richness data. Data users who are not able to obtain these publications may contact the originator to obtain copies free of charge. Knight, R.R., Gain, W.S., and Wolfe, W.J., 2012, Modelling ecological flow regime: an example from the Tennessee and Cumberland River basins: Ecohydrology, v. 5, p. 613–627, http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/eco.246 Knight, R.R., Murphy, J.C., Wolfe, W.J., Saylor, C.F., and Wales, A.K., 2014, Ecological limit functions relating fish community response to hydrologic departures of the ecological flow regime in the Tennessee River basin, United States: Ecohydrology, v. 7, p. 1262–1280, http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/eco.1460 Withers, D., 2009, Tennessee Natural Heritage Program rare animals list: Division of Natural Areas, Tennessee Department of Environment and Conservation, Nashville, TN, 61 p, https://www.tn.gov/assets/entities/environment/attachments/na_animal-list.pdf</suppInfo><dataExt><geoEle><GeoBndBox esriExtentType="search"><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode><westBL Sync="TRUE">-85.131100</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">-84.128784</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">36.918800</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">35.690000</southBL></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt></dataIdInfo><dqInfo><dqScope><scpLvl><ScopeCd value="005"/></scpLvl></dqScope><report type="DQConcConsis"><measDesc>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</measDesc></report><report type="DQCompOm"><measDesc>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</measDesc></report><report type="DQQuanAttAcc"><measDesc>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted.</measDesc></report><report type="DQAbsExtPosAcc" dimension="horizontal"><measDesc>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</measDesc></report><report type="DQAbsExtPosAcc" dimension="vertical"><measDesc>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</measDesc></report><dataLineage><prcStep><stepDesc>For each site, cumulative hydrologic departure (CHD) variables (CHD_Headw, CHD_Intol, CHD_Native, CHD_Invert, CHD_Spec_in, CHD_TopPrd, CHD_LithSp, CHD_PoolDw, CHD_RiffDw, CHD_All_Sp, and CHD_RTE_Sp) were calculated as the sum of individual hydrologic departure values for the streamflow characteristics that had significant (P&lt;0.05) 85th, 90th, or 95th regression quantiles based on quantile regression relating the departures of individual streamflow characteristics to species richness, stratified by fish group. For each CHD variable, the individual streamflow characteristics that were used to calculate the cumulative hydrologic departure values are listed in the entity and attribute description. See entity and attribute metadata and references therein for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating cumulative hydrologic departure.</stepDesc><stepDateTm>2010-01-01</stepDateTm></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>Basins were delineated using Arc Hydro Tools for ArcGIS. Fish site locations were manually aligned with a flow-accumulation-based synthetic stream network developed for the Tennessee StreamStats web application (http://water.usgs.gov/osw/streamstats/tennessee.html). The edited site locations were used as pour points for basin delineation. These basins (vector polygons) were used for subsequent computation of basin characteristics.</stepDesc><stepDateTm>2010-01-01</stepDateTm></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>To prepare for the computation of basin characteristics, elevation data and elevation derivatives created for the Tennessee StreamStats web application (http://water.usgs.gov/osw/streamstats/tennessee.html) were compiled for use in this study. For the Tennessee StreamStats application, elevation data from the 1/3 arc-second National Elevation Dataset (10-m NED) were preprocessed with hydrography data and watershed boundaries to create hydrologically-corrected digital elevation models using a custom Arc Macro Language (aml) script containing preprocessing methods similar to those described by Djokic (2008). The sources of the hydrography data used to preprocess the elevation data were the high-resolution National Hydrography Dataset (NHD) and unpublished data from the Tennessee State Base Mapping Program (TNBMP hydrography). Watershed boundaries used to preprocess the elevation data were from Watershed Boundary Dataset (WBD), which was considered a draft version at the time of processing. More information about the sources used for this process step can be found in the data source section of this metadata document.</stepDesc><stepDateTm>2006-01-01</stepDateTm></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>A raster representing the estimated long-term average percentage of infiltration-excess overland flow (Hortonian flow) was downloaded (see source input metadata), clipped to the study area, projected to TN StatePlane NAD83 (US feet), and resampled to a cell size of 30 x 30 feet. Input basins were converted to a raster with the same properties (spatial reference, cell size, origin) as the Hortonian-flow raster. Arc Hydro Tools for ArcGIS were used to calculate the mean Hortonian-flow value for each basin.</stepDesc><stepDateTm>2010-01-01</stepDateTm></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>The 2001 National Land Cover Database (NLCD2001) was downloaded and used to calculate basin characteristics (AgPct, ForestPct). Input basins were converted to a raster with the same properties (spatial reference, cell size, origin) as the land-use raster. In order to calculate land-use type (such as agricultural or forest) percentages, land-use subtypes were grouped to an appropriate category. Subtypes 52 (shrub/Scrub), 71 (grassland/herbaceous), 81 (pasture/hay), and 82 (cultivated crops) were combined to create an agricultural raster (see derived_data folder) in which agricultural types = 1 and all other types = 0. Using the same techniques, a forest grid (see derived_data folder) was created by combining subtypes 41 (deciduous forest), 42 (evergreeen forest), and 43 (mixed forest). Percentages of agricultural and forest land-use types were calculated using Arc Hydro Tools for ArcGIS.</stepDesc><stepDateTm>2010-01-01</stepDateTm></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>The 1/3 arc-second National Elevation Dataset (10-m NED) was downloaded for each 8-digit hydrologic unit code (HUC) in the study area. The elevation data for each HUC were projected to TN StatePlane NAD83 (US feet), resampled to a cell size of 30x30 feet, multiplied to convert elevation units to 100ths of feet, and merged to create a single elevation grid for the study area. Input basins were converted to a raster with the same properties (spatial reference, cell size, origin) as the elevation raster. Arc Hydro Tools for ArcGIS were used to calculate the mean value of the elevation raster (the ElevFt field) for each basin.</stepDesc><stepDateTm>2010-01-01</stepDateTm></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>For each site, departure values for individual streamflow characteristics (Dep_MA41, Dep_LRA7, Dep_E85, Dep_AMH10, Dep_LDH13, Dep_ML20, Dep_TA1, Dep_LFH7, Dep_FH6, Dep_LML18, Dep_LDL6, Dep_MA26, and Dep_TL1) were determined by calculating the numerical distance (difference) outside the reference range for each streamflow characteristic. Reference hydrologic conditions for the study area were determined using methods presented in Knight and others (2012; 2014). Reference ranges are included in the entity and attribute descriptions for the fields representing individual hydrologic departure values. See entity and attribute metadata and references therein for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating departure from hydrologic reference conditions.</stepDesc><stepDateTm>2010-01-01</stepDateTm></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>PRISM temperature and precipiation data were downloaded and used to calculate climate-related basin characteristics (MonMnPrec, JanPrecDev, DayTempRng, AugTempDev). Input basins were converted to a raster with the same properties (spatial reference, cell size, origin) as the climate raster. Arc Hydro Tools for ArcGIS was used to calculate the mean value of the climate raster for each basin. Derivative values (such as temperature-deviation characteristics) were manually calculated after the annual/monthly normal values were derived from raster analysis.</stepDesc><stepDateTm>2010-01-01</stepDateTm></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>Latitude and longitude coordinates for sites associated with data collection of fish species diversity were obtained (see source input metadata) and compiled. Site locations were imported as a vector point file based on these coordinates.</stepDesc><stepDateTm>2010-01-01</stepDateTm></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>A polygon coverage and accompanying information table representing rock depth from the Conterminous United States Multi-Layer Soil Characteristics Data Set for Regional Climate and Hydrology Modeling were downloaded. The rock depth information from the information table was joined to the coverage. The data were clipped to the study area, projected to TN StatePlane NAD83 (US feet), and converted to a grid with a cell size of 30 x 30 feet. Input basins were converted to a raster with the same properties (spatial reference, cell size, origin) as the rock-depth raster. Arc Hydro Tools for ArcGIS were used to calculate the mean depth to rock for each basin (RockDepth).</stepDesc><stepDateTm>2010-01-01</stepDateTm></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>Using basin characteristics (see previous processing steps) as independent variables, streamflow characteristics (MA41, LRA7, E85, AMH10, LDH13, ML20, TA1, LFH7, FH6, LML18, LDL6, MA26, and TL1) were estimated for each site according to Knight and others (2012). See entity and attribute metadata and references therein for detailed descriptions of methodology used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations with basin characteristics as independent variables.</stepDesc><stepDateTm>2010-01-01</stepDateTm></prcStep><dataSource><srcDesc>Source data for calculation of the basin characteristic soil factor. Additionally, an earlier version of this dataset was used as an initial source for A Conterminous United States Multi-Layer Soil Characteristics Data Set for Regional Climate and Hydrology Modeling (source for rock depth basin characteristic).</srcDesc><srcMedName><MedNameCd value="018"/></srcMedName><srcCitatn><resTitle>U.S. General Soil Map</resTitle><resAltTitle>STATSGO2</resAltTitle><date><pubDate>2006-01-01</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>U.S. Department of Agriculture - Natural Resources Conservation Service</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>Fort, Worth, TX</delPoint></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="010"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>U.S Department of Agriculture - Natural Resources Conservation Service</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><fgdcGeoform>Vector Digital Data Set</fgdcGeoform></presForm><citOnlineRes><linkage>http://websoilsurvey.sc.egov.usda.gov/App/WebSoilSurvey.aspx</linkage></citOnlineRes></srcCitatn><srcExt><exDesc>publication date</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Instant><tmPosition>2006-01-01</tmPosition></TM_Instant></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></srcExt></dataSource><dataSource><srcDesc>Provides a summary of methods used to preprocess elevation data for use in basin delineations and basin-characteristic calculations.</srcDesc><srcMedName><MedNameCd value="018"/></srcMedName><srcCitatn><resTitle>Comprehensive Terrain Preprocessing Using Arc Hydro Tools</resTitle><resAltTitle>Terrain Preprocessing Methods</resAltTitle><date><pubDate>2008-01-01</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Esri</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>http://www.arcgis.com/home/item.html?id=41c96fadd2bf49ff8851002042c0495f</delPoint></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="010"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Djokic, Dean</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><fgdcGeoform>Publication (Book)</fgdcGeoform></presForm><citOnlineRes><linkage>http://www.arcgis.com/home/item.html?id=41c96fadd2bf49ff8851002042c0495f</linkage></citOnlineRes></srcCitatn><srcExt><exDesc>publication date</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Instant><tmPosition>2008-01-01</tmPosition></TM_Instant></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></srcExt></dataSource><dataSource><srcDesc>Source information for calculating basin characteristics (MonMnPrec, JanPrecDev, DayTempRng, AugTempDev)</srcDesc><srcMedName><MedNameCd value="018"/></srcMedName><srcCitatn><resTitle>PRISM gridded climate data</resTitle><resAltTitle>PRISM climate data</resAltTitle><date><pubDate>2008-01-01</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>PRISM Climate Group</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Oregon State University</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>http://prism.oregonstate.edu</delPoint></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="010"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><fgdcGeoform>Raster Digital Data Set</fgdcGeoform></presForm><citOnlineRes><linkage>http://prism.oregonstate.edu</linkage></citOnlineRes></srcCitatn><srcExt><exDesc>publication date</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Instant><tmPosition>2008-01-01</tmPosition></TM_Instant></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></srcExt></dataSource><dataSource><srcDesc>Source information used in calculating fish species richness by fish group.</srcDesc><srcMedName><MedNameCd value="018"/></srcMedName><srcCitatn><resTitle>Unpublished fish species data</resTitle><resAltTitle>KYDOW fish data</resAltTitle><date><pubDate>2005-01-01</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Kentucky Division of Water (KYDOW)</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>unpublished</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>unpublished</delPoint></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="010"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><fgdcGeoform>Observed/Measured First-Hand</fgdcGeoform></presForm></srcCitatn><srcExt><exDesc>observed</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Period><tmBegin>2000-07-17</tmBegin><tmEnd>2005-09-08</tmEnd></TM_Period></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></srcExt></dataSource><dataSource><srcDesc>Data were used in elevation preprocessing required for basin delineations and basin-characteristic calculations.</srcDesc><srcMedName><MedNameCd value="018"/></srcMedName><srcScale><rfDenom>24000</rfDenom></srcScale><srcCitatn><resTitle>National Hydrography Dataset</resTitle><resAltTitle>NHD</resAltTitle><date><pubDate>2006-01-01</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>U.S. Geological Survey</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>U.S. Geological Survey</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>http://nhd.usgs.gov/</delPoint></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="010"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><fgdcGeoform>Raster Digital Data Set</fgdcGeoform></presForm><citOnlineRes><linkage>http://nhd.usgs.gov/</linkage></citOnlineRes></srcCitatn><srcExt><exDesc>publication date</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Instant><tmPosition>2006-01-01</tmPosition></TM_Instant></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></srcExt></dataSource><dataSource><srcDesc>Source information for calculating basin characteristic (G_Factor)</srcDesc><srcMedName><MedNameCd value="018"/></srcMedName><srcCitatn><resTitle>Regionalization of Low-Flow Streamflow-Characteristic Estimation Methods for Unregulated Streams of Tennessee</resTitle><resAltTitle>Geologic factor map for Cumberland River and Tennessee River basins</resAltTitle><date><pubDate>2009-01-01</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Scientific Investigations Report 2009–5159</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>Reston, VA</delPoint></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="010"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Law, G.S., Tasker, G.D., and Ladd, D.E.</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><fgdcGeoform>Paper Map</fgdcGeoform></presForm><citOnlineRes><linkage>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sir/2009/5159/</linkage></citOnlineRes></srcCitatn><srcExt><exDesc>publication date</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Instant><tmPosition>2009-01-01</tmPosition></TM_Instant></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></srcExt></dataSource><dataSource><srcDesc>Description of methods for calculating basin characteristic (SoilFactor)</srcDesc><srcMedName><MedNameCd value="018"/></srcMedName><srcCitatn><resTitle>Superfund GIS - Soil thickness, permeability, texture, and classification in Tennessee</resTitle><resAltTitle>Greene and Wolfe (1998) data</resAltTitle><date><pubDate>1998-01-01</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>U.S. Geological Survey</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>Nashville, TN</delPoint></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="010"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Greene, D.C., and Wolfe, W.J.</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><fgdcGeoform>Raster Digital Data Set</fgdcGeoform></presForm><citOnlineRes><linkage>http://water.usgs.gov/lookup/getspatial?statsoil</linkage></citOnlineRes></srcCitatn><srcExt><exDesc>publication date</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Instant><tmPosition>1998-01-01</tmPosition></TM_Instant></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></srcExt></dataSource><dataSource><srcDesc>Source information for calculating basin characteristic (Horton)</srcDesc><srcMedName><MedNameCd value="018"/></srcMedName><srcCitatn><resTitle>Infiltration-excess overland flow estimated by TOPMODEL for the conterminous United States</resTitle><resAltTitle>IEOF for Hortonian flow calculation</resAltTitle><date><pubDate>2003-01-01</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>U.S. Geological Survey</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>Reston, VA</delPoint></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="010"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Wolock, D.M.</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><fgdcGeoform>Raster Digital Data Set</fgdcGeoform></presForm><citOnlineRes><linkage>http://water.usgs.gov/lookup/getspatial?ieof48</linkage></citOnlineRes></srcCitatn><srcExt><exDesc>publication date</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Instant><tmPosition>2003-01-01</tmPosition></TM_Instant></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></srcExt></dataSource><dataSource><srcDesc>Source information for calculating basin characteristics (AgPct, ForestPct)</srcDesc><srcMedName><MedNameCd value="018"/></srcMedName><srcCitatn><resTitle>2001 National Land Cover Database (NLCD)</resTitle><resAltTitle>2001 NLCD land cover data</resAltTitle><date><pubDate>2001-01-01</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Multi-Resolution Land Characteristic Consortium (MRLC)</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Multi-Resolution Land Characteristic Consortium (MRLC)</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>http://www.mrlc.gov/finddata.php</delPoint></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="010"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><fgdcGeoform>Publication (Journal Article)</fgdcGeoform></presForm><citOnlineRes><linkage>http://www.mrlc.gov/finddata.php</linkage></citOnlineRes></srcCitatn><srcExt><exDesc>publication date</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Instant><tmPosition>2001-01-01</tmPosition></TM_Instant></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></srcExt></dataSource><dataSource><srcDesc>Data were used in elevation preprocessing required for basin delineations and basin-characteristic calculations.</srcDesc><srcMedName><MedNameCd value="018"/></srcMedName><srcCitatn><resTitle>Watershed Boundary Dataset</resTitle><resAltTitle>WBD</resAltTitle><date><pubDate>2006-01-01</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>U.S. Department of Agriculture - Natural Resources Conservation Service</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>http://datagateway.nrcs.usda.gov</delPoint></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="010"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>U.S. Department of Agriculture - Natural Resources Conservation Service, U.S. Geological Survey, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><fgdcGeoform>Vector Digital Data Set</fgdcGeoform></presForm><citOnlineRes><linkage>http://datagateway.nrcs.usda.gov</linkage></citOnlineRes></srcCitatn><srcExt><exDesc>publication date</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Period><tmBegin>2000-01-01</tmBegin><tmEnd>2006-01-01</tmEnd></TM_Period></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></srcExt></dataSource><dataSource><srcDesc>Data were used in elevation preprocessing required for basin delineations and basin-characteristic calculations.</srcDesc><srcMedName><MedNameCd value="018"/></srcMedName><srcScale><rfDenom>24000</rfDenom></srcScale><srcCitatn><resTitle>unpublished Tennessee State Base Mapping Program Hydrography</resTitle><resAltTitle>TNBMP hydrography</resAltTitle><date><pubDate>2005-01-01</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Tennessee Department of Finance and Administration, Office for Information Resources – GIS Services</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>unpublished</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>unpublished</delPoint></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="010"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><fgdcGeoform>Vector Digital Data Set</fgdcGeoform></presForm></srcCitatn><srcExt><exDesc>publication date</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Instant><tmPosition>2005-01-01</tmPosition></TM_Instant></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></srcExt></dataSource><dataSource><srcDesc>Source information used in calculating fish species richness by fish group.</srcDesc><srcMedName><MedNameCd value="018"/></srcMedName><srcCitatn><resTitle>Unpublished fish species data</resTitle><resAltTitle>NPS fish data</resAltTitle><date><pubDate>2006-01-01</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>National Park Service (NPS)</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>unpublished</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>unpublished</delPoint></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="010"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><fgdcGeoform>Observed/Measured First-Hand</fgdcGeoform></presForm></srcCitatn><srcExt><exDesc>observed</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Period><tmBegin>2003-06-27</tmBegin><tmEnd>2006-11-14</tmEnd></TM_Period></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></srcExt></dataSource><dataSource><srcDesc>Source information for calculating basin characteristics (IntPlatPct, BlueRdgPct)</srcDesc><srcMedName><MedNameCd value="018"/></srcMedName><srcCitatn><resTitle>Level IV Ecoregions of the Conterminous United States</resTitle><resAltTitle>Level IV ecoregions</resAltTitle><date><pubDate>2013-04-16</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>U.S. EPA Office of Research &amp; Development (ORD) - National Health and Environmental Effects Research Laboratory (NHEERL)</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>Corvallis, OR</delPoint></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="010"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>US Environmental Protection Agency</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><fgdcGeoform>Vector Digital Data Set</fgdcGeoform></presForm><citOnlineRes><linkage>ftp://ftp.epa.gov/wed/ecoregions/us/</linkage></citOnlineRes></srcCitatn><srcExt><exDesc>publication date</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Instant><tmPosition>2013-04-16</tmPosition></TM_Instant></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></srcExt></dataSource><dataSource><srcDesc>Source information for calculating basin characteristic (RockDepth)</srcDesc><srcMedName><MedNameCd value="018"/></srcMedName><srcCitatn><resTitle>A Conterminous United States Multi-Layer Soil Characteristics Data Set for Regional Climate and Hydrology Modeling</resTitle><resAltTitle>Soil Characteristics Data Set</resAltTitle><date><pubDate>1998-01-01</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Miller, D.A. and White, R.A.</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Earth Interactions</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>http://www.soilinfo.psu.edu/index.cgi?soil_data&amp;conus&amp;data_cov&amp;dtb&amp;datasets</delPoint></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="010"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><fgdcGeoform>Vector Digital Data Set</fgdcGeoform></presForm><citOnlineRes><linkage>http://www.soilinfo.psu.edu/index.cgi?soil_data&amp;conus&amp;data_cov&amp;dtb&amp;datasets</linkage></citOnlineRes></srcCitatn><srcExt><exDesc>publication date</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Instant><tmPosition>1998-01-01</tmPosition></TM_Instant></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></srcExt></dataSource><dataSource><srcDesc>Source information for calculating basin characteristic (ElevFt)</srcDesc><srcMedName><MedNameCd value="018"/></srcMedName><srcScale><rfDenom>24000</rfDenom></srcScale><srcCitatn><resTitle>The 1/3 arc-second National Elevation Dataset (10-m NED)</resTitle><resAltTitle>10-m NED elevation data</resAltTitle><date><pubDate>2006-01-01</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>U.S. Geological Survey</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>http://nationalmap.gov/elevation.html</delPoint></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="010"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>U.S. Geological Survey</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><fgdcGeoform>Raster Digital Data Set</fgdcGeoform></presForm><citOnlineRes><linkage>http://nationalmap.gov/elevation.html</linkage></citOnlineRes></srcCitatn><srcExt><exDesc>publication date</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Instant><tmPosition>2006-01-01</tmPosition></TM_Instant></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></srcExt></dataSource><dataSource><srcDesc>Source information used in calculating fish species richness by fish group.</srcDesc><srcMedName><MedNameCd value="018"/></srcMedName><srcCitatn><resTitle>Unpublished fish species data</resTitle><resAltTitle>TVA fish data</resAltTitle><date><pubDate>2005-01-01</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Tennessee Valley Authority (TVA)</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpOrgName>unpublished</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>unpublished</delPoint></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="010"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><fgdcGeoform>Observed/Measured First-Hand</fgdcGeoform></presForm></srcCitatn><srcExt><exDesc>observed</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Period><tmBegin>2000-01-01</tmBegin><tmEnd>2005-12-31</tmEnd></TM_Period></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></srcExt></dataSource></dataLineage></dqInfo><spatRepInfo><VectSpatRep><geometObjs Name="Cumberland_Plateau_streamflow_and_fish_data"><geoObjTyp><GeoObjTypCd value="004" Sync="TRUE"></GeoObjTypCd></geoObjTyp><geoObjCnt Sync="TRUE">138</geoObjCnt></geometObjs><topLvl><TopoLevCd value="001" Sync="TRUE"></TopoLevCd></topLvl></VectSpatRep></spatRepInfo><eainfo><detailed Name="Cumberland_Plateau_streamflow_and_fish_data"><enttyp><enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl><enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd><enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds><enttypt Sync="TRUE">Feature Class</enttypt><enttypc Sync="TRUE">138</enttypc></enttyp><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">FID</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">FID</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">OID</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale><attrdef Sync="TRUE">Internal feature number.</attrdef><attrdefs Sync="TRUE">Esri</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom Sync="TRUE">Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">Shape</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">Shape</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Geometry</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">0</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale><attrdef Sync="TRUE">Feature geometry.</attrdef><attrdefs Sync="TRUE">Esri</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom Sync="TRUE">Coordinates defining the features.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>ForestPct</attrlabl><attrdef>Percent forest cover—the total percentage of land cover in a watershed that is considered to be forested; see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use) used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-1.235283</rdommin><rdommax>1.593686</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">ForestPct</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>E85</attrlabl><attrdef>Streamflow value exceeded 85 percent of time, computed as the 85 percent exceedance of daily mean streamflow for the period of record normalized by basin area. See Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of streamflow characteristics and model specifications for estimating dependent variables (streamflow characteristics) from basin-scale independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-0.847851</rdommin><rdommax>-0.029544</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">E85</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>SoilFactor</attrlabl><attrdef>Percentage of area underlain by soil with a permeability of at least 5 cm per hour; see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use) used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-2.291841</rdommin><rdommax>1.502733</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">SoilFactor</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Dep_AMH10</attrlabl><attrdef>Departure from hydrologic reference conditions for the streamflow characteristic AMH10; see entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics. Departure from reference conditions is calculated as the absolute value of the difference between the estimated value of AMH10 and the reference range (defined by the 25th and 75th percentiles for the 20 sites in the study area with greatest percent forest cover). For AMH10, the 25th percentile value was -0.639 and the 75th percentile value was -0.1579. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating departure from hydrologic reference conditions.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>0.517541</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Dep_AMH10</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>JanPrecDev</attrlabl><attrdef>Mean January precipitation divided by monthly precipitation mean; see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use) used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-0.820195</rdommin><rdommax>2.264405</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">JanPrecDev</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>IntPlatPct</attrlabl><attrdef>Percent of the watershed that lies within the Interior Plateau level 3 ecoregion; see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use) used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-0.746566</rdommin><rdommax>-0.731991</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">IntPlatPct</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>BlueRdgPct</attrlabl><attrdef>Percent of the watershed that lies within the Blue Ridge level 3 ecoregion; see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use) used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-0.69114</rdommin><rdommax>-0.69114</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">BlueRdgPct</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>RockDepth</attrlabl><attrdef>Average depth of soil above bedrock; see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use) used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-1.942884</rdommin><rdommax>-0.36672</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">RockDepth</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Dep_LRA7</attrlabl><attrdef>Departure from hydrologic reference conditions for the streamflow characteristic LRA7; see entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics. Departure from reference conditions is calculated as the absolute value of the difference between the estimated value of LRA7 and the reference range (defined by the 25th and 75th percentiles for the 20 sites in the study area with greatest percent forest cover). For LRA7, the 25th percentile value was 0.7039 and the 75th percentile value was 1.1597. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating departure from hydrologic reference conditions.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>0.303837</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Dep_LRA7</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>FH6</attrlabl><attrdef>Frequency of moderate flooding, computed as the average number of high-flow events per year that are equal to or greater than three times the median annual flow for the period of record. See Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of streamflow characteristics and model specifications for estimating dependent variables (streamflow characteristics) from basin-scale independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-0.166326</rdommin><rdommax>1.052725</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">FH6</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>G_Fact_in</attrlabl><attrdef>Geologic factor multiplied by monthly mean precipitation; see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use) used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-2.561553</rdommin><rdommax>0.907042</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">G_Fact_in</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>LDH13</attrlabl><attrdef>Average 30-day maximum, computed as the log transform of the average over the period of record of the annual maximum of 30-day moving average flows divided by the median for the entire record. See Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of streamflow characteristics and model specifications for estimating dependent variables (streamflow characteristics) from basin-scale independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0.146913</rdommin><rdommax>0.971346</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">LDH13</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>ML20</attrlabl><attrdef>Base flow, computed according to the following steps: (1) divide the daily flow record into 5-day blocks; (2) assign the minimum flow for the block as a base flow for that block if 90% of that minimum flow is less than the minimum flows for the blocks on either side (otherwise, set it to zero); (3) fill in the zero values using linear interpolation; (4) compute the total flow for the entire record and the total base flow for the entire record. ML20 is the ratio of total flow to total base flow. See Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of streamflow characteristics and model specifications for estimating dependent variables (streamflow characteristics) from basin-scale independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-1.16155</rdommin><rdommax>-0.296468</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">ML20</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>AugTempDev</attrlabl><attrdef>Mean August maximum temperature minus mean annual temperature divided by mean annual temperature; see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use) used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-0.428623</rdommin><rdommax>1.121888</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">AugTempDev</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>DayTempRng</attrlabl><attrdef>Mean maximum daily temperature minus mean minimum daily temperature; see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use) used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-2.991748</rdommin><rdommax>1.197373</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">DayTempRng</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>AgPct</attrlabl><attrdef>Percent agricultural cover—the total percentage of land cover in a watershed that is considered to be agricultural; see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use) used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-1.422735</rdommin><rdommax>0.903278</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">AgPct</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>DataSource</attrlabl><attrdef>Agency from which fish community data was obtained</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>TVA</edomv><edomvd>Tennessee Valley Authority</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom><edom><edomv>KYDOW</edomv><edomvd>Kentucky Department of Water</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom><edom><edomv>NPS</edomv><edomvd>National Park Service</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">DataSource</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">254</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>RockDep_in</attrlabl><attrdef>Rock depth multiplied by monthly mean precipitation; see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use) used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-1.63165</rdommin><rdommax>0.955747</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">RockDep_in</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>SoilFac_in</attrlabl><attrdef>Soil factor multiplied by monthly mean precipitation; see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use) used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-1.932315</rdommin><rdommax>0.78197</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">SoilFac_in</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>MA26</attrlabl><attrdef>Variability of March streamflow, computed as the standard deviation for March streamflow divided by the mean streamflow for March. See Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of streamflow characteristics and model specifications for estimating dependent variables (streamflow characteristics) from basin-scale independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-0.059876</rdommin><rdommax>0.884661</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">MA26</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Long</attrlabl><attrdef>Longitude in decimal degrees</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-85.1311</rdommin><rdommax>-84.128784</rdommax><attrunit>decimal degrees</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Long</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Dep_E85</attrlabl><attrdef>Departure from hydrologic reference conditions for the streamflow characteristic E85; see entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics. Departure from reference conditions is calculated as the absolute value of the difference between the estimated value of E85 and the reference range (defined by the 25th and 75th percentiles for the 20 sites in the study area with greatest percent forest cover). For E85, the 25th percentile value was -0.7534 and the 75th percentile value was -0.3982. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating departure from hydrologic reference conditions.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>0.368656</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Dep_E85</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>LFH7</attrlabl><attrdef>Frequency of moderate flooding, computed as the log transform of the average number of high-flow events per year that are equal to or greater than seven times the median annual flow for the period of record. See Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of streamflow characteristics and model specifications for estimating dependent variables (streamflow characteristics) from basin-scale independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0.303649</rdommin><rdommax>1.00639</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">LFH7</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>G_Factor</attrlabl><attrdef>Measure of the number of days that pass as discharge recedes one complete log cycle of streamflow; see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use) used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-1.253935</rdommin><rdommax>-0.899153</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">G_Factor</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>TL1</attrlabl><attrdef>Annual minimum flow, identified as the Julian date of annual minimum flow occurrence. See Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of streamflow characteristics and model specifications for estimating dependent variables (streamflow characteristics) from basin-scale independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-0.873191</rdommin><rdommax>0.801709</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">TL1</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>AMH10</attrlabl><attrdef>Maximum October streamflow across the period of record normalized by basin area. See Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of streamflow characteristics and model specifications for estimating dependent variables (streamflow characteristics) from basin-scale independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-1.156541</rdommin><rdommax>0.350643</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">AMH10</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>MA41</attrlabl><attrdef>Mean annual runoff, computed as the annual mean daily streamflow normalized by basin area. See Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of streamflow characteristics and model specifications for estimating dependent variables (streamflow characteristics) from basin-scale independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-0.710673</rdommin><rdommax>1.834786</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">MA41</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Horton</attrlabl><attrdef>Index of Hortonian overland (infiltration excess); see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use) used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-1.673937</rdommin><rdommax>0.582255</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Horton</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Lat</attrlabl><attrdef>Latitude in decimal degrees</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>35.69</rdommin><rdommax>36.9188</rdommax><attrunit>decimal degrees</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Lat</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>MonMnPrec</attrlabl><attrdef>Average annual precipitation divided by 12; see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use) used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-0.754373</rdommin><rdommax>2.042812</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">MonMnPrec</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Spec_insec</attrlabl><attrdef>Species richness for specialized insectivores. These species feed predominately on insects found in benthic habitat and are highly susceptible to habitat degradation. See Knight and others (2014) for fish category definitions based on trophic, habitat, and tolerance characteristics.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>17</rdommax><attrunit>Number of species (count)</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Spec_insec</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">SmallInteger</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">4</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Invertivor</attrlabl><attrdef>Species richness for invertivores. These species are invertivores, primarily insectivores (excluding generalized insectivores and opportunistic feeders). See Knight and others (2014) for fish category definitions based on trophic, habitat, and tolerance characteristics.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>13</rdommax><attrunit>Number of species (count)</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Invertivor</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">SmallInteger</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">4</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Native</attrlabl><attrdef>Species richness for natives. These are resident native fish species. See Knight and others (2014) for fish category definitions based on trophic, habitat, and tolerance characteristics.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>1</rdommin><rdommax>35</rdommax><attrunit>Number of species (count)</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Native</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">SmallInteger</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">4</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Site</attrlabl><attrdef>Site identification number</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>1</rdommin><rdommax>138</rdommax><attrunit>N/A</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Site</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">SmallInteger</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">4</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Riffle_dwl</attrlabl><attrdef>Species richness for riffle dwellers. These species feed and reproduce in benthic habitats (in riffles) and are sensitive to degradation resulting from siltation and benthic oxygen depletion. See Knight and others (2014) for fish category definitions based on trophic, habitat, and tolerance characteristics.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>7</rdommax><attrunit>Number of species (count)</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Riffle_dwl</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">SmallInteger</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">4</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Lith_spawn</attrlabl><attrdef>Species richness for lithophilic spawners. These species spawn where their eggs can develop in the interstices of sand, gravel, and cobble substrates without parental care. See Knight and others (2014) for fish category definitions based on trophic, habitat, and tolerance characteristics.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>21</rdommax><attrunit>Number of species (count)</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Lith_spawn</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">SmallInteger</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">4</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Dep_MA26</attrlabl><attrdef>Departure from hydrologic reference conditions for the streamflow characteristic MA26; see entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics. Departure from reference conditions is calculated as the absolute value of the difference between the estimated value of MA26 and the reference range (defined by the 25th and 75th percentiles for the 20 sites in the study area with greatest percent forest cover). For MA26, the 25th percentile value was 0.1483 and the 75th percentile value was 0.7131. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating departure from hydrologic reference conditions.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>0.208176</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Dep_MA26</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>CHD_Native</attrlabl><attrdef>Cumulative hydrologic departure value (independent variable) that was used in quantile regression with species richness for natives (dependent variable). This value of cumulative hydrologic departure is equal to the sum of hydrologic departure values for the streamflow characteristics that had significant (P&lt;0.05) 85th, 90th, or 95th regression quantiles based on quantile regression relating the departures of individual streamflow characteristics to species richness, stratified by fish group. For natives, the individual departure value for TL1 was used to calculate cumulative hydrologic departure. See entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics, fish groups, and hydrologic departure values. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating cumulative hydrologic departure.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>0.757709</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">CHD_Native</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>CHD_Intol</attrlabl><attrdef>Cumulative hydrologic departure value (independent variable) that was used in quantile regression with species richness for intolerants (dependent variable). This value of cumulative hydrologic departure is equal to the sum of hydrologic departure values for the streamflow characteristics that had significant (P&lt;0.05) 85th, 90th, or 95th regression quantiles based on quantile regression relating the departures of individual streamflow characteristics to species richness, stratified by fish group. For intolerants, individual departure values for AMH10, ML20, and TL1 were used to calculate cumulative hydrologic departure. See entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics, fish groups, and hydrologic departure values. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating cumulative hydrologic departure.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>1.243179</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">CHD_Intol</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>CHD_Headw</attrlabl><attrdef>Cumulative hydrologic departure value (independent variable) that was used in quantile regression with species richness for headwater intolerants (dependent variable). This value of cumulative hydrologic departure is equal to the sum of hydrologic departure values for the streamflow characteristics that had significant (P&lt;0.05) 85th, 90th, or 95th regression quantiles based on quantile regression relating the departures of individual streamflow characteristics to species richness, stratified by fish group. For headwater intolerants, individual departure values for AMH10, LDH13, LDL6, and TL1 were used to calculate cumulative hydrologic departure. See entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics, fish groups, and hydrologic departure values. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating cumulative hydrologic departure.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>1.411717</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">CHD_Headw</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Dep_TA1</attrlabl><attrdef>Departure from hydrologic reference conditions for the streamflow characteristic TA1; see entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics. Departure from reference conditions is calculated as the absolute value of the difference between the estimated value of TA1 and the reference range (defined by the 25th and 75th percentiles for the 20 sites in the study area with greatest percent forest cover). For TA1, the 25th percentile value was -0.6497 and the 75th percentile value was -0.2439. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating departure from hydrologic reference conditions.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>0.559332</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Dep_TA1</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>TA1</attrlabl><attrdef>Constancy, a measure the stability of flow regimes, computed by dividing daily flows into predetermined flow classes. See Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of streamflow characteristics and model specifications for estimating dependent variables (streamflow characteristics) from basin-scale independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-1.209032</rdommin><rdommax>0.009894</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">TA1</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>CHD_RTE_Sp</attrlabl><attrdef>Cumulative hydrologic departure value (independent variable) that was used in quantile regression with species richness for rare, threatened, and endangered species (dependent variable). This value of cumulative hydrologic departure is equal to the sum of hydrologic departure values for the streamflow characteristics that had significant (P&lt;0.05) 85th, 90th, or 95th regression quantiles based on quantile regression relating the departures of individual streamflow characteristics to species richness, stratified by fish group. For rare, threatened, and endangered species, individual departure values for TL1 and TA1 were used to calculate cumulative hydrologic departure. See entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics, fish groups, and hydrologic departure values. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating cumulative hydrologic departure.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>1.071821</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">CHD_RTE_Sp</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>CHD_RiffDw</attrlabl><attrdef>Cumulative hydrologic departure value (independent variable) that was used in quantile regression with species richness for riffle dwellers (dependent variable). This value of cumulative hydrologic departure is equal to the sum of hydrologic departure values for the streamflow characteristics that had significant (P&lt;0.05) 85th, 90th, or 95th regression quantiles based on quantile regression relating the departures of individual streamflow characteristics to species richness, stratified by fish group. For riffle dwellers, individual departure values for AMH10 and TL1 were used to calculate cumulative hydrologic departure. See entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics, fish groups, and hydrologic departure values. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating cumulative hydrologic departure.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>1.20493</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">CHD_RiffDw</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>All_spcs</attrlabl><attrdef>Species richness for all species. See Knight and others (2014) for fish category definitions based on trophic, habitat, and tolerance characteristics.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>1</rdommin><rdommax>37</rdommax><attrunit>Number of species (count)</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">All_spcs</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">SmallInteger</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">4</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Pool_dwl</attrlabl><attrdef>Species richness for pool dwellers. These species require pool habitat (both shallow pools and deep pools) and feed on drifting and surface invertebrates. Most are active swimmers. See Knight and others (2014) for fish category definitions based on trophic, habitat, and tolerance characteristics.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>1</rdommin><rdommax>28</rdommax><attrunit>Number of species (count)</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Pool_dwl</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">SmallInteger</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">4</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>LRA7</attrlabl><attrdef>Rate of streamflow recession, computed as the log transform of the median change in log of flow for days in which the change is negative across the entire flow record. See Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of streamflow characteristics and model specifications for estimating dependent variables (streamflow characteristics) from basin-scale independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0.400063</rdommin><rdommax>1.380505</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">LRA7</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>CHD_Spc_in</attrlabl><attrdef>Cumulative hydrologic departure value (independent variable) that was used in quantile regression with species richness for specialized insectivores (dependent variable). This value of cumulative hydrologic departure is equal to the sum of hydrologic departure values for the streamflow characteristics that had significant (P&lt;0.05) 85th, 90th, or 95th regression quantiles based on quantile regression relating the departures of individual streamflow characteristics to species richness, stratified by fish group. For specialised insectivores, individual departure values for AMH10, TL1, and TA1 were used to calculate cumulative hydrologic departure. See entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics, fish groups, and hydrologic departure values. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating cumulative hydrologic departure.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>1.20493</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">CHD_Spc_in</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>CHD_Invert</attrlabl><attrdef>Cumulative hydrologic departure value (independent variable) that was used in quantile regression with species richness for invertivores (dependent variable). This value of cumulative hydrologic departure is equal to the sum of hydrologic departure values for the streamflow characteristics that had significant (P&lt;0.05) 85th, 90th, or 95th regression quantiles based on quantile regression relating the departures of individual streamflow characteristics to species richness, stratified by fish group. For invertivores, the individual departure value for AMH10 was used to calculate cumulative hydrologic departure. See entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics, fish groups, and hydrologic departure values. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating cumulative hydrologic departure.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>0.517541</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">CHD_Invert</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Dep_LML18</attrlabl><attrdef>Departure from hydrologic reference conditions for the streamflow characteristic LML18; see entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics. Departure from reference conditions is calculated as the absolute value of the difference between the estimated value of LML18 and the reference range (defined by the 25th and 75th percentiles for the 20 sites in the study area with greatest percent forest cover). For LML18, the 25th percentile value was 0.2971 and the 75th percentile value was 0.7334. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating departure from hydrologic reference conditions.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>0.463162</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Dep_LML18</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Dep_FH6</attrlabl><attrdef>Departure from hydrologic reference conditions for the streamflow characteristic FH6; see entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics. Departure from reference conditions is calculated as the absolute value of the difference between the estimated value of FH6 and the reference range (defined by the 25th and 75th percentiles for the 20 sites in the study area with greatest percent forest cover). For FH6, the 25th percentile value was 0.1221 and the 75th percentile value was 0.7247. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating departure from hydrologic reference conditions.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>0.328025</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Dep_FH6</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Dep_LFH7</attrlabl><attrdef>Departure from hydrologic reference conditions for the streamflow characteristic LFH7; see entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics. Departure from reference conditions is calculated as the absolute value of the difference between the estimated value of LFH7 and the reference range (defined by the 25th and 75th percentiles for the 20 sites in the study area with greatest percent forest cover). For LFH7, the 25th percentile value was 0.5543 and the 75th percentile value was 0.8789. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating departure from hydrologic reference conditions.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>0.250651</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Dep_LFH7</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Dep_LDH13</attrlabl><attrdef>Departure from hydrologic reference conditions for the streamflow characteristic LDH13; see entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics. Departure from reference conditions is calculated as the absolute value of the difference between the estimated value of LDH13 and the reference range (defined by the 25th and 75th percentiles for the 20 sites in the study area with greatest percent forest cover). For LDH13, the 25th percentile value was 0.3537 and the 75th percentile value was 0.7679. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating departure from hydrologic reference conditions.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>0.206787</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Dep_LDH13</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>LDL6</attrlabl><attrdef>Variability of annual minimum daily average streamflow, computed as the log transform of the standard deviation for the minimum daily average streamflow. Multiply by 100 and divide by the mean streamflow for the period. See Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of streamflow characteristics and model specifications for estimating dependent variables (streamflow characteristics) from basin-scale independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-0.003628</rdommin><rdommax>1.234901</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">LDL6</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>LML18</attrlabl><attrdef>Variability in base flow, computed as the log transform of the standard deviation of the ratios of 7-day moving average flows to mean annual flows for each year multiplied by 100. See Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of streamflow characteristics and model specifications for estimating dependent variables (streamflow characteristics) from basin-scale independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0.056688</rdommin><rdommax>1.196562</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">LML18</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Dep_MA41</attrlabl><attrdef>Departure from hydrologic reference conditions for the streamflow characteristic MA41; see entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics. Departure from reference conditions is calculated as the absolute value of the difference between the estimated value of MA41 and the reference range (defined by the 25th and 75th percentiles for the 20 sites in the study area with greatest percent forest cover). For MA41, the 25th percentile value was -0.4378 and the 75th percentile value was 0.4214. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating departure from hydrologic reference conditions.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>1.413386</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Dep_MA41</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Intolerant</attrlabl><attrdef>Species richness for intolerants. These are species that are intolerant of various chemical and physical perturbations, and typically are the first species to disappear after a disturbance. See Knight and others (2014) for fish category definitions based on trophic, habitat, and tolerance characteristics.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>7</rdommax><attrunit>Number of species (count)</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Intolerant</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">SmallInteger</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">4</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Head_intol</attrlabl><attrdef>Species richness for headwater intolerants. These are intolerant species (see definition for the "Intolerant" attribute) that thrive to maturity in headwaters. See Knight and others (2014) for fish category definitions based on trophic, habitat, and tolerance characteristics.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>5</rdommax><attrunit>Number of species (count)</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Head_intol</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">SmallInteger</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">4</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>CHD_All_Sp</attrlabl><attrdef>Cumulative hydrologic departure value (independent variable) that was used in quantile regression with species richness for all species (dependent variable). This value of cumulative hydrologic departure is equal to the sum of hydrologic departure values for the streamflow characteristics that had significant (P&lt;0.05) 85th, 90th, or 95th regression quantiles based on quantile regression relating the departures of individual streamflow characteristics to species richness, stratified by fish group. For all species, the individual departure value for TL1 was used to calculate cumulative hydrologic departure. See entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics, fish groups, and hydrologic departure values. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating cumulative hydrologic departure.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>0.757709</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">CHD_All_Sp</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>RTE_spcs</attrlabl><attrdef>Species richness for rare, threatened, and endangered species. These species are defined according to Withers (2009).</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>3</rdommax><attrunit>Number of species (count)</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">RTE_spcs</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">SmallInteger</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">4</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Top_pred</attrlabl><attrdef>Species richness for top predators. These species feed, as adults, predominately on fish, other vertebrates, or crayfish. See Knight and others (2014) for fish category definitions based on trophic, habitat, and tolerance characteristics.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>6</rdommax><attrunit>Number of species (count)</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Top_pred</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">SmallInteger</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">4</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Dep_LDL6</attrlabl><attrdef>Departure from hydrologic reference conditions for the streamflow characteristic LDL6; see entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics. Departure from reference conditions is calculated as the absolute value of the difference between the estimated value of LDL6 and the reference range (defined by the 25th and 75th percentiles for the 20 sites in the study area with greatest percent forest cover). For LDL6, the 25th percentile value was 0.4113 and the 75th percentile value was 0.908. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating departure from hydrologic reference conditions.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>0.414928</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Dep_LDL6</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>CHD_LithSp</attrlabl><attrdef>Cumulative hydrologic departure value (independent variable) that was used in quantile regression with species richness for lithophilic spawners (dependent variable). This value of cumulative hydrologic departure is equal to the sum of hydrologic departure values for the streamflow characteristics that had significant (P&lt;0.05) 85th, 90th, or 95th regression quantiles based on quantile regression relating the departures of individual streamflow characteristics to species richness, stratified by fish group. For lithophilic spawners, individual departure values for AMH10, TL1, and TA1 were used to calculate cumulative hydrologic departure. See entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics, fish groups, and hydrologic departure values. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating cumulative hydrologic departure.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>1.20493</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">CHD_LithSp</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>CHD_TopPrd</attrlabl><attrdef>Cumulative hydrologic departure value (independent variable) that was used in quantile regression with species richness for top predators (dependent variable). This value of cumulative hydrologic departure is equal to the sum of hydrologic departure values for the streamflow characteristics that had significant (P&lt;0.05) 85th, 90th, or 95th regression quantiles based on quantile regression relating the departures of individual streamflow characteristics to species richness, stratified by fish group. For top predators, individual departure values for MA41 and TL1 were used to calculate cumulative hydrologic departure. See entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics, fish groups, and hydrologic departure values. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating cumulative hydrologic departure.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>2.164104</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">CHD_TopPrd</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Dep_ML20</attrlabl><attrdef>Departure from hydrologic reference conditions for the streamflow characteristic ML20; see entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics. Departure from reference conditions is calculated as the absolute value of the difference between the estimated value of ML20 and the reference range (defined by the 25th and 75th percentiles for the 20 sites in the study area with greatest percent forest cover). For ML20, the 25th percentile value was -1.0035 and the 75th percentile value was -0.6059. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating departure from hydrologic reference conditions.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>0.309432</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Dep_ML20</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>ElevFt</attrlabl><attrdef>Mean basin elevation derived from 1/3 arc-second digital elevation model; see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of independent variables (climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use) used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>-0.637112</rdommin><rdommax>0.627739</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">ElevFt</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>Dep_TL1</attrlabl><attrdef>Departure from hydrologic reference conditions for the streamflow characteristic TL1; see entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics. Departure from reference conditions is calculated as the absolute value of the difference between the estimated value of TL1 and the reference range (defined by the 25th and 75th percentiles for the 20 sites in the study area with greatest percent forest cover). For TL1, the 25th percentile value was -0.669 and the 75th percentile value was 0.044. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating departure from hydrologic reference conditions.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>0.757709</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Dep_TL1</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl>CHD_PoolDw</attrlabl><attrdef>Cumulative hydrologic departure value (independent variable) that was used in quantile regression with species richness for pool dwellers (dependent variable). This value of cumulative hydrologic departure is equal to the sum of hydrologic departure values for the streamflow characteristics that had significant (P&lt;0.05) 85th, 90th, or 95th regression quantiles based on quantile regression relating the departures of individual streamflow characteristics to species richness, stratified by fish group. For pool dwellers, individual departure values for TL1 and TA1 were used to calculate cumulative hydrologic departure. See entity and attribute metadata for definitions of all streamflow characteristics, fish groups, and hydrologic departure values. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating cumulative hydrologic departure.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>1.071821</rdommax><attrunit>standardized units</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">CHD_PoolDw</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">16</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">15</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">6</attscale></attr></detailed><overview><eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes datasets to support development of ecological limit functions for the Cumberland Plateau in northeastern Middle Tennessee and southeastern Kentucky. The datasets contain values of basin characteristics, estimates of streamflow characteristics, measures of individual and cumulative departure of streamflow characteristics from reference hydrologic conditions, and fish species richness for 138 sites in the study area. The basin characteristics describe climate, physical landscape features, regional indicators, and land use. These basin characteristics were used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations according to Knight and others (2012). The basin characteristics are: AgPct, ForestPct, IntPlatPct, BlueRdgPct, ElevFt, Horton, SoilFactor, G_Factor, MonMnPrec, JanPrecDev, DayTempRng, AugTempDev, RockDepth, SoilFac_in, RockDep_in, and G_Fact_in. A brief definition for each basin characteristic is provided in the entity and attribute description. Please see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of all basin characteristics and of methodology used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations using these basin characteristics as independent variables. The estimates of streamflow characteristics include measures of the magnitude, duration, frequency, timing, and rate of change of the annual hydrograph. These estimates were calculated according to Knight and others (2012) using regional predictive equations with basin characteristics as independent variables. The estimates of streamflow characteristics are: MA41, LRA7, E85, AMH10, LDH13, ML20, TA1, LFH7, FH6, LML18, LDL6, MA26, and TL1. A brief definition for each streamflow characteristic is provided in the entity and attribute description. Please see Knight and others (2012) for detailed descriptions of all streamflow characteristics and of methodology used to estimate streamflow characteristics based on regional predictive equations with basin characteristics as independent variables. Departure values for individual streamflow characteristics were determined by calculating the numerical distance (difference) outside the reference range for each streamflow characteristic. Reference hydrologic conditions for the study area were determined using methods presented in Knight and others (2012; 2014). Reference ranges are included in the entity and attribute descriptions for the fields representing individual hydrologic departure values. These individual hydrologic departure values are: Dep_MA41, Dep_LRA7, Dep_E85, Dep_AMH10, Dep_LDH13, Dep_ML20, Dep_TA1, Dep_LFH7, Dep_FH6, Dep_LML18, Dep_LDL6, Dep_MA26, and Dep_TL1. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating departure from hydrologic reference conditions. Cumulative departure of streamflow characteristics from reference hydrologic conditions is equal to the sum of individual hydrologic departure values for the streamflow characteristics that had significant (P&lt;0.05) 85th, 90th, or 95th regression quantiles based on quantile regression relating the departures of individual streamflow characteristics to species richness, stratified by fish group. The cumulative hydrologic departure (CHD) variables are: CHD_Headw, CHD_Intol, CHD_Native, CHD_Invert, CHD_Spec_in, CHD_TopPrd, CHD_LithSp, CHD_PoolDw, CHD_RiffDw, CHD_All_Sp, and CHD_RTE_Sp. For each CHD variable, the individual streamflow characteristics that were used to calculate the cumulative hydrologic departure values are listed in the entity and attribute description. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of methodology for calculating cumulative hydrologic departure. Fish species richness (counts) are presented for each fish group. The fish groups are: Head_intol, Intolerant, Native, Invertivor, Spec_insec, Top_pred, Lith_spawn, Pool_dwl, Riffle_dwl, All_spcs, and RTE_spcs. A brief definition for each fish group is provided in the entity and attribute description. See Knight and others (2014) for detailed descriptions of fish groups based on trophic, habitat, and tolerance characteristics. See Withers (2009) for lists of fish species that are considered rare, threatened, or endangered (RTE). References: Knight, R.R., Gain, W.S., and Wolfe, W.J., 2012, Modelling ecological flow regime: an example from the Tennessee and Cumberland River basins: Ecohydrology, v. 5, p. 613–627, http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/eco.246 Knight, R.R., Murphy, J.C., Wolfe, W.J., Saylor, C.F., and Wales, A.K., 2014, Ecological limit functions relating fish community response to hydrologic departures of the ecological flow regime in the Tennessee River basin, United States: Ecohydrology, v. 7, p. 1262–1280, http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/eco.1460 Withers, D., 2009, Tennessee Natural Heritage Program rare animals list: Division of Natural Areas, Tennessee Department of Environment and Conservation, Nashville, TN, 61 p, last accessed on November 19, 2015, at https://www.tn.gov/assets/entities/environment/attachments/na_animal-list.pdf</eaover><eadetcit>All entity and attribute information was generated by the originator of the data set. Please review the overview description and individual attribute definitions for more information.</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><mdHrLvName Sync="TRUE">dataset</mdHrLvName><refSysInfo><RefSystem><refSysID><identCode code="4269" Sync="TRUE"></identCode><idCodeSpace Sync="TRUE">EPSG</idCodeSpace><idVersion Sync="TRUE">8.2.6</idVersion></refSysID></RefSystem></refSysInfo><spdoinfo><ptvctinf><esriterm Name="Cumberland_Plateau_streamflow_and_fish_data"><efeatyp Sync="TRUE">Simple</efeatyp><efeageom code="1" Sync="TRUE"></efeageom><esritopo Sync="TRUE">FALSE</esritopo><efeacnt Sync="TRUE">138</efeacnt><spindex Sync="TRUE">TRUE</spindex><linrefer Sync="TRUE">FALSE</linrefer></esriterm></ptvctinf></spdoinfo></metadata>
