<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Mark C. Kasmarek</origin>
        <origin>Jason K. Ramage</origin>
        <pubdate>20160324</pubdate>
        <title>DATA Water-Level Measurement Data Collected during 2015-2016 and Approximate Long-term Water-Level Altitude Changes of Wells Screened in the Chicot, Jasper, and Evangeline Aquifers in the Houston-Galveston Region, Texas.</title>
        <geoform>csv</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Austin, TX</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F77H1GP3</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The U.S. Geological Survey in cooperation with the Harris‐Galveston Subsidence District, City of Houston, Fort Bend Subsidence District, and Lone Star Groundwater Conservation District has produced this dataset of water‐level altitudes and water‐level changes in the Chicot, Evangeline, and Jasper aquifers in the Houston‐Galveston region, Texas.This dataset shows current‐year (2015-2016) water‐level altitudes for each aquifer, 5‐year (2011‐16) water‐level changes for each aquifer, long‐term (1990‐2016 and 1977‐2016) water‐level changes for the Chicot and Evangeline aquifers, and long‐term (2000‐2016) water‐level change for the Jasper aquifer. For the 1‐year (2015-16) water‐level changes, data were computed as the difference in water‐level altitude at each point (well) for which a water‐level measurement was made in 2015 and 2016. Five‐year (2011‐16) water‐level changes were computed the same as for the 1‐year water-level changes; the difference in water‐level altitude at each point for which a water‐level measurement was made in 2011 and 2016. The water‐level measurements in the dataset are built upon and stored in the National Water Information System: Web Interface, groundwater information, field measurements website located here:
http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7P55KJN
This site is a publicly available, searchable, online database of water information.</abstract>
      <purpose>Most of the land-surface subsidence in the Houston-Galveston region, Texas, occurs as a direct result of groundwater withdrawals for municipal supply, commercial and industrial use, and irrigation that depressured and dewatered the Chicot, Evangeline, and Jasper aquifers, thereby causing compaction of the aquifer sediments, mostly in the fine-grained silt and clay layers. This dataset, part of an annual series of reports, was created by the U.S. Geological Survey, in cooperation with the Harris‐Galveston Subsidence District, City of Houston, Fort Bend Subsidence District, Lone Star Groundwater Conservation District, and Brazoria County Groundwater Conservation District, to provide resource managers, public officials, researchers, and the general public with ready access to accurate, impartial, scientific information regarding groundwater‐level changes and altitudes in Harris, Galveston, Fort Bend, Montgomery, Brazoria, Chambers, Grimes, Liberty, San Jacinto, Walker, and Waller Counties, Texas</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20151207</begdate>
          <enddate>20160304</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Annually</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Data were measured in wells in 11 counties in the Houston-Galveston region, Texas.</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-96.042013726453</westbc>
        <eastbc>-94.851762914057</eastbc>
        <northbc>31.333428024661</northbc>
        <southbc>29.915310111785</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>groundwater</themekey>
        <themekey>subsidence</themekey>
        <themekey>hydrology</themekey>
        <themekey>aquifer</themekey>
        <themekey>hypsometry</themekey>
        <themekey>water-level altitude</themekey>
        <themekey>Chicot aquifer</themekey>
        <themekey>Evangeline aquifer</themekey>
        <themekey>Jasper aquifer</themekey>
        <themekey>elevation</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System (GNIS)</placekt>
        <placekey>Texas</placekey>
        <placekey>Harris County</placekey>
        <placekey>Fort Bend County</placekey>
        <placekey>Montgomery County</placekey>
        <placekey>Walker County</placekey>
        <placekey>Brazoria County</placekey>
        <placekey>Waller County</placekey>
        <placekey>Grimes County</placekey>
        <placekey>Liberty County</placekey>
        <placekey>San Jacinto County</placekey>
        <placekey>Galveston County</placekey>
        <placekey>Chambers County</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Texas Water Science Center Public Information Officer</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1505 Ferguson Lane</address>
          <city>Austin</city>
          <state>TX</state>
          <postal>78754</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(512) 927-3500</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>gs-w-txpublic-info@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>Harris-Galveston Subsidence District, Lone Star Groundwater Conservation District, City of Houston, Fort Bend Subsidence District, Brazoria County Groundwater Conservation District</datacred>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>All feature attribute values were peer reviewed. Values were checked for correct data type and for presence/absence of data. For the 1‐year (2015‐16) water‐level changes, data were computed as the difference in water‐level altitude at each point (well) for which a water‐level measurement was made in 2015 and 2016. For the 5‐year (2011‐16) change water‐level changes were computed the same as for the 1‐year water-level changes; the difference in water‐level altitude at each point for which a water‐level measurement was made in 2011 and 2016. See Process Steps for historical water-level altitude calculations.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>All water‐level altitude or water‐level change point data (wells) match up with the details provided about it and values fall within the expected ranges.</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Horizontal positional accuracy of the point data is dependent on the source data used to define the location of the well (digital orthophotograph, GPS, survey, etc.). Only the source data type and accuracy associated with the location of the well were retained in the Groundwater Site‐Inventory System (U.S.&#xD;
Geological Survey, 1998) of the U.S. Geological Survey National Water Information System (U.S. Geological Survey, 2002) accessed here, http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7P55KJN</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>Vertical positional accuracy of the point data is referenced to NAVD 88 and is dependent on the source data used to define the location of the well (U.S. Geological Survey 7.5‐minute topographic quadrangle, digital elevation model (DEM), GPS, survey, etc. and the method (calibrated steel tape, air line, and electric water‐level tape, or from reports of well operators) and accuracy of the measurement (0.01, 0.1 or to the nearest foot) of the depth to the potentiometric surface of the aquifer. Only the source data type and accuracy associated with the location of the well were retained in the Groundwater Site‐Inventory System of the U.S. Geological Survey National Water Information System accessed here, http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7P55KJN.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>Field</methtype>
        <methdesc>Water‐level data were obtained by calibrated steel tape, air line, electric water‐level tape, and from reported data by company well operators. The reported water-level (whole number, tenths or hundredths) and level of measurement accuracy is determined at the discretion of the field personnel.</methdesc>
      </method>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Mark C. Kasmarek, Jason K. Ramage, Natalie A. Houston, Michaela R. Johnson, and Tiffany S. Schmidt</origin>
            <pubdate>20151016</pubdate>
            <title>Water-level altitudes 2015 and water-level changes in the Chicot, Evangeline, and Jasper aquifers and compaction 1973-2014 in the Chicot and Evangeline aquifers, Houston-Galveston region, Texas</title>
            <geoform>numerical</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Reston, Virginia</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/sim3337</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>Report</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>20141201</begdate>
              <enddate>20150331</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Scientific Investigations Map</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Texas Water Science Center</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>2002</pubdate>
            <title>NWISWeb: New Site for the Nation's Water Data</title>
            <geoform>numerical</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Reston, Virginia</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/fs/FS‐148‐02/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>Fact Sheet</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>20160101</begdate>
              <enddate>20160102</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>NWIS</srccitea>
        <srccontr>U.S. Geological Survey</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>R.K. Gabrysch</origin>
            <pubdate>1979</pubdate>
            <title>Approximate water-level changes in wells in the Chicot and Evangeline aquifers, 1977-79, and measured compaction, 1973-79, in Harris and Galveston Counties, Texas</title>
            <geoform>text</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Reston, Virginia</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr79693</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>Report</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>19770111</begdate>
              <enddate>19790205</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Open-File Report 79-693</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Texas Water Science Center</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>William L. Cunningham and Charles W. Schalk</origin>
            <pubdate>2011</pubdate>
            <title>Groundwater Technical Procedures of the U.S. Geological Survey</title>
            <geoform>text</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Reston, Virginia</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/tm/1a1/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>Report</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>20110101</begdate>
              <enddate>20111231</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>data compilation</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>USGS Techniques and Methods</srccitea>
        <srccontr>U.S. Geological Survey</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Water‐level data were obtained by calibrated steel tape, air line, electric water‐level tape, and from reported data by company well operators (Cunningham and Schalk, 2011). The data were then imported into a database using approved and standard procedures. Depth to water measurement accuracy is to the nearest hundredth and at the discretion of field personnel. Altitude measurements are rounded to whole numbers as explained in Kasmarek and others (2015) in the "Source Information" metadata. All blank data cells represent unavailable data or data not measured in a particular well.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160304</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>For the 1‐year (2015-16) water‐level changes, data were computed as the difference in water‐level altitude at each point (well) for which a water‐level measurement was made in 2015 and 2016. Five‐year (2011‐16) water‐level changes were computed the same as for the 1‐year water-level changes; the difference in water‐level altitude at each point for which a water‐level measurement was made in 2011 and 2016.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160312</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>For the historical (2000‐2016, 1990‐2016, 1977‐2016) water‐level‐changes, change values were computed as the difference in water‐level altitude at each point (well) for which a water‐level measurement was made in 2016 and the water‐level altitude at that point on a gridded surface of the historical water‐level‐altitude map (Kasmarek and others, 2015).</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160312</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>For the Chicot aquifer:&#xD;
195 water‐level measurements were used to calculate the 2016 water‐level altitude, 181 water‐level pairs were used for the 2015‐16 water‐level change, 151 water‐level pairs for the 2011‐16 water‐level change, 169 water‐level pairs for the 1990‐2016 water‐level change, and 151 water‐level pairs for the 1977‐2016 water‐level change.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160312</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>For the Evangeline aquifer:&#xD;
361 water‐level measurements were used for the 2016 water‐level altitude, 361 water‐level pairs were used for the 2015‐16 water‐level change, 296 water‐level pairs for the 2011‐16 water‐level change, 298 water‐level pairs for the 1990‐2016 water‐level change, and 284 water‐level pairs for the 1977‐2016 water‐level change.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160312</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>For the Jasper aquifer:&#xD;
112 water‐level measurements were used for the 2016 water‐level altitude, 112 water‐level pairs were used for the 2015‐16 water‐level change, 79 water‐level pairs for the 2011‐16 water‐level change, and 93 water‐level pairs for the 2000‐2016 water‐level change.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160312</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>To create the shapefile of the 2016 water-level measuring points: Database retrieval from NWIS GWSI of water‐level measurements to comma‐delimited text file. In ESRI ArcMap,  added latitude and longitude exported the points to generate a shapefile of 2016 water‐level measurements, in feet below land surface. Export native geographic NAD83 point features using the data frame properties (set to UTM, Zone 15, NAD 83).</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160312</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>To calculate 2016 water level altitude in feet referenced to NAVD 88 for each aquifer: [WLALT16 = LSALT ‐ DTW16]. Water level altitudes for 1977, 1990, 2000, 2011, and 2016 have already been calculated by this method and were published in the reports listed in the preceding 'Source_Information' section. These data will be used in the section describing the water-level change datasets.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160312</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Water-level change (1-year) for each aquifer (Chicot, Jasper, and Evangeline): [DIFF1516] = [LSALT ‐ DTW16] - [LSALT ‐ DTW15].</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160313</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Water-level change (5-year) for each aquifer (Chicot, Jasper, and Evangeline): [DIFF1116 = WLALT16 ‐ WLALT11]</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160313</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Water-level change, 1990‐2016 for the Chicot and Evangeline aquifer: [DIFF9016 = WLALT16 ‐ WLALT90]. Note: Many of the wells in 1990 were not measured in 2016 or have been destroyed. Conversely, some of the wells measured in 2016 either were not measured or were not in existence in 1990. As a result, the value from the 1990 water‐level altitude grid was assigned to the point in the attribute, WLALT90GD. For these subset of wells: [DIFF9016 = WLALT16 - WLALT90GD] (Gabrysch, 1979).</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160313</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Water-level change, 1977‐2016 for the Chicot and Evangeline aquifer: [DIFF7716 = WLALT16 - WLALT77].  Note: Many of the wells in 1977 were not measured in 2016 or have been destroyed. Conversely, some of the wells measured in 2016 either were not measured or were not in existence in 1977. As a result, the value from the 1977 water‐level altitude grid was assigned to the point in the attribute, WLALT77GD. For these subset of wells: [DIFF7716 = WLALT16 - WLALT77GD] (Gabrysch, 1979).</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160313</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Water-level change, 2000‐2016 the Jasper aquifer: [DIFF0016 = WLALT16 - WLALT00]. Note: Many of the wells in 2000 were not measured in 2016 or have been destroyed. Conversely, some of the wells measured in 2016 either were not measured or were not in existence in 2000. As a result, the value from the 2000 water‐level altitude grid was assigned to the point in the attribute, WLALT00GD. For these subset of wells: [DIFF0016 = WLALT16 - WLALT00GD] (Gabrysch, 1979).</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160313</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Point</direct>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>Transverse Mercator</mapprojn>
          <transmer>
            <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
            <longcm>-93.0</longcm>
            <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
            <feast>500000.0</feast>
            <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
          </transmer>
        </mapproj>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>Clarke 1866</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378206.4</semiaxis>
        <denflat>294.978698</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
    <vertdef>
      <altsys>
        <altdatum>North American Vertical Datum of 1988</altdatum>
        <altres>1.0</altres>
        <altunits>feet</altunits>
        <altenc>Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc>
      </altsys>
    </vertdef>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>2015_16_WL_Changes.csv</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set. The contents of this dataset include water-level measurement data collected during 2015 to 2016 and approximate long-term water-level altitudes from 1977 to 2016 of wells screened in the Chicot, Jasper, and Evangeline aquifers in an 11-county area in the Houston-Galveston region, Texas.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>U.S. Geological Survey Texas Water Science Center</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>USGS_SITE_NO</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>U.S. Geological Survey 15‐digit site identification number in the NWIS database. This number is the primary ID used to retrieve data from NWIS.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unique identifier.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>STATION_NM</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Name of well defined by county identifier and state well number.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unique identifier.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DTW16</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>2016 depth to water in feet measured from land surface.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>2.72</rdommin>
            <rdommax>421.74</rdommax>
            <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DIFF1516</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>One-year water‐level changes, 2015 to 2016.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-65</rdommin>
            <rdommax>75</rdommax>
            <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>WLALT16</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Approximate 2016 water‐level altitudes referenced to North American Vertical Datum of 1988.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-281</rdommin>
            <rdommax>253</rdommax>
            <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DATE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Date of the water-level measurement, December 2015 to March 2016.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Month, day, and year of water level measurement, December 2015 to March 2016.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>LSALT</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Land surface elevation referenced to North American Vertical Datum of 1988.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>409.09</rdommax>
            <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DTW16</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>2016 depth to water in feet measured from land surface.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>2.72</rdommin>
            <rdommax>421.74</rdommax>
            <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>AQUIFER</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The name of the aquifer where the measured well is screened. The aquifer name came corresponding to each well can be retrieved from NWIS.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Various entities.</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Represents the name of the aquifer or hydrogeologic unit.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>REGAREA</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The defined regulatory area where the well is located.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Entities making up the regulatory areas in the study include Harris-Galveston Subsidence District, Lone Star Groundwater Conservation District, Brazoria County Groundwater Conservation District, City of Houston, and Fort Bend Subsidence District. Fields marked as "not applicable" represent wells located in unregulated areas in the 11-county region.</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>The field represents the name of a regulatory area in the 11 county region including Houston, Texas.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DEC_LAT</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Latitude in decimal degrees.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Latitude in decimal degrees. This number can be retrieved from NWIS.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DEC_LONG</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Longitude in decimal degrees. This number can be retrieved from NWIS.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Longitude of point (well).</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>FID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SHAPE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Coordinates defining features.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Coordinates defining features.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DTW15</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>2015 depth to water in feet measured from land surface.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>424.5</rdommax>
            <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>WLALT11</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>2011 water-level altitude referenced to North American Vertical Datum of 1988.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-320</rdommin>
            <rdommax>262</rdommax>
            <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DIFF1116</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Change in water level altitude, 2011 to 2016.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-104</rdommin>
            <rdommax>101</rdommax>
            <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>WLALT00</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>2000 water-level altitude referenced to North American Vertical Datum of 1988.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-102</rdommin>
            <rdommax>275</rdommax>
            <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>WLALT00GD</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>2000 Water-level altitude extracted from the 2000 water-level altitude grid in feet referenced to North American Vertical Datum 1988.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-87</rdommin>
            <rdommax>276</rdommax>
            <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DIFF0016</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Change in water level altitude in feet, 2000 to 2016.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-225</rdommin>
            <rdommax>-2</rdommax>
            <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>WLALT90</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>1990 water-level altitude referenced to North American Vertical Datum of 1988 (NAVD 1988)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-393</rdommin>
            <rdommax>174</rdommax>
            <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>WLALT90GD</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>1990 water-level altitude extracted from the 1990 water-level altitude grid in feet referenced to North American Vertical Datum 1988.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-355</rdommin>
            <rdommax>174</rdommax>
            <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DIFF9016</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Change in water level altitude in feet, 1990 to 2016.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-202</rdommin>
            <rdommax>187</rdommax>
            <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>WLALT77</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Water-level altitude measurements in wells in 1977.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-391</rdommin>
            <rdommax>174</rdommax>
            <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>WLALT77GD</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>1977 water-level altitude extracted from the 1977 water-level altitude grid in feet referenced to North American Vertical Datum 1988.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-369</rdommin>
            <rdommax>174</rdommax>
            <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DIFF7716</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Change in water level altitude in feet, 1977 to 2016.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-338</rdommin>
            <rdommax>283</rdommax>
            <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>U.S. Geological Survey</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items must be secured from the copyright owner whenever applicable. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although the data have been subjected to rigorous review and are substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, the data are released on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from authorized or unauthorized use. Although the data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Users of this data are advised to read all metadata and associated documentation thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>csv</formname>
          <formvern>Microsoft Excel</formvern>
          <formspec>csv file</formspec>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F77H1GP3</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160426</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Texas Water Science Center Public Information Officer</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1505 Ferguson Ln</address>
          <city>Austin</city>
          <state>TX</state>
          <postal>78754</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(512) 927-3500</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>gs-w-txpublic-info@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>

