<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="fgdc_classic.xsl"?>
<metadata xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/metadata/usgswrd/fgdc-std-001-1998.xsd">
	<idinfo>
		<citation>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin>Denver, Judith M.</origin>
				<origin>Nardi, Mark R.</origin>
				<pubdate>05/2016</pubdate>
				<title>Thickness of the Surficial Aquifer, Delmarva Peninsula, Maryland and Delaware</title>
				<geoform>Raster Digital Data Set</geoform>
				<serinfo>
					<sername>U.S. Geological Survey data release</sername>
					<issue></issue>
				</serinfo>
				<pubinfo>
					<pubplace>Reston, Virginia</pubplace>
					<publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
				</pubinfo>
				<onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7610XFT</onlink>
			</citeinfo>
		</citation>
		<descript>
			<abstract>A digital map of the thickness of the surficial unconfined aquifer, including from the land surface and unsaturated zone to the bottom of sediments of geologic units identified as part of the surficial aquifer, was produced to improve understanding of the hydrologic system in the Maryland and Delaware portions of the Delmarva Peninsula. The map is intended to be used in conjunction with other environmental coverages (such land use, wetlands, and soil characteristics) to provide a subsurface hydrogeologic component to studies of nitrate transport that have historically relied on maps of surficial features. It could also be used to study the transport of other water soluble chemicals.

	The map was made using the best currently available data, which was of varying scales. It was created by overlaying a high resolution land surface and bathymetry digital elevation model (DEM) on a digital representation of the base of the surficial aquifer, part of hydrogeologic framework, as defined by Andreasen and others (2013).  Thickness was calculated as the difference between the top of land surface and the bottom of the surficial aquifer sediments, which include sediments from geologic formations of late-Miocene through Quaternary age.   Geologic formations with predominantly sandy surficial sediments that comprise the surficial aquifer on the Delmarva Peninsula include the Parsonsburg Sand, Sinepuxent Formation (Fm.), and parts of the Omar Fm. north of Indian River Bay in Delaware, the Columbia Fm., Beaverdam Fm., and Pennsauken Fm. (Ator and others 2005; Owens and Denney, 1986; Mixon, 1985; Bachman and Wilson, 1984). Formations with mixed texture and sandy stratigraphy including the Scotts Corner Fm. and Lynch Heights Fm. in Delaware are also considered part of the surficial aquifer (Ramsey, 1997).  Subcropping aquifers and confining beds underlie the surficial aquifer throughout the Peninsula and may increase or limit its thickness, respectively (Andreasen and others, 2013). Stream incision through the surficial aquifer into older fine-textured sediments is more common in the northern part of the Peninsula where confined aquifers and their confining beds subcrop beneath the surficial aquifer. The potential for nitrate transport is greatest where relatively coarse sediments of the unconfined surficial aquifer (such as sand and gravel), are present beneath uplands and streams. Where these sediments are truncated and the streambed is incised into underlying fine-textured sediments, the potential for nitrate transport is much less and typically limited to stream-bank seeps that flow across the floodplain.  

	In parts of south-central Maryland and southern Delaware the surficial aquifer sediments are complex with surficial sandy sediments generally less than 20 ft thick (indicated as 19 ft on the map). They include the Parsonsburg Sand and some surficial sandy facies of the Omar Fm. underlain by predominantly fine-textured sediments of the Walston Silt and Omar Fm. (Denney and others, 1979; Owens and Denney, 1979). Even though the surficial aquifer is relatively thin in this area, extensive ditching of flat poorly drained farmland allows seasonal transport of nitrate from groundwater to streams when the water table is above the base of the ditches (Lindsey and others, 2003).

	Geologic units of the Coastal Lowlands that surround the Peninsula are relatively thin in many areas and are primarily composed of fine-grained estuarine deposits with some coarse-textured sediments, in particular remnant beach-ridge and dune deposits (Ator and others, 2005).  The Kent Island Fm. (Owens and Denney, 1986), which is part of the Coastal Lowlands on the western side of the Peninsula, has predominantly fine-grained sediments and is not included in the surficial aquifer in Maryland, as defined by Bachman and Wilson (1984); the surficial aquifer is shown to have 0 ft thickness on the map in the area mapped as Kent Island Fm. Also shown on the map as 0 ft thickness are areas in the northern most portion of the peninsula in New Castle and Cecil counties where surficial aquifer sediments are not present and other areas such as stream valleys where surficial aquifer sediments are also not present. Nitrate transport through groundwater to surface water is limited in the areas with fine-grained sediments at or near the land surface that promote denitrification in groundwater (Ator and others, 2005). Where extensive tidal marshes overly the Coastal Lowlands they also limit nitrate transport to surface waters.

	Available sub-regional or county-scale geologic maps produced by the Delaware and Maryland State Geologic Surveys should be consulted when using this product (www.dgs.udel.edu; www.mgs.md.gov).  Local-scale maps will be particularly important in understanding areas such as where the surficial aquifer is completely truncated or very thin and overlies confining beds or confined aquifers, in the Coastal Lowlands, and in south-central Maryland and Delaware. 




			References:

			Andreasen, D.C., Staley, A.W., and Achmad, Grufon, 2013.  Maryland Coastal Plain Aquifer Information system:  Hydrogeological Framework: Maryland Department of Natural Resources Resource Assessment Service Maryland Geological Survey Open-File Report No. 12-02-20,121 p. 

			Ator, S.W., Denver, J.M., Krantz D.E., Newell, W.L., and Martucci, S.K., 2005.  A surficial hydrogeologic framework for the Mid-Atlantic Coastal Plain: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 1680, 44 p., 4 plates.

			Bachman, L.J. and Wilson, J.M., 1984.  The Columbia Aquifer of the Eastern Shore of Maryland:  Maryland Geological Survey Report of Investigations No. 40, 144 p.
			Denney, C.S., Owens, J.P. and Sirkin, L.A., 1979. The Parsonsburg Sand in the Central Delmarva Peninsula, Maryland and Delaware: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 1067-B, 16 p.

			Lindsey, B.D., Phillips, S.W., Donnelly, C.A., Speiran, G.K., Plummer, L.N., Böhlke, J.K., Focazio, M.J., Burton, W.C., and Busenberg, Eurybiades, 2003.  Residence times and nitrate transport in ground water discharging to streams in the Chesapeake Bay watershed:  U.S. Geological Survey Water-Resources Investigations Report 03-4035, 201 p.

			Mixon, R.B., 1985.  Stratigraphic and geomorphic framework of the upper most Cenozoic deposits in the southern Delmarva Peninsula, Virginia and Maryland: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 1067-G, 53 p.

			Owens, J.P. and Denney, C.S., 1979.  Upper Cenozoic Deposits of the Central Delmarva Peninsula, Maryland and Delaware:  U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 1067-A, 28 p.

			--------, 1986.  Geologic map of Dorchester County, Maryland:  Maryland Geological Survey, 1 sheet, scale 1:62,500.

			Ramsey, K.W., 1997.  Geology of the Milford and Mispillion River Quadrangles, Delaware:  Delaware Geological Survey Report of Investigations No. 55, 40 p.
			</abstract>
			<purpose>The purpose of this dataset is to inform resource managers and the public about the thickness of the surficial aquifer of the Delmarva Peninsula.  Thickness of the surficial aquifer can impact nutrient transport and characteristics of groundwater flow paths which can in turn effect the fate and transport of contaminants.</purpose>
			<supplinf>Users of this dataset may notice a moire, or secondary pattern superimposed on the data, that may cause a certain appearance of blockiness.  This effect is the result of overlaying fine grained, 100 foot or 30.48 meter, grid cell land surface and bathymetric raster data on hydrogeologic framework raster data (Surficial aquifer base) that has a raster cell size of 2,500 feet or 762 meters.  The resulting dataset was stored at 30 meter resolution in order to maintain the fine stream network geometry.  Additionally in some very flat areas of the map, thickness rasters may express themselves as large squares of equal value.  This is also due to scale issues between high resolution lidar based DEM vs. the lower resolution hydrogeologic framework.</supplinf>
		</descript>
		<timeperd>
			<timeinfo>
				<sngdate>
					<caldate>20151230</caldate>
				</sngdate>
			</timeinfo>
			<current>ground condition</current>
		</timeperd>
		<status>
			<progress>Complete</progress>
			<update>None planned</update>
		</status>
		<spdom>
			<bounding>
				<westbc>-76.970494634</westbc>
				<eastbc>-74.409714184</eastbc>
				<northbc>40.003394977</northbc>
				<southbc>37.336811492</southbc>
			</bounding>
		</spdom>
		<keywords>
			<theme>
				<themekt>None</themekt>
				<themekey>Coastal Plain Aquifer</themekey>
				<themekey>Quaternary Sediments</themekey>
				<themekey>Groundwater</themekey>
				<themekey>Water Quality</themekey>
				<themekey>Aquifer Thickness</themekey>
				<themekey>Raster Dataset</themekey>
			</theme>
			<theme>
				<themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
				<themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
				<themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
				<themekey>environment</themekey>
			</theme>
			<place>
				<placekt>None</placekt>
				<placekey>United States</placekey>
				<placekey>Northern Atlantic Coastal Plain</placekey>
				<placekey>Maryland</placekey>
				<placekey>Delaware</placekey>
				<placekey>Coastal Plain</placekey>
			</place>
		</keywords>
		<accconst>None. Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</accconst>
		<useconst>This map is intended to be used in conjunction with other environmental maps (including land use, wetlands, and soil characteristics) to add a subsurface hydrogeologic component to studies of nutrient transport that have historically relied on maps of surficial features.</useconst>
		<ptcontac>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntorgp>
					<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Northeast Region</cntorg>
					<cntper>Mark R Nardi</cntper>
				</cntorgp>
				<cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
					<address>1289 McD Drive</address>
					<city>Dover</city>
					<state>DE</state>
					<postal>19901</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>302-734-2506 x227</cntvoice>
				<cntfax>302-734-2964</cntfax>
				<cntemail>mrnardi@usgs.gov</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</ptcontac>
		<browse>
			<browsen>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/file/get/57100de4e4b0ef3b7ca3589b?f=__disk__ca%2F5e%2F76%2Fca5e76dbcea472eee0371b45d92d005c80582d55</browsen>
			<browsed>Image of the thickness of the Surficial Aquifer, Delmarva Peninsula, Maryland and Delaware</browsed>
			<browset>png</browset>
		</browse>
		<datacred>Maryland Geological Survey, Delaware Geological Survey, Maryland Department of Natural Resources, Delaware Department of Natural Resources and Environmental Control</datacred>
		<secinfo>
			<secsys>None</secsys>
			<secclass>Unclassified</secclass>
			<sechandl>None required, data unclassified</sechandl>
		</secinfo>
		<native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.2.2 (Build 3552) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native>
		<crossref>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin>Maryland Geological Survey</origin>
				<pubdate>20121202</pubdate>
				<title>Maryland Coastal Plain Aquifer Information system: Hydrogeological Framework</title>
				<geoform>map</geoform>
				<serinfo>
					<sername>Maryland Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
					<issue>DNR Publication No. 12-2272013-628</issue>
				</serinfo>
				<pubinfo>
					<pubplace>Annapolis, MD</pubplace>
					<publish>Maryland Department of Natural Resources</publish>
				</pubinfo>
			</citeinfo>
		</crossref>
	</idinfo>
	<dataqual>
		<attracc>
			<attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted.</attraccr>
		</attracc>
		<logic>All grid cells in study area have thickness values assigned as integers. NoData values have been set to -9999</logic>
		<complete>Data are complete in the study area.</complete>
		<posacc>
			<horizpa>
				<horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</horizpar>
			</horizpa>
			<vertacc>
				<vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr>
			</vertacc>
		</posacc>
		<lineage>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>Andreasen</origin>
						<pubdate>2013</pubdate>
						<title>Maryland Coastal Plain Aquifer Information system: Hydrogeological Framework</title>
						<geoform>Other</geoform>
						<pubinfo>
							<pubplace>Annapolis, MD</pubplace>
							<publish>Maryland Geological Survey</publish>
						</pubinfo>
						<onlink>http://www.mgs.md.gov/reports/OFR_12-02-20.pdf</onlink>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<srcscale>1000000</srcscale>
				<typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
				<srctime>
					<timeinfo>
						<sngdate>
							<caldate>2013</caldate>
						</sngdate>
					</timeinfo>
					<srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
				</srctime>
				<srccitea>Framework</srccitea>
				<srccontr>Hydrogeologic framework used to calculate aquifer thickness.</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>U.S. Geological Survey, Ryan Stumvoll, David Selnick, and Roger Barlow</origin>
						<pubdate>Unpublished</pubdate>
						<title>Delmarva DEM; combined land surface and bathymetric data from various best available sources</title>
						<geoform>Raster Digital Data</geoform>
						<pubinfo>
							<publish>Unpublished material</publish>
						</pubinfo>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<srcscale>1200</srcscale>
				<typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
				<srctime>
					<timeinfo>
						<rngdates>
							<begdate>20131217</begdate>
							<enddate>20140406</enddate>
						</rngdates>
					</timeinfo>
					<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
				</srctime>
				<srccitea>DEM</srccitea>
				<srccontr>Used as land surface elevation</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>Scott W. Ator and others</origin>
						<pubdate>2005</pubdate>
						<title>Surficial Geology for the Mid-Atlantic Coastal Plain</title>
						<geoform>Vector Digital Data Set</geoform>
						<pubinfo>
							<pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
							<publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
						</pubinfo>
						<onlink>http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/metadata/usgswrd/XML/pp1680_srfgl.xml</onlink>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<srcscale>1000000</srcscale>
				<typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
				<srctime>
					<timeinfo>
						<sngdate>
							<caldate>2001</caldate>
						</sngdate>
					</timeinfo>
					<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
				</srctime>
				<srccitea>Coastal Lowlands</srccitea>
				<srccontr>Used to mask areas of coastal lowlands where aquifer system is thin</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>Owens, J.P. and Denney, C.S</origin>
						<pubdate>1979</pubdate>
						<title>Upper Cenozoic Deposits of the Central Delmarva Peninsula</title>
						<geoform>Other</geoform>
						<pubinfo>
							<pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
							<publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
						</pubinfo>
						<onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/pp/1067a/report.pdf</onlink>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<srcscale>1000000</srcscale>
				<typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
				<srctime>
					<timeinfo>
						<sngdate>
							<caldate>1979</caldate>
						</sngdate>
					</timeinfo>
					<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
				</srctime>
				<srccitea>Walston Silt and Parsonsburg Sand</srccitea>
				<srccontr>Used to mask areas of Walston Silt and  Parsonsburg Sand where aquifer system is thin</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Framework data in grid format subtracted from land surface elevation grid to calculate surficial thickness.</procdesc>
				<procdate>2014</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Areas identified from published reports as having limited aquifer production such as the Coastal Lowlands (Ator, S.W., Denver, J.M., Krantz D.E., Newell, W.L., and Martucci, S.K., 2005.) were masked and given thickness values of 0 ft, as in the case of Coastal Lowlands or 19 ft as in the case of Parsonsburg Sand and Walston Silt  .</procdesc>
				<procdate>20151001</procdate>
			</procstep>
		</lineage>
	</dataqual>
	<spdoinfo>
		<direct>Raster</direct>
		<rastinfo>
			<rasttype>Grid Cell</rasttype>
			<rowcount>8984</rowcount>
			<colcount>5579</colcount>
			<vrtcount>1</vrtcount>
		</rastinfo>
	</spdoinfo>
	<spref>
		<horizsys>
			<planar>
				<mapproj>
					<mapprojn>Albers Conical Equal Area</mapprojn>
					<albers>
						<stdparll>29.5</stdparll>
						<stdparll>45.5</stdparll>
						<longcm>-96.0</longcm>
						<latprjo>23.0</latprjo>
						<feast>0.0</feast>
						<fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
					</albers>
				</mapproj>
				<planci>
					<plance>row and column</plance>
					<coordrep>
						<absres>30.0</absres>
						<ordres>30.0</ordres>
					</coordrep>
					<plandu>meters</plandu>
				</planci>
			</planar>
			<geodetic>
				<horizdn>D_North_American_1983</horizdn>
				<ellips>GRS_1980</ellips>
				<semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
				<denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
			</geodetic>
		</horizsys>
	</spref>
	<eainfo>
		<detailed>
			<enttyp>
				<enttypl>Raster Value</enttypl>
				<enttypd>Raster values represent aquifer thickness</enttypd>
				<enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
			</enttyp>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>Value</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>The "VALUE" in the grid is the thickness of the surficial aquifer (NAVD88 elevation top of land surface - NAVD88 elevation of next lower confining unit) in feet.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>0</rdommin>
						<rdommax>208</rdommax>
						<attrunit>Feet</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
		</detailed>
		<overview>
			<eaover>This dataset is an integer raster image with no attribute table. Individual raster cell values represent aquifer thickness.</eaover>
			<eadetcit>The raster values were generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Please review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit>
		</overview>
	</eainfo>
	<distinfo>
		<distrib>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntorgp>
					<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
					<cntper></cntper>
				</cntorgp>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
					<address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
					<city>Denver</city>
					<state>CO</state>
					<postal>80225</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>1-888-275-8747 (1-888-ASK-USGS)</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</distrib>
		<distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although the data have been subjected to rigorous review and are substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, the data are released on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from authorized or unauthorized use. Although the data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the USGS, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The USGS shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Users of the data are advised to read all metadata and associated documentation thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.
				 </distliab>
		<stdorder>
			<digform>
				<digtinfo>
					<formname>Raster Digital Data Set</formname>
				</digtinfo>
				<digtopt>
					<onlinopt>
						<computer>
							<networka>
								<networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7610XFT</networkr>
							</networka>
						</computer>
					</onlinopt>
				</digtopt>
			</digform>
			<fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
		</stdorder>
	</distinfo>
	<metainfo>
		<metd>20160415</metd>
		<metc>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntorgp>
					<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey MD-DE-DC Water Science Center</cntorg>
					 <cntper>Mark Nardi</cntper>
				</cntorgp>
				<cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>mailing</addrtype>
					<address>1289 McD Drive</address>
					<city>Dover</city>
					<state>DE</state>
					<postal>19901</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>302-734-2506</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>mrnardi@usgs.gov</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</metc>
		<metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
		<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
	<mettc>local time</mettc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>