<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>P. Ryan Jackson</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Spatial distribution of Rhodamine WT dye concentration measured in the Des Plaines River and the Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal, Chicago, IL in November 2011</title>
        <geoform>Excel spreadsheet and Google Earth KMZ file with locations of all instrument deployments</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7HH6H55</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>These data were collected during a dye tracing study of the lower Des Plaines River and lower Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal (CSSC) in November 2011 by the U.S. Geological Survey. The study attempted to identify potential inflows of Des Plaines River water through the fractured bedrock that separates the two water bodies. Data include Rhodamine WT dye concentrations measured every 3 or 10 minutes by means of Turner Designs C3 and C6 fluorometers with internal dataloggers at three fixed locations on the Des Plaines River, in three groundwater monitoring wells, at two fixed locations on the CSSC, and from a mobile vessel in the CSSC.</abstract>
      <purpose>These data were collected in support of the interbasin transport study for invasive Asian carp.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20160407</caldate>
        </sngdate>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20111114</begdate>
          <enddate>20111129</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-88.093872070379</westbc>
        <eastbc>-87.753295898517</eastbc>
        <northbc>41.836501878315</northbc>
        <southbc>41.590469618495</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Dye</themekey>
        <themekey>Tracer</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal</placekey>
        <placekey>Des Plaines River</placekey>
        <placekey>Illinois</placekey>
        <placekey>Will County</placekey>
        <placekey>Cook County</placekey>
        <placekey>Dupage County</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>P. Ryan Jackson</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Illinois Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>405 N. Goodwin Ave.</address>
          <city>Urbana</city>
          <state>IL</state>
          <postal>61800</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>2173289719</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pjackson@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>n/a</methtype>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Raw data files were downloaded from the deployed instruments and imported to each worksheet of the Excel spreadsheet. When necessary, outliers due to turbidity spikes were identified and the data were plotted against time for comparison. The "samples" worksheet in the spreadsheet shows concentrations of Rhodamine WT dye in grab samples collected at some of the deployment locations and in wetlands between the Des Plaines River and the Chicago Sanitary and Ship canal. Samples were collected and stored in 150 mL opaque plastic sample bottles and concentrations were measured with a Turner Designs 10AU benchtop fluorometer.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20111201</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>A description of the Turner Designs C3 fluorometer including raw data files can be found at:&#xD;
http://www.turnerdesigns.com/t2/doc/manuals/9982300.pdf&#xD;
Attributes in the AllDeployments_Data.xlsx data file:&#xD;
Raw data file worksheets (named by deployment site name) include a 7-line header including calibration information (9-lines for the C6 fluorometer)&#xD;
Date_Time: Date and time&#xD;
Rhodamine: Rhodamine WT concentration in parts per billion (ppb)&#xD;
Turbidity: Relative Turbidity values (uncalibrated) in either relative fluorescence units (RFU) of Nephelometic turbidity units (NTU)&#xD;
Temp: Water temperature in degrees Celsius&#xD;
Rhodamine Filtered On Turbidity: Rhodamine WT concentration in parts per billion (ppb) after applying turbidity spike removal filter&#xD;
Depth: Fluorometer sensor depth, in meters</eaover>
      <eadetcit>A description of the Turner Designs C3 fluorometer including raw data files can be found at:&#xD;
http://www.turnerdesigns.com/t2/doc/manuals/9982300.pdf&#xD;
The "samples" worksheet in the spreadsheet shows concentrations of Rhodamine WT dye in grab samples collected at some of the deployment locations and in wetlands between the Des Plaines River and the Chicago Sanitary and Ship canal. Samples were collected and stored in 150 ml opaque plastic sample bottles and concentrations were measured with a Turner Designs 10AU benchtop fluorometer.</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160504</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>P. Ryan Jackson</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Illinois Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>405 N. Goodwin Ave.</address>
          <city>Urbana</city>
          <state>IL</state>
          <postal>61801</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>2173289719</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pjackson@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>

