<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>R.D. Catchings</origin>
        <origin>L.M. Strayer</origin>
        <origin>M.R. Goldman</origin>
        <origin>C.J. Criley</origin>
        <origin>S.H. Garcia</origin>
        <origin>R.R. Sickler</origin>
        <origin>M.K. Catchings</origin>
        <origin>J.H. Chan</origin>
        <origin>L. Gordon</origin>
        <origin>S. Haefner</origin>
        <origin>L. Blair</origin>
        <origin>G. Gandhok</origin>
        <origin>M. Johnson</origin>
        <pubdate>20150323</pubdate>
        <title>2013 East Bay Seismic Experiment (EBSE) -- Implosion Data, Hayward, Calif</title>
        <geoform>.TRD.gz and .segy</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>ScienceBase</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/folder/54860802e4b02acb4f0c7ea6</onlink>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7BR8Q75</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>In August 2013, the California State University, East Bay (CSUEB) in Hayward, California imploded a 13-story building (Warren Hall) that was deemed unsafe because of its immediate proximity to the active trace of the Hayward Fault.  The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and the CSUEB collaborated on a program to record the seismic waves generated by the collapse of the building.  We refer to this collaboration as the East Bay Seismic Experiment (EBSE).  The principal objective of recording the seismic energy was to observe ground shaking as it radiated from the source, but the data also may be useful for other purposes.  For example, the seismic data may be useful in evaluating the implosion process as it relates to structural engineering purposes.  This report provides the metadata needed to utilize the seismic data.</abstract>
      <purpose>Seven seismograph arrays were deployed to capture seismic energy from the implosion and collapse of Warren Hall.  In this report, we focus only on the arrays designed to primarily capture the implosion and collapse of Warren Hall.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20130817</begdate>
          <enddate>20130817</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>observed</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Hayward Hills within the eastern San Francisco Bay area of California</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-122.3</westbc>
        <eastbc>-121.9</eastbc>
        <northbc>37.9</northbc>
        <southbc>37.4</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>seismology</themekey>
        <themekey>earthquake</themekey>
        <themekey>seismic</themekey>
        <themekey>seismograph</themekey>
        <themekey>shaking</themekey>
        <themekey>Hayward</themekey>
        <themekey>fault</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>California State University, East Bay (CSUEB)</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Rufus D. Catching</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <address>345 Middlefield Road, MS-977</address>
          <city>Menlo Park</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>94025</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>650-329-4749</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>catching@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <browse>
      <browsen>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/file/get/54860802e4b02acb4f0c7ea6?f=__disk__25%2F93%2Ff9%2F2593f9e130e0d5403e4c651617a9f4b10bc8d49c&amp;width=900&amp;height=813</browsen>
      <browsed>map of study area</browsed>
      <browset>PNG</browset>
    </browse>
    <datacred>We thank the California State University - East Bay for hosting the command center, providing the seismic source, and providing access to their property.  We also thank CalTrans, the East Bay Regional Parks District, the Hayward Area Recreation and Park District, the City of Hayward, the Hayward Unified School District, Kmart (Hayward), and the hundreds of citizens who volunteered their properties as recording sites.  A large number of individuals assisted acquiring the EBSE data by deploying and retrieving seismographs, contacting property owners, and surveying recording sites.  We especially thank Rebecca Biestman and Risk Management Solutions, Inc. for providing a large number of field volunteers, and we thank the ARC of Alameda County, which provided a number of volunteers and transportation. Individual volunteers who helped in the field include:  Pranshu Agarwal, Mukul Agarwal, Gabriel Alcantar, Megan Arnold, Lee Baker, Lesley Barnes, Katherine Baylor, Marguerite Bello, Daniel Brooks, Stefan Burns, Matt Bussman, Joanna Chang, Katherine Chapman, Coye Criley, Charles Dodge, Jennifer Dreiling, Gareth Evans, Gwyneth Evans, Ryan Fay, Gini Gandhok, Marius Isken, Christopher Johnson, Jerry Kolb, Dhir Kothar, Ron Lee, John MacDougal, Raleigh McLemore, Felix Meneau, Matt Miller, Christorpher Mitchell, Shannon Muha, Sheldon Owyong, Vinay Pandey, Tom Quintero, Megan Ricobono, Cari Roughley, Emma Scalon, Joseph Schwarz, Janet Snyder, Camgna Thach, Thanh, Brett Treece, Honglei Wang, Barbara Wilcox, Ray Wong, FuYen Yang, and Michael Young.  We thank Monique Beeler, John Evans, Mike Diggles, Delphine Fitzenz, Paul Laustsen, Justin Pressfield (USGS), Barry Zepel (CSU), and numerous news media outlets for publicizing the project, which assisted with permissions and access.  We especially thank IRIS-PASSCAL for graciously providing the seismographs used to record the data and for technical assistance.  Funding for this work was provided by the U.S. Geological Survey's Earthquake Hazards Program.  Reviews by Brad Aagaard and Alan Yong are greatly appreciated.</datacred>
    <tool>
      <tooldesc>Most of the above-described arrays were deployed one or two days before the implosion/collapse of Warren Hall, and the recording arrays were left in place to record passive seismic data for several days after the implosion.  Appendices 1-7 contain the approximate deployment and pickup times, as well as locations for arrays 1-7.  All data were recorded in the IRIS-PASSCAL field format, with individual files having the format, "IxxxxRAW.TRD", where xxxx is the 4-digit seismograph (DAS) number.  For conversion to other formats, contact the IRIS-PASSCAL data center or contact the authors of this report.  The trd files consist of continuously recorded data for each seismograph, and each file extends from the turn-on time until that seismograph was turned off following pickup from the recording sites.  Collectively, the compressed trd files are about 37 GB in size.  To use these data for most purposes, the continuous files must be cut into smaller files. The trd files are available at the following website:  https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/5508bacbe4b02e76d757c5be.  We have converted the implosion data that was recorded with the GS11-D sensors to SEGY format.  Data from about 15 seconds before the implosion to approximately 105 seconds following the implosion are in SEGY format for the radial/circular and linear arrays.  Those files are approximately 45 MB in size and are available at the following website:  https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/5508bacbe4b02e76d757c5be.  The data are standard SEGY files (data samples stored as 40 byte IBM floating point values), with the first sample at UTC time:  2013:229:15:59:30 and a total of 120 seconds of record time.  The DAS (seismograph) 4-digit serial number of the recorder is stored at byte 175 of the trace header as a 2-byte integer, as named in the appendices of this report.  The scheme shown in Table 3 is used to define the field file I D (FFID, bytes 9-12) and channel (CHAN, bytes 13-16) for each trace in the SEGY file:</tooldesc>
      <toolacc>
        <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2005/1311/</onlink>
        <toolinst>The following is the bibliographical citation for a report that provides both documentation and source code that you can use in your C++ compiler to convert SEGY to ASCII: &#xD;
&#xD;
Goldman, Mark R., 2005, SEGY to ASCII conversion and plotting program 2.0: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 2005-1311 http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2005/1311/.</toolinst>
      </toolacc>
    </tool>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>Field</methtype>
        <methdesc>Seven seismograph arrays were deployed to capture seismic energy from the implosion and collapse of Warren Hall.  In this report, we focus only on the arrays designed to primarily capture the implosion and collapse of Warren Hall.  Warren Hall was centered at the following coordinates:  Latitude: 37.655278; Longitude  -122.057222; Elevation 147 m.</methdesc>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Seven seismograph arrays were deployed to capture seismic energy from the implosion and collapse of Warren Hall.  In this report, we focus only on the arrays designed to primarily capture the implosion and collapse of Warren Hall.  Warren Hall was centered at the following coordinates:  Latitude: 37.655278; Longitude  -122.057222; Elevation 147 m.  &#xD;
&#xD;
(1) Radial/Circular Array:&#xD;
We refer to the primary array as the radial/circular array, where individual seismographs were spaced at 200-m intervals along 30 radial arrays extending from Warren Hall.  Each radial array consisted of 10 seismographs, thereby forming a 2-km-long radial line.  Each radial line was spaced at ~12-degree intervals, forming ten 360-degree circular arrays that were centered on Warren Hall.  All circular arrays, except those with diameters less than about 600 m, crossed the active strand of the Hayward Fault and included seismographs within the East Bay Alluvial Plain, the Hayward Hills, and the Hayward Fault zone.  All circular arrays included seismographs positioned along topographically varying surfaces.  There were 300 recording sites selected for the radial/circular array.  However, a few of the sites could not be occupied because homeowners could not be contacted, or access was denied.  Nearly every recorded site was within about 20 m of our desired location, and the listed coordinates for the recording sites are accurate to within about 5 m in most cases. &#xD;
&#xD;
(2) Near-Source Array: &#xD;
For measurements closest to the implosion, we deployed six 3-component seismograph arrays at an average of about 75 m from the center of Warren Hall. These stations approximately encircled Warren Hall, but the azimuthal spacing was highly variable (average of ~60 degrees) due to the presence of nearby buildings. &#xD;
&#xD;
 (3) Linear Array:&#xD;
A linear array that extended from the San Francisco Bay through the center of Warren Hall to San Ramon (25 km) was also planned.  However, due to limited access, sites within 2.4 km of the San Francisco Bay were not occupied.  Most planned sites from 2.4 km east of the San Francisco Bay to the City of San Ramon were occupied at 400-m intervals, except for sites within 2 km of Warren Hall, which were occupied at 200-m intervals. &#xD;
&#xD;
(4) Schools Array:&#xD;
A small array was also deployed at greater epicentral distances from the center of Warren Hall than the primary radial/circular array.  This array was deployed principally within the East Bay Alluvial Plain on local public school properties and is referred to as the "Schools" array.  When supplemented with stations from the linear array, the Schools Array largely encircles Warren Hall at distances of about 5 km or more.  &#xD;
&#xD;
(5) Hayward Fault Zone Cross-Fault Arrays:&#xD;
In addition to the seismographs within the radial/circular array that were within the Hayward Fault zone, two small dedicated seismograph arrays were deployed across the active trace of the Hayward Fault to record seismic energy from the implosion/collapse of Warren Hall.  (a) One cross-fault array (Carlos Bee Array) was deployed near Carlos Bee Boulevard in Hayward and consisted of four 3-component seismograph systems.  Stations were recorded along the active trace and hundreds of meters southwest and northeast of the active trace. (b) A second cross-fault seismograph array (Chabot Array) was deployed approximately 9 km north of Warren Hall in San Leandro, and it also consisted of three 3-component seismograph systems.  As with the Carlos Bee array, stations along the Chabot Array were recorded along the active trace and hundreds of meters southwest and northeast of the active trace.&#xD;
&#xD;
(6) Hayward Fault Zone Linear Array:&#xD;
An array of six seismographs was deployed along the Hayward Fault zone from Warren Hall to Chabot Park in San Leandro.  This array was designed to record seismic energy along the fault zone from the implosion source to about 10 km to the northwest.  All stations along the linear array were single component, except stations co-located on the cross-fault arrays.&#xD;
&#xD;
(7) Far Field Array:&#xD;
We also deployed an array that extended beyond the immediate study site, with stations located to the north, west, and southwest of Warren Hall at epicentral distances up to 32 km.  To the north, stations were located in Berkeley, Oakland, Alameda, Castro Valley, and Hayward, and to the west and southwest, stations were located in Menlo Park, Palo Alto, Belmont, Union City, and Fremont.  When combined with some of the stations along the linear array, the far field array partially encircles Warren Hall at distant offsets.  All far-field-array stations were recorded using single-component seismograph systems.&#xD;
&#xD;
Other Arrays:&#xD;
Several additional arrays were deployed to record data in the days following the implosion and collapse of Warren Hall.  Those data are not considered part of the EBSE and will be included in a separate data release.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20130817</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>no other</indspref>
    <direct>Point</direct>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <geograph>
        <latres>1.0E-5</latres>
        <longres>1.0E-5</longres>
        <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
      </geograph>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>North American Vertical Datum of 1988 (NAVD 88)</horizdn>
        <semiaxis xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:nil="true" />
        <denflat xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:nil="true" />
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>In August 2013, the California State University, East Bay (CSUEB) in Hayward, California imploded a 13-story building (Warren Hall) that was deemed unsafe because of its immediate proximity to the active trace of the Hayward Fault.  The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and the CSUEB collaborated on a program to record the seismic waves generated by the collapse of the building.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/folder/54860802e4b02acb4f0c7ea6</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Rufus D. Catching</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>345 Middlefield Road, MS-977</address>
          <city>Menlo Park</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>94025</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>650-329-4749</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>catching@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>This database has been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although this database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, it is released on condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government shall be held liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized use.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150324</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Mark Goldman</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Geophysicist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>345 Middlefield Road, MS-977</address>
          <city>Menlo Park</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>94025</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>650-329-5496</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>goldman@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>

