<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>P. Ryan Jackson</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Acoustic Doppler current profiler velocity data collected in the Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal in 2010 and 2011 in support of the interbasin transport study for invasive Asian carp</title>
        <geoform>CSV files of time- and depth-averaged velocity data (5-second temporal average)</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7S180KR</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Water velocities were measured in the Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal (CSSC) in 2010 and 2011 using Teledyne Rio Grande 600 kHz and 1200 kHz acoustic Doppler current profilers (ADCP). The data were georeferenced with differential GPS receivers with submeter accuracy. Data were processed using the Velocity Mapping Toolbox (Parsons et al., 2013). Any data assigned a value of "­-9999" are bad or missing data and should not be used for analysis.&#xD;
&#xD;
Parsons, D. R., Jackson, P. R., Czuba, J. A., Engel, F. L., Rhoads, B. L., Oberg, K. A., Best, J. L., Mueller, D. S., Johnson, K. K. and Riley, J. D. (2013), Velocity Mapping Toolbox (VMT): a processing and visualization suite for moving-vessel ADCP measurements. Earth Surf. Process. Landforms, 38: 1244–1260. doi: 10.1002/esp.3367</abstract>
      <purpose>These velocity data were collected in support of the interbasin transport study for invasive Asian carp, and were concurrent with collection of water quality data on March 2 and 3, 2010, eDNA sampling by the USFWS on December 7, 2010, and a dye-tracing study on November 16, 2011.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20160407</caldate>
        </sngdate>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20100302</begdate>
          <enddate>20111116</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-88.14331054695</westbc>
        <eastbc>-87.775268554777</eastbc>
        <northbc>41.791466470932</northbc>
        <southbc>41.606901063461</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Velocity</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal</placekey>
        <placekey>Illinois</placekey>
        <placekey>Cook County</placekey>
        <placekey>Will County</placekey>
        <placekey>Dupage County</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>P. Ryan Jackson</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Illinois Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>405 N. Goodwin Ave.</address>
          <city>Urbana</city>
          <state>IL</state>
          <postal>61801</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>2173289719</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pjackson@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>n/a</methtype>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data processed per the Velocity Mapping Toolbox (VMT) v. 4.07 ASCII2GIS utility with full-depth averaging and 5-second temporal averaging.&#xD;
For details on VMT and its utilities, see: https://hydroacoustics.usgs.gov/movingboat/VMT/VMT.shtml&#xD;
NOTE: Any data assigned a value of "9999" are bad or missing data and should not be used for analysis.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160321</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>NOTE: Any data assigned a value of "9999" are bad or missing data and should not be used for analysis.&#xD;
NAME DESCRIPTION&#xD;
EnsNo Ensemble Number&#xD;
Year Year of sample&#xD;
Month Month of sample&#xD;
Day Day of sample&#xD;
Hour Hour of sample&#xD;
Min Minute of sample&#xD;
Sec Second of sample&#xD;
Lat_WGS84 Latitude in WGS84&#xD;
Lon_WGS84 Longitude in WGS84&#xD;
Heading_deg Heading reading at time of sample in degrees from true north&#xD;
Pitch_deg Pitch reading at time of sample in degrees&#xD;
Roll_deg Roll reading at time of sample in degrees&#xD;
Temp_C Temperature at time of sample in deg. C&#xD;
Depth_m Mean bed depth at time of sample in meters&#xD;
B1Depth_m Beam 1 bed depth at time of sample in meters&#xD;
B2Depth_m Beam 2 bed depth at time of sample in meters&#xD;
B3Depth_m Beam 3 bed depth at time of sample in meters&#xD;
B4Depth_m Beam 4 bed depth at time of sample in meters&#xD;
Backscatter_db Acoustic backscatter in dB&#xD;
DAVeast_cmps Depth- or Layer-averaged velocity (east component) in cm/s&#xD;
DAVnorth_cmps Depth- or Layer-averaged velocity (north component) in cm/s&#xD;
DAVmag_cmps Depth- or Layer-averaged velocity magnitude in cm/s&#xD;
DAVdir_deg Depth- or Layer- averaged velocity direction in degrees from true north&#xD;
DAVvert_cmps Depth- or Layer-averaged velocity (vertical) in cm/s (+ is up)</eaover>
      <eadetcit>https://hydroacoustics.usgs.gov/movingboat/VMT/VMT.shtml (see The Velocity Mapping Toolbox Users Guide, specifically the output file format&#xD;
for the ASCII2GIS utility).</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160504</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>P. Ryan Jackson</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Illinois Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>405 N. Goodwin Ave.</address>
          <city>Urbana</city>
          <state>IL</state>
          <postal>61801</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>2173289719</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pjackson@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>

