<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
 <idinfo>
  <citation>
   <citeinfo>
    <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, Western Ecological Research Center, Dixon Field Station</origin>
    <pubdate>20140801</pubdate>
    <title>Nevada and California Regional Sage-grouse Habitat Suitability Index (August 2014)</title>
    <geoform>Raster Digital Data Set</geoform>
    <othercit>Coates, P.S., Casazza, M.L., Brussee, B.E., Ricca, M.A., Gustafson, K.B., Overton, C.T., Sanchez-Chopitea, E., Kroger, T., Mauch, K., Niell, L., Howe, K., Gardner, S., Espinosa, S., and Delehanty, D.J. 2014, Spatially explicit modeling of greater sage-grouse (Centrocercus urophasianus) habitat in Nevada and northeastern California—A decision-support tool for management: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 2014-1163, 83 p., http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ofr20141163.</othercit>
    <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F75D8PW8</onlink>
   </citeinfo>
  </citation>
  <descript>
   <abstract>This raster represents a continuous surface of sage-grouse habitat probability values for Nevada and California. These values are derived from modeling the resource selection function (RSF) for the region (see supplemental information for more details). Higher values indicate a higher probability of quality sage-grouse habitat.NOTE: This file does not include habitat for the Bi-State management area.Coates, P.S., Casazza, M.L., Brussee, B.E., Ricca, M.A., Gustafson, K.B., Overton, C.T., Sanchez-Chopitea, E., Kroger, T., Mauch, K., Niell, L., Howe, K., Gardner, S., Espinosa, S., and Delehanty, D.J. 2014, Spatially explicit modeling of greater sage-grouse (Centrocercus urophasianus) habitat in Nevada and northeastern California—A decision-support tool for management: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 2014-1163, 83 p., http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ofr20141163. ISSN 2331-1258 (online)</abstract>
   <purpose>The purpose of this data is to provide wildlife managers with an additional resource to aid in planning and management of Greater Sage-grouse populations.</purpose>
   <supplinf>The RSF was derived from a generalized linear mixed model (specified the binomial distribution) that contrasted data from multiple environmental factors at used sites (telemetry locations) and available sites (random locations). Predictor variables for the model represented vegetation communities at multiple spatial scales, water resources, habitat configuration, urbanization, roads, recreational indices, elevation, ruggedness indices, and slope. Vegetation data was derived from various mapping products, which included Southwest Regional GAP, SageStitch, Landfire, and Fire and Resource Assessment Program. The model was partitioned into 12 subregions which consisted of 35,883 telemetry locations using 1,612 adult sage-grouse over a 15-year period (1998 – 2013).An RSF was calculated for each subregion using generalized linear models to derive model-averaged parameter estimates for each covariate across a set of additive models. Subregions were then averaged together to produce an overall statewide RSF of which a relative probability of occurrence was calculated (0 to 1) for each pixel. Values were then extracted from independent telemetry point locations (not used in developing the RSF model) to determine habitat versus non-habitat. The cutoff values were based on the mean minus 0.5, 1.0, 1.5 and 2.0 standard deviations. For validation a separate dataset of telemetry points was used to evaluate model fit which resulted in an agreement of 93 – 97%.</supplinf>
  </descript>
  <timeperd>
   <timeinfo>
    <rngdates>
     <begdate>19980101</begdate>
     <enddate>20131231</enddate>
    </rngdates>
   </timeinfo>
   <current>This dataset was derived from multiple spatial datasets that fell within the Nevada management area.</current>
  </timeperd>
  <status>
   <progress>Complete</progress>
   <update>None planned</update>
  </status>
  <spdom>
   <bounding>
    <westbc>-121.555475871</westbc>
    <eastbc>-113.858710517</eastbc>
    <northbc>42.086443587</northbc>
    <southbc>37.489634678</southbc>
   </bounding>
  </spdom>
  <keywords>
   <theme>
    <themekt>None</themekt>
    <themekey>Nevada, Sage-grouse, Habitat</themekey>
   </theme>
   <theme>
    <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
    <themekey>biota</themekey>
    <themekey>environment</themekey>
   </theme>
   <place>
    <placekt>None</placekt>
    <placekey>USA, Great Basin, Nevada</placekey>
   </place>
   <temporal>
    <tempkt>None</tempkt>
    <tempkey>2014</tempkey>
   </temporal>
  </keywords>
  <accconst>None</accconst>
  <useconst>The authors of these data require that users direct any questions pertaining to appropriate use or assistance with understanding limitations and interpretation of the data to the individuals/organization listed in the Point of Contact section.</useconst>
  <ptcontac>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntorgp>
     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Western Ecological Research Center</cntorg>
     <cntper>Peter Coates</cntper>
    </cntorgp>
    <cntpos>Research Wildlife Biologist</cntpos>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
     <address>800 Business Park Drive, Suite D</address>
     <city>Dixon</city>
     <state>CA</state>
     <postal>95620</postal>
     <country>US</country>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>(530) 669-5073</cntvoice>
    <cntfax>(707) 678-5039</cntfax>
    <cntemail>pcoates@usgs.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
  </ptcontac>
  <datacred>U.S. Geological Survey, Western Ecological Research Center, Dixon Field Station, Dixon, CA.
Nevada Sagebrush Ecosystem Program, Carson City, NV.</datacred>
  <native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.2.2 (Build 3552) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native>
 </idinfo>
 <dataqual>
  <attracc>
   <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted.</attraccr>
  </attracc>
  <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic>
  <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
  <posacc>
   <horizpa>
    <horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</horizpar>
   </horizpa>
   <vertacc>
    <vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr>
   </vertacc>
  </posacc>
  <lineage>
   <procstep>
    <procdesc>Development of the data set by the agency / individuals identified in the 'Originator' element in the Identification Info section of the record.</procdesc>
    <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
   </procstep>
  </lineage>
 </dataqual>
 <spdoinfo>
  <direct>Raster</direct>
  <rastinfo>
   <rasttype>Grid Cell</rasttype>
   <rowcount>7404</rowcount>
   <colcount>9520</colcount>
   <vrtcount>1</vrtcount>
  </rastinfo>
 </spdoinfo>
 <spref>
  <horizsys>
   <planar>
    <mapproj>
     <mapprojn>WGS 1984 Web Mercator Auxiliary Sphere (ESRI Full Name: WGS_1984_Web_Mercator_Auxiliary_Sphere)</mapprojn>
     <mercator>
      <stdparll>0.0</stdparll>
      <longcm>0.0</longcm>
      <feast>0.0</feast>
      <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
     </mercator>
    </mapproj>
    <planci>
     <plance>row and column</plance>
     <coordrep>
      <absres>90.0</absres>
      <ordres>90.0</ordres>
     </coordrep>
     <plandu>Meter</plandu>
    </planci>
   </planar>
   <geodetic>
    <horizdn>D_WGS_1984</horizdn>
    <ellips>WGS_1984</ellips>
    <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
    <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
   </geodetic>
  </horizsys>
 </spref>
 <distinfo>
  <distrib>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntorgp>
     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
    </cntorgp>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
     <address>Denver Federal Center</address>
     <address>Buidling 810</address>
     <address>Mail Stop 302</address>
     <city>Denver</city>
     <state>CO</state>
     <postal>80225</postal>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>800-275-8747</cntvoice>
    <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
  </distrib>
  <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab>
  <custom>The data will be available on the USGS Sciencebase web site. http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F75D8PW8</custom>
 </distinfo>
 <metainfo>
  <metd>20151119</metd>
  <metc>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntorgp>
     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Western Ecological Research Center, Dixon Field Station</cntorg>
     <cntper>K. Benjamin Gustafson</cntper>
    </cntorgp>
    <cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
     <address>800 Business Park Drive, Suite D</address>
     <city>Dixon</city>
     <state>CA</state>
     <postal>95620</postal>
     <country>US</country>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>530-669-5069</cntvoice>
    <cntfax>707-678-5039</cntfax>
    <cntemail>bgustafson@usgs.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
  </metc>
  <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
  <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  <mettc>local time</mettc>
 </metainfo>
</metadata>
