<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Julia C. Buck</origin>
        <origin>Kevin D. Lafferty</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Host Influence and Risk of Parasite Recruitment in a Snail-Trematode System at Carpinteria Salt Marsh, 2012-2015 Observations</title>
        <geoform>Tabular Digital Data</geoform>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7GX48P2</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The project is located at Carpinteria Salt Marsh, part of the University of California Reserve System. The marsh is located at 34.40°N, 119.53°W, which is near the city of Carpinteria, CA.
The data set includes information on site name (site), cage number (cage), the influence of final hosts (birds and raccoons), the biomass of snails within a cage (cagebiomass), the biomass of snails in the surrounding area (surroundingbiomass), and the number of egg-transmitted (egginf) and miracidium-transmitted (mirainf) trematode infections per cage.
This data set accompanies a manuscript entitled “Host density increases parasite recruitment but decreases host risk in a snail-trematode system” by J.C. Buck and K.D. Lafferty.</abstract>
      <purpose>The data were used to test the encounter-dilution effect.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Data were developed primarily through a field experiment. Observations of final hosts (from which finalhostinfluence was calculated) were developed through field visits.
Please contact julia.buck@gmail.com for larger data set containing information on length and infection status of each snail.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <current>See Supplemental Info</current>
      <timeinfo>
        <mdattim>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>201201</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>201303</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20150716</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20151120</caldate>
          </sngdate>
        </mdattim>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None planned</update>
    </status>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Encounter-dilution</themekey>
        <themekey>Cerithideopsis californica</themekey>
        <themekey>Cerithidea</themekey>
        <themekey>Horn snail</themekey>
        <themekey>Host density</themekey>
        <themekey>Parasite</themekey>
        <themekey>Trematode</themekey>
        <themekey>Complex life cycle</themekey>
        <themekey>Transmission mode</themekey>
        <themekey>Spatial scale</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Carpinteria Salt Marsh</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None. Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</accconst>
    <useconst>The authors of these data require that users direct any questions pertaining to appropriate use or assistance with understanding limitations and interpretation of the data to the individuals/organization listed in the Point of Contact section.</useconst>
    <datacred>Data on final-host influence were collected by T. Stewart, R Hechinger, and K. Lafferty and were analyzed by K. Lafferty. Funding: This material is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation under Grant No. (DEB-0224565).</datacred>
    <native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1 (Build 4959) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-119.5457446575</westbc>
        <eastbc>-119.5296299458</eastbc>
        <northbc>34.4058562885</northbc>
        <southbc>34.3969508154</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, PACIFIC REGION</cntorg>
          <cntper>Kevin D Lafferty</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>Research Ecologist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>UC Santa Barbara</address>
          <city>Santa Barbara</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>93106</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>805-893-8778</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>805-893-8062</cntfax>
        <cntemail>klafferty@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>As described in the manuscript, sentinel snails were triple-screened on two occasions, one month apart, to ensure that they were uninfected at the beginning of the experiment.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdate>2015</procdate>
        <procdesc>finalhostinfluence = Influence increased with body mass, and declined exponentially with distance from the site according to a Gaussian distribution with a 0.036 tuning parameter fit to the observed infection incidence.
cagebiomass = Length of each snail was measured and mass was calculated as 0.0001*(length^2.4146). Mass of all snails in a cage was summed and then multiplied by 14.1755 to give grams per meter squared.
surroundingbiomass = Snails per 0.25m2 quadrat were counted and length was measured. Mass was calculated as 0.0001*(length^2.4146). Mass of snails in a quadrat was summed and then multiplied by 16 to give grams per meter squared.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdate>2015</procdate>
        <procdesc>1) Data were analyzed using generalized linear mixed-effects models (function glmer within package lme4) in R (version 3.2.2).
2) R and the lme4 package are available from https://cran.r-project.org/
3) Final host influence was modeled bird species by bird species using Mathematica. For each bird species, we estimated the spatial position of each individual observed over a twelve month period within Carpinteria Salt Marsh. Then, for each site, we calculated its distance from each bird observation. The influence of each bird individual was estimated as an exponential decay function of distance from the site, so that birds far from sites had less influence than birds close to sites. Summing the influences of all individuals within a species gave the influence of a bird species.  To get the influence of the bird community, species influences were summed after weighting by species body masses.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>site</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Site number. There are a total of 8 sites. C = channel sites, F = flat sites</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS Author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>C2</edomv>
            <edomvd>C2 = 34.40166582°N, -119.54055297°W</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>C3</edomv>
            <edomvd>C3 = 34.40265562°N, -119.54057082°W</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>C8</edomv>
            <edomvd>C8 = 34.39795033°N, -119.53158237°W</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>F1</edomv>
            <edomvd>F1 = 34.40297647°N, -119.53926295°W</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>F2</edomv>
            <edomvd>F2 = 34.39745728°N, -119.52774503°W</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>F3</edomv>
            <edomvd>F3 = 34.40406982°N, -119.54024070°W</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>F4</edomv>
            <edomvd>F4 = 34.40041638°N, -119.53700234°W</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>F5</edomv>
            <edomvd>F5 = 34.40310770°N, -119.54199536°W</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>cage</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Cage number. N = 83 (10 or 11 cages per site).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS Author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>1</rdommin>
            <rdommax>83</rdommax>
            <attrunit>Count</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>finalhosti</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Influence of birds and raccoons (g).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS Author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>1984427.627</rdommin>
            <rdommax>109417701.4</rdommax>
            <attrunit>g (grams)</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>cagebiomas</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Biomass density of snails in each cage (g/m2).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS Author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>2.260010664</rdommin>
            <rdommax>253.028263</rdommax>
            <attrunit>g/m2</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>surroundbi</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Biomass density of snails at each site (g/m2).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS Author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>6.159667149</rdommin>
            <rdommax>67.5300088</rdommax>
            <attrunit>g/m2</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>egginf</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Number of egg-transmitted infections per cage.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS Author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>16</rdommax>
            <attrunit>Count</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mirainf</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Number of miracidium-transmitted infections per cage.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS Author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>10</rdommax>
            <attrunit>Count</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <overview>
      <eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes the tabular data associated with the data set. Please review the detailed descriptions that are provided (the individual attribute descriptions) for information on the values that appear as fields/table entries of the data set.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>The entity and attribute information was generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Please review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Tabular Digital Data</formname>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7GX48P2</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center</address>
          <address>Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160614</metd>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, PACIFIC REGION</cntorg>
          <cntper>Pai Hui Yu</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Cartographic Technician</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>3020 State University Dr. East</address>
          <city>Sacramento</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>95819</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>916-278-9467</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pyu@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>