<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, Western Ecological Research Center, Dixon Field Station</origin>
        <pubdate>20151001</pubdate>
        <title>Hydrological Areas of Nevada for the Greater Sage-grouse</title>
        <edition>FINAL</edition>
        <geoform>Vector Digital Data Set (Polygon)</geoform>
        <othercit>Unpublished Data</othercit>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7CC0XRV</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Delehanty, D.J.</origin>
            <origin>Casazza, M.L.</origin>
            <origin>Sanchez-Chopitea, E.</origin>
            <origin>Brussee, B.E.</origin>
            <origin>Niell, L.</origin>
            <origin>Coates, P.S.</origin>
            <origin>Gustafson, K.B.</origin>
            <origin>Espinosa, S.</origin>
            <origin>Mauch, K.</origin>
            <origin>Gardner, S.</origin>
            <origin>Ricca, M.A.</origin>
            <pubdate>20160520</pubdate>
            <title>Spatially explicit modeling of annual and seasonal habitat for greater sage-grouse (Centrocercus urophasianus) in Nevada and Northeastern California—An updated decision-support tool for management</title>
            <geoform>Publication (Other)</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
              <issue>2016-1080, 160 p.</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
              <publish>USGS</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ofr20161080</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The Great Basin is characterized by strong patterns of precipitation along approximate north-south gradients (Miller and others, 2013). Hence, we used a hydrographic boundary layer developed by Mason (1999), to divide the region-wide extent of sage-grouse habitat mapping analysis into North and South regions that align coarsely with respective mesic (wet) and xeric (dry) regions of the state. Flood regions are based largely on patterns of snowmelt, summer thunderstorms or cyclonic rainfall, and the 8-digit Watershed Boundary Dataset (WBD, 2015) was used to select appropriate watersheds within our mapping extent that corresponded to the Mason (1999) boundary. Slight adjustments, made in ArcMap 10.3, included joining region 2 and 3 to comprise the majority of the North region (where a relatively low number of sampled sites precluded keeping regions 2 and 3 separate), and pooling the more xeric Owyhee Desert (located in the center of the northern part of Nevada) within the drier South region. 
Use of the hydrographic boundary allowed for an accounting of broad-scale variation in habitat availability and selection patterns for sage-grouse (for example, habitat classified as highly suitable in wet areas could be classified as less suitable in drier areas because these habitats are less available). Interim statewide habitat suitability maps were clipped by the hydrographic boundary and relativized according to their respective maximum values for map classification purposes (see Coates and others 2014), the independent set of sage-grouse telemetry points was also split by the hydrographic boundary. For the spring map, 837 points informed the North region while 794 informed the South region. For the summer map, 604 points informed the North and 794 the South. For winter, 326 informed the North and 411 the South. For our composite annual map made from the multiplicative product of the seasonal maps, 1767 points were used for the North and 1999 for the South. 

References: 

Coates, P.S., Casazza, M.L., Brussee, B.E., Ricca, M.A., Gustafson, K.B., Overton, C.T., Sanchez-Chopitea, E., Kroger, T., Mauch, K., Niell, L., Howe, K., Gardner, S., Espinosa, S., and Delehanty, D.J. 2014, Spatially explicit modeling of greater sage-grouse (Centrocercus urophasianus) habitat in Nevada and northeastern California—A decision-support tool for management: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 2014-1163, 83 p., http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ofr20141163. ISSN 2331-1258 (online) 

Mason, R.R. 1999. The National Flood-Frequency Program—Methods For Estimating Flood Magnitude And Frequency In Rural Areas In Nevada U.S. Geological Survey Fact Sheet 123-98 September, 1999, Prepared by Robert R. Mason, Jr. and Kernell G. Ries III, of the U.S. Geological Survey; and Jeffrey N. King and Wilbert O. Thomas, Jr., of Michael Baker, Jr., Inc. http://pubs.usgs.gov/fs/fs-123-98/ 

Miller RF, Chambers JC, Pyke DA, Pierson FB, Williams CJ. 2013. A review of fire effects on vegetation and soils in the Great Basin Region: response and ecological site characteristics. Gen. Tech. Rep. RMRS-GTR-308. Fort Collins, CO: U.S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, Rocky Mountain Research Station. http://www.fs.fed.us/rm/pubs/rmrs_gtr308.html. 

WBD, 2015. Coordinated effort between the United States Department of Agriculture-Natural Resources Conservation Service (USDA-NRCS), the United States Geological Survey (USGS), and the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA). The Watershed Boundary Dataset (WBD) was created from a variety of sources from each state and aggregated into a standard national layer for use in strategic planning and accountability. Watershed Boundary Dataset for {HUC#8}, Nevada_ST.zip [ftp://rockyftp.cr.usgs.gov/vdelivery/Datasets/Staged/Hydro/FileGDB101/]. Available URL: http://datagateway.nrcs.usda.gov [Accessed 01/10/2015].</abstract>
      <purpose>This boundary, based on published hydrographic characteristics, was used to facilitate modeling of broad-scale geographic varaibility in habitat suitabilty maps for greater sage-grouse in Nevada and northeastern California.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Our study area was defined by the Nevada Department of Wildlife's Sage-grouse Population Management Units plus a 10-km buffer.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>19990522</begdate>
          <enddate>20131031</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>See Supplemental Info</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-121.133902905</westbc>
        <eastbc>-113.743796683</eastbc>
        <northbc>42.127902591</northbc>
        <southbc>37.503786628</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Sagebrush Ecosystem Council</themekey>
        <themekey>Greater Sage-Grouse</themekey>
        <themekey>Habitat</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
        <themekey>biota</themekey>
        <themekey>environment</themekey>
        <themekey>boundaries</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Great Basin</placekey>
        <placekey>North America</placekey>
        <placekey>California</placekey>
        <placekey>United States</placekey>
        <placekey>Nevada</placekey>
      </place>
      <temporal>
        <tempkt>None</tempkt>
        <tempkey>2015</tempkey>
      </temporal>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government</accconst>
    <useconst>The authors of these data require that users direct any questions pertaining to appropriate use or assistance with understanding limitations and interpretation of the data to the individuals/organization listed in the Point of Contact section.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Western Ecological Research Center</cntorg>
          <cntper>Peter Coates</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>Research Wildlife Biologist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>800 Business Park Drive, Suite D</address>
          <city>Dixon</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>95620</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(530) 669-5073</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>(707) 678-5039</cntfax>
        <cntemail>pcoates@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>U.S. Geological Survey, Western Ecological Research Center, Dixon Field Station, Dixon. CA. Nevada Sagebrush Ecosystem Program, Carson City, NV.</datacred>
    <native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.2.2 (Build 3552) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Accuracy of the habitat categorization was assessed with validation datasets comprising: 1) independent telemetry locations from the remaining, unused 10% of the sample sets from subregion resource selection modeling (RSF); 2) telemetry locations from regions that did not meet sample size criteria (i.e., non-RSF subregions); 3) lek locations. Because the number of telemetry locations collected for individual birds varied among study sites (e.g. VHF vs. GPS), we calculated the proportion of validation locations falling within habitat categories for each unique bird, and then averaged those proportions across all birds. Averages were then compared to a normal distribution with expected values based on standard deviations (expected high = 69.1%, moderate=15.0%, low=9.2%, none=6.7%). We found that all three datasets exceeded observed validation values from Coates et al. 2014.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>This boundary layer was created by WERC using the watershed boundary HUC 8 to select polygons that roughly resembled the boundary layer created by Mason 1999. Zones 2 and 3 were joined to represent the Mesic area and the area consisting of the Owyhee Desert, in the north, was lumped with the Xeric portion.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160323</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>G-polygon</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>3</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>11</utmzone>
            <transmer>
              <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
              <longcm>-117.0</longcm>
              <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
              <feast>500000.0</feast>
              <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
            </transmer>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>0.6096</absres>
            <ordres>0.6096</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>Meter</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D_North_American_1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS_1980</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Half</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Relative moisture content for each portion of Nevada and NE California</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>user defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Mesic</edomv>
            <edomvd>Relatively wetter</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Xeric</edomv>
            <edomvd>Relatively dryer</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <overview>
      <eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes the tabular data associated with the data set. Please review the detailed descriptions that are provided (the individual attribute descriptions) for information on the values that appear as fields/table entries of the data set.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>The entity and attribute information was generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Please review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Vector Digital Data Set (Polygon)</formname>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7CC0XRV</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160331</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, PACIFIC REGION</cntorg>
          <cntper>Erika N Sanchez-chopitea</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>Cartographic Technician</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>3020 State University Drive East</address>
          <address>Modoc Hall</address>
          <address>Suite 4004</address>
          <city>Sacramento</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>95819</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>916-278-9483</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>esanchez-chopitea@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
    <metuc>The authors of these data require that users direct any questions pertaining to appropriate use or assistance with understanding limitations and interpretation of the data to the individuals/organization listed in the Point of Contact section.</metuc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>