<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Keith Loftin</origin>
        <origin>Jimmy Clark</origin>
        <origin>Celeste Journey</origin>
        <origin>Dana Kolpin</origin>
        <origin>Peter VanMetre</origin>
        <origin>Thomas Burley</origin>
        <origin>Paul Bradley</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Periphyton (1993-2011) and Water Quality (2014) Data for ET&amp;C Article Entitled Spatial and Temporal Variation in Microcystins Occurrence in Wadeable Streams in the Southeastern USA</title>
        <geoform>data tables in csv format</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Denver</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7VQ30RM</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Spatial reconnaissance of fluvial microcystins (MC) concentrations and select water-quality parameters, including nutrients and periphyton biomass, in 75 wadeable streams in the Piedmont region of the southeastern USA during 2014. Data set includes only those data specifically discussed in the associated journal article: Loftin, K.A., Clark, J.M., Journey, C.A., Kolpin, D.W., Van Metre, P.C., and Bradley, P.M., 2016, Spatial and temporal variation in microcystins occurrence in wadeable streams in the southeastern USA: Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry, http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/etc.3391. </abstract>
      <purpose>In the southeastern USA, cyanobacteria blooms and associated taste and odor issues have been documented in run-of-river impoundments, but information on MC concentrations in associated fluvial systems is lacking. This data set summarizes historical data on the presence of potential cyanotoxin-producing periphyton in streams in the southeastern USA  from 1993 to 2011 and includes results of a synoptic reconnaissance of total microcystins (MC) concentrations and associated water-quality data in 75 perennial, wadeable southeastern Piedmont streams during the summer of 2014.  Water samples were collected by the USGS NAWQA Southeastern Stream Quality Assessment (SESQA) study and analyzed by the USGS Toxic Substances Hydrology Program (TSHP) as part of a long-term TSHP research focus on cyanotoxin environmental health effects. Total microcystins concentrations were quanitifed using ELISA.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20140401</begdate>
          <enddate>20141031</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Piedmont ecoregion of southeastern USA, including Alabama, Georgia, South Carolina, North Carolina, and Virginia</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-86.85516357434</westbc>
        <eastbc>-76.791687012242</eastbc>
        <northbc>38.530636625453</northbc>
        <southbc>33.045141059259</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>none</themekt>
        <themekey>microcystin</themekey>
        <themekey>cyanobacteria</themekey>
        <themekey>periphyton</themekey>
        <themekey>headwater streams</themekey>
        <themekey>harmful algal blooms</themekey>
        <themekey>wadable streams</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Oregon GEO Place Keywords</placekt>
        <placekey>United States</placekey>
        <placekey>Alabama</placekey>
        <placekey>Georgia</placekey>
        <placekey>South Carolina</placekey>
        <placekey>North Carolina</placekey>
        <placekey>Virginia</placekey>
        <placekey>stream</placekey>
        <placekey>stream channel</placekey>
      </place>
      <temporal>
        <tempkt>Oregon GEO Temporal Keywords</tempkt>
        <tempkey>summer</tempkey>
        <tempkey>april</tempkey>
        <tempkey>may</tempkey>
        <tempkey>june</tempkey>
        <tempkey>july</tempkey>
        <tempkey>august</tempkey>
        <tempkey>september</tempkey>
        <tempkey>october</tempkey>
        <tempkey>2014</tempkey>
      </temporal>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Paul M. Bradley</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) Toxic Substances Hydrology Program (TSHP), USGS National Water Quality Program (NWQP)</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>720 Gracern Rd, Suite 129</address>
          <city>Columbia</city>
          <state>SC</state>
          <postal>29210</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-803-750-6125</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pbradley@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>USGS Toxics Substances Hydrology Program (TSHP); National Water Quality Program, National Water Quality Assessment Project (NWQP NAWQA)</datacred>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>both</methtype>
        <methdesc>The historical presence of potential cyanotoxin producers in southeastern USA streams was assessed using periphyton data from the United States Geological Survey (USGS) BioData database (http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.5066/F77W698B). Taxonomy and periphyton calculations were completed by the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia (http://diatom.ansp.org/nawqa/pdfs/titlepgcontentsintro.pdf). Unfiltered water samples were collected by the USGS NWQP NAWQA Southeastern Stream Quality Assessment (SESQA) study from 75 perennial, wadeable headwater stream sites in five southeastern states (Alabama, Georgia, South Carolina, North Carolina, Virginia). Field parameters and water quality parameters including nutrients, and periphyton biomass were measured using standard USGS protocols  (http://water.usgs.gov/owq/FieldManual/). Total microcystins and cross-reactive nodularins concentrations were measured by the USGS TSHP  at the USGS Organic Geochemistry Research Laboratory (OGRL) in Lawrence, Kansas using Enzyme Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA) as documented  (http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2008/1341/).</methdesc>
      </method>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>USGS</origin>
            <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
            <title>BioData - Aquatic Bioassessment Data for the Nation</title>
            <geoform>database</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Reston</pubplace>
              <publish>USGS</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.5066/F77W698B</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>Biological Data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>19930324</begdate>
              <enddate>20110914</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>none</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>BioData</srccitea>
        <srccontr>none</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>USGS</origin>
            <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
            <title>USGS Water Data for the Nation</title>
            <geoform>database</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Reston</pubplace>
              <publish>USGS</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7P55KJN</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>Water Quality Data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>20140401</begdate>
              <enddate>20141031</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>none</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>NWIS</srccitea>
        <srccontr>none</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Select water quality parameters for 10 samples collected at each site from April to June 2014 were summarized as maximum, median, and minimum statistics.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20150803</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <geograph>
        <latres>1.0E-5</latres>
        <longres>1.0E-5</longres>
        <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
      </geograph>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>North American Datum 1983</horizdn>
        <semiaxis xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:nil="true" />
        <denflat xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:nil="true" />
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Table 1  Site Information</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Description of stream watersheds within the Ridge and Valley, Blue Ridge, and Piedmont Level III Ecoregions in the southeastern United States that were assessed as part of the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) National Water-Quality Assessment (NAWQA) Southeastern Stream Quality Assessment (SESQA) and Toxics Substance Hydrology Program in 2014.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>USGS Toxic Substances Hydrology Program, USGS National Water Quality Assessment Program</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Table 1 Site Information columns 1-13</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Site information data corresponding to column headings NWIS station number, NWIS station name, Field ID, Urban center, Site type, State, Latitude, Longitude, Drainage area (square miles), Continuous streamflow, Continuous water quality, Water-quality sampling events, Microcystin sampling events</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>National Water Information System, NWIS, http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7P55KJN; producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>tabular data corresponding to column headers and specified units</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Hydrologic Disturbance Index</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Hydrologic Disturbance Index (unitless)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>DOI: 10.1890/09-0889.1</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-- (none)</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>unitless</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Percent Urban Land Use</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>NLCD 2012</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>National Land Cover Database 2012</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Table 2 Microcystin &amp; Water Quality</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Synoptic results of the periphyton biomass and microcystin data (accessible at http://waterdata.usgs.gov/nwis) collected in June 2014  and statistical summary of the hydrologic, nutrient, and major ion data (source data accessible at http://waterdata.usgs.gov/nwis) collected April to June, 2014, at selected stream sites in the southeastern United States that were assessed as part of the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) National Water-Quality Assessment (NAWQA) Southeastern Stream Quality Assessment (SESQA) and Toxics Substance Hydrology Program.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>USGS Toxic Substances Hydrology Program, USGS National Water Quality Assessment Program</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Table 2 Site information corresponding to column headers 1-7</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Columns 1-7 including NWIS Station Number, Field ID, UrbanCenter, Site Type, Drainage Area, Hydrologic Disturbance Index,Urban Land Use</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>National Water Information System, NWIS, http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7P55KJN; producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>tabular data corresponding to column headers and specified units</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Instantaneous water quality data corresponding to column headers 8-15</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Columns 8-15 including Periphyton Ash-Free Dry Mass, Periphyton Chlorophyll a, Periphyton Pheophytin a, Periphyton Pheophytin to Chlorophyll Ratio, Periphyton Biomass as ash weight, Periphyton Biomass as dry weight, Periphyton Biomass to Chlorophyll a Ratio, Total Microcystin</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>National Water Information System, NWIS; http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7P55KJN</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>units corresponding to column heading 8-15</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Maximum, median, and minimum statistics for 10 weekly water samples water quality parameters in columns 16-74</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Columns 16-74 including Instantaneous Discharge Max (cubic feet per second),Instantaneous Discharge Median (cubic feet per second),Instantaneous Discharge  Min (cubic feet per second),Specific Conductance Max (microSiemens per centimeter at 25 degrees Celsius,Specific Conductance Median (microSiemens per centimeter at 25 degrees Celsius,Specific Conductance Min (microSiemens per centimeter at 25 degrees Celsius,Water Temperature Max (degrees Celsius),Water Temperature Median (degrees Celsius),Water Temperature Min (degrees Celsius),pH Max (standard units),pH Median (standard units),pH Min (standard units),Dissolved Nitrate plus nitrite Max (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Nitrate plus nitrite Median (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Nitrate plus nitrite Min (milligrams per liter),Total Organic Nitrogen Max (milligrams per liter),Total Organic Nitrogen Median (milligrams per liter),Total Organic Nitrogen Min (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Orthophosphate Max (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Orthophosphate Median (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Orthophosphate Min (milligrams per liter),Total Phosphorus Max (milligrams per liter),Total Phosphorus Median (milligrams per liter),Total Phosphorus Min (milligrams per liter),Total Nitrogen Max (milligrams per liter),Total Nitrogen Median (milligrams per liter),Total Nitrogen Min (milligrams per liter),Total Nitrogen to Total Phosphorus Ratio Max (unitless),Total Nitrogen to Total Phosphorus Ratio Median (unitless),Total Nitrogen to Total Phosphorus Ratio Min (unitless),Dissolved Inorganic Nitrogen Max (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Inorganic Nitrogen Median (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Inorganic Nitrogen Min (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Inorganic Nitrogen to Dissolved Inorganic Phosphorus Ratio Max (unitless),Dissolved Inorganic Nitrogen to Dissolved Inorganic Phosphorus Ratio Median (unitless),Dissolved Inorganic Nitrogen to Dissolved Inorganic Phosphorus Ratio Min (unitless),Dissolved Calcium Max (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Calcium Median (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Calcium Min (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Chloride Max (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Chloride Median (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Chloride Min (milligrams per liter),Hardness Max (milligrams per liter as calcium carbonate),Hardness Median (milligrams per liter as calcium carbonate),Hardness  Min (milligrams per liter as calcium carbonate),Dissolved Magnesium Max (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Magnesium Median (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Magnesium Min (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Potassium Max (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Potassium  Median (milligrams per liter),Dissolved PotassiumMin  (milligrams per liter),Fraction of Sodium to Cations Max (unitless),Fraction of Sodium to Cations Median (unitless),Fraction of Sodium to Cations Min (unitless),Dissolved Sodium Max (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Sodium Median (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Sodium Min (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Sulfate Max (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Sulfate Median (milligrams per liter),Dissolved Sulfate Min (milligrams per liter)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>National Water Information System, NWIS; http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7P55KJN</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>units corresponding to column heading 16-75</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Table 3 Southeast Historical Periphyton Data</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Summary of historical periphyton data (BioData) from Alabama, Georgia, South Carolina, and North Carolina. Data collected by NAWQA during 1993-2011</enttypd>
        <enttypds>USGS National Water Quality Assessment Program</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Tabular data corresponding to column headings</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Columns 1-9 including Measurement,Cyanobacteria,Cryptophytes,Diatoms,Dinoflagelates,Euglenoids,Green Algae,Red Algae,Yellow-Green Algae</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS BioData; http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.5066/F77W698B</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Table 4 Southeast Historical Potential Cyanotoxin Producers</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Summary of potential cyanotoxin-producing genera in historical periphyton data (BioData) from Alabama and Georgia and South Carolina and and North Carolina. Data collected by NAWQA during 1993-2011</enttypd>
        <enttypds>USGS National Water Quality Assessment Program</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Tabular data corresponding to column headings</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Columns 1-24 including Genera Name,Nostoc,Rivularia,Synechococcus,Planktothrix,Plectonema,Rhabdogloea,Snowella,Aphanothece,Microcoleus,Synechocystis,Microcystis,Schizothrix,Aphanocapsa,Geitlerinema,Planktolyngbya,Merismopedia,Oscillatoria,Lyngbya,Calothrix,Anabaena,Pseudanabaena,Phormidium,Leptolyngbya</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS BioData; http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.5066/F77W698B</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Potential cyanotoxin genera names, genera morphology, and percent occurrence</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center</address>
          <address>Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>
                Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement
                by the U.S. Government. Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain,
                it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items
                must be secured from the copyright owner whenever applicable. The data have been approved for release
                and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although the data have been subjected to rigorous
                review and are substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further
                analysis and review. Furthermore, the data are released on the condition that neither the USGS nor
                the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from authorized or unauthorized use.
                Although the data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey,
                no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system,
                or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.
                The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described
                and/or contained herein.
                Users of this data are advised to read all metadata and associated documentation thoroughly to understand
                appropriate use and data limitations.
                </distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7VQ30RM</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160223</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Paul M. Bradley</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) Toxic Substances Hydrology Program (TSHP), USGS National Water Quality Program (NWQP)</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Research Ecologist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>720 Gracern Rd, Suite 129</address>
          <city>Columbia</city>
          <state>South Carolina</state>
          <postal>29210</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>803-750-6125</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pbradley@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>