<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Robert H. Diehl</origin>
        <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
        <title>Radar Image Data from the Ivanpah Solar Electric Generating System (ISEGS) Facility Recorded by the USGS during Spring and Fall 2014</title>
        <geoform>Image files (.PNG)</geoform>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7GM85DN</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Robert H. Diehl</origin>
            <origin>Paul M. Cryan</origin>
            <origin>Ernest W. Valdez</origin>
            <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
            <title>Evaluating the Effectiveness of Wildlife Detection and Observation Technologies at a Solar Power Tower Facility</title>
            <edition>NA</edition>
            <geoform>Publication (Journal)</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>PLOS ONE</sername>
              <issue>NA</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>NA</pubplace>
              <publish>Public Library of Science</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.plosone.org/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>In this observational pilot study, we worked at the largest existing solar tower facility in the world (Ivanpah Solar Electric Generating System - ISEGS) to assess the efficacy of using radar, surveillance video, and insect trapping to monitor animals flying near the towers.  During week-long site visits in May and September, we monitored the airspace surrounding towers and observed insects, occasional birds, and bats under a variety of environmental and operational conditions.  This dataset consists of raster portable network graphics (png) images of the planned position indicator (ppi) display from a Furuno FR2127 portable radar unit to a maximum range of 1.5 km.  A new image is written with each rotation of the radar's antenna every ~2.5 seconds yielding over 500,000 images in this study.  The vast majority of radar scatterers detected by the radar represent flying animals, both vertebrates and invertebrates.

Locational Information Associated with the Towers from which Recordings were Captured:

Tower 1
Recording start date: 9/7/2014
Recording end date: 9/11/2014
Easting (X location, UTM meters): 639348
Northing (Y location, UTM meters): 3933455
UTM Zone: 11 North
Altitude above sea level (meters): 915
Elevation angle (meters): 6.5

Tower 2
Recording start date: 9/3/2014
Recording end date: 9/7/2014
Easting (X location, UTM meters): 637708
Northing (Y location, UTM meters): 3936197
UTM Zone: 11 North
Altitude above sea level (meters): 968
Elevation angle (meters): 4.2

Tower 3
Recording start date: 5/11/2014
Recording end date: 5/22/2014
Easting (X location, UTM meters): 637362
Northing (Y location, UTM meters): 3938890
UTM Zone: 11 North
Altitude above sea level (meters): 985
Elevation angle (meters): 9.0

Coordinate information based on UTM Projection, Zone 11 (Datum: NAD 1983_CORS96, Ellipsoid: GRS_1980)</abstract>
      <purpose>Solar power towers produce electrical energy from sunlight at an industrial scale.  Little is known about the effects of this emerging technology on flying animals.  Bird mortality attributable to collisions and burn injuries were reported at a solar tower in the 1980's and more recently at a new, larger facility.  Smoking objects are sometimes observed co-occurring with reflected, concentrated light (“solar flux”) in the airspace around solar towers, yet the identity and origins of such objects can be difficult to determine.  Because of the large size of new solar towers (taller than 40-story buildings), few established methods exist for observing animals flying near them.  This was a pilot study to experiment with different types of observational technologies for determining the presence and identity of animals and objects flying in the airspace near the tops of solar power towers and is not appropriate for quantitative analysis.  Data from radar complements other technologies used in this study by offering a wider-scale view of the movements of flying animals through the ISEGS facility, although clutter produced by solar tower structure prevented radar from capturing the behaviors of flying animsls in close proximity to towers.  This imagery was not gathered in a systematic enough way to draw inference beyond anecdotal observations.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <mdattim>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140514</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140515</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140516</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140517</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140518</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140519</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140520</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140521</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140522</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140903</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140904</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140905</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140906</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140907</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140908</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140909</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140910</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20140911</caldate>
          </sngdate>
        </mdattim>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>observed</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-115.484815646</westbc>
        <eastbc>-115.461980077</eastbc>
        <northbc>35.584205178</northbc>
        <southbc>35.534939936</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Alexandria Digital Library Feature Type Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>power generation sites</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>wildlife</themekey>
        <themekey>birds</themekey>
        <themekey>insects</themekey>
        <themekey>bats</themekey>
        <themekey>video monitoring</themekey>
        <themekey>videography</themekey>
        <themekey>videos</themekey>
        <themekey>infrared</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Federal Agencies and Programs</themekt>
        <themekey>Wildlife and Fisheries</themekey>
        <themekey>Solar Energy</themekey>
        <themekey>Monitoring and Evaluation</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Solar power towers</themekey>
        <themekey>migration</themekey>
        <themekey>solar power</themekey>
        <themekey>solar flux</themekey>
        <themekey>animal movement</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Mojave Desert</placekey>
        <placekey>Ivanpah Solar Electric Generating System</placekey>
        <placekey>Ivanpah Valley</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None. Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</accconst>
    <useconst>None. Users are advised to read the data set's metadata and associated scientific publication  thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Northwest Region</cntorg>
          <cntper>Robert H Diehl</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>Research Ecologist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>2327 University Way</address>
          <city>Bozeman</city>
          <state>MT</state>
          <postal>59715</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>406-994-7481</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>406-994-6556</cntfax>
        <cntemail>rhdiehl@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>This study was funded by the USGS Quick Response Program.</datacred>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted, however radar data for this study concerns location information of flying animals and the factors that influence accuracy in radar location are well established (see below).</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic>
    <complete>These data are limited in spatial extent to a geographic area within ~1.5 km radius of radar locations on Ivanpah Solar Electric Generating System grounds and variously sample an airspace between 22 m and 273 m above radar level.  Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Horizontal accuracy of bioscatter locations is largely determined by accuracy in range and azimuth.  Two flying animals may be distinguishable in range at the pulse width of this radar (0.07 us) if they are separated by &gt;10.5 m.  The density aloft of vertebrates and large insects is usually far below this.  Accuracy in azimuth is determined by antenna beam width which in turn in influenced by range from the radar, antenna design, and by the size of the flying animal on radar.  Sizes of flying animals in this study varied, but other parameters are known.  The radar was fitted with a parabolic antenna with a half-power beam width of 2.1 degrees.  As an example, two flying animals at the same range, say 1000 m, should be distinguishable if they are separated by &gt;37 m.  This number varies as a function of range*sin(beam_width).  Again, this spatial resolution is well within that needed to resolve individuals during most vertebrate and large insect movements.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>Because the radar antenna is parabolic, accuracy in vertical position is determined by the same factors that influence accurracy in azimuth (see above).</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Development of the data set by the agency / individuals identified in the 'Originator' element in the Identification Info section of the record.</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>11</utmzone>
            <transmer>
              <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
              <longcm>-117.0</longcm>
              <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
              <feast>500000.0</feast>
              <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
            </transmer>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>0.6096</absres>
            <ordres>0.6096</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>Meter</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D_NAD_1983_CORS96</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS_1980</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</addrtype>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Distributor assumes no liability for misuse of data.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Image files (.PNG)</formname>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7GM85DN</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20151119</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Robert H Diehl</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, NORTHWEST REGION</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Research Ecologist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>2327 University Way</address>
          <city>Bozeman</city>
          <state>MT</state>
          <postal>59715</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>406-994-7481</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>406-994-6556</cntfax>
        <cntemail>rhdiehl@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>