<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
 <idinfo>
  <citation>
   <citeinfo>
    <origin>Dr. Wenguang Zhao</origin>
    <origin>Dr. Richard Allen</origin>
    <origin>Dr. Ricardo Trezza</origin>
    <origin>Clarence Robison</origin>
    <pubdate>20151217</pubdate>
    <title>Evapotranspiration in the Upper Klamath Basin for October 2013</title>
    <geoform>Raster Digital Data Set</geoform>
    <pubinfo>
     <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
    </pubinfo>
    <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F72J68ZW</onlink>
   </citeinfo>
  </citation>
  <descript>
   <abstract>The evapotranspiration (ET) datasets were created under contract for this study by the University of Idaho. A high-resolution remote sensing technique known as Mapping Evapotranspiration at High Resolution and Internalized Calibration (METRIC) was used to create estimates of the spatial distribution of ET. The METRIC technique uses thermal infrared Landsat imagery to quantify actual evapotranspiration at a 30-meter resolution that can be related to individual irrigated fields. Because evaporation uses heat energy, ground surfaces with large ET rates are left cooler as a result of ET than ground surfaces that have less ET. As a consequence, irrigated fields appear in the Landsat images as cooler than nonirrigated fields. Products produced from this study include total seasonal and total monthly (April-October) actual evapotranspiration maps for 2013.</abstract>
   <purpose>This dataset adds to the collection of METRIC-derived evapotranspiration products in the Klamath Basin.</purpose>
   <supplinf>See the University of Idaho report, titled: Production of Satellite-based Maps of Evapotranspiration using the METRICtm Model for Year 2013 in the Klamath River Basin of Oregon-- Landsat Path 45 Rows 30 and 31</supplinf>
  </descript>
  <timeperd>
   <timeinfo>
    <rngdates>
     <begdate>20131001</begdate>
     <enddate>20131031</enddate>
    </rngdates>
   </timeinfo>
   <current>ground condition</current>
  </timeperd>
  <status>
   <progress>Complete</progress>
   <update>Not planned</update>
  </status>
  <spdom>
   <bounding>
    <westbc>-123.699460027</westbc>
    <eastbc>-120.443401757</eastbc>
    <northbc>44.164299208</northbc>
    <southbc>40.775037988</southbc>
   </bounding>
  </spdom>
  <keywords>
   <theme>
    <themekt>None</themekt>
    <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
    <themekey>Evapotranspiration</themekey>
    <themekey>METRIC</themekey>
    <themekey>Landsat</themekey>
    <themekey>Remote sensing</themekey>
   </theme>
   <place>
    <placekt>None</placekt>
    <placekey>Upper Klamath Basin</placekey>
    <placekey>Sprague River Basin</placekey>
    <placekey>Wood River Basin</placekey>
    <placekey>Williamson River Basin</placekey>
    <placekey>Lost River Basin</placekey>
    <placekey>Oregon</placekey>
    <placekey>California</placekey>
   </place>
  </keywords>
  <accconst>none</accconst>
  <useconst>none</useconst>
  <ptcontac>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntperp>
     <cntper>Jonathan Haynes</cntper>
     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
    </cntperp>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
     <address>2130 SW 5th Avenue</address>
     <city>Portland</city>
     <state>Oregon</state>
     <postal>97201</postal>
     <country>USA</country>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>503-251-3468</cntvoice>
    <cntemail>jhaynes@usgs.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
  </ptcontac>
  <browse>
   <browsen>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F72J68ZW</browsen>
   <browsed>Thumbnail image of 30-meter ERDAS IMAGINE raster showing monthly evapotranspiration for October, 2013 in Landsat Path 45, Rows 30 and 31</browsed>
   <browset>jpg</browset>
  </browse>
  <native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1 (Build 4959) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native>
 </idinfo>
 <dataqual>
  <attracc>
   <attraccr>See the University of Idaho report, titled: Production of Satellite-based Maps of Evapotranspiration using the METRICtm Model for Year 2013 in the Klamath River Basin of Oregon-- Landsat Path 45 Rows 30 and 31. See section 2 for details on how Landsat images were selected and pre-processed. See sections 3 and 5 for METRIC model calibration. See section 4 for weather data quality assessment and quality control. See section 6 for image sharpening, Landsat 7 gapfilling, cloud cover management, open-water ET, and comparing ET with precipitation.</attraccr>
  </attracc>
  <logic>See the University of Idaho report, titled: Production of Satellite-based Maps of Evapotranspiration using the METRICtm Model for Year 2013 in the Klamath River Basin of Oregon-- Landsat Path 45 Rows 30 and 31. See sections 3-5 for discussions on calibration of the METRIC model.</logic>
  <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details and the accompanying University of Idaho report, titled: Production of Satellite-based Maps of Evapotranspiration using the METRICtm Model for Year 2013 in the Klamath River Basin of Oregon-- Landsat Path 45 Rows 30 and 31.</complete>
  <posacc>
   <horizpa>
    <horizpar>No formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has been conducted. The horizontal accuracy is limited to METRIC input datasets described in the metadata source input section.</horizpar>
   </horizpa>
   <vertacc>
    <vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set is not applicable.</vertaccr>
   </vertacc>
  </posacc>
  <lineage>
   <srcinfo>
    <srccite>
     <citeinfo>
      <origin>U.S. Geological Survey Center for Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS)</origin>
      <pubdate>2013</pubdate>
      <title>Landsat Thematic Mapper (TM)</title>
      <geoform>Raster Digital Data (Aerial Imagery)</geoform>
      <pubinfo>
       <pubplace>online</pubplace>
       <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
      </pubinfo>
      <onlink>http://glovis.usgs.gov/</onlink>
     </citeinfo>
    </srccite>
    <typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
    <srctime>
     <timeinfo>
      <rngdates>
       <begdate>20130330</begdate>
       <enddate>20131101</enddate>
      </rngdates>
     </timeinfo>
     <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
    </srctime>
    <srccitea>Landsat</srccitea>
    <srccontr>The METRIC procedure used to generate this dataset utilizes the visible, near-infrared and thermal infrared energy spectrum bands from Landsat satellite images and weather data to calculate ET on a pixel by pixel basis.</srccontr>
   </srcinfo>
   <srcinfo>
    <srccite>
     <citeinfo>
      <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
      <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
      <title>National Landcover Database</title>
      <geoform>Raster Digital Data Set</geoform>
      <pubinfo>
       <pubplace>online</pubplace>
       <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
      </pubinfo>
      <onlink>http://seamless.usgs.gov/nlcd.php</onlink>
     </citeinfo>
    </srccite>
    <typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
    <srctime>
     <timeinfo>
      <sngdate>
       <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
      </sngdate>
     </timeinfo>
     <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
    </srctime>
    <srccitea>NLCD</srccitea>
    <srccontr>A land use map was used to support the estimation of aerodynamic roughness and soil heat flux during METRIC processing.</srccontr>
   </srcinfo>
   <srcinfo>
    <srccite>
     <citeinfo>
      <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
      <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
      <title>National Elevation Dataset</title>
      <geoform>Raster Digital Data Set</geoform>
      <pubinfo>
       <pubplace>online</pubplace>
       <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
      </pubinfo>
      <onlink>http://seamless.usgs.gov</onlink>
     </citeinfo>
    </srccite>
    <typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
    <srctime>
     <timeinfo>
      <sngdate>
       <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
      </sngdate>
     </timeinfo>
     <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
    </srctime>
    <srccitea>DEM</srccitea>
    <srccontr>A digital elevation map (DEM) is used during METRIC processing to adjust surface temperatures for lapse effects caused by elevation variation. Maps of slope and aspect (aspect is the cardinal direction of an inclined surface) are also derived from the DEM at 30 m resolution and are used in estimating solar radiation on slopes.  These images were created using the tools of the ERDAS Imagine processing system based on the DEM.</srccontr>
   </srcinfo>
   <srcinfo>
    <srccite>
     <citeinfo>
      <origin>U.S. Bureau of Reclamation</origin>
      <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
      <title>AgriMet Weather Network</title>
      <geoform>Vector Digital Data Set</geoform>
      <pubinfo>
       <pubplace>online</pubplace>
       <publish>U.S. Bureau of Reclamation</publish>
      </pubinfo>
      <onlink>http://www.usbr.gov/pn/agrimet/index.html</onlink>
     </citeinfo>
    </srccite>
    <typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
    <srctime>
     <timeinfo>
      <sngdate>
       <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
      </sngdate>
     </timeinfo>
     <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
    </srctime>
    <srccitea>AgriMet</srccitea>
    <srccontr>AgriMet weather station data were used to calculate reference evapotranspiration for use in the METRIC model.</srccontr>
   </srcinfo>
   <srcinfo>
    <srccite>
     <citeinfo>
      <origin>National Interagency Fire Center</origin>
      <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
      <title>Remote Automatic Weather Station</title>
      <geoform>Vector Digital Data Set</geoform>
      <pubinfo>
       <pubplace>online</pubplace>
       <publish>National Interagency Fire Center</publish>
      </pubinfo>
      <onlink>http://raws.fam.nwcg.gov/index.html</onlink>
     </citeinfo>
    </srccite>
    <typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
    <srctime>
     <timeinfo>
      <sngdate>
       <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
      </sngdate>
     </timeinfo>
     <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
    </srctime>
    <srccitea>RAWS</srccitea>
    <srccontr>RAWS data were used to calculate reference evapotranspiration for use in the METRIC model.</srccontr>
   </srcinfo>
   <srcinfo>
    <srccite>
     <citeinfo>
      <origin>California Department of Water Resources</origin>
      <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
      <title>California Irrigation Management Information System</title>
      <geoform>Vector Digital Data Set</geoform>
      <pubinfo>
       <pubplace>online</pubplace>
       <publish>California Department of Water Resources</publish>
      </pubinfo>
      <onlink>http://www.cimis.water.ca.gov/</onlink>
     </citeinfo>
    </srccite>
    <typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
    <srctime>
     <timeinfo>
      <sngdate>
       <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
      </sngdate>
     </timeinfo>
     <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
    </srctime>
    <srccitea>CIMIS</srccitea>
    <srccontr>CIMIS weather station data were used to calculate reference evapotranspiration for use in the METRIC model.</srccontr>
   </srcinfo>
   <procstep>
    <procdesc>See the University of Idaho report, titled: Production of Satellite-based Maps of Evapotranspiration using the METRICtm Model for Year 2013 in the Klamath River Basin of Oregon-- Landsat Path 45 Rows 30 and 31</procdesc>
    <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
   </procstep>
  </lineage>
  <cloud>Unknown</cloud>
 </dataqual>
 <spdoinfo>
  <direct>Raster</direct>
  <rastinfo>
   <rasttype>Grid Cell</rasttype>
   <rowcount>12453</rowcount>
   <colcount>8681</colcount>
   <vrtcount>1</vrtcount>
  </rastinfo>
 </spdoinfo>
 <spref>
  <horizsys>
   <planar>
    <gridsys>
     <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
     <utm>
      <utmzone>10</utmzone>
      <transmer>
       <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
       <longcm>-123.0</longcm>
       <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
       <feast>500000.0</feast>
       <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
      </transmer>
     </utm>
    </gridsys>
    <planci>
     <plance>row and column</plance>
     <coordrep>
      <absres>30.0</absres>
      <ordres>30.0</ordres>
     </coordrep>
     <plandu>Meter</plandu>
    </planci>
   </planar>
   <geodetic>
    <horizdn>D_WGS_1984</horizdn>
    <ellips>WGS_1984</ellips>
    <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
    <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
   </geodetic>
  </horizsys>
 </spref>
 <eainfo>
  <detailed>
   <enttyp>
    <enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl>
    <enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd>
    <enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
   </enttyp>
   <attr>
    <attrlabl>Value</attrlabl>
    <attrdef>Evapotranspiration, in mm, for the month of October, 2013. ET values less than zero should be considered equal to zero. Values of 200 and -200 outside of image boundaries should be considered no data.</attrdef>
    <attrdefs>University of Idaho</attrdefs>
    <attrdomv>
     <rdom>
      <rdommin>-200</rdommin>
      <rdommax>200</rdommax>
      <attrunit>millimeters</attrunit>
     </rdom>
    </attrdomv>
   </attr>
  </detailed>
  <overview>
   <eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes the tabular data associated with the data set. Review the detailed descriptions that are provided (the individual attribute descriptions) for information on the values that appear as fields/table entries of the data set.</eaover>
   <eadetcit>The entity and attribute information was generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit>
  </overview>
 </eainfo>
 <distinfo>
  <distrib>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntperp>
     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
    </cntperp>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
     <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
     <city>Denver</city>
     <state>CO</state>
     <postal>80225</postal>
     <country>USA</country>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
    <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
  </distrib>
  <distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items must be secured from the copyright owner whenever applicable. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although the data have been subjected to rigorous review and are substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, the data are released on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from authorized or unauthorized use. Although the data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
  <stdorder>
   <digform>
    <digtinfo>
     <formname>Raster Digital Data Set</formname>
     <formvern>Unknown</formvern>
     <formcont>PKZIP compression</formcont>
     <filedec>Winzip</filedec>
    </digtinfo>
    <digtopt>
     <onlinopt>
      <computer>
       <networka>
        <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F72J68ZW</networkr>
       </networka>
      </computer>
     </onlinopt>
    </digtopt>
   </digform>
   <fees>No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
  </stdorder>
 </distinfo>
 <metainfo>
  <metd>20151023</metd>
  <metc>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntperp>
     <cntper>Jonathan Haynes</cntper>
     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
    </cntperp>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
     <address>2130 SW 5th Avenue</address>
     <city>Portland</city>
     <state>Oregon</state>
     <postal>97201</postal>
     <country>USA</country>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>503-251-3468</cntvoice>
    <cntemail>jhaynes@usgs.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
  </metc>
  <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
  <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
 </metainfo>
</metadata>
