<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Frank L. Engel</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Acoustic Doppler current profiler velocity data collected in the approach channel of Brandon Road Lock and Dam in 2015</title>
        <geoform>CSV files of time- and depth-averaged velocity data (5-second temporal average)</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F76W986V</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Water velocities were measured in the Des Plaines River from approximately river mile 286 to river mile 284 on October 19–21, 2015 using Teledyne Rio Grande 1200 kHz acoustic Doppler current profilers (ADCP). The data were georeferenced with differential GPS receivers with submeter accuracy. These velocity data were collected in support of the US Army Corps of Engineers Great Lakes and Mississippi River Interbasin Study (GLMRIS), and were concurrent with a dye-tracing study.
	  
	  ADCP data were collected in the approach channel of the Brandon Road Lock and downstream in the main channel of the Des Plaines River to determine the spatial distribution of depth-averaged velocity in the river on October 19–21, 2015. The data have been depth­-averaged over the entire measured portion of the water column and temporally averaged over 5 second intervals to reduce noise. Data were processed using the Velocity Mapping Toolbox (Parsons and other, 2013). Any data assigned a value of "­9999" are invalid or missing and should not be used for analysis.
	  The ADCP data collected on October 19 and 20, 2015 also included velocity measurements at cross sections in the Des Plaines River. These data were also processed with the Velocity Mapping Toolbox (Parsons and others, 2013) to obtain a mean velocity field for each cross section derived from one or more individual transects at each location.
	  
	  Parsons, D. R., Jackson, P. R., Czuba, J. A., Engel, F. L., Rhoads, B. L., Oberg, K. A., Best, J. L., Mueller, D. S., Johnson, K. K. and Riley, J. D. (2013), Velocity Mapping Toolbox (VMT): a processing and visualization suite for moving-vessel ADCP measurements. Earth Surf. Process. Landforms, 38: 1244–1260. doi: 10.1002/esp.3367</abstract>
      <purpose>These data were collected in support of the US Army Corps of Engineers Great Lakes and Mississippi River Interbasin Study (GLMRIS), and were concurrent with a dye-tracing study.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20160513</caldate>
        </sngdate>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20151019</begdate>
          <enddate>20151021</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Des Plaines River, Joliet, IL</descgeog>
      <bounding><westbc>-88.1292772293</westbc><eastbc>-88.1040859222</eastbc><northbc>41.5027601604</northbc><southbc>41.4862057787</southbc></bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Velocity</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>Des Plaines River</placekey>
        <placekey>Illinois</placekey>
        <placekey>Will County</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Frank L. Engel</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Illinois Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>405 N. Goodwin Ave.</address>
          <city>Urbana</city>
          <state>IL</state>
          <postal>61801</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>2173289774</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>fengel@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>n/a</methtype>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data processed per the Velocity Mapping Toolbox (VMT) v. 4.08 ASCII2GIS utility with full-depth averaging and 5-second temporal averaging.
		For details on VMT and its utilities, see:  https://hydroacoustics.usgs.gov/movingboat/VMT/VMT.shtml
		NOTE: Any data assigned a value of "-9999" are invalid or missing data and should not be used for analysis.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160510</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>NOTE: Any data assigned a value of "-9999" are invalid or missing data and should not be used for analysis.
	  NAME DESCRIPTION
	  EnsNo Ensemble Number
	  Year Year of sample
	  Month Month of sample
	  Day Day of sample
	  Hour Hour of sample
	  Min Minute of sample
	  Sec Second of sample
	  Lat_WGS84 Latitude in WGS84
	  Lon_WGS84 Longitude in WGS84
	  Heading_deg Heading reading at time of sample in degrees from true north
	  Pitch_deg Pitch reading at time of sample in degrees
	  Roll_deg Roll reading at time of sample in degrees
	  Temp_C Temperature at time of sample in deg. C
	  Depth_m Mean bed depth at time of sample in meters
	  B1Depth_m Beam 1 bed depth at time of sample in meters
	  B2Depth_m Beam 2 bed depth at time of sample in meters
	  B3Depth_m Beam 3 bed depth at time of sample in meters
	  B4Depth_m Beam 4 bed depth at time of sample in meters
	  Backscatter_db Acoustic backscatter in dB
	  DAVeast_cmps Depth- or Layer-averaged velocity (east component) in cm/s
	  DAVnorth_cmps Depth- or Layer-averaged velocity (north component) in cm/s
	  DAVmag_cmps Depth- or Layer-averaged velocity magnitude in cm/s
	  DAVdir_deg Depth- or Layer-averaged velocity direction in degrees from true north
	  DAVvert_cmps Depth- or Layer-averaged velocity (vertical) in cm/s (+ is up)</eaover>
      <eadetcit>https://hydroacoustics.usgs.gov/movingboat/VMT/VMT.shtml (see The Velocity Mapping Toolbox Users Guide, specifically the output file format for the ASCII2GIS utility).</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160513</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Frank L. Engel</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Illinois Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>405 N. Goodwin Ave.</address>
          <city>Urbana</city>
          <state>IL</state>
          <postal>61801</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>2173289774</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>fenge@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>

