<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Western Ecological Research Center</origin>
		<origin>Jon E. Keeley</origin>
        <pubdate>20150731</pubdate>
        <title>Arctostaphylos Fire Data</title>
        <geoform>tabular digital data</geoform>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7ZK5DQF</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>V. Thomas Parker</origin>
            <origin>Jon E. Keeley</origin>
            <origin>Michael Vasey</origin>
            <pubdate>20151030</pubdate>
            <title>Resprouting and Seeding Hypotheses: A Test of the Gap-Dependent Model Using Resprouting and Obligate Seeding Subspecies of Arctostaphylos</title>
            <geoform>Publication (Journal)</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>none listed</pubplace>
              <publish>Plant Ecology</publish>
            </pubinfo>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Abstract Ecological factors favoring either resprouting or obligate seeding in plants have received considerable attention recently. Three ecological models have been proposed to explain patterns of these two life history types. In this study we test these three models using data from California chaparral. We take an innovative approach to testing these models by not testing community or landscape patterns, but instead, investigating environmental patterns characteristic of pairs of either resprouting or obligate seeding subspecies of Arctostaphylos (Ericaceae), a dominant and diverse shrub genus in chaparral. Four species were investigated that contain both a resprouting and an obligate seeding subspecies. Data were analyzed for % bare ground, elevation, annual precipitation, number of fires, and time between fires and were compared independently for each subspecies pair. Results were consistently supportive of the gap-dependent model suggesting that obligate seeders are favored when post-disturbance gaps are large. Results for other aspects were inconclusive or contrary to expectations for either of the other models.</abstract>
      <purpose>The data from the FRAP database, PRISM database and the species data from the Consortium of California Herbaria was used in order to compare the fire frequency at each site over the last 100 years and the resprouting of Arctostaphylos subspecies.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>18980101</begdate>
          <enddate>20140101</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>publication date</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-123.914900</westbc>
        <eastbc>-115.233174</eastbc>
        <northbc>41.301500</northbc>
        <southbc>30.513421</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekey>disturbance</themekey>
        <themekey>reproduction</themekey>
        <themekey>seeders</themekey>
        <themekey>regeneration</themekey>
        <themekey>resprouters</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>California</placekey>
        <placekey>Baja California</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None. Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</accconst>
    <useconst>There are no constraints on the use of the data. Distributor assumes no liability for misuse of data.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Western Ecological Research Center</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jon E Keeley</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>Research Ecologist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing</addrtype>
          <address>47050 Generals Highway</address>
          <city>Three Rivers</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>93271</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>559-565-3170</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>559-565-3177</cntfax>
        <cntemail>jon_keeley@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>V. Thomas Parker, Department of Biology, San Francisco State University, San Francisco, CA 94132 USA Michael C. Vasey, Department of Biology, San Francisco State University, San Francisco, CA 94132 USA</datacred>
    <native>Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.1.1.3143</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>For taxa well represented in collections we took a random sample of 30 specimens, but most taxa had many fewer collections and in these cases all available specimens, not representing duplicate sites, were selected.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>The hypothesis of disturbance frequency was tested by comparing the fire frequency at each site over the last 100 years. The coordinates used to locate each population were entered into the State of California, CalFire FRAP database. The data was extracted from 3 existing databases and combined into a single table. Analysis were drawn from studies of the different locations using all the information derived from the databaes and use of google earth for location verification.</logic>
    <complete>Fire history for the last 104 years based on the Cal Fire FRAP fire history database and average annual precipitation based on PRISM data for sites occupied by resprouting and seeding subspecies of Arctostaphylos and fire history for the last 104 years. Note: Baja California not included in either the FRAP or PRISM databases. These values were extrapolated from the literature; ^ fires per 1000 ha for Sierra Juarez (subspecies juarezensis) and Sierra San Pedro Martir (subspecies peninsularis) from Minnich et al. 1993; precipitation data from Hugh Safford unpublished data). The Baja California sites are those with Latitude lower than 33 degree north.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Latitude and longitude (WGS84 projections) for each site were entered into Google Earth and sites located. An approximate 0.1 km diameter circle was estimated around the sample location and the community type was determined and the percentage bare ground (lacking woody cover) estimated to the nearest 5% by overlaying a grid imprinted on acetate.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>The elevation values for the samples were obtained from the FRAP database. A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Northwest Alliance for computational Science and engineering</origin>
            <pubdate>20100101</pubdate>
            <title>PRISM Climate Group</title>
            <geoform>Observed/Measured First-Hand</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Online</pubplace>
              <publish>PRISM Climate Group</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.prism.oregonstate.edu/normals/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>hardcopy</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>19810101</begdate>
              <enddate>20100101</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>PRISM data 30 Year Normals</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Source information used in support of the development of the data set.</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>California Department of Forestry and Fire Protection</origin>
            <pubdate>20150701</pubdate>
            <title>The Fire and Resource Assessment Program</title>
            <geoform>Vector Digital Data Set</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Online</pubplace>
              <publish>California Department of Forestry and Fire Protection</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://frap.cdf.ca.gov/data/frapgisdata-sw-fireperimeters_download.php</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>hardcopy</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>18980101</begdate>
              <enddate>20150101</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Final_Arctostaphylos data</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Source information used in support of the development of the data set.</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Data provided by the participants of the Consortium of California Herbaria</origin>
            <pubdate>20150731</pubdate>
            <title>Consortium of California Herbaria</title>
            <geoform>Observed/Measured First-Hand</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Online</pubplace>
              <publish>Consortium of California Herbaria</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://ucjeps.berkeley.edu/consortium/index.html</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>hardcopy</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>19940528</begdate>
              <enddate>20150619</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Species and Subspecies data</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Source information used in support of the development of the data set.</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>A test of the first hypothesis was to compare the extent of bare ground in mature stands of each subspecies as this should be strongly associated with the size of gaps suitable for seedling establishment after fire. Populations were located from herbarium collections documented in the California Consortium of Herbaria and personal collections. For taxa well represented in collections we took a random sample of 30 specimens, but most taxa had many fewer collections and in these cases all available specimens, not representing duplicate sites, were selected. Latitude and longitude (WGS84 projections) for each site were entered into Google Earth and sites located. An approximate 0.1 km diameter circle was estimated around the sample location and the community type was determined and the percentage bare ground (lacking woody cover) estimated to the nearest 5% by overlaying a grid imprinted on acetate. These data and metadata are available online. Within each species the estimated bare ground in resprouting and non-resprouting populations were compared statistically with the two sample t-test. The hypothesis of disturbance frequency was tested by comparing the fire frequency at each site over the last 100 years. The coordinates used to locate each population were entered into the State of California, CalFire FRAP database (http://frap.cdf.ca.gov/data/fire_data/history/fire_historyfr.html, accessed 13 July 2015) and fire histories extracted for each site in California. For the Baja California populations we relied on data assembled by Minnich et al. (1993). California sites with multiple samples were compared statistically with a t-test. Competition is a notoriously difficult parameter to estimate. Clarke et al. (2005) used various surrogate measures of site productivity. In Mediterranean-climate California annual precipitation is a reasonably good surrogate measure for site productivity. Using 30 year norms from the PRISM database (http://www.prism.oregonstate.edu/normals/, accessed 15 July 2015), sites with multiple samples of subspecies were compared statistically with a t-test.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20150713</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Point</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>148</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <geograph>
        <latres>8.983152841195215e-009</latres>
        <longres>8.983152841195215e-009</longres>
        <geogunit>Decimal Degrees</geogunit>
      </geograph>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D WGS 1984</horizdn>
        <ellips>WGS 1984</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed xmlns="">
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>ArctostaphylosFireData</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Point locations where Fires have occurred in the past and new Arctostaphylos have been seen resprouting thus reseach locations.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>author</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr xmlns="">
        <attrlabl>SPECIES</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Arctostaphylos species epithet.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom xmlns="">
            <edomv>manzanita</edomv>
            <edomvd>Species type</edomvd>
            <edomvds>scientific definitions</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom xmlns="">
            <edomv>mewukka</edomv>
            <edomvd>Species type</edomvd>
            <edomvds>scientific definitions</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom xmlns="">
            <edomv>parryana</edomv>
            <edomvd>Species type</edomvd>
            <edomvds>scientific definitions</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom xmlns="">
            <edomv>peninsularis</edomv>
            <edomvd>Species type</edomvd>
            <edomvds>scientific definitions</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr xmlns="">
        <attrlabl>SUB_SPECIES</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Subspecies epithet</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom xmlns="">
            <edomv>manzanita</edomv>
            <edomvd>subspecies</edomvd>
            <edomvds>scientific definition</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom xmlns="">
            <edomv>roofii</edomv>
            <edomvd>subspecies</edomvd>
            <edomvds>scientific definition</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom xmlns="">
            <edomv>truei</edomv>
            <edomvd>subspecies</edomvd>
            <edomvds>scientific definition</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom xmlns="">
            <edomv>mewukka</edomv>
            <edomvd>subspecies</edomvd>
            <edomvds>scientific definition</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom xmlns="">
            <edomv>parryana</edomv>
            <edomvd>subspecies</edomvd>
            <edomvds>scientific definition</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom xmlns="">
            <edomv>desertica</edomv>
            <edomvd>subspecies</edomvd>
            <edomvds>scientific definition</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom xmlns="">
            <edomv>juarezensis</edomv>
            <edomvd>subspecies</edomvd>
            <edomvds>scientific definition</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom xmlns="">
            <edomv>peninsularis</edomv>
            <edomvd>subspecies</edomvd>
            <edomvds>scientific definition</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr xmlns="">
        <attrlabl>MODE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Whether it is a postfire seeder or postfire resprouter.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom xmlns="">
            <edomv>seeder</edomv>
            <edomvd>what type of plant is represented</edomvd>
            <edomvds>scientific definition</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom xmlns="">
            <edomv>resprouter</edomv>
            <edomvd>what type of plant is represented</edomvd>
            <edomvds>scientific definition</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr xmlns="">
        <attrlabl>DATE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Date of Google Earth imagery used to calculate percentage bareground.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>2004</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2015</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
        <begdatea>20041231</begdatea>
        <enddatea>20150623</enddatea>
      </attr>
      <attr xmlns="">
        <attrlabl>LATITUDE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Latitude in WGS84 projection.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>30.513421</rdommin>
            <rdommax>41.3015</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr xmlns="">
        <attrlabl>LONGITUDE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Longitude WGS84 projection.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>-123.9149</rdommin>
            <rdommax>-115.233174</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr xmlns="">
        <attrlabl>ELEV_M</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Elevation of sample location in meters.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>42.3672</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2236.0128</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr xmlns="">
        <attrlabl>BARE_GROUND</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Value represents the estimated percentage of bare ground lacking woody cover.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>84</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr xmlns="">
        <attrlabl>PRISM_PPT</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>30 year normal annual mm of precipitation for the latitude and longitude of given sample.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>120</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2514</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr xmlns="">
        <attrlabl>NUMBER</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Total number of fires recorded in the FRAP database for that latitude and longitude from 1910 - 2014.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>6</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr xmlns="">
        <attrlabl>FIRE1</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Year of most recent fire at that latitude and longitude.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>0000</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2014</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr xmlns="">
        <attrlabl>FIRE2</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Year of second most recent fire at that latitude and longitude.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>0000</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2014</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr xmlns="">
        <attrlabl>FIRE3</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Year of third most recent fire at that latitude and longitude.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>0000</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2014</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr xmlns="">
        <attrlabl>FIRE4</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Year of fourth most recent fire at that latitude and longitude.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>0000</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2014</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr xmlns="">
        <attrlabl>FIRE5</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Year of fifth most recent fire at that latitude and longitude.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>0000</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2014</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr xmlns="">
        <attrlabl>FIRE6</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Year of sixth most recent fire at that latitude and longitude.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>0000</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2014</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>INTERVAL1</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The time in years from the beginning of the record to the first fire event.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>000</rdommin>
            <rdommax>105</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>INTERVAL2</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The time in years from the first fire to the next fire or to the end of the time period if no fire #2.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>000</rdommin>
            <rdommax>105</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>INTERVAL3</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The time in years from the second fire to the next fire or to the end of the time period if no fire #3.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>000</rdommin>
            <rdommax>105</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>INTERVAL4</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The time in years from the third fire to the next fire or to the end of the time period if no fire #4.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>000</rdommin>
            <rdommax>105</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>INTERVAL5</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The time in years from the fourth fire to the next fire or to the end of the time period if no fire #5.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom xmlns="">
            <rdommin>000</rdommin>
            <rdommax>105</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>INTERVAL6</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The time in years from the fifth fire to the next fire or to the end of the time period if no fire #6.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>000</rdommin>
            <rdommax>105</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>attr<attr><attrlabl>AVE FIRE INTERVAL</attrlabl><attrdef>The average time in years between fires, if no fires it is &gt;= to 105, If there is one fire then it is the average of intervals 1 and 2, if 2 fires then the average of intervals 1,2,3 etc</attrdef><attrdefs>author</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom xmlns=""><rdommin>000</rdommin><rdommax>105</rdommax></rdom></attrdomv></attr></detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>There are no constraints on the use of the data.  Distributor assumes no liability for misuse of data.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Vector Digital Data Set (Point)</formname>
          <formvern>Final</formvern>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://www.werc.usgs.gov/</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20151207</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Western Ecological Research Center</cntorg>
          <cntper>Roberto V Lugo</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>Physical Scientist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing</addrtype>
          <address>Mail Stop 4003, 3020 State University Dr. East</address>
          <city>Sacramento</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>95819</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>916-278-9509</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>916-278-9475</cntfax>
        <cntemail>rlugo@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
