<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Brian Collins</origin>
        <pubdate>20150724</pubdate>
        <title>Video data files to accompany USGS OFR 2015-1142--Assessment of existing and potential landslide hazards resulting from the April 25, 2015 Gorkha, Nepal earthquake sequence</title>
        <geoform>.mp4 and .kmz</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>ScienceBase</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7X928BN</onlink>
        <onlink>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/55b24f7ee4b09a3b01b5361e</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>On April 25, 2015, a large ( M7.8) earthquake shook much of central Nepal and was followed by a series of M&gt;6 aftershocks, including a M7.3 event on May 12, 2015. This earthquake and aftershocks, referred to as the Gorkha earthquake sequence, caused thousands of fatalities, damaged and destroyed entire villages, and displaced millions of residents. The earthquakes also triggered thousands of landslides in the exceedingly steep topography of Nepal; these landslides were responsible for hundreds of fatalities, and blocked vital roads and trails to affected villages.  With the support of the United States Agency for International Development (USAID), Office of Foreign Disaster Assistance (OFDA), and in collaboration with earthquake-hazard organizations from both the United States and Nepal, the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) responded to this crisis by providing landslide-hazard expertise to Nepalese agencies and affected villages.  During these assessments, over 11 hours of helicopter-based video coverage of earthquake-affected areas was collected.  A report available on-line provides a report on landslide assessments conducted by the USGS.  The video resources contained herein provide high resolution coverage of approximately 1,000 kilometers (km) of river valleys and surrounding terrain affected by the Gorkha earthquake sequence.</abstract>
      <purpose>Video data was collected to record earthquake-affected river valleys and surrounding terrain from the April 25, 2015 Gorkha, Nepal earthquake sequence.</purpose>
      <supplinf>This data accompanies U.S. Geological Survey Open File Report 2015-1142.  The appendix of this report provides additional information on the video files.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20150527</begdate>
          <enddate>20150601</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Central Nepal</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>83.322502852018</westbc>
        <eastbc>86.8205499951</eastbc>
        <northbc>29.293696635832</northbc>
        <southbc>27.242534198561</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Nepal</themekey>
        <themekey>earthquake</themekey>
        <themekey>landslide</themekey>
        <themekey>helicopter</themekey>
        <themekey>video</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>Nepal</placekey>
        <placekey>Gorkha</placekey>
        <placekey>Kathmandu</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Brian Collins</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
          <address>345 Middlefield Road, MS973</address>
          <city>Menlo Park</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>94025</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>650-329-5466</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>bcollins@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <browse>
      <browsen>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/file/get/55b24f7ee4b09a3b01b5361e?f=__disk__3b%2Ff3%2F59%2F3bf359a3d162ba6a018875c2b127559638199190&amp;allowOpen=true</browsen>
      <browsed>Thumbnail image of a clip from the USGS_Nepal_05272015-K.mp4 video file at 31 seconds from the beginning of the video.</browsed>
      <browset>PNG</browset>
    </browse>
    <datacred>U.S. Department of State, USAID Office of Foreign Disaster Assistance</datacred>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Start and end of video files were checked for consistency with geographic locations in KMZ files.</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Video files were organized by date and titled accordingly.</procdesc>
        <procdate>2015</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
    <cloud>0</cloud>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>See KMZ file that accompanies the video files.</indspref>
    <direct>Raster</direct>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Video data</eaover>
      <eadetcit>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/55b24f7ee4b09a3b01b5361e</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>This database has been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although this database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, it is released on condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government shall be held liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized use.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Digital Geospatial Datasets</formname>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7X928BN</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150724</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Brian Collins</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>345 Middlefield Road, MS973</address>
          <city>Menlo Park</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>94025</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>650-329-5466</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>bcollins@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>