<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
 <idinfo>
  <citation>
   <citeinfo>
    <origin>Eric D. Anderson</origin>
    <origin>Heather L. Parks</origin>
    <origin>Michael C. Jenkins</origin>
    <origin>Duc M. Nguyen</origin>
    <origin>B. Carter Hearn, Jr</origin>
    <origin>Michael L Zientek</origin>
    <pubdate>20160524</pubdate>
    <title>Missouri Breaks Project, Montana - Digitized aeromagnetic data</title>
    <geoform>Vector Digital Data Set (Point)</geoform>
    <pubinfo>
     <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
     <publish>United States Geological Survey</publish>
    </pubinfo>
    <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7TH8JTN</onlink>
   </citeinfo>
  </citation>
  <descript>
   <abstract>From February 12 to March 8, 1981, EG and G Geometrics conducted an aeromagnetic survey in Montana for Anaconda Copper Company. A Piper Navajo aircraft was used to conducted the survey. The survey was flown along north-south flightlines spaced 660 feet at a nominal height of 450 feet above the terrain. Five uniformly spaced east-west tie-lines were also flown. During processing, the International Geomagnetic Reference Field (IGRF) of 1975 was updated to 1981 and removed from the survey observations. The resultant anomalous magnetic field was contoured at a 4.0 gamma interval and plotted to map sheets. In 2016, the map sheets were scanned, registered, and the contours were digitized. The point data released here were extracted from the digitized contour lines and include: latitude, longitude, and magnetic-field value (gamma).</abstract>
   <purpose>Aeromagnetic surveys are used for geophysical prospecting. Some variations in magnetic measurements are caused by rocks that contain significant amounts of magnetic minerals (magnetite being the most common). These anomalies reflect variations in the amount and type of magnetic material and the shape and depth of the body of rock. The features and patterns of aeromagnetic anomalies can also be used to delineate details of subsurface geology including the locations of buried faults and the thickness of surficial sedimentary rocks.</purpose>
   <supplinf>The aeromagnetic contour maps are available from the University of Wyoming, American Heritage Center, Anaconda Collection (http://www.uwyo.edu/ahc/collections/anaconda/).</supplinf>
  </descript>
  <timeperd>
   <timeinfo>
    <sngdate>
     <caldate>19810101</caldate>
    </sngdate>
   </timeinfo>
   <current>ground condition</current>
  </timeperd>
  <status>
   <progress>Complete</progress>
   <update>None planned</update>
  </status>
  <spdom>
   <bounding>
    <westbc>-109.002552105</westbc>
    <eastbc>-108.33873906</eastbc>
    <northbc>48.0280572626</northbc>
    <southbc>47.6885183876</southbc>
   </bounding>
  </spdom>
  <keywords>
   <theme>
    <themekt>none</themekt>
    <themekey>geophysical surveys</themekey>
    <themekey>aeromagnetic data</themekey>
    <themekey>airborne surveys</themekey>
    <themekey>magnetic surveys</themekey>
    <themekey>residual magnetic field</themekey>
    <themekey>total field</themekey>
    <themekey>magnetic</themekey>
   </theme>
   <theme>
    <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
    <themekey>geophysics</themekey>
    <themekey>geospatial datasets</themekey>
    <themekey>magnetic field (earth)</themekey>
    <themekey>aeromagnetic surveying</themekey>
    <themekey>field monitoring stations</themekey>
	<themekey>GIS</themekey>
   </theme>
   <place>
    <placekt>Geographic Names Information Systems (GNIS)</placekt>
    <placekey>Montana</placekey>
    <placekey>Blaine County</placekey>
    <placekey>Fergus County</placekey>
    <placekey>Phillips County</placekey>
    <placekey>Zortman Quadrangle</placekey>
    <placekey>Lewistown Quadrangle</placekey>
    <placekey>Havre Quadrangle</placekey>
    <placekey>Dodson Quadrangle</placekey>
    <placekey>Little Rocky Mountains</placekey>
   </place>
  </keywords>
  <accconst>None. Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</accconst>
  <useconst>There is no guarantee concerning the accuracy of the data. Any user who modifies the data is obligated to describe the types of modifications they perform. Data have been checked to ensure the accuracy. If any errors are detected, please notify the originating office. The U.S. Geological Survey strongly recommends that careful attention be paid to the metadata file associated with these data. Acknowledgment of the U.S. Geological Survey would be appreciated in products derived from these data. User specifically agrees not to misrepresent the data, nor to imply that changes made were approved or endorsed by the U.S. Geological Survey. Please refer to http://www.usgs.gov/privacy.html for the USGS disclaimer.</useconst>
  <ptcontac>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntorgp>
     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Southwest Region</cntorg>
     <cntper>Eric D. Anderson</cntper>
    </cntorgp>
    <cntpos>Geologist</cntpos>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
     <address>Mail Stop 964, W 6th Ave Kipling St</address>
     <city>Lakewood</city>
     <state>CO</state>
     <postal>80225</postal>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>303-236-5652</cntvoice>
    <cntfax>303-236-1425</cntfax>
    <cntemail>ericanderson@usgs.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
  </ptcontac>
  <datacred>Anaconda Copper Company</datacred>
  <native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft [Unknown] Version 6.2 (Build 9200) ; Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1 (Build 4959) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native>
 </idinfo>
 <dataqual>
  <attracc>
   <attraccr>The data shown on the original map have been processed using various formulas and methods that are not usually documented but that represent industry standard practices for airborne data reduction.  For example, position is listed as latitude and longitude, but these values were derived from the raw navigation data depending on the system used. (see notes under horizontal accuracy). Line numbers were added to records, and unusable data at flight-line ends were discarded (as aircraft slowed and turned around). Separate recordings were correlated by time and assigned to the correct location. 
   Flight line position position was recovered from 35mm film following each flight, and these picks were checked at Geometrics following preliminary plotouts. Magnetic and radar altimeter profile plots appeared to be of high quality and low noise. The barometric altimeter, though generally correct, occasionally suffered from some harmonic noise problems.
   The exact accuracies of these processing steps may not be known. They are discussed in the sections on attribute or positional accuracies.</attraccr>
  </attracc>
  <logic>The data on the original map were collected by a single contractor or group who were responsible for collecting and processing the data. The data from this survey were collected using the same instruments (magnetometers, altimeters, navigational systems) throughout the survey and were collected in a normal length of time with no long delays between survey beginning and end. Survey layout specified the conditions and specifications under which these data were collected. Standard industry practices of the time were followed in data collection and processing.</logic>
  <complete>This dataset contains the point data extracted from the digitized contours from the original maps in Blaine, Phillips, and Fergus counties, Montana.</complete>
  <posacc>
   <horizpa>
    <horizpar>Flight Path Recovery: Horizontal position of the survey aircraft used to collect data were determined by reconciling down-looking photographs (recorded on continuous-strip film) with topographic maps and orthophotoquadrangle maps.  Fiducial numbers and marks, impressed on any paper strips that were recording data or added to magnetic tape records, were included as a function of time to further reconcile location with instrumentation.
	The horizontal accuracy of these data are a combination of the flight path recovery, registration accuracy, and digitization accuracy. The quantitative accuracy was not determined.</horizpar>
   </horizpa>
   <vertacc>
    <vertaccr>The aircraft vertical position was determined using the navigational positioning equipment on the aircraft, which were radar altimeter and barometric altimeter.
	The vertical accuracy of these data are a combination of the flight path recovery, registration accuracy, and digitization accuracy. The quantitative accuracy was not determined.</vertaccr>
   </vertacc>
  </posacc>
  <lineage>
   <srcinfo>
    <srccite>
     <citeinfo>
      <origin>EG and G Geometrics</origin>
      <pubdate>19810101</pubdate>
      <title>Missouri Breaks Project, Montana</title>
      <geoform>Paper Map</geoform>
      <pubinfo>
       <pubplace>University of Wyoming, American Heritage Center, Anaconda Collection</pubplace>
       <publish>Anaconda Copper Company</publish>
      </pubinfo>
     </citeinfo>
    </srccite>
    <srcscale>24,000</srcscale>
    <typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
    <srctime>
     <timeinfo>
      <sngdate>
       <caldate>19810101</caldate>
      </sngdate>
     </timeinfo>
     <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
    </srctime>
    <srccitea>Aeromagnetic contour map</srccitea>
    <srccontr>The contour map provides values for the magnetic field variation.</srccontr>
   </srcinfo>
   <procstep>
    <procdesc>In 1981, the aeromagnetic data were collected using a Geometrics G-813 proton magnetomter attached to a Piper Navajo aircraft. The total magnetic intensity data were leveled using five tie lines and the earth's regional field (IGRF) was removed prior to plotting at a horizontal scale of 1:24,000. Subsequent to leveling and removal of IGRF, the magnetic data along flight lines were extrapolated to a grid and machine plotted at a scale of 1:24,000. Herringbone patterns were observed and attributed to varying terrain clearance, shallow basement, and outcropping intrusives. No other substantial errors were found by Geometrics. A plot of radar altimeter confirmed terrain clearance variation. Minor improvements to the contour maps were made by manually adjusting tie line intersections (leveling) and the intended contour two gamma contour interval was changed to four gammas for contour map presentation.
	In 2016, the original contour map sheets were scanned using large format scanner. Electronic images of the maps were registered to geographic coordinates using GIS software. The contour lines representing magnetic anomaly values were then digitized and attributed with the corresponding magnetic value. The vector lines were subsequently converted to points at 30 meter intervals along the lines. Finally, an ASCII file containing Longtitude, Latitude, and magnetic value for each point was generated.</procdesc>
    <procdate>20160201</procdate>
   </procstep>
  </lineage>
 </dataqual>
 <spdoinfo>
  <direct>Point</direct>
  <ptvctinf>
   <sdtsterm>
    <sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
    <ptvctcnt>294025</ptvctcnt>
   </sdtsterm>
  </ptvctinf>
 </spdoinfo>
 <spref>
  <horizsys>
   <geograph>
    <latres>0.0197132429</latres>
    <longres>0.0292004005</longres>
    <geogunit>Decimal seconds</geogunit>
   </geograph>
   <geodetic>
    <horizdn>D_WGS_1984</horizdn>
    <ellips>WGS_1984</ellips>
    <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
    <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
   </geodetic>
  </horizsys>
 </spref>
 <eainfo>
  <detailed Name="MO_Breaks_Mag">
   <enttyp>
    <enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl>
    <enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd>
    <enttypds>U.S. Geological Survey</enttypds>
   </enttyp>
   <attr>
    <attrlabl>X</attrlabl>
    <attrdef>Longitude</attrdef>
    <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
    <attrdomv>
     <rdom>
      <rdommin>-109.002552</rdommin>
      <rdommax>-108.338739</rdommax>
      <attrunit>Decimal degree</attrunit>
     </rdom>
    </attrdomv>
   </attr>
   <attr>
    <attrlabl>Y</attrlabl>
    <attrdef>Latitude</attrdef>
    <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
    <attrdomv>
     <rdom>
      <rdommin>47.688518</rdommin>
      <rdommax>48.028057</rdommax>
      <attrunit>Decimal degree</attrunit>
     </rdom>
    </attrdomv>
   </attr>
   <attr>
    <attrlabl>Mag</attrlabl>
    <attrdef>Magnetic value represented on map. This is the total field value with an arbitrary datum removed.</attrdef>
    <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
    <attrdomv>
     <rdom>
      <rdommin>-392</rdommin>
      <rdommax>52</rdommax>
      <attrunit>Gamma</attrunit>
     </rdom>
    </attrdomv>
   </attr>
  </detailed>
  <overview>
   <eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes the tabular data associated with the data set. Please review the detailed descriptions that are provided (the individual attribute descriptions) for information on the values that appear as fields/table entries of the data set.</eaover>
   <eadetcit>The entity and attribute information were generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Please review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit>
  </overview>
 </eainfo>
 <distinfo>
  <distrib>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntorgp>
     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey – ScienceBase</cntorg>
    </cntorgp>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
     <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302, Denver, CO 80225</address>
     <city>Lakewood</city>
     <state>CO</state>
     <postal>80225</postal>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
    <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
  </distrib>
  <distliab>These data have been approved for release and publication by the Director of the USGS. Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the U.S. Geological Survey regarding the utility of the data on any other system, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. No responsibility is assumed by the U.S. Geological Survey in the use of these data.</distliab>
  <stdorder>
   <digform>
    <digtinfo>
     <formname>Vector Digital Data Set (Point)</formname>
    </digtinfo>
    <digtopt>
     <onlinopt>
      <computer>
       <networka>
        <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7TH8JTN</networkr>
       </networka>
      </computer>
     </onlinopt>
    </digtopt>
   </digform>
   <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
  </stdorder>
 </distinfo>
 <metainfo>
  <metd>20160524</metd>
  <metc>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntperp>
     <cntper>Eric D. Anderson</cntper>
     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Southwest Region</cntorg>
    </cntperp>
    <cntpos>Geologist</cntpos>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
     <address>Mail Stop 964, W 6th Ave Kipling St</address>
     <city>Lakewood</city>
     <state>CO</state>
     <postal>80225</postal>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>303-236-5652</cntvoice>
    <cntfax>303-236-1425</cntfax>
    <cntemail>ericanderson@usgs.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
  </metc>
  <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
  <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
 </metainfo>
</metadata>
