<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>USGS,  Western Ecological Research Center</origin><pubdate>20150901</pubdate><title>Modifed Great Basin Extent (Buffered)</title><geoform>Vector Digital Data Set (Polygon)</geoform><onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7K35RRS</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>Two different great basin perimeter files were intersected and dissolved using ArcGIS 10.2.2 to create the outer perimeter of the great basin for use modeling long-term wildfire effects on sage-grouse population growth, and development of sage-grouse concentration areas based on modeled habitat quality, lek density, and population abundance (Coates et al. 2015). These two perimeter files included a 1:1,000,000 map of hydrographic areas in the Great Basin) (Buto 2009), and vegetation characteristics (Karl et al. 2001). The resulting Modified Great Basin Extent represented a combination of hydrographic and floristic features best suited for the defining the spatial extent of the analyses. To ensure moving window analyses of habitat and fire areas covered the entire extent, the extent was then buffered by 15.8 km. The extent also encompasses large parts of sage-grouse management zones III (Southern Great Basin), IV (Snake River Plain), and V (Northern Great Basin). A small portion (&lt; 5%) of management zone II (Wyoming Basins) is also encompassed.
REFERENCES
Buto, S.G., 2009, Digital Representation of 1:1,000,000-scale Hydrographic Areas of the Great Basin: U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 457, 5 p .http://pubs.usgs.gov/ds/457
Coates, P.S., Ricca, M.A., Prochazka, B.G., Doherty, K. D., Brooks, M.L., Casazza, M.L. 2015. Long-term effects of wildfire on greater sage-grouse - integrating population and ecosystem concepts for management in Great Basin. http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr20151165
Karl, M., Durtsche, B.M., Morgan, K. 2001. Great Basin Restoration Initiative Area. http://sagemap.wr.usgs.gov/SearchData.aspx</abstract><purpose>To create a layer of modified delineation of the outer perimeter of the Great Basin for use in analyses of long-term wildfire effects on sage-grouse population growth. This defined the extent of sage-grouse concentration areas based on modeled habitat quality, lek density, and population abundance (Coates et al. 2015).</purpose><supplinf>Coates, P.S., Ricca, M.A., Prochazka, B.G., Doherty, K. D.,, Brooks, M.L., Casazza, M.L. 2015. Long-term effects of wildfire on greater sage-grouse - integrating population and ecosystem concepts for management in Great Basin.  http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr20151165</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>19840101</begdate><enddate>20141201</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><current>See Supplemental Info</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-122.574408201</westbc><eastbc>-110.232476221</eastbc><northbc>45.356651206</northbc><southbc>34.865628483</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>Greater Sage-Grouse</themekey><themekey>Wildfire</themekey><themekey>Cheatgrass</themekey><themekey>Planning Tool</themekey><themekey>Boundary</themekey></theme><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt><themekey>biota</themekey><themekey>boundaries</themekey><themekey>environment</themekey></theme><place><placekt>None</placekt><placekey>United States</placekey><placekey>North America</placekey><placekey>Great Basin</placekey><placekey>Nevada</placekey><placekey>California</placekey><placekey>Utah</placekey><placekey>Oregon</placekey><placekey>Idaho</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>The authors of these data require that users direct any questions pertaining to appropriate use or assistance with understanding limitations and interpretation of the data to the individuals/organization listed in the Point of Contact section.</useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, PACIFIC REGION</cntorg><cntper>Peter S Coates</cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>Research Wildlife Biologist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>800 Business Park Drive</address><city>Dixon</city><state>CA</state><postal>95620</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>530-669-5073</cntvoice><cntfax>707-678-5039</cntfax><cntemail>pcoates@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac><datacred>U.S. Geological Survey, Western Ecological Research Center, Dixon Field Station, Dixon, CA.</datacred><native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.2.2 (Build 3552) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted.</attraccr></attracc><logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic><complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>Development of the data set by the agency / individuals identified in the 'Originator' element in the Identification Info section of the record.</procdesc><procdate>Unknown</procdate></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><direct>Vector</direct><ptvctinf><sdtsterm><sdtstype>G-polygon</sdtstype><ptvctcnt>1</ptvctcnt></sdtsterm></ptvctinf></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><planar><mapproj><mapprojn>Albers meters cm114 NAD83 (ESRI Full Name: Albers_meters_cm114_NAD83)</mapprojn><albers><stdparll>29.5</stdparll><stdparll>45.5</stdparll><longcm>-114.0</longcm><latprjo>23.0</latprjo><feast>0.0</feast><fnorth>0.0</fnorth></albers></mapproj><planci><plance>coordinate pair</plance><coordrep><absres>0.6096</absres><ordres>0.6096</ordres></coordrep><plandu>Meter</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>D_North_American_1983</horizdn><ellips>GRS_1980</ellips><semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis><denflat>298.257222101</denflat></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl><enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd><enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>BUFF_DIST</attrlabl><attrdef>Buffer distance</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>15840</rdommin><rdommax>15840</rdommax><attrunit>meters</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>SHAPE_Leng</attrlabl><attrdef>Unknown</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>4527905.82736</rdommin><rdommax>4527905.82736</rdommax></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>SHAPE_Area</attrlabl><attrdef>Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef><attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>727512199476</rdommin><rdommax>727512199476</rdommax></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>AreaKm</attrlabl><attrdef>area of extent in square kilometers</attrdef><attrdefs>N/A</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>727512.199476</rdommin><rdommax>727512.199476</rdommax><attrunit>square km</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr></detailed><overview><eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes the tabular data associated with the data set. Please review the detailed descriptions that are provided (the individual attribute descriptions) for information on the values that appear as fields/table entries of the data set.</eaover><eadetcit>The entity and attribute information was generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Please review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><distrib><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg></cntorgp><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>Denver Federal Center</address><address>Building 810</address><address>Mail Stop 302</address><city>Denver</city><state>CO</state><postal>80225</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice><cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib><distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Vector Digital Data Set (Polygon)</formname></digtinfo><digtopt><onlinopt><computer><networka><networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7K35RRS</networkr></networka></computer></onlinopt></digtopt></digform><fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees></stdorder></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20160127</metd><metc><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, PACIFIC REGION</cntorg><cntper>Mark Ricca</cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>Wildlife Biologist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>800 Business Park Drive</address><city>Dixon</city><state>CA</state><postal>95620</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>530-669-5089</cntvoice><cntfax>707-678-5039</cntfax><cntemail>mark_ricca@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></metc><metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv><mettc>local time</mettc></metainfo></metadata>