<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Michael Adams</origin>
        <origin>Christopher Pearl</origin>
        <origin>Brome McCreary</origin>
        <origin>Stephanie Galvan</origin>
        <origin>Jennifer Rowe</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Oregon Spotted Frog (Rana pretiosa) Monitoring in the Oregon Cascades 2012-2015</title>
        <geoform>Microsoft Access Database exported as separate comma-delimited files</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7JM27PD</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This dataset contains information from visual encounter surveys conducted between 2012 and 2015 by USGS as part of an ongoing Oregon spotted frog (Rana pretiosa) monitoring effort in the Oregon Cascade Mountain Range. We surveyed 91 sites using a rotating frame design in the Klamath and Deschutes Basins, Oregon, which encompass most of the species' core extant range. Data consist of spotted frog counts aggregated by date, location, and life stage, as well as data on environmental conditions at the time of each survey.</abstract>
      <purpose>USGS FRESC (Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center, Corvallis, Oregon) conducted research activities as part of an ongoing effort to study the population status and recovery of the Oregon spotted frog (Rana pretiosa) in the Oregon Cascades. Data were collected between 2012 and 2015 to assess trends in site occupancy and the influence of environmental factors on demographic parameters. The results of this study will contribute to our understanding of the biology of this sensitive species and have implications for improved management efforts.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20120611</begdate>
          <enddate>present</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>In progress</progress>
      <update>Annually</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>East Slope Cascade Mountain Range, Central Oregon, USA; Deschutes Basin; Klamath Basin; Deschutes, Klamath, Linn, Lane, and Wasco Counties</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-122.4516</westbc>
        <eastbc>-121.4633</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.1393</northbc>
        <southbc>42.1051</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Population dynamics</themekey>
        <themekey>Native species</themekey>
        <themekey>Aquatic ecology</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>Cascade Range</placekey>
        <placekey>Deschutes County</placekey>
        <placekey>Lane County</placekey>
        <placekey>Linn County</placekey>
        <placekey>Klamath County</placekey>
        <placekey>Wasco County</placekey>
        <placekey>Oregon</placekey>
        <placekey>OR</placekey>
        <placekey>Pacific Northwest</placekey>
      </place>
      <stratum>
        <stratkt>Oregon GEO Stratum Keywords</stratkt>
        <stratkey>Land surface</stratkey>
        <stratkey>Aquatic</stratkey>
        <stratkey>Riparian</stratkey>
      </stratum>
      <temporal>
        <tempkt>Oregon GEO Temporal Keywords</tempkt>
        <tempkey>Modern</tempkey>
        <tempkey>Day</tempkey>
        <tempkey>Summer</tempkey>
      </temporal>
    </keywords>
    <taxonomy>
      <keywtax>
        <taxonkt>USGS Biocomplexity Thesaurus</taxonkt>
        <taxonkey>Amphibians</taxonkey>
      </keywtax>
      <taxonsys>
        <classsys>
          <classcit>
            <citeinfo>
              <origin>Crother, Brian I., Jeff Boundy, Jonathan A. Campbell, Kevin De Queiroz, Darrel R. Frost, Richard Highton, John B. Iverson, Peter A. Meylan, Tod W. Reeder, Michael E. Seidel, Jack W. Sites Jr., Travis W. Taggart, Stephen G.Tilley, and David B.Wake</origin>
              <pubdate>2001</pubdate>
              <title>Scientific and standard English names of amphibians and reptiles of North America north of Mexico, with comments regarding confidence in our understanding</title>
              <geoform>Microsoft Access Database exported as separate comma-delimited files</geoform>
              <pubinfo>
                <pubplace>Lawrence, Kansas</pubplace>
                <publish>Society for the Study of Amphibians and Reptiles</publish>
              </pubinfo>
            </citeinfo>
          </classcit>
        </classsys>
        <idref>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Jones, Lawrence L.C., William P. Leonard, and Deanna H. Olson, editors.</origin>
            <pubdate>2005</pubdate>
            <title>Amphibians of the Pacific Northwest</title>
            <geoform>Microsoft Access Database exported as separate comma-delimited files</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Seattle, WA</pubplace>
              <publish>Seattle Audubon Society</publish>
            </pubinfo>
          </citeinfo>
        </idref>
        <ider>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>Brome McCreary</cntper>
              <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
              <address>3200 SW Jefferson Way</address>
              <city>Corvallis</city>
              <state>OR</state>
              <postal>97330</postal>
              <country>United States</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(541) 750-1012</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>brome_mccreary@usgs.gov</cntemail>
          </cntinfo>
        </ider>
        <taxonpro>expert advice;;identification keys</taxonpro>
        <taxoncom>After being trained on proper species identification in the field, crew members used a variety of resources to ensure species identifications were robust. If an animal could not be positively identified during a survey, it was captured with a dip-net and examined closely. If any uncertainty remained, the observer referred to a field guide and/or took photos of the animal to be reviewed by an expert. Oregon spotted frogs are easily distinguishable from most other amphibian species in our study area. Thus, we are confident in the accuracy of our identifications.</taxoncom>
      </taxonsys>
      <taxongen>All amphibians were identified to the level of species in the data.</taxongen>
      <taxoncl>
        <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
        <taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
        <taxoncl>
          <taxonrn>Subkingdom</taxonrn>
          <taxonrv>Bilateria</taxonrv>
          <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Infrakingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Deuterostomia</taxonrv>
            <taxoncl>
              <taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
              <taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
              <taxoncl>
                <taxonrn>Subphylum</taxonrn>
                <taxonrv>Vertebrata</taxonrv>
                <taxoncl>
                  <taxonrn>Infraphylum</taxonrn>
                  <taxonrv>Gnathostomata</taxonrv>
                  <taxoncl>
                    <taxonrn>Superclass</taxonrn>
                    <taxonrv>Tetrapoda</taxonrv>
                    <taxoncl>
                      <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
                      <taxonrv>Amphibia</taxonrv>
                      <taxoncl>
                        <taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
                        <taxonrv>Anura</taxonrv>
                        <taxoncl>
                          <taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
                          <taxonrv>Ranidae</taxonrv>
                          <taxoncl>
                            <taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
                            <taxonrv>Rana</taxonrv>
                            <taxoncl>
                              <taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
                              <taxonrv>Rana pretiosa</taxonrv>
                              <common>Oregon Spotted Frog</common>
                            </taxoncl>
                          </taxoncl>
                        </taxoncl>
                      </taxoncl>
                    </taxoncl>
                  </taxoncl>
                </taxoncl>
              </taxoncl>
            </taxoncl>
          </taxoncl>
        </taxoncl>
      </taxoncl>
    </taxonomy>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>FRESC Communications and Information Management</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>777 NW 9th St, Suite 400</address>
          <city>Corvallis</city>
          <state>OR</state>
          <postal>97330</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(541) 750-1030</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>This study was made possible in part by funding from the Interagency Special Status/Sensitive Species Program (ISSSSP). The ISSSP is a cooperative program of the Pacific Northwest Regional Office of the U.S. Forest Service and Oregon/Washington State Office of the Bureau of Land Management. Additional funding was provided by the U.S. Geological Survey's Amphibian Research and Monitoring Initiative (ARMI). The U.S. Forest Service, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, U.S. Bureau of Land Management, and landowners contributed site information. U.S. Geological Survey seasonal technicians performed surveys.</datacred>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Field data were collected on paper and reviewed (QA/QC) in the field for accuracy and completeness by one member of the crew (not the data recorder) at the end of each survey. Those data were entered into a Microsoft Access database and reviewed by a different individual to confirm that the data had been entered correctly. Once all data were entered and checked for completeness and accuracy, a random 10% subsample of that year’s surveys were once again screened for errors.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Data were checked for logical consistency by writing grouping queries to examine the proper spelling and standardization of all text fields. Range queries were written to confirm that numerical values were not outside a reasonable range for a particular field. We performed outlier checks by plotting numerical values bounded within a range (e.g., elevation, temperature, frog snout-urostyle length, frog mass). Bounding dates were confirmed as correct. Site coordinates were reviewed with Maptech, ArcMap, or other mapping software.</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>GPS data were downloaded from the device at the end of the field week. Spatial data were projected on an ArcMap layer to ensure positional accuracy.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>Field</methtype>
        <methdesc>A survey consisted of two technicians searching all portions of a site with water less than 1 m deep for Oregon spotted frogs. Crews recorded air temperature at start, midway, and conclusion of surveys. Technicians searched by slowly walking the perimeter of the site, visually searching for amphibians of any stage, and completing a minimum of five dip-net sweeps at least 10 m apart in microhabitats that could conceal amphibians. Surveys were conducted between 08:00 and 20:00 hours from late May/early June to mid-August from 2012 through 2015. Habitat variables were recorded during each survey.</methdesc>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data from datasheets were entered into respective project databases.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20150706-20150725</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data were checked for omissions and logical consistency following QA/QC protocol.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20151015</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Frog counts were aggregated by survey date, location, and life stage using script in R statistical analysis software. Data were exported as a comma separated file and formatted into final Observations spreadsheet.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160309</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Point</direct>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>Transverse Mercator</mapprojn>
          <transmer>
            <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
            <longcm>-123.0</longcm>
            <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
            <feast>500000.0</feast>
            <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
          </transmer>
        </mapproj>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>World Geodetic System of 1984 (WGS 1984)</horizdn>
        <ellips>WGS 1984</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Observations</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Spreadsheet contains information on observations (counts) of Oregon spotted frogs at sites within the study area, aggregated by date, location, and life stage.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Database developer</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SiteID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Name of study site</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unbounded list of study sites, based on rotating frame design.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SurveyDate</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Date of observation</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Survey date, in format mm-dd-yyyy</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Count</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Total number of Oregon spotted frogs observed for each life stage on the given date.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unbounded count or number observed</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>LifeStage</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Life stage observed; larva, metamorph, juvenile, subadult, or adult</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>larva</edomv>
            <edomvd>Visible gills and 0-3 extruded legs (salamanders) or tail present, and 0-3 extruded legs (anurans)</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>metamorph</edomv>
            <edomvd>All four legs extruded, still has tail</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>juvenile</edomv>
            <edomvd>Animal has taken adult form (possibly still has tail stump), but is small and not sexually mature</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>subadult</edomv>
            <edomvd>Animal is older than one year, but is not sexually mature</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>adult</edomv>
            <edomvd>Animal has fully taken adult form and is sexually mature. Typically greater than 40 mm snout-urostyle length.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Township</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Township location for the observation, according to the Public Land Survey System (PLSS)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Public Land Survey System (PLSS)</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>05S</rdommin>
            <rdommax>40S</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Range</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Range location for the observation, according to the Public Land Survey System (PLSS)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Public Land Survey System (PLSS)</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>03E</rdommin>
            <rdommax>11E</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Section</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Section location for the observation, according to the Public Land Survey System (PLSS)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Public Land Survey System (PLSS)</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>1</rdommin>
            <rdommax>36</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Surveys</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Spreadsheet containing data on date and time of surveys, observers, environmental conditions, and notes for each survey.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Database developer</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SiteID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Name of study site</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unbounded list of unique site names</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SurveyDate</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Date on which survey occurred</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Survey date, in format mm-dd-yyyy</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>#Observers</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Number of observers participating in the survey</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unbounded number of observers conducting survey</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Dry</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Indicates whether or not the site was dry</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>no</edomv>
            <edomvd>Site was not dry</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>yes</edomv>
            <edomvd>Site was dry</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>StartTime</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Survey start time</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Time format; hh:mm:ss (24-hour clock)</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>EndTime</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Survey end time</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Time format; hh:mm:ss (24-hour clock)</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Weather</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Weather conditions at the beginning of the survey</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>clear or few clouds</edomv>
            <edomvd>0-50% cloud cover (without precipitation) during survey</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>mostly cloudy or overcast</edomv>
            <edomvd>51-100% cloud cover (without precipitation) during survey</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>showers or light rain</edomv>
            <edomvd>Intermittent or light precipitation that disturbs less than 50% of the water surface</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>heavy rain</edomv>
            <edomvd>Precipitation that disturbs more than 50% of the water surface</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Wind</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Wind conditions at the beginning of the survey</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>calm</edomv>
            <edomvd>No obvious wind activity; water surface is calm, herbaceous vegetation (grasses and sedges) and tree leaves remain still.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>light breeze</edomv>
            <edomvd>Windy conditions that create weak or no water disturbances; herbaceous vegetation(grasses and sedges) moves but tree leaves do not.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>strong breeze</edomv>
            <edomvd>Windy conditions that create strong water disturbances (e.g., ripples); herbaceous vegetation(grasses and sedges) and tree leaves move.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>gusts</edomv>
            <edomvd>Intermittent, strong winds that substantially disturbs water surface (e.g., raised peaks), herbaceous vegetation (grasses and sedges), and tree leaves.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>StartAirTemp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Air temperature, in Celsius, at the beginning of the survey.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>7</rdommin>
            <rdommax>35</rdommax>
            <attrunit>Degrees Celsius</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>StartWaterTemp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Water temperature, in Celsius, at the beginning of the survey. Blank records indicate null values (no data).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>5</rdommin>
            <rdommax>34</rdommax>
            <attrunit>Degrees Celsius</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>MidAirTemp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Air temperature, in Celsius, taken at the mid-point of the survey. Blank records indicate null values (no data).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>8</rdommin>
            <rdommax>36</rdommax>
            <attrunit>Degrees Celsius</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>MidWaterTemp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Water temperature, in Celsius, taken at the mid-point of the survey. Blank records indicate null values (no data).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>8</rdommin>
            <rdommax>38</rdommax>
            <attrunit>Degrees Celsius</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>EndAirTemp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Air temperature, in Celsius, at the end of the survey. Blank records indicate null values (no data).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>7</rdommin>
            <rdommax>36</rdommax>
            <attrunit>Degrees Celsius</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>EndWaterTemp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Water temperature, in Celsius, at the end of the survey. Blank records indicate null values (no data).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>8</rdommin>
            <rdommax>35</rdommax>
            <attrunit>Degrees Celsius</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SurfaceDisturbed</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Indicates whether or not rain or wind disturbed the surface of the water more than 25% of the survey time</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>yes</edomv>
            <edomvd>Rain or wind disturbed the surface of the water more than 25% of the survey time</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>no</edomv>
            <edomvd>Rain or wind did not disturb the surface of the water more than 25% of the survey time</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Forest</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Percent of shoreline with trees (&gt;5 m tall) within 30 meters of high water</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer define</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>Percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>BeaverEvidence</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Indicates what kind of beaver evidence, if any, was detected at the survey site</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>evidence of recent beaver activity</edomv>
            <edomvd>Recent or active evidence that beaver occupy survey site, such as fresh chews or girdling, active runs or dams, or actual beaver sighting</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>evidence of old beaver activity</edomv>
            <edomvd>Evidence that beaver occupied the survey site at one time, such as old chews or girdling and old runs or dams</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>no evidence of beaver</edomv>
            <edomvd>No evidence of beaver was detected at the site</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Database developer</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>BeaverDam</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Indicates what kind of beaver dam, if any, was detected at the survey site</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>no dam</edomv>
            <edomvd>No dam was detected</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>active dam</edomv>
            <edomvd>Active dam was detected</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>inactive dam</edomv>
            <edomvd>Inactive dam was detected</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SurveyNotes</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Any notes associated with this particular survey that provide additional information not captured in other fields. Blank records indicate that surveyors had no additional information to report.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unbounded list of text</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Frame</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Sampling frame to which each site was assigned</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>A</edomv>
            <edomvd>Site is in Frame A</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>B</edomv>
            <edomvd>Site is in Frame B</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>C</edomv>
            <edomvd>Site is in Frame C</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>D</edomv>
            <edomvd>Site is in Frame D</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>E</edomv>
            <edomvd>Site is in Frame E</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper></cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a U.S. Geological Survey server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160310</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Metadata Coordinator</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos></cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>777 NW 9th St, Suite 400</address>
          <city>Corvallis</city>
          <state>OR</state>
          <postal>97330</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(541) 750-1030</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>