<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Michael Adams</origin>
        <origin>Christopher Pearl</origin>
        <origin>Brome McCreary</origin>
        <origin>Stephanie Galvan</origin>
        <origin>Jennifer Rowe</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Oregon Spotted Frog (Rana pretiosa) Monitoring at Jack Creek 2015</title>
        <geoform>Microsoft Access Database exported as separate comma-delimited files</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7DV1GZP</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This dataset contains information from mark-recapture surveys conducted in 2015 by USGS as part of an ongoing Oregon spotted frog (Rana pretiosa) monitoring effort at Jack Creek, Klamath County, Oregon. Data consist of spotted frog counts aggregated by date, location, life stage, and sex, as well data on environmental conditions at the time each survey.</abstract>
      <purpose>This site is part of ongoing studies of Oregon spotted frog habitat use and population dynamics throughout its Pacific Northwest range. The results of this study will contribute to our understanding of the biology of this sensitive species and have implications for improved management efforts.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20150326</begdate>
          <enddate>20150903</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>In progress</progress>
      <update>Annually</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Jack Creek, Williamson River watershed in Klamath County, Oregon</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-121.66259765498</westbc>
        <eastbc>-121.43737792843</eastbc>
        <northbc>43.266887720666</northbc>
        <southbc>43.058534922082</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Population dynamics</themekey>
        <themekey>Native species</themekey>
        <themekey>Aquatic ecology</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>Jack Creek</placekey>
        <placekey>Klamath County</placekey>
        <placekey>Oregon</placekey>
      </place>
      <stratum>
        <stratkt>Oregon GEO Stratum Keywords</stratkt>
        <stratkey>Riparian</stratkey>
        <stratkey>Aquatic</stratkey>
        <stratkey>Land surface</stratkey>
      </stratum>
      <temporal>
        <tempkt>Oregon GEO Temporal Keywords</tempkt>
        <tempkey>Modern</tempkey>
        <tempkey>Day</tempkey>
        <tempkey>Spring</tempkey>
        <tempkey>Summer</tempkey>
        <tempkey>Fall</tempkey>
      </temporal>
    </keywords>
    <taxonomy>
      <keywtax>
        <taxonkt>USGS Biocomplexity Thesaurus</taxonkt>
        <taxonkey>Amphibians</taxonkey>
      </keywtax>
      <taxonsys>
        <classsys>
          <classcit>
            <citeinfo>
              <origin>Crother, Brian I., Jeff Boundy, Jonathan A. Campbell, Kevin De Queiroz, Darrel R. Frost, Richard Highton, John B. Iverson, Peter A. Meylan, Tod W. Reeder, Michael E. Seidel, Jack W. Sites Jr., Travis W. Taggart, Stephen G.Tilley, and David B.Wake</origin>
              <pubdate>2001</pubdate>
              <title>Scientific and standard English names of amphibians and reptiles of North America north of Mexico, with comments regarding confidence in our understanding</title>
              <geoform>Microsoft Access Database exported as separate comma-delimited files</geoform>
              <pubinfo>
                <pubplace>Lawrence, Kansas</pubplace>
                <publish>Society for the Study of Amphibians and Reptiles</publish>
              </pubinfo>
            </citeinfo>
          </classcit>
        </classsys>
        <idref>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Jones, Lawrence L.C., William P. LEonard, and Deanna H. Olson, editors.</origin>
            <pubdate>2005</pubdate>
            <title>Amphibians of the Pacific Northwest</title>
            <geoform>Microsoft Access Database exported as separate comma-delimited files</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Seattle, WA</pubplace>
              <publish>Seattle Audubon Society</publish>
            </pubinfo>
          </citeinfo>
        </idref>
        <ider>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>Brome McCreary</cntper>
              <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
              <address>3200 SW Jefferson Way</address>
              <city>Corvallis</city>
              <state>OR</state>
              <postal>97331</postal>
              <country>United States</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(541) 750-1012</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>brome_mccreary@usgs.gov</cntemail>
          </cntinfo>
        </ider>
        <taxonpro>expert advice;;identification keys</taxonpro>
        <taxoncom>After being trained on proper species identification in the field, crew members used a variety of resources to ensure species identifications were robust. If an animal could not be positively identified during a survey, it was captured with a dip-net and examined closely. If any uncertainty remained, the observer referred to a field guide and/or took photos of the animal to be reviewed by an expert. Oregon spotted frogs are easily distinguishable from most other amphibian species in our study area. Thus, we are confident in the accuracy of our identifications.</taxoncom>
      </taxonsys>
      <taxongen>All amphibians were identified to the level of species in the data</taxongen>
      <taxoncl>
        <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
        <taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
        <taxoncl>
          <taxonrn>Subkingdom</taxonrn>
          <taxonrv>Bilateria</taxonrv>
          <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Infrakingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Deuterostomia</taxonrv>
            <taxoncl>
              <taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
              <taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
              <taxoncl>
                <taxonrn>Subphylum</taxonrn>
                <taxonrv>Vertebrata</taxonrv>
                <taxoncl>
                  <taxonrn>Infraphylum</taxonrn>
                  <taxonrv>Gnathostomata</taxonrv>
                  <taxoncl>
                    <taxonrn>Superclass</taxonrn>
                    <taxonrv>Tetrapoda</taxonrv>
                    <taxoncl>
                      <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
                      <taxonrv>Amphibia</taxonrv>
                      <taxoncl>
                        <taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
                        <taxonrv>Anura</taxonrv>
                        <taxoncl>
                          <taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
                          <taxonrv>Ranidae</taxonrv>
                          <taxoncl>
                            <taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
                            <taxonrv>Rana</taxonrv>
                            <taxoncl>
                              <taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
                              <taxonrv>Rana pretiosa</taxonrv>
                              <common>Oregon Spotted Frog</common>
                            </taxoncl>
                          </taxoncl>
                        </taxoncl>
                      </taxoncl>
                    </taxoncl>
                  </taxoncl>
                </taxoncl>
              </taxoncl>
            </taxoncl>
          </taxoncl>
        </taxoncl>
      </taxoncl>
    </taxonomy>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>FRESC Communications and Information Management</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>777 NW 9th St, Suite 400</address>
          <city>Corvallis</city>
          <state>OR</state>
          <postal>97330</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(541) 750-1030</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>U.S. Forest Service, U.S. Geological Survey seasonal technicians, landowners</datacred>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Field data were collected on paper and reviewed (QA/QC) in the field for accuracy and completeness by one member of the crew (not the data recorder) at the end of each survey. Those data were entered into a Microsoft Access database and reviewed by a different individual to confirm that the data had been entered correctly. Once all data were entered and checked for completeness and accuracy, a random 10% subsample of that year’s surveys were once again screened for errors.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Data were checked for logical consistency by writing grouping queries to examine the proper spelling and standardization of all text fields. Range queries were written to confirm that numerical values were not outside a reasonable range for a particular field. We performed outlier checks by plotting numerical values bounded within a range (e.g., elevation, temperature, frog snout-urostyle length, frog mass). Bounding dates were confirmed as correct. Site coordinates were reviewed with Maptech, ArcMap, or other mapping software.</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>GPS data were downloaded from the device at the end of the field week. Spatial  data were projected on an ArcMap layer to ensure positional accuracy.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>Field</methtype>
        <methdesc>Oregon spotted frog breeding surveys were conducted on March 26, April 8, and April 9 of 2015. During each site visit, surveyors counted Oregon spotted frog egg masses (keeping track of old and new masses) and quantified oviposition site variables. Mark-recapture surveys were completed over three days from Sept 1 to Sept 3, 2015. At each pond/site, crew members worked in pairs or individually to search for Oregon spotted frogs in all suitable microhabitats. Upon entering a site, researchers sanitized hands with 70% alcohol-based sanitizer and allowed it to dry before rinsing hands in site water. Hands were sanitized between the handling of individual frogs. During each site visit, sub-adult and adult frogs (&gt; 40 mm SUL) were caught, scanned for a PIT tag, given a new tag if necessary, and released at the point of capture. Every effort was made to complete the process efficiently with minimal disturbance to the frog. A sterilized PIT tag was inserted into the dorsum of a suitably-sized frog only after researchers confirmed (by scanning with a tag reader and visual inspection) that the frog did not have an existing tag. Once inserted, the PIT tag was manipulated into proper position under the skin just above the urostyle. If it was necessary to hold animals in queue for processing, each individual was placed in a separate zip-closure plastic bag filled with site water and vegetation. Animals were held in shaded areas and for no longer than 15 minutes. When a frog was captured, it was processed efficiently and released as to reduce disturbance to the frog.</methdesc>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data from datasheets were entered into respective project databases.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20150925</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data were checked for omissions and logical consistency following QA/QC protocol.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20151009</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Frog counts were aggregated by survey date, location, life stage, and sex using script in R statistical analysis software. Data were exported as a comma-separated file and formatted into final Observations spreadsheet.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160121</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>Jack Creek, Klamath County, Oregon</indspref>
    <direct>Point</direct>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>Transverse Mercator</mapprojn>
          <transmer>
            <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
            <longcm>-123.0</longcm>
            <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
            <feast>500000.0</feast>
            <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
          </transmer>
        </mapproj>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>World Geodetic System of 1984 (WGS 1984)</horizdn>
        <ellips>WGS 1984</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Observations</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Spreadsheet contains information on observations (counts) of Oregon spotted frogs at sites within the Jack Creek study area, aggregated by date, location, life stage, and sex.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Database developer</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SurveyDate</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Date of observation</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Survey date, in format mm-dd-yyyy</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SiteID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Name of study site</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unbounded list of unique site names</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Count</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Number of Oregon spotted frogs observed. For egg masses, this number is # of egg masses detected on that date that were not detected previously. For all other life stages, it is the total number observed on that date.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unbounded count or number observed</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>LifeStage</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Life stage observed; eggmass, juvenile, subadult, or adult</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>egg mass</edomv>
            <edomvd>Oregon spotted frog discrete cluster of embryos (eggmass)</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>juvenile</edomv>
            <edomvd>Oregon spotted frog juvenile; animal has taken adult form (possibly still has tail stump), but is small and not sexually mature</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>subadult</edomv>
            <edomvd>Oregon spotted frog subadult; animal is older than one year, but is not sexually mature</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>adult</edomv>
            <edomvd>Oregon spotted frog adult; animal has fully taken adult form and is sexually mature. Typically greater than 40 mm snout-urostyle length.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Sex</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Sex of animal (if determined)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>male</edomv>
            <edomvd>Having male morphology</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>female</edomv>
            <edomvd>Having female morphology</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>unknown</edomv>
            <edomvd>Undetermined sex</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Township</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Township location for the observation, according to Public Land Survey System (PLSS)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Public Land Survey System (PLSS)</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>27S</rdommin>
            <rdommax>27S</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Range</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Range location for the observation, according to Public Land Survey System (PLSS)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Public Land Survey System (PLSS)</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>09E</rdommin>
            <rdommax>10E</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Section</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Section location for the observation, according to Public Land Survey System (PLSS)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Public Land Survey System (PLSS)</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>13</rdommin>
            <rdommax>32</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Surveys</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Spreadsheet containing data on date and time of surveys, observers, environmental conditions, and notes for each survey.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Database developer</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SiteID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Name of study site</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unbounded list of unique site names</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SurveyDate</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Date of survey</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Survey date, in format mm-dd-yyyy</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl># Observers</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Number of observers participating in survey</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unbounded number of observers conducting survey</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>StartTime</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Survey start time</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Time format; hh:mm:ss (24-hour clock)</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>EndTime</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Survey end time</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Time format; hh:mm:ss (24-hour clock)</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Weather</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Weather conditions at start of survey</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>clear or slightly cloudy</edomv>
            <edomvd>0-50% cloud cover (without precipitation) during survey</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>clear</edomv>
            <edomvd>Sky completely clear of cloud cover</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>overcast</edomv>
            <edomvd>51-100% cloud cover (without precipitation) during survey</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Wind</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Wind conditions at start of survey</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>calm</edomv>
            <edomvd>Water surface smooth, smoke rises vertically</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Beufort Wind Scale</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>light breeze</edomv>
            <edomvd>Small ripples in water, leaves rustle</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Beufort Wind Scale</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>windy</edomv>
            <edomvd>Large branches move</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Beufort Wind Scale</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>AirTemp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Air temperature at start of survey</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>11</rdommin>
            <rdommax>75</rdommax>
            <attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>AirTempType</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Units of air temperature measurements;  Fahrenheit or Celsius</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>C</edomv>
            <edomvd>Degrees Celsius</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>F</edomv>
            <edomvd>Degrees Fahrenheit</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SurveyNotes</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Notes taken during the survey</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unbounded list of text</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper></cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a U.S. Geological Survey server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160310</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Metadata Coordinator</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos></cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>777 NW 9th St, Suite 400</address>
          <city>Corvallis</city>
          <state>OR</state>
          <postal>97330</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(541) 750-1030</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>