<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Mark W. Carter</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Photographs from the Blue Ridge Parkway in Virginia (Peaks of Otter region)</title>
        <geoform>JPG</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Restion, VA</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7DN434F</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This dataset contains photographs keyed to station points along the Blue Ridge Parkway in Virginia. Photographs are titled and arranged by 7.5-minute quadrangle, and station points are located in the "Detailed geologic mapping geodatabase for the Blue Ridge Parkway in Virginia." The first part of the photograph's filename corresponds to the FieldID attribute of the PhotoPoints entity in the Blue Ridge Parkway Geodatabase. The photographs in this collection are for the Peaks of Otter quadrangle, but are also part of a larger data release (Carter et al., 2016). For Peaks of Otter, there are 45 jpg in the collection.

Carter, M.W., Crider, E.A., Southworth, C.S., and Aleinikoff, J.N., 2016, Detailed geologic mapping geodatabase for the Blue Ridge Parkway in Virginia with station point photographs: U.S. Geological Survey data release, http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7DN434F.</abstract>
      <purpose>The purpose of this dataset is to provide photographs taken by the author during the course of geologic mapping along the Blue Ridge Parkway in Virginia.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>2009</begdate>
          <enddate>2013</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-80.936999864</westbc>
        <eastbc>-78.86015197</eastbc>
        <northbc>38.046603894</northbc>
        <southbc>36.538440594</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115</themekt>
        <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>geology</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>Virginia</placekey>
      </place>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Blue Ridge Parkway</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Mark W. Carter</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Mail Stop 926A, 12201 Sunrise Valley Dr</address>
          <city>Reston</city>
          <state>VA</state>
          <postal>20192</postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>703-648-6910</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>mcarter@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Photos were taken with an Olympic digital camera, model uT6000,ST6000 and an Apple IPad, Model MC744LL/A.</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items must be secured from the copyright owner whenever applicable. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although the data have been subjected to rigorous review and are substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, the data are released on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from authorized or unauthorized use. Although the data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Users of the data are advised to read all metadata and associated documentation thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>JPG</formname>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7DN434F</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160224</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Mark W. Carter</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Research Geologist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Mail Stop 926A, 12201 Sunrise Valley Dr</address>
          <city>Reston</city>
          <state>VA</state>
          <postal>20192</postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>703-648-6910</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>mcarter@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>