<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Prinos, S.T.</origin>
        <origin>Dixon, J.F.</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Points for Maps: ArcGIS layer providing the site locations and the water-level statistics used for creating the water-level contour maps</title>
        <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7DJ5CP8</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Prinos, S.T.</origin>
            <origin>Dixon, J.F.</origin>
            <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
            <title>Statistical analysis and Mapping of Water Levels in the Biscayne Aquifer, Water Conservation Areas, and Everglades National Park, Miami-Dade County, Florida, 2000-2009</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Report</sername>
              <issue>5005</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/sir20165005</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Statistical analyses and maps representing mean, high, and low water-level conditions in the surface water and groundwater of Miami-Dade County were made by the U.S. Geological Survey, in cooperation with the Miami-Dade County Department of Regulatory and Economic Resources, to help inform decisions necessary for urban planning and development. Sixteen maps were created that show contours of  (1) the mean of daily water levels at each site during October and May for the 2000-2009 water years; (2) the 25th, 50th, and 75th percentiles of the daily water levels at each site during October and May and for all months during 2000-2009; and (3) the differences between mean October and May water levels, as well as the differences in the percentiles of water levels for all months, between 1990-1999 and 2000-2009. The 80th, 90th, and 96th percentiles of the annual maximums of daily groundwater levels during 1974-2009 (a 35-year period) were computed to provide an indication of unusually high groundwater-level conditions. These maps and statistics provide a generalized understanding of the variations of water levels in the aquifer, rather than a survey of concurrent water levels. Water-level measurements from 473 sites in Miami-Dade County and surrounding counties were analyzed to generate statistical analyses. The monitored water levels included surface-water levels in canals and wetland areas and groundwater levels in the Biscayne aquifer. Maps were created by importing site coordinates, summary water-level statistics, and completeness of record statistics into a geographic information system, and by interpolating between water levels at monitoring sites in the canals and water levels along the coastline.  Raster surfaces were created from these data by using the triangular irregular network interpolation method. The raster surfaces were contoured by using geographic information system software.  These contours were imprecise in some areas because the software could not fully evaluate the hydrology given available information; therefore, contours were manually modified where necessary. The ability to evaluate differences in water levels between 1990-1999 and 2000-2009 is limited in some areas because most of the monitoring sites did not have 80 percent complete records for one or both of these periods. The quality of the analyses was limited by (1) deficiencies in spatial coverage; (2) the combination of pre- and post-construction water levels in areas where canals, levees, retention basins, detention basins, or water-control structures were installed or removed; (3) an inability to address the potential effects of the vertical hydraulic head gradient on water levels in wells of different depths; and (4) an inability to correct for the differences between daily water-level statistics. Contours are dashed in areas where the locations of contours have been approximated because of the uncertainty caused by these limitations. Although the ability of the maps to depict differences in water levels between 1990-1999 and 2000-2009 was limited by missing data, results indicate that near the coast water levels were generally higher in May during 2000-2009 than during 1990-1999; and that inland water levels were generally lower during 2000-2009 than during 1990-1999. Generally, the 25th, 50th, and 75th percentiles of water levels from all months were also higher near the coast and lower inland during 2000–2009 than during 1990-1999.  Mean October water levels during 2000-2009 were generally higher than during 1990-1999 in much of western Miami-Dade County, but were lower in a large part of eastern Miami-Dade County.</abstract>
      <purpose>Shows the groundwater and surface water sites used to create the potentiometric surface contours of water levels for the water years 2000-2009 of the Biscayne aquifer in Miami-Dade County, Florida.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>19891001</begdate>
          <begtime>010000</begtime>
          <enddate>20090930</enddate>
          <endtime>010000</endtime>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Unknown</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Miami Dade County, Florida</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-80.964855</westbc>
        <eastbc>-80.146031</eastbc>
        <northbc>26.119128</northbc>
        <southbc>25.074456</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Potentiometric surface</themekey>
        <themekey>water levels</themekey>
        <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
        <themekey>contours</themekey>
        <themekey>Biscayne aquifer</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
        <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Florida Bay</placekey>
        <placekey>Florida</placekey>
        <placekey>Miami-Dade County</placekey>
        <placekey>Biscayne Bay</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Scott T. Prinos</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>7500 SW 36 St</address>
          <city>Davie</city>
          <state>FL</state>
          <postal>33314</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747  (1-888-ASK-USGS)</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>stprinos@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>Principal investigators include Scott Prinos and Joann Dixon. This study was prepared in cooperation with the Miami-Dade County Department of Regulatory and Economic Resources.</datacred>
    <secinfo>
      <secsys>None</secsys>
      <secclass>Unclassified</secclass>
      <sechandl>None</sechandl>
    </secinfo>
    <native>Version 6.2 (Build 9200) ; Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1.4959</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>The precision with which contours of the water levels in a given area could be determined, depends on the number of monitoring sites in an area relative to the changes in the water surface. In some areas changes can be tightly constrained because there are many monitoring sites that provide a detailed understanding of changes. In other areas the network is less dense and uncertainty in the location of contour lines is greater. This is discussed in greater detail in the report associated with this geographic information system layer in the Discussion section.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>All data were visually evaluated and reviewed to be consistent and correct.</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record and the report for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>n/a</methtype>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Water-level information from monitoring sites on canals were used to interpolate water levels in each segment of the canal using a routing system.  The water levels from these interpolations were assigned to a series of locations (called control points) that traced the course of each of the monitored canals.  The triangulated irregular network (TIN) interpolation method was selected to create a water-level surface that could be contoured. The points in the shapefile were input into the ArcGIS tool Create TIN to create a TIN surface. Lakes, canals, well fields, and major roads also were used as input features in this tool. The resulting TIN surface was used to create the contours using the ArcGIS tool Surface Contour. All of the contours generated using the Surface Contour tool had to be manually modified. All contours were manually smoothed on a segment-by-segment basis to ensure that the contours did not overlap and that they passed through water-control structures or other points where necessary. Please refer to the report at http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/sir20165005/ for more information.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20131224</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>498</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>NAD 1983 HARN StatePlane Florida East FIPS 0901</mapprojn>
          <transmer>
            <sfctrmer>0.9999411764705882</sfctrmer>
            <longcm>-81.0</longcm>
            <latprjo>24.33333333333333</latprjo>
            <feast>656166.6666666666</feast>
            <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
          </transmer>
        </mapproj>
        <planci>
          <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>7.286005132556284E-9</absres>
            <ordres>7.286005132556284E-9</ordres>
          </coordrep>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D North American 1983 HARN</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS 1980</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>AllSites</enttypl>
        <enttypd>All sites used for analysis.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>USGS</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>FID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Longitude</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Longitude</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Longitude coordinates defining the features in decimal degrees NAD 1983 datum.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Latitude</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Latitude</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Latitude coordinates defining the features in decimal degrees NAD 1983 datum.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SiteName</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Site name</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Site name identifying the well or station.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SiteID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Site identifier</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Site ID identifying the well or station.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Provider</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Agency provider</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <codesetd>
            <codesetn>NPS - National Park Service, SFWMD - South Florida Water Management District, USGS - U.S. Geological Survey</codesetn>
            <codesets>USGS</codesets>
          </codesetd>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DailyStat</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Daily statistic</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <codesetd>
            <codesetn>MAXIMUM, MEAN</codesetn>
            <codesets>USGS</codesets>
          </codesetd>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SiteType</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Site Type.  GW - Groundwater site, SW - Surface water site</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <codesetd>
            <codesetn>GW, SW</codesetn>
            <codesets>USGS</codesets>
          </codesetd>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ConFactor</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Conversion factor used to covert the water level information from its original datum to the final datum.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Conversion factor dependent on latitude-longitude coordinates</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>OrigVertDa</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Original vertical datum of the water level information used to compute the statistics shown for this site ID or DBKEY.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <codesetd>
            <codesetn>NAVD88, NGVD29</codesetn>
            <codesets>USGS</codesets>
          </codesetd>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>FinVertDat</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Final vertical datum of the water level information used to compute the statistics shown for this site ID or DBKEY</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>NAVD88</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Map1</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Average of May water levels for the water years 2000-2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-2.68</rdommin>
            <rdommax>9.01</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Map2</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Average of October water levels for the water years 2000-2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-4.88</rdommin>
            <rdommax>10.26</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Map3</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>25th percentile of May water levels for the water years 2000-2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-7.7</rdommin>
            <rdommax>8.82</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Map4</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>50th percentile of May water levels for the water years 2000-2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-5.97</rdommin>
            <rdommax>9.00</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Map5</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>75th percentile of May water levels for the water years 2000-2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-3.43</rdommin>
            <rdommax>9.21</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Map6</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>25th percentile of October water levels for the water years 2000-2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-7.38</rdommin>
            <rdommax>10.06</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Map7</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>50th percentile of October water levels for the water years 2000-2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-5.52</rdommin>
            <rdommax>10.19</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Map8</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>75th percentile of October water levels for the water years 2000-2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-2.60</rdommin>
            <rdommax>10.68</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Map9</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>50th percentile of water levels from all months for the water years 2000-2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-5.59</rdommin>
            <rdommax>9.71</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Map10</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>25th percentile of water levels from all months for the water years 2000-2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-7.55</rdommin>
            <rdommax>9.38</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Map11</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>75th percentile of water levels from all months for the water years 2000-2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-3.52</rdommin>
            <rdommax>10.06</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Map12</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Difference in May average water levels from the water-year periods 1990 to 1999 and 2000 to 2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-2.23</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2.13</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Map13</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Difference in October average water levels from the water-year periods 1990 to 1999 and 2000 to 2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-2.68</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1.31</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Map14</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Difference in 25th percentile of all water levels from the water-year periods 1990 to 1999 and 2000 to 2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-1.77</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1.92</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Map15</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Difference in 50th percentile of all water levels from the water-year periods 1990 to 1999 and 2000 to 2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-3.27</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2.35</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Map16</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Difference in 75th percentile of all water levels from the water-year periods 1990 to 1999 and 2000 to 2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-3.22</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2.9</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Notes</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Notes about dataset</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Notes about dataset</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>PrctCmpAll</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Percentage of complete water level record for the period 2000 to 2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>PrctCmpMay</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Percentage of complete water level record for the months of May during the period 2000 to 2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>PrctCmpOct</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Percentage of complete water level record for the months of October during the period 2000 to 2009.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>PrctCmpA_1</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Percentage of complete water level record for the period 1990 to 1999.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>PcntCmpMay</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Percentage of complete water level record for the months of May during the period 1990 to 1999.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>PrcntCmpOc</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Percentage of complete water level record for the months of October during the period 1990 to 1999.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Index_MapI</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Grid Identification number from Figure 3 in the report.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Grid identification number.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Index_Num</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Index number displayed on Figure 3 in the report</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unique map identification number.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Scott T. Prinos</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>7500 SW 36 St</address>
          <city>Davie</city>
          <state>FL</state>
          <postal>33314</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747  (1-888-ASK-USGS)</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>stprinos@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>See access and use constraints information.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>SHP</formname>
          <formvern>ArcGIS 10</formvern>
          <formspec>ESRI Shapefile</formspec>
          <formcont>Online accessible data</formcont>
          <transize>4.9</transize>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7DJ5CP8</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160115</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Joann F. Dixon</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>USGS</cntorg>
          <cntper>Joann Dixon</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>IT Specialist (GIS)</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>12703 Research Parkway</address>
          <city>Orlando</city>
          <state>FL</state>
          <postal>32826</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>407-803-5500</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jdixon@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>

