<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Kenneth Belitz</origin>
        <origin>Bryant C. Jurgens</origin>
        <origin>Tyler D. Johnson</origin>
        <pubdate>20160406</pubdate>
        <title>Classification of Chloride-to-Sulfate Mass Ratio for U.S. Groundwater With Respect to the Potential to Promote Galvanic Corrosion of Lead, 1991-2015; Water Well Data and Characteristic Values for States</title>
        <geoform>Vector Digital Data Set (Polygon)</geoform>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7MC8X40</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Kenneth Belitz</origin>
            <origin>Bryant C. Jurgens</origin>
            <origin>Tyler D. Johnson</origin>
            <pubdate>20160623</pubdate>
            <title>Potential Corrosivity of Untreated Groundwater in the United States</title>
            <geoform>Publication (Other)</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>Scientific Investigations Report</sername>
              <issue>2016-5092</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>
Galvanic corrosion of lead in water distribution systems can occur when lead pipe or lead solder is in contact with a dissimilar metal such as copper. If the source water entering those systems has a relatively elevated chloride-to-sulfate mass ratio (CSMR), the potential for galvanic corrosion to occur is elevated (Gregory 1985; Edwards and Triantafyllidou, 2007), especially in water with low values of alkalinity (Nguyen and others, 2011).  Values of CSMR were computed for untreated groundwater samples from 26,631 locations in the United States.  Three levels, identified by Nguyen and others (2011), were used to classify CSMR values relative to their potential for promoting galvanic corrosion of lead.  The three-level classification, defined here as the potential to promote galvanic corrosion (PPGC), was based on values of CSMR and alkalinity (Nguyen and others, 2011). The data and maps presented in this report do not indicate the occurrence of lead pipe or lead solder in distribution systems across the U.S., rather they reflect the potential of the untreated groundwater resource to promote galvanic corrosion where lead and other metals might occur in distribution systems. 
The data for calculating CSMR and PPGC at sites were obtained from the US Geological Survey (USGS) National Water Information System (NWIS). The data included in this report are for untreated groundwater samples obtained during the period 1991-2015. At each location, the most recent sample (during the period 1991-2015) with the necessary measurements was used to calculate CSMR and PPGC. Of the 26,631 sites, the PPGC is: high at 8%, moderate at 67%, and low at 26%. The values of PPGC at sites presented in this report can be used to identify which areas in the U.S. might be more susceptible to galvanic corrosion of lead from drinking water distribution systems and which areas may be less susceptible. A companion dataset provides characteristic values for each groundwater site. 
Characteristic statewide values of PPGC were computed for the fifty states and District of Columbia of the United States.  The characteristic statewide values were computed using PPGC values from 26,631 untreated groundwater sites.  For each state, four characteristic values were computed: proportion of sites where PPGC is low; proportion of sites where PPGC is moderate; proportion of sites where PPGC is high; and, a statewide category. The number of sites in each state is also reported. The characteristic statewide values of PPGC presented in this report can be used to identify which state(s) in the U.S. might be more susceptible to galvanic corrosion of lead from drinking water distribution systems and which state(s) may be less susceptible. 
Please see the individual metadata for the two datasets contained within the geodatabase for detailed descriptions of the process steps and attributes. 
</abstract>
      <purpose>The purpose of this report is to provide information for U.S. groundwater that may be indicative of the potential to promote galvanic corrosion of lead.</purpose>
      <supplinf>
At each groundwater site, the potential for promoting galvanic corrosion of lead was classified at three levels: low if CSMR is less than 0.2; moderate if CSMR is greater than or equal to 0.2 and less than or equal to 0.5, or if CMSR is greater than 0.5 and alkalinity is greater than or equal to 50 milligrams per liter (as calcium carbonate); and, high if CSMR is greater than 0.5 and alkalinity is less than 50 milligrams per liter (as calcium carbonate). Nguyen and others (2011), who defined the criteria, previously characterized the three classes as: “no concern” (low in this report); “significant concern” (moderate in this report); and, “serious concern” (high in this report). For the purposes of visualization, states were categorized as low if more than 50% of the sites in the state were classified as low; as high if more than 25% of the sites were classified as high; otherwise, moderate.
References:  
Edwards, M. and Triantafyllidou, S., 2007. Chloride-to-sulfate mass ratio and lead leaching to water. Journal of the American Water Works Association, 99(7), pp.96-109.
Gregory, R., 1985. Galvanic corrosion of lead in copper pipework: Phase I, measurement of galvanic corrosion potential in selected waters. Water Research Centre Engineering, Swindon, England.
Nguyen, C.K., Stone, K.R. and Edwards, M.A., 2011. Chloride-to-sulfate mass ratio: Practical studies in galvanic corrosion of lead solder. Journal of the American Water Works Association, 103(1), p.81.
</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>19910111</begdate>
          <enddate>20151124</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>See Supplemental Info</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-179.133392334</westbc>
        <eastbc>179.788208008</eastbc>
        <northbc>71.3980484005</northbc>
        <southbc>18.9154930113</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Groundwater, Wells, Corrosivity, Chloride to Sulfate Mass Ratio, CSMR, Alkalinity, Galvanic Corrosion, Lead, NWIS, PPGC</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>United States</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None. Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</accconst>
    <useconst>None.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Headquarters</cntorg>
          <cntper>Kenneth Belitz</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>Chief, NAWQA Groundwater Assessments</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>10 Bearfoot Road</address>
          <city>Northborough</city>
          <state>MA</state>
          <postal>01532</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>858-775-6309</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>kbelitz@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1 (Build 4959) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted. However, the accuracy of the well locations vary. Latitude and longitude were extracted from the USGS NWIS system and assumed to be in the North American Datum of 1983. The state that the well is located in was determined from the NWIS database. The state designation is usually recorded by local field crew when the well was initially sampled. However one well, (USGS site number 452411106301601), plotted in Montana but was listed as being it California. It was changed to MT.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Please see the individual metadata for the two datasets contained within the geodatabase for detailed descriptions of the process steps.</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center</address>
          <address>Building 810</address>
          <address>Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Although these data have been used by the U.S. Geological Survey, U.S. Department of the Interior, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the U.S. Geological Survey as to the accuracy of the data. The act of distribution shall not constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumed by the U.S. Geological Survey in the use of these data, software, or related materials. The use of firm, trade, or brand names in this report is for identification purposes only and does not constitute endorsement by the U.S. Geological Survey. The names mentioned in this document may be trademarks or registered trademarks of their respective trademark owners.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Vector Digital Data Set (Polygon)</formname>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7MC8X40</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160705</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, PACIFIC REGION</cntorg>
          <cntper>Tyler D. Johnson</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>4165 Spruance Road</address>
          <address>Suite 200</address>
          <city>San Diego</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>92101</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>619-225-6100</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>619-225-6101</cntfax>
        <cntemail>tyjohns@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>