<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Jennifer Lanning-Rush</origin>
        <pubdate>20160401</pubdate>
        <title>Public-Supply Water Use in Kansas, 2014</title>
        <geoform>Microsoft Excel 97-2003 workbook and comma delimited files</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Lawrence, KS</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7N29V1D</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Kansas Department of Agriculture's Division of Water Resources</origin>
            <origin>Kansas Water Office</origin>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, Kansas Water Science Center</origin>
            <title>Kansas Municipal Water Use</title>
            <geoform>tabular data in PDF file format</geoform>
            <onlink>http://cdm16884.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/search/collection/p16884coll5/searchterm/WR1-2-M966/field/identi/mode/exact/conn/and/order/govern/ad/desc</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) Data Release provides derivative statistics of water used by Kansas public-supply systems in 2014. Gallons per capita per day is calculated using self-reported information in the “Part B: Monthly Water Use Summary” and “Part C: Population, Service Connections, and Water Rates” sections of the Kansas Department of Agriculture, Division of Water Resources' (DWR) annual municipal water use report (see appendixes at http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds964 for an example of a municipal water use report form.)  Percent unaccounted for water is calculated using self-reported information in “Part B: Monthly Water Use Summary” of the DWR’s municipal water-use report.  The published statistics from the previous 4 years (2010–2013) are also shown with the 2014 statistics and are used to calculate a 5-year average.  Derivative statistics of  2010, 2011, 2012, 2013, 2014, and 5-year averages for gallons per capita per day (gpcd) are also provided by the Kansas Water Authority's 14 regional planning areas, and the DWR regions used for analysis of per capita water use in Kansas.  An overall Kansas average (yearly and 5-year average) is also calculated.  Kansas state average per captia use in 2014 was 108 gpcd.</abstract>
      <purpose>The 2014 data were prepared by the U.S. Geological Survey in cooperation with the Kansas Department of Agriculture, Division of Water Resources (DWR) and with partial support from the State Water Plan Fund.  Since the late 1980's the U.S. Geological Survey and the DWR have partnered through a cooperative program to evaluate, compile, and publish data from the annual water-use reports.  For more information on other data, see the "Water Supply and Use" webpage at the USGS Kansas Water Science Center website (http://ks.water.usgs.gov/).</purpose>
      <supplinf>Mobile home parks have been excluded.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20140101</begdate>
          <enddate>20141231</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>observed</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Annually</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>State of Kansas</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-102.0506</westbc>
        <eastbc>-94.61761</eastbc>
        <northbc>40.0</northbc>
        <southbc>37.0</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS water-use terminology</themekt>
        <themekey>municipal water use</themekey>
        <themekey>public-supply water use</themekey>
        <themekey>water right</themekey>
        <themekey>water-use reporting</themekey>
        <themekey>gallons per capita per day (gpcd)</themekey>
        <themekey>unaccounted for water (ufw)</themekey>
        <themekey>water consumption</themekey>
        <themekey>municipal water supply</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System (GNIS)</placekt>
        <placekey>Kansas</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Jennifer Lanning-Rush</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Kansas Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>4821 Quail Crest Place</address>
          <city>Lawrence</city>
          <state>Kansas</state>
          <postal>66049</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>785-832-3555</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jlanning@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>This data release was prepared by the U.S. Geological Survey in cooperation with the Kansas Department of Agriculture’s Division of Water Resources with partial support from the Kansas Water Office and the Kansas State Water Plan Fund.</datacred>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Self-reported information from the “Part B: Monthly Water Use Summary” and “Part C: Population, Service Connections, and Water Rates” sections of the Kansas Department of Agriculture, Division of Water Resources' (DWR) municipal water use report (see http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds964 for an example of a water use report form) .  DWR staff send follow-up letters, emails, and made phone calls to obtain missing data and to confirm or correct anomalous data.  Further quality checks were performed by the USGS staff.  Water-use quantities in Part B are reported by 1,000 gallon units.  The reported quantities are nearly always metered but can be estimated if equipment or reporting errors were suspected.  Despite the data checks performed the data may still contain errors or inaccuracies.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Data checks are performed on the data stored in WRIS by staff from the Kansas Department of Agriculture, Division of Water Resources (DWR), Kansas Geological Survey (KGS), Kansas Water Office (KWO), and the U.S. Geological Survey.  Quality checks on this data release were performed by two peer reviewers.</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>n/a</methtype>
        <methdesc>A provision of the DWR’s water appropriation program requires all municipal water right owners to submit an annual water-use report. Public water suppliers provide details on the quantity of water diverted each calendar year; and, if applicable, the water purchased from and sold to other suppliers, sales to retail customers, metered free water, unaccounted for water, detailed service connection numbers, and population served. Retail customers can be residential; commercial; or institutions such as schools, universities, or hospitals. Retail customers can also be industrial, feedlot, pasture, stockwater, or bulk water service customers. Data submitted on the municipal water-use reports are stored in the DWR’s Water Rights Information System (WRIS). The WRIS is the record-keeping and annual use database for water rights administered by the DWR.</methdesc>
      </method>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Kansas Department of Agriculture's Division of Water Resources</origin>
            <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
            <title>Water Rights Information System (WRIS)</title>
            <geoform>retrieved from Oracle database with SQL statements</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Manhattan, Kansas</pubplace>
              <publish>Kansas Department of Agriculture's Division of Water Resources</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://hercules.kgs.ku.edu/geohydro/wimas/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>WRIS contains over 70 relational tables that store data on points of diversion (e.g. ground-water wells and surface water intakes), place of use, authorized quantity and rate allocations, historic reported water usage, and a host of other parameters.</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>19900101</begdate>
              <enddate>20150101</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>dynamic</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>WRIS</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Water Information Management and Analysis System (WIMAS) is a web based application of the WRIS Oracle database.  It allows users to query, analyze, and map Kansas water right data.  Information accessed by WIMAS is public record.</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Connect to WRIS via Oracle Discoverer client and execute SQL statements</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160101</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Import data into local MSAccess database and run checks for missing public-sypply systems, verify diverted quantities are in correct units, check for data entry errors, verify population served, and other checks of the data.  Join tables and aggregate by system to an annual total. Compute gallons per capita per day and unaccounted for water, in percent, for all systems that serve at least twenty-five individuals or have at least ten (10) service connections.  Compute averages for the DWR regions used for analysis of per capita water use in Kansas and the Kansas Water Authority's fourteen regional planning areas.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160215</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Microsoft Excel 97-2003 workbook "Public-Supply_Water_Use_in_Kansas_2014.xls", spreadsheet "KS PWS wateruse 2014" or "KS_PWS_wateruse_2014.csv"</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Derivative statistics of  2010, 2011, 2012, 2013, 2014, and 5-year averages for gallons per capita per day (gpcd) and percent unaccounted for water (ufw) are provided by individual Kansas public-supply systems active in 2014.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Derivative statistics generated from annual self-reported public-supply water use which includes details, if applicable, on the quantity of water diverted, the water purchased from and sold to other suppliers, sales to retail customers, metered free water, unaccounted for water, detailed service connection numbers, and population served.</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Public water supplier</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A public water supplier name.  A public-water supplier is defined in the Kansas Statutes Annotated § 65–162a as “a system for the provision to the public of piped water for human consumption, if such system has at least ten (10) service connections or regularly serves an average of at least twenty-five (25) individuals daily at least sixty (60) days out of the year.”</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Kansas Statutes Annotated § 65–162a</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>text</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DWR ID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>unique entity identification number assigned and stored in WRIS (also sometimes referred to as person id).  This data release aggregates the reported water-use information to this attribute.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Kansas Department of Agriculture, Division of Water Resources (DWR)</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>unique numeric values</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>EPA Water System Number</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>unique water system ID number assigned by EPA</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>United States Environmental Protection Agency</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>nine characters in length, with the first two digits composed of the state abbreviation</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Source water RPA</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Each public water supplier is assigned to a regional planning area (RPA) by the Kansas Water Office based on the location where most of the water diverted is obtained.  RPAs were adopted in 2015 as part of the "Vision for the Future of Water Supply in Kansas".  Fourteen RPAs were established to provide a process for water supply goals to be established by stakeholders as a means for measuring success and implementing the 50-year Vision.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Kansas Water Authority, Kansas Water Office</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Ci, Ew, Gb, Ks, Mc, Mo, Ne, Rh, Ss, Sr, Ua, Ur, Us, Ve</edomv>
            <edomvd>Ci = Cimarron; Ew = Equus-Walnut; Gb = Great Bend Prairie; Ks = Kansas; Mc = Marais des Cygnes; Mo = Missouri; Ne = Neosho; Rh = Red Hills; Ss = Smoky Hill-Saline; Sr = Solomon-Republican; Ua = Upper Arkansas; Ur = Upper Republican; Us = Upper Smoky Hill; Ve = Verdigris</edomvd>
            <edomvds>KWO</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GPCD Region</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Kansas has been grouped into eight regions to account for precipitation patterns and to provide meaningful comparisons between suppliers.  The regions are mostly based on county boundaries.  Each public water supplier is assigned to one of eight regions.  Regions 6, 7 and 8 are further subdivided by population served.  See map as figure 1 in http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds964.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Kansas Department of Agriculture, Division of Water Resources (DWR)</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>1</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region 1 represents Cheyenne, Greeley, Hamilton, Morton, Sherman, Stanton, and Wallace counties.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>DWR</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>2</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region 2 represents Finney (West of 30 Range line), Grant, Haskell, Kearny, Logan, Rawlins, Scott, Seward, Stevens, Thomas, and Wichita counties.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>DWR</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>3</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region 3 represents Decatur, Finney (East of 30 Range line), Gove, Gray, Lane, Meade, and Sheridan counties.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>DWR</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>4</edomv>
            <edomvd>Regions 4 represents Clark, Ford, Graham, Hodgeman, Ness, Norton, and Trego counties.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>DWR</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>5</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region 5 represents Comanche, Edwards, Ellis, Kiowa, Pawnee, Phillips, Rooks, and Rush counties.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>DWR</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>6S</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region 6S represents public water suppliers serving between 25 to 499 people in Barber, Barton, Ellsworth, Harper, Jewell, Kingman, Lincoln, Mitchell, Osborne, Pratt, Reno, Rice, Russell, Smith, or Stafford counties.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>DWR</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>6ML</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region 6ML represents public water suppliers serving over 500 people in Barber, Barton, Ellsworth, Harper, Jewell, Kingman, Lincoln, Mitchell, Osborne, Pratt, Reno, Rice, Russell, Smith, or Stafford counties.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>DWR</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>7S</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region 7S represents public water suppliers serving between 25 to 499 people in Butler, Chase, Chautauqua, Clay, Cloud, Coffey, Cowley, Dickinson, Elk, Geary, Greenwood, Harvey, Jackson, Lyon, Marion, Marshall, McPherson, Montgomery, Morris, Nemaha, Osage, Ottawa, Pottawatomie, Republic, Riley, Saline, Sedgwick, Shawnee, Sumner, Wabaunsee, Washington, Wilson, or Woodson counties.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>DWR</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>7M</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region 7M represents public water suppliers serving between 500 to 9,999 people in Butler, Chase, Chautauqua, Clay, Cloud, Coffey, Cowley, Dickinson, Elk, Geary, Greenwood, Harvey, Jackson, Lyon, Marion, Marshall, McPherson, Montgomery, Morris, Nemaha, Osage, Ottawa, Pottawatomie, Republic, Riley, Saline, Sedgwick, Shawnee, Sumner, Wabaunsee, Washington, Wilson, or Woodson counties.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>DWR</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>7L</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region 7L represents public water suppliers serving over 10,000 people in Butler, Chase, Chautauqua, Clay, Cloud, Coffey, Cowley, Dickinson, Elk, Geary, Greenwood, Harvey, Jackson, Lyon, Marion, Marshall, McPherson, Montgomery, Morris, Nemaha, Osage, Ottawa, Pottawatomie, Republic, Riley, Saline, Sedgwick, Shawnee, Sumner, Wabaunsee, Washington, Wilson, or Woodson counties.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>DWR</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>8S</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region 8S represents public water suppliers serving between 25 to 499 people in Allen, Anderson, Atchison, Bourbon, Brown, Cherokee, Crawford, Doniphan, Douglas, Franklin, Jefferson, Johnson, Labette, Leavenworth, Linn, Miami, Neosho, or Wyandotte counties.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>DWR</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>8M</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region 8M represents public water suppliers serving between 500 to 9,999 people in Allen, Anderson, Atchison, Bourbon, Brown, Cherokee, Crawford, Doniphan, Douglas, Franklin, Jefferson, Johnson, Labette, Leavenworth, Linn, Miami, Neosho, or Wyandotte counties.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>DWR</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <edom>
            <edomv>8L</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region 8L represents public water suppliers serving over 10,000 people in Allen, Anderson, Atchison, Bourbon, Brown, Cherokee, Crawford, Doniphan, Douglas, Franklin, Jefferson, Johnson, Labette, Leavenworth, Linn, Miami, Neosho, or Wyandotte counties.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>DWR</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GPCD 2010</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Gallons per capita per day (GPCD) is the average amount of public-supply water used per person per day in 2010 (from USGS Data Series 964). GPCD use includes water sold to residential and commercial customers, metered free uses, and unaccounted for water.  GPCD use does not include sales to other suppliers, industries, bulk uses, or farmsteads using more than 200,000 gallons per year.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>33</rdommin>
            <rdommax>797</rdommax>
            <attrunit>gallons per capita (or per person) per day</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>“na” or -9999 are shown if insufficient or erroneous information was provided on the water-use report or if no water-use report was filed.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GPCD 2011</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Gallons per capita per day (GPCD) is the average amount of public-supply water used per person per day in 2011 (from USGS Data Series 964). GPCD use includes water sold to residential and commercial customers, metered free uses, and unaccounted for water.  GPCD use does not include sales to other suppliers, industries, bulk uses, or farmsteads using more than 200,000 gallons per year.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>35</rdommin>
            <rdommax>800</rdommax>
            <attrunit>gallons per capita (or per person) per day</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>“na” or -9999 are shown if insufficient or erroneous information was provided on the water-use report or if no water-use report was filed.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GPCD 2012</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Gallons per capita per day (GPCD) is the average amount of public-supply water used per person per day in 2012 (from USGS Data Series 964).  GPCD use includes water sold to residential and commercial customers, metered free uses, and unaccounted for water.  GPCD use does not include sales to other suppliers, industries, bulk uses, or farmsteads using more than 200,000 gallons per year.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>34</rdommin>
            <rdommax>972</rdommax>
            <attrunit>gallons per capita (or per person) per day</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>“na” or -9999 are shown if insufficient or erroneous information was provided on the water-use report or if no water-use report was filed.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GPCD 2013</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Gallons per capita per day (GPCD) is the average amount of public-supply water used per person per day in 2013 (from USGS Data Series 964).  GPCD use includes water sold to residential and commercial customers, metered free uses, and unaccounted for water.  GPCD use does not include sales to other suppliers, industries, bulk uses, or farmsteads using more than 200,000 gallons per year.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>23</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1408</rdommax>
            <attrunit>gallons per capita (or per person) per day</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>“na” or -9999 are shown if insufficient or erroneous information was provided on the water-use report or if no water-use report was filed.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GPCD 2014</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Gallons per capita per day (GPCD) is the average amount of public-supply water used per person per day in 2014.  Gallons per capita per day is calculated using self-reported information in the “Part B: Monthly Water Use Summary” and “Part C: Population, Service Connections, and Water Rates” sections of the DWR’s municipal water-use report (see appendix, http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds964) where quantities are reported in thousands of gallons and are computed as: gpcd=(DIV+PUR-SOL-IND)/(POP*0.365)  where gpcd is water use in gallons per capita per day, DIV is the water diverted for all points of diversion under the supplier’s water rights (column 1 in part B), PUR is the water purchased from other suppliers or through the KWO’s Water Marketing Program (column 2 in part B), SOL is the water sold to all other public water suppliers (column 3 in part B), IND is the water sold to industrial, livestock, pasture, feedlot, and other bulk water service connections (column 4 in part B), POP is the estimated number of people served directly by residential and commercial customers (part C), and 0.365 is a multiplier to account for the number of days in the year.  GPCD use includes water sold to residential and commercial customers, metered free uses, and unaccounted for water.  GPCD use does not include sales to other suppliers, industries, bulk uses, or farmsteads using more than 200,000 gallons per year.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>37</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2543</rdommax>
            <attrunit>gallons per capita (or per person) per day</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>“na” or -9999 are shown if insufficient or erroneous information was provided on the water-use report or if no water-use report was filed.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GPCD Average 2010-2014</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>5-year average gallons of public-supply water used per person per day from 2010 to 2014.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>34</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1256</rdommax>
            <attrunit>gallons per capita (or per person) per day</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>“na” or -9999 are shown if insufficient or erroneous information was provided on the water-use report or if water-use reports were not filed from 2010 to 2014.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>UFW 2010, in percent</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Unsold water in 2010 that is not metered is considered unaccounted for water and is shown as percentages of total water pumped and/or purchased (from USGS Data Series 964).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>3</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>in percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>"na" or -9999 are used when a water-use report is not available for the year, insufficient or erroneous information was provided, or the computed unaccounted for water is less than 3 percent (from USGS Data Series 964).</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>UFW 2011, in percent</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Unsold water in 2011 that is not metered is considered unaccounted for water and is shown as percentages of total water pumped and/or purchased.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>3</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>in percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>"na" or -9999 are used when a water-use report is not available for the year, insufficient or erroneous information was provided, or the computed unaccounted for water is less than 3 percent .</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>UFW 2012, in percent</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Unsold water in 2012 that is not metered is considered unaccounted for water and is shown as percentages of total water pumped and/or purchased (from USGS Data Series 964).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>3</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>in percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>"na" or -9999 are used when a water-use report is not available for the year, insufficient or erroneous information was provided, or the computed unaccounted for water is less than 3 percent.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>UFW 2013, in percent</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Unsold water in 2013 that is not metered is considered unaccounted for water and is shown as percentages of total water pumped and/or purchased (from USGS Data Series 964).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>3</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>in percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>"na" or -9999 are used when a water-use report is not available for the year, insufficient or erroneous information was provided, or the computed unaccounted for water is less than 3 percent.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>UFW 2014, in percent</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Unsold water in 2014 that is not metered is considered unaccounted for water and is shown as percentages of total water pumped and/or purchased. Percent unaccounted for water (ufw) is calculated using self-reported information in “Part B: Monthly Water Use Summary” of the DWR’s municipal water-use report and is computed as: ufw=[(DIV+PUR-SOL-IND-CUST-FREE)/ (DIV+PUR)]*100  where ufw is the unaccounted for water, in percent; DIV is the water diverted for all points of diversion under the supplier’s water rights (column 1 in part B appendix); PUR is the water purchased from other suppliers or through the KWO’s Water Marketing Program (column 2 in part B); SOL is the water sold to all other public water suppliers (column 3 in part B); IND is the water sold to industrial, livestock, pasture, feedlot, and other bulk water service connections (column 4 in part B); CUST is the water sold to residential and commercial customers (column 5 in part B); and FREE is the metered water provided free (column 6 in part B).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>3</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>in percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>"na" or -9999 are used when a water-use report is not available for the year, insufficient or erroneous information was provided, or the computed unaccounted for water is less than 3 percent.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>UFW Average, 2010-2014</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>5-year average unaccounted for public-supply water from 2010 to 2014, expressed as a percentage.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>3</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>in percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>“na” or -9999 are shown if insufficient or erroneous information was provided on the water-use report or if water-use reports were not filed from 2010 to 2014.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>In Regional Average</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Four rural water districts (RWDs) are excluded from regional averages because over 40 percent of their service connections are livestock, and the amount supplied to those connections cannot be split from residential sales. The excluded RWDs are: Barber County RWD #02, Comanche County RWD #02, Osborne County RWD #01A, and Phillips County RWD #01.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Yes; No</edomv>
            <edomvd>Yes=included in regional averages; No=excluded from regional averages.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Microsoft Excel 97-2003 workbook "Public-Supply_Water_Use_in_Kansas_2014.xls", spreadsheet "GPCD AVG by DWR region" or "GPCD_AVG_by_DWR_region.csv"</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Derivative statistics of  2010, 2011, 2012, 2013, 2014, and a 5-year averages of public-supply water gpcd by regions used in the analysis of per capita water use in Kansas.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Derivative statistics generated from annual self-reported public-supply water use which includes details, if applicable, on the quantity of water diverted, the water purchased from and sold to other suppliers, sales to retail customers, metered free water, unaccounted for water, detailed service connection numbers, and population served.</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GPCD Region</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Kansas has been grouped into eight regions to account for precipitation patterns and to provide meaningful comparisons between suppliers.  The regions are mostly based on county boundaries.  Each public water supplier is assigned to one of eight regions.  Regions 6, 7 and 8 are further subdivided by population served.  See map as figure 1 in http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds964.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Kansas Department of Agriculture, Divison of Water Resources</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>(see complete definition above)</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Average 2010 GPCD</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Gallons per capita per day (GPCD) is the average amount of public-supply water used per person per day in 2010 in each GPCD region.  An overall Kansas average is also calculated and presented (from USGS Data Series 964).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>79</rdommin>
            <rdommax>259</rdommax>
            <attrunit>gallons per capita (or per person) per day</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Average 2011 GPCD</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Gallons per capita per day (GPCD) is the average amount of public-supply water used per person per day in 2011 in each GPCD region.  An overall Kansas average is also calculated and presented (from USGS Data Series 964).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>81</rdommin>
            <rdommax>282</rdommax>
            <attrunit>gallons per captia (or per person) per day</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Average 2012 GPCD</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Gallons per capita per day (GPCD) is the average amount of public-supply water used per person per day in 2012 in each GPCD region.  An overall Kansas average is also calculated and presented (from USGS Data Series 964).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>81</rdommin>
            <rdommax>316</rdommax>
            <attrunit>gallons per capita (or per person) per day</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Average 2013 GPCD</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Gallons per capita per day (GPCD) is the average amount of public-supply water used per person per day in 2013 in each GPCD region.  An overall Kansas average is also calculated and presented (from USGS Data Series 964).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>73</rdommin>
            <rdommax>280</rdommax>
            <attrunit>gallons per capita (or per person) per day</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Average 2014 GPCD</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Gallons per capita per day (GPCD) is the average amount of public-supply water used per person per day in 2014 in each GPCD region.  An overall Kansas average is also calculated and presented.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>73</rdommin>
            <rdommax>264</rdommax>
            <attrunit>gallons per capita (or per person) per day</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>2010-2014 average gpcd</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Gallons per capita per day (GPCD) 5-year average is the amount of public-supply water used per person per day between 2010 to 2014 in each GPCD region. An overall Kansas average is also calculated and presented.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 964</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>77</rdommin>
            <rdommax>280</rdommax>
            <attrunit>gallons per capita (or per person) per day</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Microsoft Excel 97-2003 workbook "Public-Supply_Water_Use_in_Kansas_2014.xls", spreadsheet "GPCD AVG by RPA" or "GPCD_AVG_by_RPA.csv"</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Derivative statistics of the year 2014 gallons per capita per day (gpcd) by the Kansas Water Authority's 14 regional planning areas.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Derivative statistics generated from annual self-reported public-supply water use which includes details, if applicable, on the quantity of water diverted, the water purchased from and sold to other suppliers, sales to retail customers, metered free water, unaccounted for water, detailed service connection numbers, and population served.</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Source-water regional planning area</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Each public water supplier is assigned to a regional planning area (RPA) by the Kansas Water Office based on the location where most of the water diverted is obtained.  RPAs were adopted in 2015 as part of the "Vision for the Future of Water Supply in Kansas".  Fourteen RPAs were established to provide a process for water supply goals to be established by stakeholders as a means for measuring success and implementing the Vision.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Kansas Water Authority, Kansas Water Office</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <codesetd>
            <codesetn>Cimarron, Equus-Walnut, Great Bend Prairie, Kansas, Marais des Cygnes, Missouri, Neosho, Red Hills, Smoky Hill-Saline, Solomon-Republican, Upper Arkansas, Upper Republican, Upper Smoky Hill, Verdigris</codesetn>
            <codesets>KWO</codesets>
          </codesetd>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Regional planning area abbreviations</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>shortened version of the regional planning area name</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Kansas Water Authority, Kansas Water Office</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <codesetd>
            <codesetn>Ci, Ew, Gb, Ks, Mc, Mo, Ne, Rh, Ss, Sr, Ua, Ur, Us, Ve</codesetn>
            <codesets>KWO</codesets>
          </codesetd>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>2014 average gpcd</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Gallons per capita per day (GPCD) is the average amount of public-supply water used per person per day in 2014 in each regional planning area.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Kansas Water Authority, Kansas Water Office</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>79</rdommin>
            <rdommax>254</rdommax>
            <attrunit>gallons per capita (or per person) per day</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160420</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Jennifer Lanning-Rush</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Kansas Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>4821 Quail Crest Place</address>
          <city>Lawrence</city>
          <state>Kansas</state>
          <postal>66049</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>785-832-3555</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jlanning@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>

