<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Douglas L. Moyer</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Nitrogen, Phosphorus, and Suspended-Sediment Loads and Trends measured in Nine Chesapeake Bay Tributaries: Monthly Loads - Water Years 1985-2015</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Richmond, Va</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7Q81B5N</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Nitrogen, phosphorus, and suspended-sediment loads, and changes in loads, in rivers across the Chesapeake Bay watershed have been calculated using monitoring data from the nine Chesapeake Bay River Input Monitoring (RIM) stations for the period 1985 through 2015. Nutrient and suspended-sediment loads and changes in loads were determined by applying a weighted regression approach called WRTDS (Weighted Regression on  Time, Discharge, and Season).  The load results represent the total mass of nitrogen, phosphorus, and suspended sediment that was exported from each of the nine RIM watersheds.  When summed, the loads from the nine RIM stations represents the total load delivered from nearly eighty-percent of the bay watershed.  To determine the trend in loads, the annual load results are flow normalized to integrate out the year-to-year variability in river discharge.  The trend in load is derived from the  flow-normalized load timeseries and represents the change in load resulting from changes in sources, delays associated with storage or transport of historical inputs, and (or) implemented management actions.</abstract>
      <purpose>The purpose of this data set is to communicate the monthly loads of nitrogen, phosphorus, and suspended-sediment being generated across the nontidal portion of the bay watershed.</purpose>
      <supplinf>This annual update of nitrogen, phosphorus, and suspended-sediment loads and trends is performed in cooperation with Maryland Department of Natural Resources, Virginia Department of Environmental Quality, and Environmental Protection Agency, Chesapeake Bay Program Office.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>19851001</begdate>
          <enddate>20150930</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Annually</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-79.167480469182</westbc>
        <eastbc>-74.904785156852</eastbc>
        <northbc>42.714410712674</northbc>
        <southbc>36.208470061656</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Water Quality</themekey>
        <themekey>Nitrogen Loads</themekey>
        <themekey>Phosphorus Loads</themekey>
        <themekey>Suspended Sediment Loads</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>GNIS</placekt>
        <placekey>Chesapeake Bay</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Douglas L. Moyer</cntper>
          <cntorg>USGS Virginia-West Virginia Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1730 E. Parham Road</address>
          <city>Richmond</city>
          <state>Virginia</state>
          <postal>23228</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>804-261-2634</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>dlmoyer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Methods: Total nitrogen loads were estimated using a weighted regression approach called Weighted Regressions on Time, Discharge, and Season (WRTDS) (Hirsch and others, 2010), which is included in the R (version 3.1.2) software package called EGRET - Exploration and Graphics for River Trends (version 2.5.1) (Hirsch and DeCicco, 2015). The application of WRTDS to generate the results provided in this table is documented in Chanat and others, 2016. Monthly loads were calculated and summed for the period January through May. 

References Cited: Hirsch, R.M., Moyer, D.L., and Archfield, S.A., 2010, Weighted regressions on time, discharge, and season (WRTDS), with an application to Chesapeake Bay river inputs: Journal of the American Water Resources Research Association, v. 46, no. 5, p. 857-880 

Hirsch, R.M. and De Cicco, Laura, 2015, User guide to Exploration and Graphics for RivEr Trends (EGRET) and dataRetrieval: R packages for hydrologic data (version 2.0, February 2015): U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods book 4, chap. A10, 93 p., http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/tm4A10.(accessed May 24, 2016) 

Chanat, J.G., Moyer, D.L., Blomquist, J.D., Hyer, K.E., and Langland, M.J., 2016, Application of a weighted regression model for reporting nutrient and sediment concentrations, fluxes, and trends in concentration and flux for the Chesapeake Bay Nontidal Water-Quality Monitoring Network, results through water year 2012: U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Report 2015-5133, 139 p. http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/sir20155133</procdesc>
        <procdate>20160701</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>RIM2015_MonLoadTab.csv</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Annual nitrogen, phosphorus, and suspended sediment load results for the nine river input monitoring stations</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Douglas L. Moyer, USGS Virginia Water Science Center</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>STAID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>USGS Station ID - where:
 "01491000 - CHOPTANK RIVER NEAR GREENSBORO, MD."
"01578310 - SUSQUEHANNA RIVER AT CONOWINGO, MD."
"01594440 - PATUXENT RIVER NEAR BOWIE, MD."
"01646580 - POTOMAC RIVER AT CHAIN BRIDGE, AT WASHINGTON, D.C."
"01668000 - RAPPAHANNOCK RIVER NEAR FREDEROCKSBURG, VA."
"01673000 - PAMUNKEY RIVER NEAR HANOVER, VA."
"01674500 - MATTAPONI RIVER NEAR BEULAHVILLE, VA."
"02035000 - JAMES RIVER AT CARTERSVILLE, VA."
"02041650 - APPOMATTOX RIVER AT MATOACA, VA."</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS Standard Gaging Station Number</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>USGS Standard Gaging Station Number</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>PCODE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>PCODE = Parameter Code where:
P00600 = Total nitrogen (as N)
P00631 = Nitrate (as N)
P00665 = Total phosphorus (as P)
P00671 = Orthophosphorus (as P)
P80154 = Suspended sediment</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>USGS Standard Constituent Parameter Code</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>USGS Standard Constituent Parameter Code</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Water Year</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Water Year</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Water year (October - September)</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Water year = October - September</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Q</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Q = Mean annual flow for all the days in the year in cubic feet per second (ft3/s),</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Q = Mean annual flow for all the days in the year in cubic feet per second (ft3/s),</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Conc</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Conc = Mean annual concentration for all the days in the year in milligrams per liter (mg/L)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Conc = Mean annual concentration for all the days in the year in milligrams per liter (mg/L)</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Flux</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Flux = Annual load for all the days in the year in pounds per year</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Flux = Annual load for all the days in the year in pounds per year,</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>FNConc</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>FNConc = Flow normalized mean annual concentration for all the days in the year in mg/L</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>FNConc = Flow normalized mean annual concentration for all the days in the year in mg/L</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>FNFlux</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>FNFlux = Flow normalized annual load for all the days in the year in pounds per year</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>FNFlux = Flow normalized annual load for all the days in the year in pounds per year</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>STRAT_YR</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>START_YR = First water year of modeling period used to estimate load</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>START_YR = First water year of modeling period used to estimate load,</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>END_YR</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>END_YR = Last water year of modeling period used to estimate load</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>END_YR = Last water year of modeling period used to estimate load</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Month</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Month = Month of year</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>1</rdommin>
            <rdommax>12</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The USGS or the U.S. Government shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160701</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Douglas L. Moyer</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Supervisory Hydrologist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1730 East Parham Road</address>
          <city>Richmond</city>
          <state>VA</state>
          <postal>23228</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>804-261-2634</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>dlmoyer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>