<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>USGS, Western Ecological Research Center, Dixon Field Station</origin><pubdate>20150901</pubdate><title>Great Basin Sage-Grouse Concentration Areas.</title><geoform>Vector Digital Data Set (Polygon)</geoform><onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7K35RRS</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>Indices of habitat suitability and animal abundance provide useful proxy-based measures adaptive management (Coates et al. 2015a). Doherty et al. (in review) derived a range-wide population index model for sage-grouse using such indices that incorporated sage-grouse habitat suitability generated from Random Forest models (Evans et al. 2011), and spatially explicit abundance measures based on fixed kernel density functions informed by distributions of lek locations (lek locations defined by Western Association of Fish and Wildlife Agencies, see Coates et al. 2015b). The kernels were generated using two bandwidth distances representing the majority of breeding habitat in relation to leks (6.4 km) and seasonal movements (18.0 km). Relationships between abundance indices and the overall population index model were then evaluated to demarcate areas that are the most meaningful to sage-grouse populations (i.e., sage-grouse concentration areas). 
REFERENCES
Coates, P. S., M. L. Casazza, M. A. Ricca, B. E. Brussee, E. J. Blomberg, K. B. Gustafson, C. T. Overton, D. Davis, L. Neill, S. P. Espinosa, S. C. Gardner, and D. J. Delehanty. 2015a. Integrating spatially explicit indices of abundance and habitat quality: an applied example for greater sage-grouse management. J. Appl. Ecol. (available at http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1365-2664.12558/epdf).
Coates, P. S., M. A. Ricca, B. G. Prochazka, K. E. Doherty, M. L. Brooks, and M. L. Casazza. 2015b. Long-term effects of wildfire on greater sage-grouse - integrating population and ecosystem concepts for management in the Great Basin. Report 2015-1165, Reston, VA. http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr20151165 
Doherty, K. E., J. S. Evans, P. S. Coates, L. Juliusson, and B. C. Fedy. In review. Importance of regional variation in conservation planning and defining thresholds for a declining species: a range-wide example of the greater sage-grouse. Ecosphere. 
Evans, J. S., M. A. Murphy, Z. A. Holden, and S. A. Cushman. 2011. Modeling species distribution and change using Random Forests in Predictive species and habitat modeling.in C. A. Drew, W. Y.F., and F. Huettmann editors. Landscape ecology: concepts and applications. Springer, New York.
Vander Wal, E., and A. R. Rodgers. 2012. An individual-based quantitative approach for delineating core areas of animal space use. Ecological Modelling 224:48-53.</abstract><purpose>This dataset identifies sage-grouse concentration areas in the Great Basin, which comprise areas of both high habitat suitability and high population abundance, and can be used to help guide fire suppression and restoration efforts.</purpose><supplinf>Coates, P.S., Ricca, M.A., Prochazka, B.G., Doherty, K. D.,, Brooks, M.L., Casazza, M.L. 2015. Long-term effects of wildfire on greater sage-grouse - integrating population and ecosystem concepts for management in Great Basin. http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr20151165</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>20090101</begdate><enddate>20141201</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><current>ground condition</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-121.928948749</westbc><eastbc>-110.027878197</eastbc><northbc>45.502484679</northbc><southbc>36.409769941</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>Wildfire</themekey><themekey>Monitoring Trends in Widlifire Severity (MTBS)</themekey><themekey>Greater Sage-Grouse</themekey><themekey>Habitat</themekey><themekey>Fire Suppression</themekey></theme><place><placekt>None</placekt><placekey>Great Basin</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>The authors of these data require that users direct any questions pertaining to appropriate use or assistance with understanding limitations and interpretation of the data to the individuals/organization listed in the Point of Contact section.</useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, PACIFIC REGION</cntorg><cntper>Peter S Coates</cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>Research Wildlife Biologist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>800 Business Park Drive</address><city>Dixon</city><state>CA</state><postal>95620</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>530-669-5073</cntvoice><cntfax>707-678-5039</cntfax><cntemail>pcoates@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac><datacred>U.S. Geological Survey, Western Ecological Research Center, Dixon Field Station
U.S. Fish &amp; Wildlife Service, 134 Union Blvd, Lakewood, Colorado U.S.A.</datacred><native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.2.2 (Build 3552) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted.</attraccr></attracc><logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic><complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>The range-wide continuous population index layer was clipped to the Modified Great Basin Extent (Buffered), and extracted isopleths for the percentage of cumulative volume under the layer at 5 percent increments starting at 65 percent using ArcGIS 10.2.2 software. We then overlaid locations of active leks (defined as leks with greater than two males observed in greater than two of the previous 5 years) and pending leks (defined as greater than two males observed only once over the previous 5 years) on the clipped layer and extracted the maximum lek count from 2009 to 2014 as an index of population size within each isopleth class. Active and pending leks (n = 1,896) had at least one count greater than two males during the time interval. For each successive isopleth class, we calculated the ratio of the cumulative increase in population size to cumulative area added to the population index model, and rescaled the ratio between zero and 100. To determine a cut-point for the population index model that represented where sage-grouse density was most concentrated in suitable habitat, we fit an exponential regression using R 3.13 software between population index model isopleth values and the cumulative ratio of increasing population size to area added, and determined where the slope of the line equaled 1.0 (Vander Wal and Rodgers, 2012). The slope equaled 1.0 at the 76.4 percent isopleth, which when rounded to 75 percent was used to demarcate sage-grouse concentration areas, which represent concentrated high quality sage-grouse habitat and high density sage-grouse areas. Sage-grouse concentration comprise &gt; 64,000 km2 of habitat, are estimated to contain 78% of active and pending leks (as of 2014) and 89% of population size (based on male lek attendance). Coates et al. (2015b) describe how increased fire suppression efforts in sage-grouse concentration areas may help slow or halt projected long-term population declines driven by wildfire.
REFERENCES
Coates, P. S., M. L. Casazza, M. A. Ricca, B. E. Brussee, E. J. Blomberg, K. B. Gustafson, C. T. Overton, D. Davis, L. Neill, S. P. Espinosa, S. C. Gardner, and D. J. Delehanty. 2015a. Integrating spatially explicit indices of abundance and habitat quality: an applied example for greater sage-grouse management. J. Appl. Ecol. (available at http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1365-2664.12558/epdf).
Coates, P. S., M. A. Ricca, B. G. Prochazka, K. E. Doherty, M. L. Brooks, and M. L. Casazza. 2015b. Long-term effects of wildfire on greater sage-grouse - integrating population and ecosystem concepts for management in the Great Basin. Report 2015-1165, Reston, VA. http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr20151165 
Doherty, K. E., J. S. Evans, P. S. Coates, L. Juliusson, and B. C. Fedy. In review. Importance of regional variation in conservation planning and defining thresholds for a declining species: a range-wide example of the greater sage-grouse. Ecosphere. 
Evans, J. S., M. A. Murphy, Z. A. Holden, and S. A. Cushman. 2011. Modeling species distribution and change using Random Forests in Predictive species and habitat modeling.in C. A. Drew, W. Y.F., and F. Huettmann editors. Landscape ecology: concepts and applications. Springer, New York.
Vander Wal, E., and A. R. Rodgers. 2012. An individual-based quantitative approach for delineating core areas of animal space use. Ecological Modelling 224:48-53.</procdesc><procdate>20150701</procdate></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><direct>Vector</direct><ptvctinf><sdtsterm><sdtstype>G-polygon</sdtstype><ptvctcnt>1</ptvctcnt></sdtsterm></ptvctinf></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><planar><mapproj><mapprojn>North American 1983 Albers (ESRI Full Name: North_American_1983_Albers)</mapprojn><albers><stdparll>29.5</stdparll><stdparll>45.5</stdparll><longcm>-96.0</longcm><latprjo>23.0</latprjo><feast>0.0</feast><fnorth>0.0</fnorth></albers></mapproj><planci><plance>coordinate pair</plance><coordrep><absres>0.6096</absres><ordres>0.6096</ordres></coordrep><plandu>Meter</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>D_North_American_1983</horizdn><ellips>GRS_1980</ellips><semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis><denflat>298.257222101</denflat></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl><enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd><enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl><attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef><attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>1</rdommin><rdommax>1</rdommax></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>ISO</attrlabl><attrdef>Isopleth value</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>75</rdommin><rdommax>75</rdommax><attrunit>percent</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape_Leng</attrlabl><attrdef>Unknown</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>18045112.6671</rdommin><rdommax>18045112.6671</rdommax></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape_Area</attrlabl><attrdef>Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef><attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>64858189132</rdommin><rdommax>64858189132</rdommax></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>ACRES</attrlabl><attrdef>Acres</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>16026807.5667</rdommin><rdommax>16026807.5667</rdommax><attrunit>Acres</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr></detailed><overview><eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes the tabular data associated with the data set. Please review the detailed descriptions that are provided (the individual attribute descriptions) for information on the values that appear as fields/table entries of the data set.</eaover><eadetcit>The entity and attribute information was generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Please review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><distrib><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg></cntorgp><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>Denver Federal Center</address><address>Building 810</address><address>Mail Stop 302</address><city>Denver</city><state>CO</state><postal>80225</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice><cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib><distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Vector Digital Data Set (Polygon)</formname></digtinfo><digtopt><onlinopt><computer><networka><networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7K35RRS</networkr></networka></computer></onlinopt></digtopt></digform><fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees></stdorder></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20160127</metd><metc><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, PACIFIC REGION</cntorg><cntper>Mark Ricca</cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>Wildlife Biologist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>800 Business Park Drive</address><city>Dixon</city><state>CA</state><postal>95620</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>530-669-5089</cntvoice><cntfax>707-678-5039</cntfax><cntemail>mark_ricca@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></metc><metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv><mettc>local time</mettc></metainfo></metadata>