<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
 <idinfo>
  <citation>
   <citeinfo>
    <origin>M. Tim Tinker</origin>
    <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
    <title>Geospatial data collected from tagged sea otters in central California, 1998-2012</title>
    <geoform>Tabular Digital Data</geoform>
    <onlink>http://www.dx.doi.org/10.5066/F76H4FH8</onlink>
    <lworkcit>
     <citeinfo>
      <origin>Tinker, M. T.</origin>
      <origin>D. F. Doak</origin>
      <origin>J. A. Estes</origin>
      <pubdate>20081001</pubdate>
      <title>Using demography and movement behavior to predict range expansion of the southern sea otter.</title>
      <geoform>Publication (Journal)</geoform>
      <serinfo>
       <sername>Ecological Applications</sername>
       <issue>18(7), pp. 1781-1794</issue>
      </serinfo>
      <pubinfo>
       <pubplace>Washington, DC</pubplace>
       <publish>Ecological Society of America</publish>
      </pubinfo>
      <onlink>http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1890/07-0735.1/pdf</onlink>
     </citeinfo>
    </lworkcit>
   </citeinfo>
  </citation>
  <descript>
   <abstract>The data are .csv files of tagged sea otter re-sighting locations (henceforth, resights) collected in the field using a combination of VHF radio telemetry and direct observation using high powered (80x) telescopes.  Sea otters were tracked by shore based observers from the date of tagging until the time of radio battery failure or the animal’s death, whichever comes first. The frequency of re-sighting was opportunistic, depending on logistical factors such as coastal access, but generally ranged from daily to weekly.  Location coordinates are reported as X and Y coordinates in the projection/datum California Teale-Albers NAD 1927. Each file contains resight data for one individual sea otter collected over a period of 1-10 years. Fields include individual identification number, geographic coordinates, the date and time of the sighting location, and associated behavioral state of the individual at the time of re-sighting.</abstract>
   <purpose>All data were collected as part of population studies led by the U.S. Geological Survey, in collaboration with the Monterey Bay Aquarium, UC Santa Cruz and California Dept. of Fish and Wildlife, with the overall goal of understanding factors affecting population recovery. Separate research studies were conducted under this broader umbrella research program, whose goals were often more specific (e.g. understanding the impacts of specific stressors in particular areas of the sea otters range).  By tagging and monitoring individual sea otters over multiple years, the researchers were able to describe spatial ecology (e.g. movements and habitat use patterns), behavior (e,g, time-activity budgets, diet choice) and demographic parameters including survival and reproductive rates.  The resight data files here have been used previously for statistical analysis of individual home ranges, habitat selection behavior and movement behavior via biased correlated random walk models.</purpose>
  </descript>
  <timeperd>
   <timeinfo>
    <rngdates>
     <begdate>1998</begdate>
     <enddate>2012</enddate>
    </rngdates>
   </timeinfo>
   <current>ground condition</current>
  </timeperd>
  <status>
   <progress>In work</progress>
   <update>Irregular</update>
  </status>
  <spdom>
   <bounding>
    <westbc>-122.502403</westbc>
    <eastbc>-119.373150</eastbc>
    <northbc>37.491854</northbc>
    <southbc>33.196258</southbc>
   </bounding>
  </spdom>
  <keywords>
   <theme>
    <themekt>None</themekt>
    <themekey>Southern sea otter</themekey>
    <themekey>sighting locations</themekey>
    <themekey>VHF radio telemetry</themekey>
    <themekey>space use</themekey>
    <themekey>animal movement</themekey>
   </theme>
   <place>
    <placekt>Common geographic areas</placekt>
    <placekey>California</placekey>
    <placekey>Santa Barbara</placekey>
    <placekey>Santa Barbara Channel Islands</placekey>
   </place>
   <place>
    <placekt>None</placekt>
    <placekey>Half Moon Bay</placekey>
   </place>
  </keywords>
  <accconst>The data report locations of tagged southern sea otters (Enhydra lutris nereis) which are listed as threatened by IUCN and are protected under the Marine Mammal Protection Act.  Because the data were collected by U.S. Geological Survey biologists in collaboration with biologists from collaborating organizations, including Monterey Bay Aquarium and UC Santa Cruz, there are issues of data ownership and appropriate acknowledgement for data useage that may vary from file to file.  Researchers wishing to use the data are encouraged to contact the owners to acquire appropriate data permissions and also obtain additional meta-data for tagged sea otters.</accconst>
  <useconst>The authors of these data require that users direct any questions pertaining to appropriate use or assistance with understanding limitations and interpretation of the data to the individuals/organization listed in the Point of Contact section.</useconst>
  <ptcontac>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntorgp>
     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, PACIFIC REGION</cntorg>
     <cntper>M. Tim Tinker</cntper>
    </cntorgp>
    <cntpos>Supv. Research Wildlife Biologist</cntpos>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
     <address>100 Shaffer Road</address>
     <city>Santa Cruz</city>
     <state>CA</state>
     <postal>95060</postal>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>831-459-2357</cntvoice>
    <cntfax>831-459-2249</cntfax>
    <cntemail>ttinker@usgs.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
  </ptcontac>
  <datacred>Monterey Bay Aquarium Sea Otter Research and Conservation department, 
contact: Michelle Staedler
University of California Santa Cruz, Dept. Ecology and Evolutionary Biology 
contact: M. Tim Tinker</datacred>
  <native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.2.2 (Build 3552) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native>
 </idinfo>
 <dataqual>
  <attracc>
   <attraccr>All data were spot checked by researchers upon entry into the database. Occasional errors observed included 180 degree flips in compass bearings caused by faulty compasses: these points were easily identified (due to their terrestrial location) and removed from the dataset.  GIS coordinates for each data point were computed based on compass bearing and distance (determined by laser range finder) from observer, but additional descriptive data fields (distance from shore, local study site) allowed for cross checking to ensure that the GIS coordinates of each individual resight matched the descriptive data fields.</attraccr>
  </attracc>
  <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic>
  <complete>The data to be uploaded is a subset of the larger dataset. At this time we have included only animals at two locations (Big Sur and Monterey Bay, CA) that have a minimum of 20 sighting locations over a 2-year period.  These data are provided according to data accessibility policy, in association with the following manuscript:
Tarjan, L. M. and Tinker, M. T. Permissible Home Range Estimation (PHRE) in restricted habitats: a new algorithm and an evaluation for sea otters (Enhydra lutris). (In Rev. PLOS ONE)</complete>
  <posacc>
   <horizpa>
    <horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</horizpar>
   </horizpa>
   <vertacc>
    <vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr>
   </vertacc>
  </posacc>
  <lineage>
   <procstep>
    <procdesc>Raw data are initially entered into hand-help field computers at the time of observation at the field site.  Data are then uploaded on a daily basis to an Access relational database application (“Wild Sea Otter Database”), with error checking for quality control occuring on a weekly basis by field team supervisors, who review daily resight data in GIS to ensure accuracy, and delete any erroneous data points.  Data for individual otters were then extracted from this database and saved to csv files over the period October 2014 - July 2015.</procdesc>
    <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
   </procstep>
  </lineage>
 </dataqual>
 <eainfo>
  <detailed>
   <enttyp>
    <enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl>
    <enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd>
    <enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
   </enttyp>
   <attr>
    <attrlabl>FIXNUM</attrlabl>
    <attrdef>Unique identifier for a particular re-sighting event for a particular sea otter. Primary key for data table in relational database.</attrdef>
    <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
    <attrdomv>
     <udom>Unique ID</udom>
    </attrdomv>
   </attr>
   <attr>
    <attrlabl>OTTERNO</attrlabl>
    <attrdef>Unique identifying code for each individual sea otter, assigned at time of first capture by U.S. Geological Survey Biologists.  Number can be used to cross reference geospatial data with other types of data or with biological samples collected during tagging event.</attrdef>
    <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
    <attrdomv>
     <udom>Unique ID</udom>
    </attrdomv>
   </attr>
   <attr>
    <attrlabl>OTTERNAME</attrlabl>
    <attrdef>Additional identifying text or number used to designate an individual tagged southern sea otters</attrdef>
    <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
    <attrdomv>
     <udom>Identifier</udom>
    </attrdomv>
   </attr>
   <attr>
    <attrlabl>Date</attrlabl>
    <attrdef>Date that a re-sight observation of an individual sea otter is collected. Example : 7/24/00</attrdef>
    <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
    <attrdomv>
     <rdom>
      <rdommin>6/29/2000</rdommin>
      <rdommax>4/9/2012</rdommax>
      <attrunit>date</attrunit>
     </rdom>
    </attrdomv>
   </attr>
   <attr>
    <attrlabl>STATUS</attrlabl>
    <attrdef>demographic classification of focal animal, entered as one of 8 codes.</attrdef>
    <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>d</edomv>
      <edomvd>dependent pup</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>f</edomv>
      <edomvd>single female</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>l</edomv>
      <edomvd>female with large pup</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>m</edomv>
      <edomvd>Single Male</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>p</edomv>
      <edomvd>female with pup</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>r</edomv>
      <edomvd>Rehab otter</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>s</edomv>
      <edomvd>female with small pup</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>t</edomv>
      <edomvd>territorial male (determined based on characteristic behaviors such as patrolling)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>u</edomv>
      <edomvd>undetermined status</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>x</edomv>
      <edomvd>female, unknown if parous</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>y</edomv>
      <edomvd>female with dead pup</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>z</edomv>
      <edomvd>dead (carcass only)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
   </attr>
   <attr>
    <attrlabl>ACTIV</attrlabl>
    <attrdef>General designation of instantaneous behavior of focal animal at time of resight, classified as either “active” or “inactive”</attrdef>
    <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>a</edomv>
      <edomvd>active</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>i</edomv>
      <edomvd>inactive (passive grooming, resting, suckling body parts)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>u</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
   </attr>
   <attr>
    <attrlabl>BEHAV</attrlabl>
    <attrdef>Specific designation of instantaneous behavior of focal animal at time of resight, classified as one of 16 codes;
Note: * codes entered based on radio signal only, with no visual made of otter.</attrdef>
    <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>b</edomv>
      <edomvd>suckling body parts</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>c</edomv>
      <edomvd>pacing/swimming back and forth (nervous behavior)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>d</edomv>
      <edomvd>female grooming pup</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>e</edomv>
      <edomvd>female-pup interaction(not grooming or nursing)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>f</edomv>
      <edomvd>foraging (Note: Activ code must be "a")</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>g</edomv>
      <edomvd>grooming</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>gt</edomv>
      <edomvd>grooming while swimming</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>h</edomv>
      <edomvd>hauled out on land</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>i</edomv>
      <edomvd>otter interacting with another otter (not pup)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>l</edomv>
      <edomvd>stress roll grooming</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>m</edomv>
      <edomvd>mounting or copulatory behavior</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>n</edomv>
      <edomvd>female nursing pup</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>o</edomv>
      <edomvd>other behavior (but NOT feeding)*</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>p</edomv>
      <edomvd>person interacting with otter</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>r</edomv>
      <edomvd>resting or sleeping</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>s</edomv>
      <edomvd>swimming/travelling</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>sc</edomv>
      <edomvd>sculling, forelimbs and head dry, swimming with tail and/or hind flipper</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>sw</edomv>
      <edomvd>directional surface belly swimming</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>u</edomv>
      <edomvd>unknown behavior *</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>x</edomv>
      <edomvd>being sniffed or nosed by another otter</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
   </attr>
   <attr>
    <attrlabl>Xcoord</attrlabl>
    <attrdef>X coordinate of the point location with projection/datum California Teale-Albers NAD 1927</attrdef>
    <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
    <attrdomv>
     <rdom>
      <rdommin>-207893.5078</rdommin>
      <rdommax>-74986.43559</rdommax>
      <attrunit>meters</attrunit>
     </rdom>
    </attrdomv>
   </attr>
   <attr>
    <attrlabl>Ycoord</attrlabl>
    <attrdef>Y coordinate of the point location with projection/datum California Teale-Albers NAD 1927</attrdef>
    <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
    <attrdomv>
     <rdom>
      <rdommin>-314568.7544</rdommin>
      <rdommax>-97839.54198</rdommax>
      <attrunit>meters</attrunit>
     </rdom>
    </attrdomv>
   </attr>
  </detailed>
  <overview>
   <eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes the tabular data associated with the data set. Please review the detailed descriptions that are provided (the individual attribute descriptions) for information on the values that appear as fields/table entries of the data set.</eaover>
   <eadetcit>The entity and attribute information was generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Please review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit>
  </overview>
 </eainfo>
 <distinfo>
  <distrib>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntorgp>
     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
    </cntorgp>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
     <address>Denver Federal Center</address>
     <address>Building 810</address>
     <city>Denver</city>
     <state>CO</state>
     <postal>80225</postal>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
    <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
  </distrib>
  <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.
Data are available for use by other researchers, subject to caveats: Because the data were collected by U.S. Geological Survey biologists in collaboration with biologists from collaborating organizations, including Monterey Bay Aquarium and UC Santa Cruz, there are issues of data ownership and appropriate acknowledgement for data useage that may vary from file to file.  Researchers wishing to use the data are encouraged to contact the owners to acquire appropriate data permissions and also obtain additional meta-data for tagged sea otters.</distliab>
  <stdorder>
   <digform>
    <digtinfo>
     <formname>Tabular Digital Data</formname>
    </digtinfo>
    <digtopt>
     <onlinopt>
      <computer>
       <networka>
        <networkr>http://www.dx.doi.org/10.5066/F76H4FH8</networkr>
       </networka>
      </computer>
     </onlinopt>
    </digtopt>
   </digform>
   <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
  </stdorder>
 </distinfo>
 <metainfo>
  <metd>20160309</metd>
  <metc>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntperp>
     <cntper>M. Tim Tinker</cntper>
     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, PACIFIC REGION</cntorg>
    </cntperp>
    <cntpos>Supv. Research Wildlife Biologist</cntpos>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
     <address>100 Shaffer Road</address>
     <city>Santa Cruz</city>
     <state>CA</state>
     <postal>95060</postal>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>831-459-2357</cntvoice>
    <cntfax>831-459-2249</cntfax>
    <cntemail>ttinker@usgs.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
  </metc>
  <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
  <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
 </metainfo>
</metadata>
