<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>R. Blaine McCleskey</origin>
        <pubdate>201605</pubdate>
        <title>Electrical Conductivity Data for the Snake River, Yellowstone National Park and Grand Teton National Park</title>
        <geoform>spreadsheet</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Boulder, CO</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7BC3WMG</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and the National Park Service (NPS) have collaborated on monitoring the chloride flux in the major rivers of Yellowstone National Park by periodically sampling the rivers and analyzing chloride concentrations in discrete water samples since the 1970's. However, restrictions of winter travel, great distances between sites, and sampling and analytical costs have limited collection to approximately 28 samples per site annually. Electrical conductivity data can be used as a proxy for chloride concentrations in many of the major rivers of Yellowstone National Park. Electrical conductivity is a measure of the ability of water to pass an electrical current, and it is affected by the presence of inorganic ions such as chloride and other geothermal solutes. In 2012, an electrical conductivity probe was installed in the Snake River above Jackson Lake near Flagg Ranch. Continuous (every 15 minutes) electrical conductivity measurements provide high-resolution data that can be used to rapidly calculate chloride flux in the Snake River.</abstract>
      <purpose>The purpose of this dataset is to provide chemical data and electrical conductivity monitoring data from a site along the Snake River above Jackson Lake near Flagg Ranch, Grand Teton National Park. The site location (Latitude 44°6'0.3", Longitude 110°40'6.6" (NAD83)) is approximately 90 meters downstream from USGS gaging station 13010065. For additional information on the methods used to collect and analyze samples, equipment utilized, and quality-assurance and quality-control procedures see the following publication [http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.apgeochem.2012.07.019].</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20120928</begdate>
          <enddate>20150930</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>observed</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>In work</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>44.1</westbc>
        <eastbc>44.1</eastbc>
        <northbc>110.668</northbc>
        <southbc>110.668</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Chloride Flux Yellowstone National Park</themekt>
        <themekey>electrical conductivity</themekey>
        <themekey>specific conductance</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekey>Yellowstone National Park</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>R. Blaine McCleskey</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>3215 Marine St.</address>
          <city>Boulder</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80303</postal>
          <country>Boulder</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(303) 541-3079</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>rbmccles@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Continuous data was checked against discrete measurements multiple times annually.</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>with GPS</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>n/a</methtype>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>The electrical conductivity was downloaded to a field computer and the data converted to *.csv.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20151001</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Continuous (every 15-minute) electrical conductivity (µS/cm) and temperature (°C) data</eaover>
      <eadetcit>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7BC3WMG (SnakeRiverElectricalConductivity.csv)</eadetcit>
    </overview>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Results of water analyses for the Snake River near Flagg Ranch, 2012 – 2015. Data includes sample collection date and time, pH, electrical conductivity, and concentrations of calcium, magnesium, sodium, potassium, chloride, sulfate, alkalinity, fluoride, nitrate, bromide, iron, silica, boron, aluminum, lithium, strontium, barium, rubidium, manganese, molybdenum, copper, zinc, cadmium, cobalt, chromium, lead, nickel, vanadium arsenic, antimony, and beryllium. The charge imbalance and electrical conductivity balance are also reported.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7BC3WMG (SnakeRiverChemicalData.csv)</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>ScienceBase</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items must be secured from the copyright owner whenever applicable. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although the data have been subjected to rigorous review and are substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, the data are released on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from authorized or unauthorized use. Although the data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Users of the data are advised to read all metadata and associated documentation thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160518</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Richard Blaine McCleskey</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Research Chemist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>3215 Marine St.</address>
          <city>Boulder</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80303</postal>
          <country>Boulder</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(303)541-3079</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>rbmccles@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>

