<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Gordon Reese</origin>
        <origin>Benjamin Rashford</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Projected row crop proportions under climate change used in developing wetland density projections</title>
        <geoform>Tabular Digital Data</geoform>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7VX0DMQ</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Helen R. Sofaer</origin>
            <origin>Susan K. Skagen</origin>
            <origin>Joseph J. Barsugli</origin>
            <origin>Benjamin S. Rashford</origin>
            <origin>Gordon C. Reese</origin>
            <origin>Jennifer A. Hoeting</origin>
            <origin>Andrew W. Wood</origin>
            <origin>Barry R. Noon</origin>
            <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
            <title>Projected wetland densities under climate change: habitat loss but little geographic shift in conservation strategy</title>
            <geoform>Publication (Journal)</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>Ecological Applications</sername>
              <issue>Not yet known</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>USA</pubplace>
              <publish>Wiley</publish>
            </pubinfo>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The impact of climate change on land conversion was assessed by projecting the land-use model under GCM hindcast and forecast climatic conditions. For each GCM, we projected future row crop proportions under 40 years of average hindcast conditions (i.e., assuming historical climate prevails into the future), and under 20 year of average hindcast conditions followed by 20 years of average forecast conditions. We used twenty years of forecast conditions to avoid assuming that climate changes projected for mid-century would have occurred immediately. The 20-20 assumption approximates a linear transition from the historic to future climate and is not limiting since the probabilities will converge given sufficient years under a given climate regime. Projected climate change impacts differed in direction and spatial pattern between GCMs (Fig. S3). Projected changes in the proportion of the landscape planted in row crops were generally small (mean change = 0.01), but included increases of over 0.25 of the landscape and declines of over 0.3 of the landscape (Fig. S3). Conversion probabilities responded to precipitation as expected, with an increase in precipitation associated with higher probabilities that grass converts to crops and lower probabilities that crops convert to grass.</abstract>
      <purpose>Projections used to evaluate how altered land use in response to climate change could affect wetland densities in the Prairie Pothole Region.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>19710101</begdate>
          <enddate>20701231</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>projected</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Prairie Pothole Region</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-113.1875</westbc>
        <eastbc>-96.6875
</eastbc>
        <northbc>48.8125
</northbc>
        <southbc>43.1875</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>effects of climate change</themekey>
        <themekey>agriculture</themekey>
        <themekey>land use change</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Prairie Pothole Region</placekey>
      </place>
      <place>
        <placekt>Common geographic areas</placekt>
        <placekey>North Dakota</placekey>
        <placekey>South Dakota</placekey>
        <placekey>Montana</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None. Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</accconst>
    <useconst>None. Users are advised to read the data set's metadata thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Southwest Region</cntorg>
          <cntper>Gordon C Reese</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>Science Technician</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>2150 Centre Avenue Bldg C</address>
          <city>Fort Collins</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80526</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>970-226-9257</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>970-226-9230</cntfax>
        <cntemail>greese@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>Funding for this work was provided by the North Central Climate Science Center (G13AC00390 and G12AC20504).</datacred>
    <native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1 (Build 4959) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Quality control identified cells in the Cropland Database Layer with transitions likely to represent processing errors; these cells were excluded from the pool from which a random sample was drawn for modeling the processes affecting land use transitions.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>USDA</origin>
            <pubdate>20140101</pubdate>
            <title>Cropland Data Layer</title>
            <geoform>Raster Digital Data Set</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>online</pubplace>
              <publish>USDA</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.nass.usda.gov/Research_and_Science/Cropland/SARS1a.php</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2006</begdate>
              <enddate>2013</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Source Input 1</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Source information used in support of the development of the data set.</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Maurer, E. P., L. Brekke, T. Pruitt, and P. B. Duffy</origin>
            <pubdate>20130101</pubdate>
            <title>Climate Projections</title>
            <geoform>Raster Digital Data Set</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>USA</pubplace>
              <publish>Bureau of Reclamation</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://gdo-dcp.ucllnl.org/downscaled_cmip_projections/dcpInterface.html</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>19710101</begdate>
              <enddate>20701231</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>projected</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Source Input 2</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Source information used in support of the development of the data set.</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>For each GCM, we projected future row crop proportions under 40 years of average hindcast conditions (i.e., assuming historical climate prevails into the future), and under 20 year of average hindcast conditions followed by 20 years of average forecast conditions. We used twenty years of forecast conditions to avoid assuming that climate changes projected for mid-century would have occurred immediately.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20140101</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>F1</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>row number</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>This column added by default by write.csv in R</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>S_T_S</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Segment ID</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Concatenation of Statrum, Transect, and Segment in USFWS Waterfowl Breeding Population and Habitat Survey (Traditional Strata only)</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GCM</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Global Climate Model ID</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Name of each of the 10 climate models used to develop land use projections under climate change</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TimePeriod</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Time period for projections of row crop proportions</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>20H20F</edomv>
            <edomvd>These projections were based on 20 yrs of mean conditions from the GCM historical simulation followed by 20 yrs of mean conditions in the future simulation (20H20F).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>40H0F</edomv>
            <edomvd>These projections were based on 40 yrs of mean conditions from the hindcast simulation (40H0F).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ProjPropCrop</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Projected proportion of row crops in survey area for each  USFWS Waterfowl Breeding Population and Habitat Survey segment under each climate scenario.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>0.834</rdommax>
            <attrunit>proportion</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <overview>
      <eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes the tabular data associated with the data set. Please review the detailed descriptions that are provided (the individual attribute descriptions) for information on the values that appear as fields/table entries of the data set.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>The entity and attribute information was generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Please review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
          <cntper>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center</address>
          <address>Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items must be secured from the copyright owner whenever applicable. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although the data have been subjected to rigorous review and are substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, the data are released on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from authorized or unauthorized use. Although the data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Users of the data are advised to read all metadata and associated documentation thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Tabular Digital Data</formname>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7VX0DMQ</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160401</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>GS-RMA-FORT Data Management</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>FORT Metadata Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>U.S. Geological Survey, Fort Collins Science Center (FORT)</address>
          <address>2150 Centre Avenue, Bldg C</address>
          <city>Fort Collins</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80521</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(970) 226-9100</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>fortdatamanagement@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>