<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
	<idinfo>
		<citation>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin> U.S. Geological Survey, Lower Mississippi and Gulf Water Science Center</origin>
				<origin>Jennifer Cartwright</origin>
				<pubdate>20131202</pubdate>
				<title>Volumetric soil water content, measured both by time-domain reflectometry and by thermogravimetric anaysis, for 120 point locations within limestone cedar glades at Stones River National Battlefield near Murfreesboro, Tennessee</title>
				<geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
				<othercit>Recommended citation: 
J. Cartwright. 2015, Volumetric soil water content, measured both by time-domain reflectometry and by thermogravimetric anaysis, for 120 point locations within limestone cedar glades at Stones River National Battlefield near Murfreesboro, Tennessee: U.S. Geological Survey Data Release, http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7NV9G9C </othercit>
				<onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7NV9G9C </onlink>
				<lworkcit>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin> U.S. Geological Survey, Lower Mississippi and Gulf Water Science Center</origin>
						<pubdate>2015</pubdate>
						<title>2015 Hydrologic and soil data collected in limestone cedar glades at Stones River National Battlefield, Tennessee (USGS Data Release)</title>
						<onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7NV9G9C </onlink>
					</citeinfo>
				</lworkcit>
			</citeinfo>
		</citation>
		<descript>
			<abstract>This dataset contains data collected within limestone cedar glades at Stones River National Battlefield (STRI) near Murfreesboro, Tennessee. This dataset contains measurements of volumetric soil water content at certain quadrat locations (points) within 12 selected cedar glades. For points at which soil water content was measured by thermogravimetric analysis (oven-drying), which are points indicated by the code OD in the field SWC_Meth, the soil-water-content values contained in this dataset are identical to those for the matching dates and points in the file STRI_Glades_Soil_Water_Content_OD.shp. For details on the procedure used to calculate volumetric soil water content using the thermogravimetric method, see the description paragraph in the metadata section of the dataset STRI_Glades_Soil_Water_Content_OD.shp. For points at which soil water content was measured by portable time-domain reflectometry (points for which the field SWC_Meth has the code TDR), the values in this dataset represent the oven-drying equivalent of the time-domain-reflectometry-measured soil water content values in the file STRI_Glades_Soil_Water_Content_TDR.shp, calculated using a specially-formulated calibration curve (described below). For details on the procedure used to measure volumetric soil water content using the portable time-domain-reflectometry method, see the description paragraph in the metadata section of the dataset STRI_Glades_Soil_Water_Content_TDR.shp. To enable comparisons of soil water content between points which were measured using different methods (time-domain-reflectometry at some points and oven-drying at others), a calibration curve was established between the two methods. Forty-eight paired measurements used to establish the calibration curve were obtained on four dates: November 10, 2011; November 15, 2011; January 15, 2013; and May 29, 2013. Calibration measurements were obtained separately, and on separate days, from routine field visits. However, the methods employed to obtain calibration measurements by time-domain-reflectometry and thermogravimentric methods were identical to those described in the metadata sections of STRI_Glades_Soil_Water_Content_TDR.shp and STRI_Glades_Soil_Water_Content_OD.shp, respectively. Soil-water-content measurements by both methods were natural-log transformed prior to fitting a linear calibration curve. The R-squared value for the calibration curve was 0.9547 and the equation established between the two methods, which was subsequently used to convert time-domain-reflectometry measurements to thermogravimetric equivalents, was: Ln (SWC_OD) = 1.6881 (Ln (SWC_TDR)) – 2.7187, where SWC_TDR is the volumetric soil water content measured by time-domain-reflectometry (expressed as volumetric percent) and SWC_OD is the volumetric soil water content calculated from bulk density and gravimetric soil water content as measured by oven drying (also expressed as volumetric percent).Detailed descriptions of experimental design, field data collection procedures, laboratory procedures, and data analysis are presented in Cartwright (2014).References:Cartwright, J. (2014). Soil ecology of a rock outcrop ecosystem: abiotic stresses, soil respiration, and microbial community profiles in limestone cedar glades. Ph.D. dissertation, Tennessee State University.Cofer, M., Walck, J., and Hidayati, S. (2008). Species richness and exotic species invasion in Middle Tennessee cedar glades in relation to abiotic and biotic factors. The Journal of the Torrey Botanical Society, 135(4), 540–553.</abstract>
			<purpose>This dataset was developed by the U.S. Geological Survey Tennessee Water Science Center (TNWSC) in partnership with the National Park Service staff at Stones River National Battlefield (STRI) for the purpose of characterizing seasonal patterns of soil water content for a subset of limestone cedar glades present within STRI.</purpose>
		</descript>
		<timeperd>
			<timeinfo>
				<rngdates>
					<begdate>20120206</begdate>
					<enddate>20130513</enddate>
				</rngdates>
			</timeinfo>
			<current>Soil water content measurements were obtained from February 6 2012 through May 13 2013.</current>
		</timeperd>
		<status>
			<progress>Complete</progress>
			<update>None planned</update>
		</status>
		<spdom>
			<bounding>
				<westbc>-86.439035</westbc>
				<eastbc>-86.433061</eastbc>
				<northbc>35.874084</northbc>
				<southbc>35.870747</southbc>
			</bounding>
		</spdom>
		<keywords>
			<theme>
				<themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
				<themekey>environment</themekey>
				<themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
			</theme>
			<place>
				<placekt>None</placekt>
				<placekey>Stones River National Battlefiled, STRI</placekey>
			</place>
		</keywords>
		<accconst>None</accconst>
		<useconst>No portion of this dataset may be copied, distributed, published, publicly presented, or cited without express written authorization from the U.S. Geological Survey. Use of trade, firm, or product names is for the purpose of identification only and implies no endorsement by the U.S. Government.</useconst>
		<ptcontac>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntorgp>
					<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Tennessee Water Science Center (TNWSC) </cntorg>
					<cntper>Jennifer Cartwright</cntper>
				</cntorgp>
				<cntpos>Biologist</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>unknown</addrtype>
					<address>640 Grassmere Park, Suite 100</address>
					<city>Nashville</city>
					<state>TN</state>
					<postal>37211</postal>
					<country>USA</country>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>(615) 383-5761</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>jmcart@usgs.gov</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</ptcontac>
		<datacred>Jennifer Cartwright, U.S. Geological Survey Tennessee Water Science Center (TNWSC) tn.water.usgs.gov 640 Grassmere Park, Suite 100 Nashville, TN 37211 (615) 837-4700</datacred>
		<native>Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.2.1.3497</native>
	</idinfo>
	<dataqual>
		<attracc>
			<attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted.</attraccr>
		</attracc>
		<logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic>
		<complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
		<posacc>
			<horizpa>
				<horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</horizpar>
			</horizpa>
			<vertacc>
				<vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr>
			</vertacc>
		</posacc>
		<lineage>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>An unpublished polygon shapefile of 40 limestone glades within Stones River National Battlefield was acquired (National Park Service, undated). Following preliminary field visits to determine accessibility, 12 of the 40 glades were chosen for study (for details on glade selection methodology see Cartwright, 2014). The ArcGIS Buffer tool (Esri, 2010) was used to create a 3-meter buffer around each glade polygon. The ArcGIS Create Random Points tool (Esri, 2010) was used to create a point feature class of 120 random sampling locations within and near the 12 glades; 80% of the points were generated within the glade interiors, and 20% of the points were generated within their 3-meter buffers. Detailed descriptions of experimental design, field data collection procedures, laboratory procedures, and data analysis are presented in Cartwright (2014). For details about tabular attributes included in this data set, see the entity and attributes section of this metadata document. 

References 

Cartwright, J. (2014). Soil ecology of a rock outcrop ecosystem: abiotic stresses, soil respiration, and microbial community profiles in limestone cedar glades. Ph.D. dissertation, Tennessee State University. 

Esri, 2010, ArcGIS: Release 10. Redlands, CA: Esri. 

National Park Service, undated, Unpublished polygon shapefile of 40 limestone glades at Stones River National Battlefield.</procdesc>
				<procdate>20111101</procdate>
			</procstep>
		</lineage>
	</dataqual>
	<spdoinfo>
		<direct>Vector</direct>
		<ptvctinf>
			<sdtsterm>
				<sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
				<ptvctcnt>120</ptvctcnt>
			</sdtsterm>
		</ptvctinf>
	</spdoinfo>
	<spref>
		<horizsys>
			<planar>
				<mapproj>
					<mapprojn>NAD 1983 UTM Zone 16N</mapprojn>
					<transmer>
						<sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
						<longcm>-87.0</longcm>
						<latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
						<feast>500000.0</feast>
						<fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
					</transmer>
				</mapproj>
				<planci>
					<plance>coordinate pair</plance>
					<coordrep>
						<absres>0.000000002220024164500956</absres>
						<ordres>0.000000002220024164500956</ordres>
					</coordrep>
					<plandu>meter</plandu>
				</planci>
			</planar>
			<geodetic>
				<horizdn>D North American 1983</horizdn>
				<ellips>GRS 1980</ellips>
				<semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
				<denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
			</geodetic>
		</horizsys>
	</spref>
	<eainfo>
		<detailed>
			<enttyp>
				<enttypl>STRI_glades_soil_water_content_all</enttypl>
				<enttypd>Tabular Information Associated with the Dataset</enttypd>
				<enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
			</enttyp>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>FID</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>Glade</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Unique identifier according to glade numbering system internal to this study. To cross-reference these glade numbers with a previous numbering system used by the National Park Service and published by Cofer et al (2008), see the accompanying file STRI_glades_point_characterization.shp.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Unique identifier according to glade numbering system internal to this study. To cross-reference these glade numbers with a previous numbering system used by the National Park Service and published by Cofer et al (2008), see the accompanying file STRI_glades_point_characterization.shp.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>Soil</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Indicates whether or not a given point was also used for ongoing lab analysis of soil physical, chemical, and microbiological properties. 1 indicates yes, 0 indicates no.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Indicates whether or not a given point was also used for ongoing lab analysis of soil physical, chemical, and microbiological properties. 1 indicates yes, 0 indicates no.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>SWC_Meth</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Indicates the method by which soil water content was measured at a given point. Time-domain reflectometry measurements are indicated by the code TDR and were made using a portable time-domain reflectometry probe. Oven-drying measurements are indicated by the code OD and were made using gravimetric analysis by oven drying. Direct-observation measurements are indicated by the code DIR and were made by direct observation indicating the presence or absence of standing water upon exposed bedrock. For detailed information on these methods and the calibration procedure used to compare them, see the metadata section of the files STRI_glades_soil_water_content_ALL.shp, STRI_glades_soil_water_content_TDR.shp and STRI_glades_soil_water_content_OD.shp.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Indicates the method by which soil water content was measured at a given point. Time-domain reflectometry measurements are indicated by the code TDR and were made using a portable time-domain reflectometry probe. Oven-drying measurements are indicated by the code OD and were made using gravimetric analysis by oven drying. Direct-observation measurements are indicated by the code DIR and were made by direct observation indicating the presence or absence of standing water upon exposed bedrock. For detailed information on these methods and the calibration procedure used to compare them, see the metadata section of the files STRI_glades_soil_water_content_ALL.shp, STRI_glades_soil_water_content_TDR.shp and STRI_glades_soil_water_content_OD.shp.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>Group</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Indicates the group to which a given point belongs, used to determine when measurements were made according to a rotating sampling schedule. Measurements for points in Group 1 were made on February 6, 2012; May 25, 2012; September 27, 2012; and February 18, 2013. Measurements for points in Group 2 were made on March 5, 2012; June 21, 2012; November 5, 2012; and March 19, 2013. Measurements for points in Group 3 were made on April 2, 2012; July 19, 2012; December 17, 2012; and April 15, 2013. Measurements for points in Group 4 were made on April 23, 2012; August 23, 2012; January 21, 2013; and May 13, 2013.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Indicates the group to which a given point belongs, used to determine when measurements were made according to a rotating sampling schedule. Measurements for points in Group 1 were made on February 6, 2012; May 25, 2012; September 27, 2012; and February 18, 2013. Measurements for points in Group 2 were made on March 5, 2012; June 21, 2012; November 5, 2012; and March 19, 2013. Measurements for points in Group 3 were made on April 2, 2012; July 19, 2012; December 17, 2012; and April 15, 2013. Measurements for points in Group 4 were made on April 23, 2012; August 23, 2012; January 21, 2013; and May 13, 2013.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>Point_Code</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>A 3 or 4 digit code serving as a unique identifier for all points in this study.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>A 3 or 4 digit code serving as a unique identifier for all points in this study.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>020612</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on February 6, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on February 6, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>030512</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on March 5, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on March 5, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>040212</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on April 2, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.
</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on April 2, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>042312</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on April 23, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on April 23, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>052512</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on May 25, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on May 25, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>062112</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on June 21, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on June 21, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>071912</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on July 19, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on July 19, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>082312</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on August 23, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on August 23, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>092712</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on September 27, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on September 27, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>110512</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on November 5, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on November 5, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>121712</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on December 17, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on December 17, 2012. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>012113</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on January 21, 2013. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on January 21, 2013. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>021813</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on February 18, 2013. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on February 18, 2013. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>031913</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on March 19, 2013. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on March 19, 2013. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>041513</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on April 15, 2013. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on April 15, 2013. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>051313</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on May 13, 2013. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Originator</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Volumetric soil water content for selected points as measured on May 13, 2013. This field contains measurements obtained by portable TDR and also by thermogravimetric analysis. TDR measurements were transformed into oven-drying equivalents using a calibration equation. For details on this calibration procedure, see the description paragraph of the metadata section for this dataset. Missing values are indicated by the value -99999.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
		</detailed>
	</eainfo>
	<distinfo>
		<distrib>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntorgp>
					<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
				</cntorgp>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
					<address>Denver Federal Center</address>
					<address>Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
					<city>Denver</city>
					<state>CO</state>
					<postal>80225</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>1-888-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</distrib>
		<resdesc>unzip file to your computer</resdesc>
		<distliab>Although this data set has been used by the U.S. Geological Survey, U.S. Department of the Interior, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the U.S. Geological Survey as to the accuracy of the data and related materials. The act of distribution shall not constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumed by the U.S. Geological Survey in the use of this data, software, or related materials. Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab>
		<stdorder>
			<digform>
				<digtinfo>
					<formname>ESRI shapefile</formname>
					<formvern>1.0</formvern>
					<filedec>compressed winzip shapefile of data set</filedec>
				</digtinfo>
				<digtopt>
					<onlinopt>
						<computer>
							<networka>
								<networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7NV9G9C </networkr>
							</networka>
						</computer>
					</onlinopt>
				</digtopt>
			</digform>
			<fees>None</fees>
		</stdorder>
	</distinfo>
	<metainfo>
		<metd>20150722</metd>
		<metc>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntorgp>
					<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Tennessee Water Science Center (TNWSC) </cntorg>
					<cntper>Jennifer Cartwright</cntper>
				</cntorgp>
				<cntpos>Biologist</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>unknown</addrtype>
					<address>640 Grassmere Park, Suite 100</address>
					<city>Nashville</city>
					<state>TN</state>
					<postal>37211</postal>
					<country>USA</country>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>(615) 383-5761</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>jmcart@usgs.gov</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</metc>
		<metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
		<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
		<mettc>local time</mettc>
	</metainfo>
	<Esri><CreaDate>20150722</CreaDate><CreaTime>11495300</CreaTime><ArcGISstyle>ISO 19139 Metadata Implementation Specification</ArcGISstyle><SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce><DataProperties><itemProps><itemLocation><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\NWISTN\landeco\CedarGlades\GIS_files_pending\Shapefiles_for_ScienceBase\STRI_glades_soil_water_content_all_metadata</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></itemLocation></itemProps><copyHistory><copy source="\\NWISTN\landeco\CedarGlades\GIS_files_pending\XMLs_for_ScienceBase\STRI_glades_soil_water_content_all_metadata" dest="\\NWISTN\landeco\CedarGlades\GIS_files_pending\Shapefiles_for_ScienceBase\STRI_glades_soil_water_content_all_metadata" date="20150722" time="11495300"></copy></copyHistory></DataProperties></Esri></metadata>
