<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Naomi Nakagaki</origin><origin>Michael E. Wieczorek</origin><origin>Sharon L. Qi</origin><pubdate>201604</pubdate><title>Estimates of subsurface tile drainage extent for the conterminous United States, early 1990s</title><geoform>Raster Digital Data Set</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Sacramento, California</pubplace><publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7RB72QS</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This dataset is a 30-meter resolution national-scale raster of estimated subsurface tile drainage extent based on early 1990s county areas of subsurface tile drains and geospatial datasets of cropland and poorly drained soil. Specifically, it was developed using 1) county-level acres of subsurface tile drain extents from Sugg (2007); 2) the extent of cultivated cropland from the National Land Cover Database (NLCD) 2011; 3) the extent of poorly drained soil from the State Soil Geographic (STATSGO) database Version 2; 4) the extent of federally-owned land, and 5) county administrative boundaries. Sugg's (2007) area of subsurface tile drains within each county was evenly allocated to potentially drained land -- cropland with poorly drained soil. The estimated area of subsurface tile drains in each cell is expressed in square meters. In most cases, the estimated subsurface drainage extent in each cell is less than the actual area of the cell in the raster.

Sugg, Zachary, 2007, Assessing U.S. farm drainage: can GIS lead to better estimates of subsurface drainage extent?: World Resources Institute, Washington D.C., accessed December 2013, at http://www.wri.org/publication/assessing-us-farm-drainage.</abstract><purpose>This dataset was created to provide a geospatial representation of Sugg's tabular data of subsurface drainage extent. Sugg's county areas were allocated spatially over the landscape using similar methodology applied by Sugg, which assumed that row crops cultivated on poorly drained soil indicate the presence of artificial drainage. This dataset was developed in support of the Midwest Stream Quality Assessment (MSQA) study which was conducted as part of the U.S. Geological Survey National Water Quality Assessment (NAWQA) project.</purpose><supplinf>TIME_PERIOD_CONTENT-CURRENTNESS_REFERENCE:  The year 1992 is approximate. Sugg's (2007) source for subsurface tile drainage extent in all counties outside the Midwest states (and a few within the Midwest) were from the 1992 National Resources Inventory (U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1995), and his refinements within the Midwest states for the most part were from geospatial overlays of mapped poorly drained soil and mapped cropland from the NLCD 1992.  Some of his refinements, however, were a result of communications with local experts, and the data year these corresponded to were not documented in his database. In addition, this dataset was developed using up-to-date mapped cropland - NLCD 2011, which is based on imagery from February 2009 through November 2011 (Homer and others, 2015).

BACKGROUND: MSQA is one of several Regional Stream Quality Assessment (RSQA) studies that are part of the USGS National Water Quality Assessment (NAWQA) project. MSQA was a collaboration of NAWQA, the USGS Columbia Environmental Research Center (CERC), and the USEPA National Rivers and Streams Assessment (NRSA). The objective of the MSQA study was to characterize water-quality stressors - contaminants, nutrients, sediment, and habitat and ecological conditions in streams across the Midwest and to determine the relative effects of these stressors on aquatic biota in the streams (U.S. Geological Survey, 2012). One hundred streams in the Midwest study area were sampled during the spring and summer months of 2013.

Environmental characteristics of the sampled sites were quantified to support the hydrologic and ecological analyses and models developed for the MSQA study. One of many physical and anthropogenic characteristics quantified for the MSQA sites was subsurface tile drainage extent. Although subsurface tile drainage improves cropland with poorly drained soil by removing excess water from the soil subsurface, the outflow from tile drains can be high in agricultural chemicals such as nitrogen. Estimates of subsurface drainage extent were needed as input to models predicting agricultural chemicals in streams for the MSQA study area.    

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION: This dataset is a spatial representation of Sugg's (2007) county tabular estimates of subsurface tile drainage extent, where Sugg's areas were allocated and mapped to potentially drained land. But presumably, subsurface tile drainage is not exclusively found on poorly drained cropland nor partially within a grid cell, as depicted in this dataset. In addition, though a small minority, some grid cells have an estimated area of subsurface tile drains greater than the area of the grid cell. Thus, there is considerable uncertainty in this dataset, and it is strongly recommended that the user reviews this metadata document thoroughly prior to using this dataset.

Sugg's dataset was developed by using the county areas of subsurface tile drains from the 1992 National Resources Inventory or 1992 NRI (U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1995) as the starting point. Sugg refined NRI's estimates for many of the counties in the Midwest states by implementing results from geospatial analyses of row crops and poorly drained soil, and information from local experts (Sugg, 2007). Subsequently, this dataset is a spatial representation of Sugg's improved estimates for much of the Midwest states and of the 1992 NRI for the remaining counties that were not refined by Sugg.

Although the objective was to create a spatial representation of Sugg’s tabular estimates of subsurface drainage extent by applying his methodology, slightly different geospatial data sources, namely updated and more recent versions of mapped land cover and soils were implemented to develop this dataset. For mapped row crops, the NLCD 2011 (Homer and others, 2015; U.S. Geological Survey, 2014) was used in place of the NLCD 1992 (Vogelmann and others, 2001). The NLCD 2011 was selected as the source for spatial extent of cropland as it was the most recent version of the NLCD available, and mapping protocols employed to develop NLCD products have improved over the years (Fry and others, 2009). For mapped soils, the U.S. General Soil Map or STATSGO2 (U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2006) was used in place of the original State Soil Geographic (STATSGO) database (U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1994) that Sugg used because it superceded the original STATSGO database. (STATSGO2 was released shortly before Sugg's study was published.)

However, even if the geospatial data sources for land cover and soils matched perfectly, inconsistencies would remain. This is because Sugg (2007) revised his geospatially derived  estimates of subsurface tile drainage extents based on communication with local experts (Sugg, 2007).

For about 85 percent of the counties in the conterminous United States (which includes counties in the Midwest region), Sugg’s areas of subsurface tile drains were obtained from the 1992 NRI. For these counties, federally-owned lands (U.S. Geological Survey, 2005) were excluded in the development of this dataset because the NRI does not record information on Federal lands. 

The remaining 15 percent of the counties reflects Sugg’s revised estimates of subsurface tile drains in the Midwest states. Because Sugg did not document the exclusion of federally-owned land in his estimations of subsurface tile drain extents, federal land was not eliminated for these counties in the development of this dataset.

The geospatial county administrative boundaries for 2010 (Jo Ann Gronberg, U.S.Geological Survey,  written commun., 2012) were overlain with the geospatial potentially drained land to allocate Sugg's county areas of subsurface drainage extent to their respective counties. However,not all counties identified by Sugg as having subsurface tile drains are represented in this dataset: for about 3.5 percent of the counties, subsurface drains could not be mapped due to the absence of geospatial cropland with poorly drained soil (See #2 in the “Use_Constraints” section for additional information regarding these counties.)

Subsequent to Sugg's publication in 2007, Sugg's published tabular dataset was revised to correct for data errors in two states. Specifically, a total of 13 counties in Illinois and 6 counties in Minnesota that were missing data values of subsurface tile drainage extents were populated (Mark B. David, University of IL Urbana-Champaign, written commun., August 2008 and June 2014).

CITED REFERENCES (in the Supplemental Information, Use Constraints, Attribute Accuracy Report,  and Horizontal Positional Accuracy Report sections):

Fry, J.A., Coan, M.J., Homer, C.G., Meyer, D.K., and Wickham, J.D., 2009, Completion of the National Land Cover Database (NLCD) 1992-2001: Land Cover Change Retrofit product: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 2008-1379, 18 p.,available at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2008/1379/pdf/ofr2008-1379.pdf. 

Homer, C.G., Dewitz, J.A., Yang, L., Jin, S., Danielson, P., Xian, G., Coulston, J., Herold, N.D., Wickham, J.D., and Megown, K., 2015, Completion of the 2011 National Land Cover Database for the conterminous United States--Representing a decade of land cover change information. Photogrammetric Engineering and Remote Sensing, v. 81, no. 5, p. 345-354. Also available at http://www.mrlc.gov/nlcd2011.php.

Homer C.H., Fry, J.A., and Barnes, C.A., 2012, The National Land Cover Database, U.S. Geological Survey Fact Sheet 2012-3020, 4 p., available at http://pubs.usgs.gov/fs/2012/3020/.

Sugg, Zachary, 2007, Assessing U.S. farm drainage: can GIS lead to better estimates of subsurface drainage extent?: World Resources Institute, Washington D.C., accessed December 2013, at http://www.wri.org/publication/assessing-us-farm-drainage.

U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1994, State Soil Geographic (STATSGO) Data base -- Data use  information:  U.S.Department of Agriculture, Natural Resources Conservation Service Miscellaneous Publication Number 1492.

U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1995, 1992 National Resources Inventory: Natural Resources Conservation Service, Washington, D.C., and Statistical Laboratory, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa [CDROM].

U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2015, 2012 Census Publications, Desktop Data Query Tool 2.0, accessed August 17, 2015 at http://www.agcensus.usda.gov/Publications/2012/Online_Resources/Desktop_Application/

U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2006, U.S. general soil map (STATSGO2): Natural Resources Conservation Service geospatial data, accessed April 2007, at http://sdmdataaccess.nrcs.usda.gov.

U.S. Geological Survey, 2005, Federal Lands of the United States, U.S. Geological Survey, 1:2,000,000-scale vector digital data, The National Map Small Scale, accessed January 2015, at http://nationalmap.gov/small_scale/mld/fedlanp.html.

U.S. Geological Survey, 2012, The Midwest stream quality assessment: U.S. Geological Survey Fact  Sheet 2012-3124: Reston, VA, 2012; p 2.

U.S. Geological Survey, 2014, National land cover database 2011 (NLCD 2011), raster digital data, accessed February 15, 2015, at http://www.mrlc.gov/nlcd2011.php.

Vogelmann, J.E., S.M. Howard, L. Yang, C. R. Larson, B. K. Wylie, and J. N. Van Driel, 2001, Completion of the 1990's National Land Cover Data Set for the conterminous United States, Photogrammetric Engineering and Remote Sensing 67:650-662.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>1992</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>See Supplemental Info</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-127.977086659</westbc><eastbc>-65.254952344</eastbc><northbc>50.627609837</northbc><southbc>22.768624251</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>subsurface tile drainage</themekey><themekey>subsurface drainage extent</themekey><themekey>tile drain</themekey><themekey>Midwest Stream Quality Assessment</themekey><themekey>MSQA</themekey><themekey>National Water Quality Assessment</themekey><themekey>NAWQA</themekey><themekey>water quality</themekey></theme><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>environment</themekey><themekey>inlandWaters</themekey><themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey></theme><place><placekt>None</placekt><placekey>conterminous United States</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None. Acknowledgment of the U.S. Geological Survey would be appreciated in products derived from these data.</accconst><useconst>1) This dataset was created by allocating Sugg's (2007) county tabular areas of subsurface tile drainage extent to poorly drained cropland. But because subsurface tile drains are presumably not exclusively found on poorly drained cropland, nor evenly distributed in poorly drained cropland within a county, there is considerable uncertainty in this data set.
2) There are 108 counties (3.5 percent of all counties in the conterminous US) for which the subsurface tile drainage extent could not be represented in this dataset due to the absence of mapped cropland with poorly drained soil in these counties. The county areas of unaccounted subsurface tile drainage extent range from 2 to 181,200 acres, with an average of 4,629 acres (19 square kilometers). The 4 counties with the highest acreages are:
a) Imperial County, CA - county FIPS (Federal Information Processing Standard) code 6025 - 181,200 acres (733 square kilometers);
b) Riverside County, CA - county FIPS code 6065 - 37,200 acres (151 square kilometers); 
c) Hidalgo County, TX - county FIPS code 48215- 32,000 acres (129 square kilometers); and
d) Kiowa County, OK - county FIPS code 40075 - 8,300 acres (33 square kilometers)
3) This dataset does not reflect non-cropland areas where subsurface tile drains may be installed.
4) This dataset is based on Sugg's (2007) county tabular data, and the revised estimates for counties in the Midwest states have not been validated (Sugg, 2007). In addition, Sugg's (2007) subsurface drainage area for over 80 percent of conterminous US counties were obtained from the 1992 NRI (U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1995). The NRI is a survey program, and limitations to their survey methods, protocols, and sample design should all be considered before using this dataset. 
5) Although the cells in this raster are 30-by-30 meter in size and accordingly 900 square meters in area, cell values greater than 900 exist in 206 counties. These grid cells represent a greater area of subsurface tile drainage extent than the area of land they represent. Estimating subsurface tile drainage extent within a study area derived by clipping this raster to a study boundary and summing the cell values from the resultant raster could potentially result in a total estimated area of subsurface tile drainage extent greater than the total area of cropland, for example, within the study area.
6) As described in the Supplemental_Information section, Sugg (2007) used the NLCD 1992 (Vogelmann and others, 2001) for the source of mapped cropland whereas the NLCD 2011 (Homer and others, 2015; U.S. Geological Survey, 2014) was used to develop this dataset. One difference between the two NLCD products is the classification of cropland: the 2011 version has a single classification, cultivated crops whereas the NLCD 1992 has 4 classes: row crops, small grains,fallow, and orchards/vineyards/other. Nonetheless, nationally, the NLCD 1992 row crops represents 74 percent of the total area of the 4 cropland classifications; for the 12 Midwest states, 98 percent of the total cropland area is represented by row crops. Therefore, the classification differences between the NLCD 1992 and 2001 did not play a major role in introducing inconsistencies in the 12 Midwest states, but did to some degree elsewhere. 
7) The replacement of the original STATSGO (U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1994) which is what Sugg (2007) used, with STATSGO2 (U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2006), likely contributed to spatial and attribute inconsistencies because of potential differences in soil-map-unit boundaries and soil-property quantifications between the two versions. 
8) Please refer to the Horizontal_Positional_Accuracy section for information regarding the accuracy limitations of the NLCD (source for mapped cropland) and STATSGO2 (source for mapped soils) datasets.
9) State-level comparisons in the Midwest between Sugg's (2007) estimated areas of subsurface tile drains and the 2012 Census of Agriculture (U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2015) acres of land drained by tile showed that in Indiana, the areas were nearly identical; but for Illinois and Ohio, the Census 2012 areas were unexpectedly smaller than Sugg's by 8 and 13 percent respectively; for Michigan, the Census 2012 areas were larger by 10 percent; for Wisconsin, Kentucky, Missouri, Minnesota, and Iowa, the Census 2012 areas were larger by 24 to 43 percent; and for South Dakota, Kansas, and Nebraska, the Census of 2012 areas were immensely larger. Hence, based on this state-level comparison, within the Midwest states, the subsurface tile drainage extents in the western states (Iowa, Minnesota, Wisconsin, Missouri, South Dakota, Nebraska, and Kansas) increased substantially from the early 1990s to 2012, whereas subsurface drainage area in the eastern states (Illinois, Michigan, Indiana, and Ohio) remained about the same.
10) There were two (1990) counties (FIPS 12025, Dade, FL and FIPS 30113, Yellowstone National Park) in Sugg's (2007) data file that were not found in the 2010 county boundaries geospatial dataset. Sugg's (2007) data file showed zero acreage of subsurface tile drainage area for these counties. 
11) See "Distribution_Liability".</useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, PACIFIC REGION</cntorg><cntper>Naomi Nakagaki</cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>Geographer</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>6000 J Street</address><address>CSUS Placer Hall</address><city>Sacramento</city><state>CA</state><postal>95819</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>916-278-3092</cntvoice><cntfax>916-278-3070</cntfax><cntemail>nakagaki@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac><datacred>Zachary Sugg, for the published report and county estimates of subsurface tile drainage extent.</datacred><native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1 (Build 4959) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>Presumably, subsurface tile drains are not exclusively found on poorly drained cropland, nor evenly distributed on poorly drained cropland across counties. Yet as explained in the Supplemental_Information section and summarized in the Process_Steps, the methods used to develop this dataset were implemented with these criteria, resulting in grid cells with the same value within a county. In addition, Sugg's (2007) data, the source for subsurface drainage extent, were published "for collaborative validation and review" and were not validated (Sugg, 2007).</attraccr></attracc><logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic><complete>See #2,3, and 10 of the Use_Constraints section.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>NLCD products in general are intended for regional and national analyses rather than local applications (Homer and others, 2012); reliability is significantly reduced at the cell-by-cell level. Metadata for the NLCD 2011 states the land cover map to be 'provisional' until a formal accuracy assessment is complete. The NLCD 2006 and NLCD 2001 were found to have an overall Anderson Level II accuracy at 78.7 percent and 76.2 percent respectively (Homer and others, 2012).
The U.S. General Soil Map STATSGO2 dataset (U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2006) is primarily for regional, such as state or multicounty-wide applications. Soil characteristics are mapped by polygons of soil map unit, and are quantified as percentages by soil map unit. Soil map units have an average size of 975 square kilometers. All these variables contribute to some degree of uncertainty to the extent of the poorly drained soil. 
(See Supplemental_Information section for the cited references in this section.)</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set is not applicable.</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>Zachary Sugg</origin><pubdate>2007</pubdate><title>Assessing U.S. Farm Drainage: Can GIS Lead to Better Estimates of Subsurface Drainage Extent?</title><geoform>Publication (Journal Article)</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Washington, D.C.</pubplace><publish>World Resources Institute</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://www.wri.org/publication/assessing-us-farm-drainage</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2007</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>publication date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>Sugg</srccitea><srccontr>County estimates of subsurface drainage areas for the early 1990s, in acres, in the tabular data file linked to the journal article. Version used in developing this dataset included corrections made by Mark B. David (University of IL Urbana-Champaign, written commun., August 2008 and June 2014).</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin><pubdate>201410</pubdate><title>National Land Cover Database (NLCD) 2011, Land Cover (2011 Edition, amended 2014) -National Geospatial Data Asset (NGDA) Land Use Land Cover</title><geoform>Raster Digital Data Set</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Sioux Falls, SD</pubplace><publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://www.mrlc.gov/nlcd2011.php</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><srcscale>60000</srcscale><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2011</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>ground condition</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>NLCD 2011</srccitea><srccontr>cells classified as 82 which represents cultivated crops</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA), Natural Resources Conservation Service (NRCS)</origin><pubdate>2006</pubdate><title>U.S. General Soil Map - STATSGO2</title><geoform>Vector Digital Data Set</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Fort Worth, TX</pubplace><publish>U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA), Natural Resources Conservation Service (NRCS)</publish></pubinfo></citeinfo></srccite><srcscale>250000</srcscale><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2006</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>publication date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>STATSGO2</srccitea><srccontr>boundaries of soil map units and soil property attributes of the following soil drainage classes: somewhat poorly drained, poorly drained, and very poorly drained</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Geological Survey, National Atlas of the United States</origin><pubdate>200512</pubdate><title>Federal Lands of the United States</title><geoform>Vector Digital Data Set</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace><publish>U.S. Geological Survey, National Atlas of the United States</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://nationalmap.gov/small_scale</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><srcscale>2000000</srcscale><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>200512</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>publication date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>fedlanp020</srccitea><srccontr>boundaries of Federally-owned land</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>Jo Ann M. Gronberg (U.S. Geological Survey)</origin><pubdate>2012</pubdate><title>30-meter-resolution raster of 2010 counties for the conterminous United States (version April 2012)</title><geoform>Raster Digital Data Set</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>n/a</pubplace><publish>Unpublished material</publish></pubinfo></citeinfo></srccite><srcscale>60000</srcscale><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2010</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>observed</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>co2010g</srccitea><srccontr>county boundaries and county numeric codes</srccontr></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Note: Sugg's county estimates of subsurface tile drainage extents are from 1) his revised estimates for the majority of the counties in the Midwest and for the remaining counties, 2) the 1992 National Resources Inventory (NRI) data. Sugg's data table includes a "Source" field that indicates whether his final county estimate of subsurface tile drainage extent represents the 1992 NRI county total or his revised county estimate. In developing this dataset, the counties for which Sugg obtained areas of the subsurface tile drains from NRI were geoprocessed separately to exclude federally-owned land because NRI surveys do not include federal land. 

The 11 individual process steps can be summarized into 5 major steps:

a) created the geospatial datasets that was used to allocate both the 1992 NRI and Sugg's  revised estimate of subsurface tile drainage extent for Midwest states (Process steps 1-4); 

b) created the geospatial datasets that were used to allocate the 1992 NRI's estimates (Process steps 5-6); 

c) created the geospatial datasets that were used to allocate Sugg's revised estimates  (Process steps 7-8); 

d) merged the geospatial datasets created in Process steps 6 and 8 to create the final geospatial dataset representing potentially drained land (Process step 9); and 

e) calculated the cell values to be assigned to the grid cells characterized as potentially drained land and created the final raster of the subsurface tile drainage extent (Process steps 10-11).</procdesc><procdate>20150805</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>1) CREATED A 30-METER (30-m) RESOLUTION RASTER OF THE CULTIVATED CROPS CLASSIFICATION FROM THE NLCD 2011. (Hereinafter, all references to rasters are national and at the 30-m resolution). Downloaded nlcd_2011_landcover_2011_edition_2014_10_10.zip from http://www.mrlc.gov/nlcd11_data.php. Uncompressed the zip file and exported the 30-m resolution image file, nlcd_2011_landuse_2011_edition_2014_10_10.img, to a raster in a file geodatabase. Selected for cells coded as 82 (cultivated crops classification); assigned these cells a value = 1; remaining cells = 0. **Output cropland raster = nlcdROWCROP**</procdesc><procdate>20150805</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>2) CREATED A RASTER OF POORLY DRAINED SOIL USING SELECTED STATSGO2 SOIL DRAINAGE CLASSES. Determined the dominant soil drainage class for each STATSGO2 soil map unit, then joined the attribute table of the dominant STATSGO2 soil drainage class to the polygons of soil map units. Converted the soil drainage class polygons to a raster, which was selected for drainage class = 3 (poorly drained), 5 (somewhat poorly drained), and 6 (very poorly drained). Created a new raster from these selections where values of 3, 5, and 6 were reclassified as 1 and all other areas were reclassified as 0. **Output poorly drained soil raster: STATSGO2_POORRDN**</procdesc><procdate>20150805</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>3) CREATED A RASTER OF NON-FEDERAL LANDS. Using the 1: 2,000,000-scale Federal Lands feature class (fedlandp020_nt00012) downloaded from the U.S. Geological Survey's The National Map Small-Scale web site, added a new field to flag all non-Federal Land polygons and assigned them a value of 1. By using this new field as the dissolve item, dissolved the non-Federal Land polygons to reduce the number of unnecessary polygons. Converted this output feature class to a raster by using nlcdROWCROP as the snap raster so that the cells aligned. Assigned the 'nodata'-value cells (non-Federal Lands) a value of 1 and the remaining cells (Federal Lands) a value of 0. **Output non-Federal Lands raster = NONFED**</procdesc><procdate>20150805</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>4) CREATED A GEODATABASE TABLE OF SUGG'S (his revised and NRI92s estimates) COUNTY-LEVEL AREAS OF SUBSURFACE TILE DRAINS AND JOINED THIS COUNTY FILE TO THE ATTRIBUTE TABLE OF THE RASTER OF (2010) COUNTY BOUNDARIES. Converted Sugg's data table, in EXCEL format, to a geodatabase table. **Output table: county_SuggTILEDRNS**  The "Source" field in Sugg's data file was used to determine which county estimates were from NRI92.  To the county_SuggTILEDRNS table, added a new field NRI92_m2, to store the county 1992 NRI area of subsurface tile drains but expressed in square meters (Sugg's tabular file has all area fields expressed in acres). Added a new field Sugg92_m2 to store Sugg's revised estimates in square meters. Added a new field finSugg_m2 to store the final county subsurface drainage extent that was used to develop this raster dataset, in square meters. (Note: this field was equal to Sugg's revised estimate, if reported; otherwise equal to the NRI 92 estimate). Populated NRI92_m2 by multiplying the county 1992 NRI acres of subsurface drainage extent, by 4046.85642239 to convert to square meters. For counties that have null values for 1992 NRI, NRI92_m2 was assigned a  "-999". Populated the Sugg92_m2 by multiplying Sugg's estimates expressed in acres, by 4046.85642239 to convert to square meters. For counties that have null values, Sugg92_m2 was assigned a "-999". Populated finSugg_m2 by first selecting for counties in which the source for the subsurface drainage area is 1992 NRI and calculated the finSugg_m2 field to be equal to the NRI92_m2. Cleared the selection, then selected for counties in which the source was from Sugg or corrected by personnel at University of IL Urbana-Champaign (see Supplemental_Information), and calculated finSugg_m2 to be equal to Sugg92_m2. Joined the county_SuggTILEDRNS attribute table to the 2010 county boundaries raster.</procdesc><procdate>20150805</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>5) CREATED A COUNTY BOUNDARIES RASTER THAT CONSISTED OF THE SUBSET OF COUNTIES IN WHICH SUGG USED NRI92 AS THE SOURCE FOR SUBSURFACE TILE DRAINAGE EXTENT. Created a new raster using the NRI92_m2 field in the 2010 county boundaries raster (with joined attributes from county_SuggTILEDRNS table, as described in Process Step 3). Assigned no data to all cells that have a value = -999 and assigned a value of 1 otherwise. **Output raster = nriCNTY**</procdesc><procdate>20150805</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>6) CREATED A RASTER OF POTENTIALLY DRAINED LAND FOR THE SUBSET OF COUNTIES IN WHICH SUGG USED NRI92 AS THE SOURCE FOR SUBSURFACE TILE DRAINAGE EXTENT. This output raster represented cropland with poorly drained soil minus the federally-owned land, but only for those counties where NRI92 is the source for tile drains. Using nriCNTY (created in Process step 5) as the mask grid, summed the 3 rasters: a) nlcdROWCROP (cells = 1 if classified as cultivated crop; created in Process step 1); and b) STATSGO2_POORDRN (cells have a value of 1 if characterized as poorly drained soil; created in process step 2); and c) NONFED (cells have a value of 1 if located on non-federal land; created in Process step 4). **Temporary output raster = nriSUM3** From the nriSUM3 raster, selected for cells with a value of 3 (in other words, the cells that met all 3 conditions - cultivated cropland with poorly drained soil, but *not* on Federal land), and created a new raster that has a value of 1. Assigned the nodata cells to zero. **Output raster = nriROWCROP**</procdesc><procdate>20150805</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>7) CREATED A COUNTY BOUNDARIES RASTER THAT CONSISTED OF THE SUBSET OF COUNTIES FOR WHICH SUGG'S REVISED ESTIMATE WILL BE THE SOURCE FOR SUBSURFACE TILE DRAINAGE EXTENT.
Created a new raster using the Sugg92_m2 field in the 2010 county boundaries raster (with joined attributes from county_SuggTILEDRNS table, as described in Process Step 3). Assigned no data to all cells that have a value = -999 and assign a value of 1 otherwise. **Output raster = SuggCNTY**</procdesc><procdate>20150805</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>8) CREATED A RASTER OF THE POTENTIALLY DRAINED LAND FOR THE SUBSET OF COUNTIES FOR WHICH SUGG'S REVISED ESTIMATE WILL BE THE SOURCE FOR SUBSURFACE TILE DRAINAGE EXTENT. The output raster represents cropland with poorly drained soil but for only those counties with Sugg's revised estimates. Using SuggCNTY (created in Process step 7) as a mask grid, summed the following 2 rasters: a) nlcdROWCROP and b) STATSGO2_POORDRN. **Temporary output raster = suggSUM2** From the output raster, created a new raster that has a value of 1 for cells that have a summed value of 2, or cells that are characterized as cultivated cropland with poorly drained soil. Assigned the nodata cells to zero. **Output raster = suggROWCROP**</procdesc><procdate>20150805</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>9) CREATED THE COMBINED RASTER THAT REPRESENTS THE POTENTIALLY DRAINED LAND FOR ALL COUNTIES. Summed the nriROWCROP and suggROWCROP rasters (created in Process steps 6 and 8, respectively). Converted all values &gt; 0 to 1; otherwise the cells were assigned a no data. The cells equal to 1 represent the potentially drained land, or cropland with poorly drained soil. **Output raster = finalROWCROP**</procdesc><procdate>20150805</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>10) DETERMINED THE CELL VALUE OF THE AREA OF SUBSURFACE TILE DRAIN EXTENT THAT WILL BE ASSIGNED TO EACH COUNTY. Determined the total number of 30-m cells of cropland with poorly drained soil for each county using the finalROWCROP raster (produced in Process step 9). **Output table: OutZonalStats_finalROWCROP_byfips**  Added a new field to the output table called CellCnt_CROP_POORDRN and calculated it to be equal to the SUM field in the output table.  Joined the OutZonalStats_finalROWCROP_byfips table with the county_SuggTILEDRNS table (created in Process Step 3). **Output table: finalCOUNTYDATA_TILEDRN**
Added a new field (CellValue) to represent the value to assign all cells classified as cropland with poorly drained soil within a county.  Selected for CellCnt_CROP_POORDRN &gt;  0, then calculated the CellValue field to be equal to the county area of subsurface tile drainage extent from Sugg's file (the finSUGG_m2 field, calculated in Process step 3), divided by the number of cells in the county classified as cropland with poorly drained soil (the CellCnt_CROP_POORDRN field).</procdesc><procdate>20150805</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>11) CREATED THE FINAL RASTER OF THE ESTIMATES OF SUBSURFACE TILE DRAINAGE EXTENT USING finalROWCROP AS THE MASK RASTER. Joined the finalCOUNTYDATA_TILEDRN table to the attribute table of the raster of 2010 county boundaries. Using the finalROWCROP raster (created in Process step 9) as the mask raster, created the final subsurface drainage raster from the CellValue field (calculated in the previous step) in the 2010 county boundaries raster. **Output raster: SubsurfaceDrainExtentUS_90s**</procdesc><procdate>20150805</procdate></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><direct>Raster</direct><rastinfo><rasttype>Grid Cell</rasttype><rowcount>97278</rowcount><colcount>154179</colcount><vrtcount>1</vrtcount></rastinfo></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><planar><mapproj><mapprojn>USA Contiguous Albers Equal Area Conic USGS version (ESRI Full Name: USA_Contiguous_Albers_Equal_Area_Conic_USGS_version)</mapprojn><albers><stdparll>29.5</stdparll><stdparll>45.5</stdparll><longcm>-96.0</longcm><latprjo>23.0</latprjo><feast>0.0</feast><fnorth>0.0</fnorth></albers></mapproj><planci><plance>row and column</plance><coordrep><absres>30.0</absres><ordres>30.0</ordres></coordrep><plandu>Meter</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>D_North_American_1983</horizdn><ellips>GRS_1980</ellips><semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis><denflat>298.257222101</denflat></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl><enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd><enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>Value</attrlabl><attrdef>estimated area of subsurface tile drainage extent</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>543130.75</rdommax><attrunit>square meters</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr></detailed><overview><eaover>There is no value attribute table for the raster because the data values are expressed as floating numbers.The grid cell values in the raster represent the estimated area of subsurface tile drainage extent, in square meters.</eaover><eadetcit>none</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><distrib><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg></cntorgp><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing</addrtype><address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address><city>Denver</city><state>CO</state><postal>80225</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice><cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib><distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items must be secured from the copyright owner whenever applicable. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although the data have been subjected to rigorous review and are substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, the data are released on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from authorized or unauthorized use. Although the data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Users of the data are advised to read all metadata and associated documentation thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Raster Digital Data Set</formname></digtinfo><digtopt><onlinopt><computer><networka><networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7RB72QS</networkr></networka></computer></onlinopt></digtopt></digform><fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining this data set.</fees></stdorder></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20160421</metd><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Naomi Nakagaki</cntper><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, PACIFIC REGION</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Geographer</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>6000 J Street</address><address>CSUS Placer Hall</address><city>Sacramento</city><state>CA</state><postal>95819</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>916-278-3092</cntvoice><cntfax>916-278-3070</cntfax><cntemail>nakagaki@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></metc><metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv></metainfo></metadata>