<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Naomi Nakagaki</origin><origin>Michael E. Wieczorek</origin><pubdate>201604</pubdate><title>Estimates of subsurface tile drainage extent for 12 Midwest states, 2012</title><geoform>Raster Digital Data Set</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Sacramento, CA</pubplace><publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7W37TDP</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This dataset is a 30-meter resolution raster of estimated extent of subsurface tile drains, developed from tabular data of state-level estimates of agricultural land drained by tiles combined with geospatial cropland and soils in 12 Midwest States (SD, NE, KS, MN, IA, MO, WI, IL, MI, IN, OH, and KY). This dataset was created from the following four sources: 1) state-level acreages of agricultural "land drained by tiles" from the 2012 Census of Agriculture; 2) the extent of cultivated cropland from the National Land Cover Dataset (NLCD) 2011; 3) the extent of poorly and moderately drained soils from the State Soil Geographic Database (STATSGO) database Version 2; and 4) state administrative boundaries. The area of drained land was evenly allocated to potentially drained land for agriculture - cropland with poorly drained soil - except in Iowa.  For Iowa, because the reported area of land drained by tiles exceeded the area of cropland on poorly drained soils, the additional area of subsurface tile drains greater than the area of cropland on poorly drained soils was assigned to land characterized as cropland with moderately drained soil. The estimated extent of subsurface tile drains in each cell is expressed in square meters.</abstract><purpose>This dataset was created to estimate the spatial extent of subsurface tile drains in the Midwest region, in support of the Midwest Stream Quality Assessment (MSQA) study conducted by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (USEPA).</purpose><supplinf>TIME PERIOD OF CONTENT - CURRENTNESS REFERENCE:The year 2012 is approximate: 2012 represents the year in which the Census of Agriculture survey was conducted for "land drained by tile" but the spatial distribution of cultivated cropland is from the NLCD 2011, which is based on imagery from February 2009 through November 2011 (Homer and others, 2015).

BACKGROUND: MSQA is one of several Regional Stream Quality Assessment (RSQA) studies that are part of the USGS National Water Quality Assessment (NAWQA) project (U.S. Geological Survey, 2012). MSQA was a collaboration of NAWQA, the USGS Columbia Environmental Research Center (CERC), and the USEPA National Rivers and Streams Assessment (NRSA). The objective of the MSQA study was to characterize water-quality stressors - contaminants, nutrients, sediment, and habitat and ecological conditions in streams across the Midwest and to determine the relative effects of these stressors on aquatic biota in the streams (U.S. Geological Survey, 2012). One hundred streams in the Midwest study area were sampled during the spring and summer months of 2013. 

Environmental characteristics of the sampled sites were quantified to support the hydrologic and ecological analyses and models developed for the MSQA study. One of many physical and anthropogenic characteristics quantified for the MSQA sites was subsurface tile drainage extent. Although subsurface tile drainage improves cropland with poorly drained soil by removing excess water from the soil subsurface, the outflow from subsurface tile drains can be high in agricultural chemicals such as nitrogen. Estimates of subsurface drainage extent are needed as input to models predicting agricultural chemicals in streams for the MSQA study area. 

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION: Detailed geospatial data of subsurface tile drainage location and extent that have been consistently collected and compiled for the nation or Midwest region are not available. Estimated total area of subsurface drainage by county exist for the conterminous U.S. but for the early 1990s (U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1995; Sugg, 2007). Recently, the 2012 Census of Agriculture's "land drained by tile" became available, however it is reported by state (U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2015b). Although county-based or higher-detailed coverage of subsurface tile drain systems is optimal, the 2012 Census of Agriculture's state tabular data is the most current national source and can be combined with geospatial cropland and soils data to estimate the extent of subsurface tile drains. 

This dataset estimates the spatial extent of subsurface tile drains based on the assumption that it is likely to be found where crops are grown on poorly drained soil (Sugg, 2007). Presumably, subsurface tile drainage is not exclusively found on poorly drained cropland, or evenly distributed in poorly drained cropland across states, thus, there is considerable uncertainty in this data set. In addition, this dataset does not reflect non-cropland areas where subsurface tile drains may exist.

The source for the geographic extent of cropland was the 2011 National Land Cover Database (Homer and others, 2015; U.S. Geological Survey, 2014a) and the extent of poorly drained soil (and moderately drained soil for Iowa) was the U.S. General Soil map, or "STATSGO2" (U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2006). Although higher resolution geospatial soils dataset such as the Soil Survey Geographic database ("SSURGO") is available (U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2015a), it was not feasible to implement SSURGO data into the development of this dataset due to time and resource constraints. It was further concluded that the level of uncertainty in applying state-level data as was done here would not be reduced by using a higher resolution soils dataset. 

CITED REFERENCES (in Supplemental Information and the Horizontal Positional Accuracy Report sections):
Homer, C.G., Dewitz, J.A., Yang, L., Jin, S., Danielson, P., Xian, G., Coulston, J., Herold, N.D., Wickham, J.D., and Megown, K., 2015, Completion of the 2011 National Land Cover Database for the conterminous United States - Representing a decade of land cover change information. Photogrammetric Engineering and Remote Sensing, v. 81, no. 5, p. 345-354.

Homer C.H., Fry, J.A., and Barnes, C.A., 2012, The National Land Cover Database, U.S. Geological Survey Fact Sheet 2012-3020, 4 p., available at http://pubs.usgs.gov/fs/2012/3020/.

Sugg, Zachary, 2007, Assessing U.S. Farm Drainage: Can GIS lead to better estimates of subsurface drainage extent? World Resources Institute, Washington D.C., accessed August 2015, at http://www.wri.org/publication/assessing-us-farm-drainage.

U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1995, 1992 National Resources Inventory: Natural Resources Conservation Service, Washington, D.C., and Statistical Laboratory, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa [CDROM].

U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2006, U.S. general soil map (STATSGO2): Natural Resources Conservation Service geospatial data, accessed April 2007, at http://sdmdataaccess.nrcs.usda.gov/.

U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2015a, 2012 Census Publications, Desktop Data Query Tool 2.0, accessed August 17, 2015 at http://www.agcensus.usda.gov/Publications/2012/Online_Resources/Desktop_Application/.

U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2015b, Soil Survey Geographic (SSURGO) Database: Natural Resources Conservation Service, geospatial data, accessed September 2015, at http://sdmdataaccess.nrcs.usda.gov/.

U.S. Geological Survey, 2012, The Midwest stream quality assessment: U.S. Geological Survey Fact Sheet 2012-3124: Reston, VA, 2012; p 2.

U.S. Geological Survey, 2014a, National land cover database 2011 (NLCD 2011), raster digital data, accessed February 15, 2015, at http://www.mrlc.gov/nlcd2011.php.

U.S. Geological Survey, 2014b, 1:1,000,000-Scale County Boundaries of the United States, The National Map Small Scale, vector digital data, accessed January 2015, at http://nationalmap.gov/small_scale/.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2012</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>See Supplemental Info</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-105.086914166</westbc><eastbc>-78.641881702</eastbc><northbc>49.386795524</northbc><southbc>35.252808022</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>subsurface tile drainage</themekey><themekey>tile drain</themekey><themekey>subsurface drainage</themekey><themekey>land drained by tile</themekey><themekey>Census of Agriculture</themekey><themekey>Midwest Stream Quality Assessment</themekey><themekey>MSQA</themekey><themekey>Regional Stream Quality Assessment</themekey><themekey>RSQA</themekey><themekey>National Stream Quality Assessment</themekey><themekey>NAWQA</themekey><themekey>water quality</themekey></theme><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt><themekey>environment</themekey><themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey><themekey>inlandWaters</themekey></theme><place><placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt><placekey>Illinois</placekey><placekey>Indiana</placekey><placekey>Iowa</placekey><placekey>Kansas</placekey><placekey>Kentucky</placekey><placekey>Michigan</placekey><placekey>Minnesota</placekey><placekey>Missouri</placekey><placekey>Nebraska</placekey><placekey>Ohio</placekey><placekey>South Dakota</placekey><placekey>Wisconsin</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None. Acknowledgment of the U.S. Geological Survey would be appreciated in products derived from these data.</accconst><useconst>1) The Census of Agriculture areas of "land drained by tiles" were geospatially distributed and apportioned to "potentially" drained cropland, land that is characterized as cropland with poorly drained soil (and both poorly drained and moderately drained soil for Iowa only). But presumably, subsurface tile drainage is not exclusively found on poorly drained cropland, or evenly distributed on poorly drained cropland across states; thus, there is considerable uncertainty in this data set at sub-regional levels.
2) This dataset does not reflect non-cropland areas where subsurface tile drains may be installed.
3) The source data for the subsurface tile drainage extent are the 2012 Census of Agriculture's state-level acreages of "land drained by tile". The Census of Agriculture is based on information collected from surveys, and data collected in this manner may not accurately capture total subsurface tile drainage extent due to lack of participation by some farmers. Consequently, the statewide total area (and thus some cells in this raster) may be under-represented.
4) Because this raster was developed from state tabular areas of land drained by tile, this raster is most reliable for a single state or multiple states in its entirety, and increases in uncertainty as the area of interest reduces in size. 
5) For information regarding the accuracy limitations of the NLCD (source for mapped cropland) and STATSGO2 (source for mapped soils), please refer to the "Horizontal_Positional_Accuracy" section of this metadata.</useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, PACIFIC REGION</cntorg><cntper>Naomi Nakagaki</cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>Geographer</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>6000 J Street Placer Hall</address><city>Sacramento</city><state>CA</state><postal>95819</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>916-278-3092</cntvoice><cntfax>916-278-3070</cntfax><cntemail>nakagaki@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac><datacred>National Agriculture Statistics Service for the published state-level acreages of "land drained by tile".</datacred><native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1 (Build 4959) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>Please refer to the Supplemental Information as there is considerable uncertainty in this dataset. No accuracy reports were conducted on the source for tile drainage extent, the Census of Agriculture "land drained by tile".</attraccr></attracc><logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic><complete>This dataset was developed for solely the 12 states in the Midwest. Also see #2 and 3 in Use_Constraints.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>NLCD products in general are intended for regional and national analyses rather than local applications (Homer and others, 2012); reliability is significantly reduced at the cell-by-cell level. Metadata for the NLCD 2011 (U.S. Geological Survey, 2014) states the "land cover map to be 'provisional' until a formal accuracy assessment is complete". The NLCD 2006 and NLCD 2001 were found to have an overall Anderson Level II accuracy at 78.7% and 76.2% respectively (Homer and others, 2012).
The STATSGO2 soils dataset (U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2006) is designed primarily for regional, state or multicounty-wide applications. In addition, the STATSGO2 soil variables are attributed by soil map unit and percentage of the soil map unit characterized by the soil property. Because of the nature of soils - having both two- and three-dimensional properties, and characterized by polygons of soil map units, some degree of uncertainty with the spatial distribution of the poorly-drained and moderately-drained soil exists within each soil map unit, which has an average size of approximately 975 square kilometers. (See Supplemental_Information for the cited references).</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set is not applicable.</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Department of Agriculture, National Agricultural Statistics Service</origin><pubdate>2014</pubdate><title>2012 Census Publications</title><geoform>Other</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Washington, D.C.</pubplace><publish>U.S. Department of Agriculture</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://www.agcensus.usda.gov/Publications/2012/Online_Resources/Desktop_Application/</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2012</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>year of census survey</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>none</srccitea><srccontr>state acreages of "Land use practices \ Land drained by tile"</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin><pubdate>201410</pubdate><title>National Land Cover Database (NLCD) 2011, Land Cover(2011 Edition, amended 2014) - National Geospatial Data Asset (NGDA) Land Use Land Cover</title><geoform>Raster Digital Data Set</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Sioux Falls, SD</pubplace><publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://www.mrlc.gov/nlcd2011.php</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><srcscale>60000</srcscale><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>20040409</begdate><enddate>20111111</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><srccurr>from and end dates of when the imagery was captured</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>NLCD 2011</srccitea><srccontr>cells classified as "cultivated crops" (code 82) from the "nlcd_2011_landuse_2011_edition_2014_10_10.img" file</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA), Natural Resources Conservation Service (NRCS)</origin><pubdate>2006</pubdate><title>U.S. General Soil Map - STATSGO2</title><geoform>Vector Digital Data Set</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Fort Worth, TX</pubplace><publish>U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA)</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://gdg.sc.egov.usda.gov/</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><srcscale>250000</srcscale><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2006</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>publication date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>STATSGO2</srccitea><srccontr>boundaries of soil map units and soil property attributes of the soil drainage classes, "somewhat poorly drained", "poorly drained", and "very poorly drained" for all 12 states; for Iowa only- in addition, "moderately well drained"</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Geological Survey, National Atlas of the United States</origin><pubdate>201403</pubdate><title>1:1,000,000-Scale County Boundaries of the United States</title><geoform>Vector Digital Data Set</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Rolla, MO</pubplace><publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://nationalmap.gov/small_scale</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><srcscale>1000000</srcscale><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2014</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>publication date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>countyp010g</srccitea><srccontr>state boundaries</srccontr></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>The major steps are summarized as follows: a) created a national data table of tile drainage extent by state, a national raster of cropland, and a national raster of soil drainage (Process steps 1-3); b) developed the raster of subsurface tile drainage extent in the 12 Midwest States based on cropland with poorly drained soil (Process steps 4-11); c) developed the raster of subsurface tile drainage extent in Iowa based on cropland with moderately drained soil (Process steps 12-20); d) combined the subsurface drainage rasters created for cropland with poorly drained soil for all 12 Midwest States, and cropland with moderately drained soil for IA, to generate the final subsurface tile drainage raster for the Midwest (Process step 21).</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>1) CREATED A STATE-LEVEL TABLE OF THE 2012 CENSUS OF AGRICULTURE AREAS OF "LAND USE PRACTICES \ LAND DRAINED BY TILE". Downloaded the "2012 Desktop Data Query Tool" software application from the Census of Agriculture site (http://www.agcensus.usda.gov/Publications/2012/Online_Resources/Desktop_Application/). Invoked the Data Query tool using the following selections: a) Table: Table 50. Land Use Practices by Size of Farm: 2012 (reported by acres); b) Data Item: "Land use practices \ Land drained by tile"; c) Geographical Location: All States, United States. Clicked on "Get Data" followed by "Export GIS", and saved the data  as a "dbf" file. Converted the "dbf" file to a geodatabase table. Added a field, Cens2012_TileDrn_m2, to store "land drained by tile" in square meters. Multiplied acres by 4046.85642239 to convert to square meters. **Output table = Census2012_TileDrains**</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>2) CREATED A 30-METER (30-m) RESOLUTION NATIONAL RASTER OF CROPLAND. (Hereinafter, all references to rasters are at the 30-m resolution). Downloaded "nlcd_2011_landcover_2011_edition_2014_10_10.zip" from http://www.mrlc.gov/nlcd11_data.php. Uncompressed the zip file. which resulted in the 30-m resolution image file, nlcd_2011_landuse_2011_edition_2014_10_10.img. Selected for cells coded 82 ("cultivated crops" classification);  assigned these cells a value = 1; remaining cells = 0. **Output cropland raster = nlcdROWCROP**</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>3) CREATED A NATIONAL RASTER OF SOIL DRAINAGE. Determined the dominant soil drainage class for each STATSGO2 soil map unit, then joined the attribute table of the dominant STATSGO2 soil drainage class to the polygons of soil map units. Converted the soil polygons to a raster. **Output soil drainage class raster = DRCLASSDOM** .</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>4) CREATED A NATIONAL RASTER OF CROPLAND WITH POORLY DRAINED SOIL. Using the DRCLASSDOM raster, selected for drainage class = 3 (poorly drained), 5 (somewhat poorly drained), and 6 (very poorly drained), and created a new raster from these selections where values of 3, 5, and 6 were reclassified as 1 and all other areas as 0. ** Output poorly drained soil raster = STATSGO2_POORDRN**  Summed the nlcdROWCROP raster with the STATSGO2_POORDRN raster, and selected for cells with a value of "2" (in other words, cells characterized as cropland with poorly drained soil) and created a new raster so that the "2" cells were converted to "1"s and the remaining cells were "no data". **Output cropland with poorly drained soil raster = CropPoorDrn**</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>5) CREATED A STATE BOUNDARIES RASTER OF THE 12 MIDWEST STATES - SD, NE, KS, MN, IA, MO, WI, IL, MI, IN, OH, and KY. Clicked on the left bar link "Small Scale Data Download" found at http://nationalmap.gov/small_scale. Clicked on "Governmental Units/Boundaries" and scrolled down to "County Boundaries, One-Million-Scale". Clicked on the Geodatabase version available for download. Uncompressed the "countyp010g.gdb_nt00933.tar.gz" which produced a file called "countyp010g.tar". Uncompressed this file, which resulted in a geodatabase named "countyp010g.gdb" with a feature class dataset "countyp010g". Projected the county polygons, natively in the geographic coordinate system with the North American 1983 Datum, to match the projection in the datasets developed thus far (USA_Contiguous_Albers_Equal_Area_Conic). Selected for the 12 Midwest states by selecting for the field, State_fips, equal to the following: '46','31','20','27','19','29','55','17','26','18','39','21', which represented SD, NE, KS, MN, IA, MO, WI, IL, MI, IN, OH, and KY, respectively. Exported these polygons into a new feature class, and dissolved these Midwest county boundaries using State_fips as the dissolve field to create a Midwest state boundaries feature class. Converted the new feature class to a raster using a numeric version of the State_fips field to be retained in the raster's Value field. Used the CropPoorDrn raster as the snap raster so that the grid cells in the output raster would be aligned with the CropPoorDrn raster. **Output Midwest States raster = MW_States**</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>6) CREATED A STATE-LEVEL TABLE OF THE TOTAL NUMBER OF CELLS CLASSIFIED AS CROPLAND WITH POORLY DRAINED SOIL IN THE CropPoorDrn raster. Using the MW_States raster, ran a statistics tool for each zone (Midwest state) to total the number of cells classified as cropland with poorly drained soil, by state. Renamed the output SUM field to GISCropPoorDrn_CellCnt. **Output table = MW_States_CropPoorDrn**</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>7) COMBINED THE 2-STATE-LEVEL TABLES THAT HAS THE 2012 CENSUS OF AGRICULTURE'S AREA OF "LAND DRAINED BY TILE", AND NUMBER OF CELLS CLASSIFIED AS CROPLAND WITH POORLY DRAINED SOIL. Joined the 2 state-level tables, Census2012_TileDrains and MW_States_CropPoorDrn (created in Process Steps 1 and 6, respectively), using State_fips as the common field. Exported the joined table into a new table. **Output table = MWstates_TileDrains**</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>8) CALCULATED THE STATE RATIO OF THE 2012 CENSUS OF AGRICULTURE AREA OF "LAND DRAINED BY TILE" TO THE AREA CLASSIFIED AS POORLY DRAINED CROPLAND. Added and populated fields GIScropPoorDrn_m2 (to store the square meters of cropland with poorly drained soil for the state) and State_ratio to the MWstates_TileDrains table.  Calculated GISCropPoorDrn_m2=GISCropPoorDrn_CellCnt * 900 (the number of cells classified as cropland with poorly drained soil was multiplied by 900 because the area of each 30-by-30-meter cell is 900 square meters). Calculated State_Ratio= Cens2012_TileDrn_m2 / GIScropPoorDrn_m2. Note: State Ratio for Iowa was ~1.19, in other words, the Census-based area for land drained by tile (51,116,389,797 m2 or ~ 51,116 km2) was greater than the area of land classified as cropland with poorly drained soil (43,038,790,200 m2, or ~ 43,039 km2).  The difference, ~8,077 km2, of land drained by tile will be apportioned to cropland with moderately drained soil.</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>9) MADE ADJUSTMENTS FOR IOWA SO THAT THE STATE RATIO IS 1.0, AND CALCULATED THE CELL VALUE THAT WAS TO BE ASSIGNED TO EACH SUBSURFACE TILE DRAINAGE CELL FOR THE REMAINING MIDWEST STATES. Made a copy of the table MW_States_TileDrains and named it  MW_States_TileDrains_Adjusted.  In the MWStates_TileDrains_Adjusted file, selected for Iowa only, then: a) re-calculated the field Cens2012_TileDrn_m2 to be equal to the value in the GISCropPoorDrn_m2 field (43,038,790,200 m2); b)  re-calculated the field State_Ratio = 1.0. Added and populated field Cell_Value to the MW_States_TileDrains_Adjusted table. For all states except Iowa, calculated Cell_Value = Cens2012_TileDrn_m2 / GIScropPoorDrn_CellCnt. For Iowa, the Cell_Value was 900, the (maximum) area that can be defined in a 30-by-30-meter cell.</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>10) JOINED THE STATE-LEVEL TABLE THAT STORED THE CALCULATED CELL VALUES OF SUBSURFACE TILE DRAINAGE ASSOCIATED WITH CROPLAND WITH POORLY DRAINED SOIL TO THE MIDWEST STATES BOUNDARY RASTER.  Joined the  MW_States_TileDrains_Adjusted table (created in Process step 9) to the attribute table of the MW_States raster (created in Process step 5). **Output raster: MW_States_Joined_CropPoorDrn**</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>11) CREATED THE SUBSURFACE TILE DRAINAGE RASTER FOR CROPLAND WITH POORLY DRAINED SOIL FOR THE 12 MIDWEST STATES (Note: the portion in Iowa represents   ~43,039 KM2 of the 51,116 KM2 of the Census of Agriculture  "Land drained by tile"). Using the MW_States_Joined_CropPoorDrn raster created from the previous step as input, used the Cell_Value field (calculated in Process Step 9) to assign the value of the cells in the output subsurface tile drainage raster. The raster CropPoorDrn (created in Process step 4) was set as the "mask" raster so that only those cells that are classified as cropland with poorly drained soil have a data value for subsurface tile drainage extent. Converted the "no data" cells to zero. **Output raster: TileDrains_CropPoorDrn**</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>12) CREATED A VERSION OF THE  "Census2012_TileDrains" TABLE ONLY FOR IOWA TO STORE THE AREA OF THE TILE DRAINAGE EXTENT THAT WILL BE MAPPED TO CROPLAND WITH MODERATELY DRAINED SOIL. Made a copy of the Census2012_TileDrains file. Deleted all rows except for the record for Iowa. Re-calculated the value of the Cens2012_TileDrn_m2 field to be  8,077,599,597 (m2), the difference between the original Census's area of "land drained by tile" for Iowa (51,116,389,797 m2)  and the area of land classified as poorly drained cropland (43,038,790,200 m2). **Output table: Census2012_TileDrainsAdjusted_4IA**</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>13) CREATED A RASTER OF MODERATELY DRAINED SOIL. Used DRCLASSDOM as the input raster (created in Process step 3), selected for drainage class = 2 (moderately well drained). Created a new raster from this selection so that cells with a value of 2 were reclassified as 1 and all other cells were assigned 0.  **Output moderately drained soil raster = STATSGO2_MODDRN**</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>14) CREATED A RASTER OF CROPLAND WITH MODERATELY DRAINED SOIL. Summed the nlcdROWCROP cropland raster with the STATSGO2_MODDRN moderately-drained soil raster, and selected the cells that had a value of "2" (those that met both conditions) and stored in a new raster so that the "2" cells were converted to "1"s and the remaining cells were assigned "no data". **Output cropland with moderately-drained soil raster = CropModDrn**</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>15) CREATED A STATE-LEVEL TABLE OF THE TOTAL NUMBER OF CELLS CLASSIFIED AS CROPLAND WITH MODERATELY DRAINED SOIL. (Note: Although this step was conducted for all 12 Midwest states, the only data of interest is for Iowa). Using the CropModDrn Raster, ran a statistics tool for the zones (states) to total the number of cells classified as cropland with moderately drained soil. Renamed the output SUM field to GISCropModDrn_CellCnt. **Output table = MW_States_CropModDrn**</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>16) COMBINED THE 2 STATE-LEVEL TABLES THAT STORED THE 2012 CENSUS OF AGRICULTURE AREA OF "LAND DRAINED BY TILE" ADJUSTED FOR IOWA and THE CELLS CLASSIFIED AS CROPLAND WITH MODERATELY DRAINED SOIL FOR EACH RESPECTIVE STATE.  Joined the 2 state-level tables, Census2012_TileDrainsAdjusted_4IA and MW_States_CropModDrn (created in Process steps 12 and 15, respectively) using the state fips as the common field. Exported the joined table into a new table. **Output table = IA_TileDrains_ModDrn**</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>17) CALCULATED IOWA'S RATIO OF THE 2012 CENSUS OF AGRICULTURE  ADJUSTED AREA OF "LAND DRAINED BY TILE" TO THE AREA OF CELLS CLASSIFIED AS CROPLAND WITH MODERATELY DRAINED SOIL. Added and populated fields GIScropModDrn_m2 and State_ratio to the IA_TileDrains_ModDrn table. Calculated GISCropModDrn_m2 = GISCropModDrn_CellCnt * 900" (900 represents the square meters of each 30-by-30-meter cell). Calculated State_Ratio = Cens2012_TileDrn_m2 / GIScropModDrn_m2 (Note: the value of Cens2012_TileDrn_m2 for Iowa in this table is the difference between the original Census's area of "land drained by tile" and the area of land classified as poorly drained cropland, or 8,077,599,597 m2.)</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>18) CALCULATED THE CELL VALUE TO BE ASSIGNED TO EACH SUBSURFACE TILE DRAINAGE CELL IN IOWA THAT IS CLASSIFIED AS CROPLAND WITH MODERATELY DRAINED SOIL. Added and populated field Cell_Value to the IA_TileDrains_ModDrn table.  The cell value is equal to 8,077,599,597 m2 divided by the total number of cells classified as cropland with moderately drained soil in Iowa. Calculated Cell_Value = Cens2012_TileDrn_m2 / GIScropModDrn_CellCnt.</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>19) JOINED THE TABLE OF IOWA'S CALCULATED CELL VALUE OF SUBSURFACE TILE DRAINAGE ASSOCIATED WITH CROPLAND WITH MODERATELY DRAINED SOIL TO A IOWA STATE BOUNDARY RASTER. Created an Iowa state boundary raster, IA_State, by selecting for the state of Iowa from the MW_States raster. Joined the IA_TileDrains_ModDrn table with the value attribute table of the IA_State raster. **Output raster: IA_State_Joined_CropModDrn**</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>20) CREATED THE SUBSURFACE TILE DRAINAGE RASTER FOR THE CROPLAND WITH MODERATELY DRAINED SOILS IN IA. Using the IA_State_Joined_CropModDrn raster created from the previous step, used the Cell_Value field to assign the value of the cells in the subsurface tile drainage raster for Iowa's cropland with moderately drained soils. The raster CropModDrn (created in Process step 14) was set as the "mask" raster so that only those cells that were classified as cropland with moderately drained soils had a data value. Converted the "no data" cells to zero.**Output raster: TileDrains_CropModDrn_IAonly**</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>21) CREATED THE FINAL RASTER OF THE ESTIMATES OF SUBSURFACE TILE DRAINAGE EXTENT. Merged the rasters of estimates of subsurface tile drainage extent associated with cropland with poorly drained soil for all 12 Midwest states with the subsurface tile drainage extent associated with cropland in moderately drained soil for Iowa, TileDrains_CropPoorDrn and TileDrains_CropModDrn_IAonly (created in Process Steps 11 and 20, respectively).  **Output raster: SubsurfaceDrainExtentMW_2012**</procdesc><procdate>20150916</procdate></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><direct>Raster</direct><rastinfo><rasttype>Grid Cell</rasttype><rowcount>49254</rowcount><colcount>65462</colcount><vrtcount>1</vrtcount></rastinfo></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><planar><mapproj><mapprojn>USA Contiguous Albers Equal Area Conic USGS version (ESRI Full Name: USA_Contiguous_Albers_Equal_Area_Conic_USGS_version)</mapprojn><albers><stdparll>29.5</stdparll><stdparll>45.5</stdparll><longcm>-96.0</longcm><latprjo>23.0</latprjo><feast>0.0</feast><fnorth>0.0</fnorth></albers></mapproj><planci><plance>row and column</plance><coordrep><absres>30.0</absres><ordres>30.0</ordres></coordrep><plandu>Meter</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>D_North_American_1983</horizdn><ellips>GRS_1980</ellips><semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis><denflat>298.257222101</denflat></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl><enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd><enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>Value</attrlabl><attrdef>estimated area of subsurface tile drainage within the grid cell</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>900</rdommax><attrunit>square meters</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr></detailed><overview><eaover>There is no value attribute table because this is a floating raster. The cell values in the raster represent the estimated area of subsurface tile drainage extent, in square meters.</eaover><eadetcit>none</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><distrib><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - Science Base</cntorg></cntorgp><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address><city>Denver</city><state>CO</state><postal>80225</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice><cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib><distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items must be secured from the copyright owner whenever applicable. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although the data have been subjected to rigorous review and are substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, the data are released on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from authorized or unauthorized use. Although the data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall  not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Users of the data are advised to read all metadata and associated documentation thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Raster Digital Data Set</formname></digtinfo><digtopt><onlinopt><computer><networka><networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7W37TDP</networkr></networka></computer></onlinopt></digtopt></digform><fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees></stdorder></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20160422</metd><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Naomi Nakagaki</cntper><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, PACIFIC REGION</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Geographer</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>6000 J Street Placer Hall</address><city>Sacramento</city><state>CA</state><postal>95819</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>916-278-3092</cntvoice><cntfax>916-278-3070</cntfax><cntemail>nakagaki@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></metc><metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv></metainfo></metadata>