<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>James J. Duncker</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>Velocity profiling in the Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal near the US Army Corps of Engineers Electric Dispersal Barrier near Romeoville, Illinois</title>
        <geoform>ASCII files</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7J964FF</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>On August 31, 2015, U.S. Geological Survey Illinois Water Science Center staff deployed a 2000 kHz side-looking acoustic Doppler velocity meter (ADVM) in the Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal (CSSC) at the Electric Dispersal Barrier System (EDBS). These data were collected as a fully loaded commercial barge tow traversed the EDBS and passed the ADVM three times, and as several smaller vessels and an unloaded barge tow passed the ADVM. The ADVM was mounted to a rigid 2-inch PVC pipe in compliance with U.S. Army Corps of Engineers (USACE) operational safety protocols for working in or near the EDBS. The pipe with ADVM was lowered 4.5 feet below the water surface on the west (right) bank of the canal at a location approximately 477 feet upstream of the Romeo Road (135th Street) bridge (41.642050, -88.060383). The pipe was mounted to the walkway guard rail in a vertical orientation. An upstream and downstream guide line were used to provide additional tension to prevent movement or vibration on the PVC pipe.  In this deployment configuration, the ADVM was profiling from the right wall of the canal out towards the center of the channel.  

ADVM data were viewed in real-time on a laptop computer during the deployment and logged simultaneously to the internal memory of the ADVM. The ADVM data were downloaded from the ADVM to a laptop computer while on site and reviewed briefly while in the field. Upon return to the USGS Illinois Water Science Center the ADVM data were downloaded from the field laptop and reviewed following standard USGS data quality assurance protocols.</abstract>
      <purpose>These data were collected in an attempt to determine the influence of barge passage on water velocities in the Electric Dispersal Barrier System on the Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20150831</begdate>
          <enddate>20150901</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Not planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-88.060918</westbc>
        <eastbc>-88.055125</eastbc>
        <northbc>41.648534</northbc>
        <southbc>41.642242</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>streamflow</themekey>
        <themekey>surface water (non marine)</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal</placekey>
        <placekey>Will County</placekey>
        <placekey>Illinois</placekey>
        <placekey>Romeoville</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>James J. Duncker</cntper>
          <cntorg>USGS Illinois Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>405 N. Goodwin Ave.</address>
          <city>Urbana</city>
          <state>Illinois</state>
          <postal>61801</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>2173289710</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jduncker@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>Great Lakes Restoration Initiative</datacred>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>ADVM data were viewed in real-time on a laptop computer during the deployment and logged simultaneously to the internal memory of the ADVM.  The ADVM data were downloaded from the ADVM to a laptop computer while on site and reviewed briefly while in the field.  Upon return to the USGS Illinois Water Science Center the ADVM data was downloaded from the field laptop to USGS database and reviewed following standard USGS data quality assurance protocols.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20150915</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>This dataset includes BRL41508311254.arg, which is a Sontek ViewArgonaut data file that can be read by the ViewArgonaut software. This dataset also includes the following text files: BRL41508311254.ctl, BRL41508311254.dat, BRL41508311254.snr, BRL41508311254.std, and BRL41508311254.vel. BRL41508311254.ctl contains the system and user-specified configuration setup, as well as attribute definitions for the .dat, .snr, .std, and .vel text files.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>ViewArgonaut User Guide Version 3.62, April 2008</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items must be secured from the copyright owner whenever applicable. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although the data have been subjected to rigorous review and are substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, the data are released on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from authorized or unauthorized use. Although the data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Users of the data are advised to read all metadata and associated documentation thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Digital Geospatial Datasets</formname>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7J964FF</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
    </stdorder>
    <techpreq>The user must have Sontek ViewArgonaut software to read BRL41508311254.arg and software capable of reading text files to view BRL41508311254.ctl, BRL41508311254.dat, BRL41508311254.snr, BRL41508311254.std, and BRL41508311254.vel.</techpreq>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160711</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>James J. Duncker</cntper>
          <cntorg>USGS Illinois Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>405 N. Goodwin Ave.</address>
          <city>Urbana</city>
          <state>Illinois</state>
          <postal>61801</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>2173289710</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jduncker@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>