<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Shah, A.</origin>
        <pubdate>2014</pubdate>
        <title>Airborne Geophysical Surveys over the 2011 Mineral, Virginia, Earthquake Area</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F78K773V</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The 2011 moment magnitude (Mw) 5.8 central Virginia earthquake was felt by millions of people and caused significant damage in the eastern United States. As part of efforts to better understand the faults and geologic features associated with the earthquake, the U.S. Geological Survey commissioned airborne geophysical surveys over the epicentral area. The surveys were conducted from July 15, 2012 - July 25, 2012, by Sander Geophysics Limited. The area was flown along a draped surface with a nominal survey height above ground of 125 meters. The flight line spacing was 200 meters for traverse lines and 2000 meters for control lines. Here we present downloadable gravity, magnetic, and radiometric data from those surveys and summarize research results based on those datasets. The data are provided as image (GeoTiff or kmz), grid (gxf) or flight line (csv) data.</abstract>
      <purpose>Dissemination of airborne geophysical survey data collected near the 2011 moment magnitude 5.8 Mineral, Virginia (Louisa County) earthquake and summary of research results.</purpose>
      <supplinf>These data should be cited as follows: Shah, A., 2014, Airborne Geophysical Surveys over the 2011 Mineral, Virginia, Earthquake Area: U.S. Geological Survey Data Release, http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F78K773V. 

Initial interpretation of gravity and magnetic data are provided by: Shah, A.K., Horton, J.W., Jr., Burton, W.C., Spears, D.B. and Gilmer, A.K. 2015, Subsurface geologic features of the 2011 central Virginia earthquakes revealed by airborne geophysics, in Horton, J.W., Jr., Chapman, M.C., and Green, R.A., eds., The 2011 Mineral, Virginia earthquake and its significance for seismic hazards in Eastern North America: Geological Society of America Special Paper 509. doi: 10.1130/2015.2509(17) 

Initial interpretation of radiometric data are provided by: Horton Jr., J.W., Shah, A.K., McNamara, D.E., Snyder, S.L., and Carter, A.M. 2015, Aftershocks illuminate the 2011 Mineral, Virginia earthquake causative fault zone and nearby active faults, in Horton, J.W., M.C. Chapman, and R.A. Green, eds., The 2011 Mineral, Virginia earthquake and its significance for seismic hazards in Eastern North America, GSA Special Paper 509. doi: 10.1130/2015.2509(14)</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20120715</begdate>
          <enddate>20120725</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>as needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>77.942528</westbc>
        <eastbc>77.762722</eastbc>
        <northbc>38.067361</northbc>
        <southbc>37.745</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>earthquake</themekey>
        <themekey>faults</themekey>
        <themekey>gravity</themekey>
        <themekey>magnetics</themekey>
        <themekey>radiometric data</themekey>
        <themekey>airborne geophysics</themekey>
        <themekey>subsurface imaging</themekey>
        <themekey>intraplate earthquakes</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Virginia</placekey>
        <placekey>Piedmont</placekey>
        <placekey>Mineral</placekey>
        <placekey>Louisa County</placekey>
        <placekey>United States of America</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>None. Users are advised to read the data set's metadata thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Anjana K. Shah</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>DFC Bldg 20, Box 25046, Denver Federal Center, Mail Stop 964</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>303-236-1218</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>ashah@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>The surveys were funded by the U.S. Geological Survey Earthquake Hazards and National Cooperative Geologic Mapping Programs, Natural Hazards and Core Science Systems Mission Areas, Northeast Regional Office, and Crustal Geophysics and Geochemistry Science Center. The data were collected and processed by Sander Geophysics Limited.</datacred>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Anjana K. Shah</origin>
        <origin>J. Wright Horton Jr.</origin>
        <origin>William C. Burton</origin>
        <origin>David B. Spears</origin>
        <origin>Amy K. Gilmer</origin>
        <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
        <title>Subsurface geologic features of the 2011 central Virginia earthquakes revealed by airborne geophysics</title>
        <onlink>https://dx.doi.org/10.1130/2015.2509(17)</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>J. Wright Horton Jr</origin>
            <origin>Martin C. Chapman</origin>
            <origin> Russell A. Green</origin>
            <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
            <title>The 2011 Mineral, Virginia earthquake and its significance for seismic hazards in Eastern North America</title>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>Geological Society of America Special Paper </sername>
              <issue>509</issue>
            </serinfo>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>J. Wright Horton Jr.</origin>
        <origin>Anjana K. Shah</origin>
        <origin>Daniel E. McNamara </origin>
        <origin>Stephen K. Snyder </origin>
        <origin>Aina M. Carter </origin>
        <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
        <title>Aftershocks illuminate the 2011 Mineral, Virginia earthquake causative fault zone and nearby active faults</title>
        <onlink>https://dx.doi.org/10.1130/2015.2509(14)</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>J. Wright Horton Jr</origin>
            <origin>Martin C. Chapman</origin>
            <origin> Russell A. Green</origin>
            <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
            <title>The 2011 Mineral, Virginia earthquake and its significance for seismic hazards in Eastern North America</title>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>Geological Society of America Special Paper </sername>
              <issue>509</issue>
            </serinfo>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Attribute accuracy tests were completed for each of the three datasets (gravity, magnetic, radiometric) and are recorded in each metadata record. In addition further detail is described in the Survey Technical Report by Sander Geophysics at https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/53f5a9c9e4b09d12e0e86438</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Tests for logical consistency between data attributes were performed where appropriate. Final data were also compared to previous regional datasets to check for consistency. Details of data processing for all three datasets can be found in the Survey Technical Report by Sander Geophysics Limited at https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/53f5a9c9e4b09d12e0e86438</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>For details of positional accuracy tests conducted see the metadata for the three datasets (gravity, magnetic, radiometric). The Survey Technical Report by Sander Geophysics Limited at https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/53f5a9c9e4b09d12e0e86438</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>For details of positional accuracy tests conducted see the metadata for the three datasets (gravity, magnetic, radiometric). The Survey Technical Report by Sander Geophysics Limited at https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/53f5a9c9e4b09d12e0e86438</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>The Survey Technical Report by Sander Geophysics Limited describing data collection and processing in detail for the three datasets (gravity, magnetic, radiometric) can be found at https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/53f5a9c9e4b09d12e0e86438</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>18</utmzone>
            <transmer>
              <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
              <longcm>-75.0</longcm>
              <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
              <feast>500000.0</feast>
              <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
            </transmer>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plance>row and column</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>23.927070933333</absres>
            <ordres>23.927070933333</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>Meter</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D_North_American_1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS_1980</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Bldg 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Distributor assumes no liability for misuse of data. No warranty expressed or implied is made by the USGS regarding the use of the data on any other system, nor does the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Gravity Data</formname>
          <formcont>Gravity measurements indicate subtle differences in the density of rocks in Earth's crust. The gravity anomaly can be used to indirectly map the distribution of different rock types. Data include images (GeoTiff or kmz), grid (gxf) or flight line (csv) data. </formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/53f59acee4b09d12e0e845ca</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>none</fees>
    </stdorder>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Magnetic Data</formname>
          <formcont>Magnetic anomaly measurements indicate variations in the intensity of Earth's magnetic field. These variations are generated by differences in magnetic minerals such as magnetite and hematite in Earth's crust, and can be used to indirectly infer differences in rock composition. Data include images (GeoTiff or kmz), grid (gxf) or flight line (csv) data. </formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/53f59abbe4b09d12e0e845c8</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>none</fees>
    </stdorder>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Radiometric Data</formname>
          <formcont>Radiometric methods use gamma ray spectrometry to estimate relative amounts of potassium (K), uranium (U), and thorium (Th) in the upper 0.5-1 meter of Earth's crust. Data include images (GeoTiff or kmz), grid (gxf) or flight line (csv) data. </formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/53f59ad8e4b09d12e0e845cc</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>none</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150618</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Anjana K. Shah</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>DFC Bldg 20, Box 25046, Denver Federal Center, Mail Stop 964</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>303-236-1218</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>ashah@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>