<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
 <idinfo>
  <citation>
   <citeinfo>
    <origin>Jeffrey A. Coe</origin>
    <origin>Rex L. Baum</origin>
    <origin>Kate E. Allstadt</origin>
    <origin>Bernard F. Kochevar</origin>
    <origin>Robert G. Schmitt</origin>
    <origin>Matthew L. Morgan</origin>
    <origin>Jonathan L. White</origin>
    <origin>Ben T. Stratton</origin>
    <origin>Timothy A. Hayashi</origin>
    <origin>Jason W. Kean</origin>
    <pubdate>20160229</pubdate>
    <title>Map data and Unmanned Aircraft System imagery from the May 25, 2014 West Salt Creek rock avalanche in western Colorado</title>
    <geoform>Vector Digital Data Set (Point)</geoform>
    <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F74J0C55</onlink>
    <lworkcit>
     <citeinfo>
      <origin>Jeff Coe</origin>
      <origin>Rex L. Baum</origin>
      <origin>Kate E. Allstadt</origin>
      <origin>Bernard F. Kochevar</origin>
      <origin>Robert G. Schmitt</origin>
      <origin>Matthew L. Morgan</origin>
      <origin>Ben T. Stratton</origin>
      <origin>Timothy A. Hayashi</origin>
      <origin>Jason W. Kean</origin>
      <pubdate>20160229</pubdate>
      <title>Rock-avalanche dynamics revealed by large-scale field mapping and seismic signals at a highly mobile avalanche in the West Salt Creek valley, western Colorado</title>
      <geoform>Publication (Journal)</geoform>
      <serinfo>
       <sername>Geosphere</sername>
       <issue>Vol. 12, no.2</issue>
      </serinfo>
      <pubinfo>
       <pubplace>Boulder, CO</pubplace>
       <publish>Geological Soceity of America</publish>
      </pubinfo>
      <onlink>http://geosphere.gsapubs.org/content/early/2016/02/29/GES01265.1.abstract</onlink>
     </citeinfo>
    </lworkcit>
   </citeinfo>
  </citation>
  <descript>
   <abstract>On May 25, 2014, a rain-on-snow induced rock avalanche occurred in the West Salt Creek Valley on the northern flank of Grand Mesa in western Colorado. The avalanche mobilized from a preexisting rock slide and traveled 4.6 km down the confined valley, killing 3 people. The avalanche was rare for the contiguous U.S. because of its large size (54.5 Mm3) and long travel distance. To understand the avalanche failure sequence, mechanisms, and mobility, we mapped landslide structures, geology, and ponds at 1:1000-scale. We used high-resolution, Unmanned Aircraft System (UAS) imagery from July 2014 as a base for our field mapping. Herein, we present the map data and UAS imagery. The data accompany an interpretive paper published in the journal Geosphere. The full citation for this interpretive journal paper is: Coe, J.A., Baum, R.L., Allstadt, K.E., Kochevar, B.F., Schmitt, R.G., Morgan, M.L., White, J.L.,  Stratton, B. Hayashi, T.A., and Kean, J.W., 2016, Rock avalanche dynamics revealed by large-scale field mapping and seismic signals at a highly mobile avalanche in the West Salt Creek Valley, western Colorado: Geosphere, v. 12, no. 2, p. 607-631,  doi:10.1130/GES01265.1</abstract>
   <purpose>These data were used to interpret the rock avalanche failure sequence, mechanisms, and mobility. Map data include structures (i.e., faults and folds) created by the rock avalanche, geologic units and deposits, the basal-slip surface for the rock slide, and ponds and springs. The orthorectified mosaic of Unmanned Aircraft System (UAS) imagery used for field mapping is also included.</purpose>
  </descript>
  <timeperd>
   <timeinfo>
    <rngdates>
     <begdate>20140525</begdate>
     <enddate>20140930</enddate>
    </rngdates>
   </timeinfo>
   <current>publication date</current>
  </timeperd>
  <status>
   <progress>Complete</progress>
   <update>None planned</update>
  </status>
  <spdom>
   <bounding>
    <westbc>-180</westbc>
    <eastbc>180</eastbc>
    <northbc>90</northbc>
    <southbc>-90</southbc>
   </bounding>
  </spdom>
  <keywords>
   <theme>
    <themekt>None</themekt>
    <themekey>debris flow</themekey>
    <themekey>rainfall</themekey>
    <themekey>rock avalanche</themekey>
    <themekey>rain on snow</themekey>
    <themekey>snowmelt</themekey>
    <themekey>landslide</themekey>
    <themekey>fatalities</themekey>
    <themekey>rock slide</themekey>
    <themekey>Green River Formation</themekey>
    <themekey>Unmanned Aircraft System</themekey>
    <themekey>imagery</themekey>
    <themekey>faults</themekey>
    <themekey>folds</themekey>
    <themekey>debris-flow deposits</themekey>
    <themekey>alluvium</themekey>
    <themekey>breccia</themekey>
    <themekey>ponds</themekey>
    <themekey>springs</themekey>
   </theme>
   <place>
    <placekt>None</placekt>
    <placekey>Grand Mesa</placekey>
    <placekey>Colorado</placekey>
    <placekey>West Salt Creek</placekey>
    <placekey>Collbran, CO</placekey>
   </place>
  </keywords>
  <accconst>None. Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</accconst>
  <useconst>None. Users are advised to read the data set's metadata thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</useconst>
  <ptcontac>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntorgp>
     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
     <cntper>Robert Schmitt</cntper>
    </cntorgp>
    <cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
     <address>Denver Federal Center</address>
     <address>MS 966, Box 25046</address>
     <city>Denver</city>
     <state>CO</state>
     <postal>80225</postal>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>3032738583</cntvoice>
    <cntemail>rschmitt@usgs.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
  </ptcontac>
  <datacred>US Geological Survey, Mesa County Public Works Department, Colorado Geological Survey, US Forest Service</datacred>
  <native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1 (Build 4959) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native>
 </idinfo>
 <dataqual>
  <attracc>
   <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted.</attraccr>
  </attracc>
  <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic>
  <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
  <posacc>
   <horizpa>
    <horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</horizpar>
   </horizpa>
   <vertacc>
    <vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted. Vertical coordinate information is referenced to the North American Vertical Datum of 1988 (NAVD88)</vertaccr>
   </vertacc>
  </posacc>
  <lineage>
   <procstep>
    <procdesc>Field work consisted of mapping rock avalanche structures, geologic units, and hydrologic features (springs and ponds) in the field using orthorectified UAS imagery as a base map. All imagery was acquired using high-resolution Sony cameras in fixed-wing UASs between 26 May and 15 July 2014. Images from each flight were mosaicked and orthorectified by the Mesa County Department of Public Works using Trimble Business Center software. Between 1 June and 30 September 2014, we spent 10 person-weeks in the field mapping on this imagery at 1:1000 scale. After field mapping, all map linework was transferred to a shaded-relief lidar base map derived from 1 m lidar acquired by the Colorado Geological Survey during 1–3 June 2014.  LiDAR data are not part of this USGS data release, but can be requested from the Colorado Geological Survey in Golden, CO.</procdesc>
    <procdate>20140930</procdate>
   </procstep>
  </lineage>
 </dataqual>
 <spdoinfo>
  <direct>Point</direct>
  <ptvctinf>
   <sdtsterm>
    <sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
    <ptvctcnt>1</ptvctcnt>
   </sdtsterm>
  </ptvctinf>
 </spdoinfo>
 <spref>
  <horizsys>
   <planar>
    <gridsys>
     <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
     <utm>
      <utmzone>13</utmzone>
      <transmer>
       <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
       <longcm>-105.0</longcm>
       <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
       <feast>500000.0</feast>
       <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
      </transmer>
     </utm>
    </gridsys>
    <planci>
     <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
     <coordrep>
      <absres>0.6096</absres>
      <ordres>0.6096</ordres>
     </coordrep>
     <plandu>Meter</plandu>
    </planci>
   </planar>
   <geodetic>
    <horizdn>D_WGS_1984</horizdn>
    <ellips>WGS_1984</ellips>
    <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
    <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
   </geodetic>
  </horizsys>
 </spref>
 <eainfo>
  <detailed>
   <enttyp>
    <enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl>
    <enttypd>Table containting UTM coordinates of center of the headscarp.</enttypd>
    <enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
   </enttyp>
   <attr>
    <attrlabl>X</attrlabl>
    <attrdef>Meters</attrdef>
    <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
    <attrdomv>
     <rdom>
      <rdommin>254026.3887</rdommin>
      <rdommax>254026.3887</rdommax>
     </rdom>
    </attrdomv>
   </attr>
   <attr>
    <attrlabl>Y</attrlabl>
    <attrdef>Meters</attrdef>
    <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
    <attrdomv>
     <rdom>
      <rdommin>4338912.8672</rdommin>
      <rdommax>4338912.8672</rdommax>
     </rdom>
    </attrdomv>
   </attr>
  </detailed>
  <overview>
   <eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes the tabular data associated with the data set. Please review the detailed descriptions that are provided (the individual attribute descriptions) for information on the values that appear as fields/table entries of the data set.</eaover>
   <eadetcit>The entity and attribute information was generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Please review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit>
  </overview>
 </eainfo>
 <distinfo>
  <distrib>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntorgp>
     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
    </cntorgp>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
     <address>Denver Federal Center</address>
     <address>Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
     <city>Denver</city>
     <state>CO</state>
     <postal>80225</postal>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
    <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
  </distrib>
  <distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items must be secured from the copyright owner whenever applicable. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although the data have been subjected to rigorous review and are substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, the data are released on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from authorized or unauthorized use. Although the data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Users of the data are advised to read all metadata and associated documentation thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</distliab>
  <stdorder>
   <digform>
    <digtinfo>
     <formname>Vector Digital Data Set (Point)</formname>
    </digtinfo>
    <digtopt>
     <onlinopt>
      <computer>
       <networka>
        <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F74J0C55</networkr>
       </networka>
      </computer>
     </onlinopt>
    </digtopt>
   </digform>
   <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
  </stdorder>
 </distinfo>
 <metainfo>
  <metd>20160510</metd>
  <metc>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntperp>
     <cntper>Robert Schmitt</cntper>
     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
    </cntperp>
    <cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
     <address>Denver Federal Center</address>
     <address>MS 966, Box 25046</address>
     <city>Denver</city>
     <state>CO</state>
     <postal>80225</postal>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>3032738583</cntvoice>
    <cntemail>rschmitt@usgs.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
  </metc>
  <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
  <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
 </metainfo>
</metadata>
