<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
	<idinfo>
		<citation>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin>Joseph Mangano</origin>
				<origin>Greg Lind</origin>
				<origin>Roy Wellman</origin>
				<origin>Rose Wallick</origin>
				<pubdate>20160427</pubdate>
				<title>Boat-based water-surface elevation surveys along the upper Willamette River, Oregon, in March, 2015</title>
				<geoform>Vector Digital Data Set (Point)</geoform>
				<onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7TM786X</onlink>
			</citeinfo>
		</citation>
		<descript>
			<abstract>Water-surface elevation measurements were collected in March 2015 along the upper Willamette River, Oregon, between Eugene to Corvallis. These surveys were collected over a small range of discharges using a real time kinematic global positioning system (RTK-GPS) on a motorboat traveling "on plane" along the river. These datasets were collected for equipment calibration and validation for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration’s (NASA) Surface Water and Ocean Topography (SWOT) satellite mission. This is one of multiple survey datasets that will be released for this effort.</abstract>
			<purpose>The National Aeronautics and Space Administration’s (NASA) Surface Water and Ocean Topography (SWOT) satellite is scheduled for launch in 2020, which will monitor the earth’s fresh water with unprecedented resolution and precision for a space-based platform. The primary SWOT measurements will be used to, among other things, generate estimates of river discharge that are meant to obtain river fluxes globally at high accuracy and reach lengths of tens of kilometers, even in inaccessible areas of the world or areas where in-situ measurements are not available. Prior to the launch of the SWOT satellite, the wide-swath interferometer is attached to an air plane for thorough calibration and validation (at which time it is referred to as AirSWOT). The Willamette River in northwest Oregon is one site used to calibrate and validate AirSWOT measurements and discharge calculations because it is large enough for the resolution of the SWOT equipment, it is relatively accessible for intensive collection of ground-based data, and it is well-gaged and studied by regional agencies. The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and University of Oregon (UO) to collected ground-based survey measurements for validation with AirSWOT surveys of the Willamette River in the spring of 2015. In addition to the validation goals, these datasets may be useful for other studies along the reach including hydraulic models and habitat assessments.</purpose>
		</descript>
		<timeperd>
			<timeinfo>
				<rngdates>
					<begdate>20150316</begdate>
					<enddate>20150330</enddate>
				</rngdates>
			</timeinfo>
			<current>ground condition</current>
		</timeperd>
		<status>
			<progress>Complete</progress>
			<update>None planned</update>
		</status>
		<spdom>
			<bounding>
				<westbc>-123.257985971</westbc>
				<eastbc>-123.111143924</eastbc>
				<northbc>44.554926397</northbc>
				<southbc>44.130685546</southbc>
			</bounding>
		</spdom>
		<keywords>
			<theme>
				<themekt>None</themekt>
				<themekey>water surface elevation</themekey>
				<themekey>river</themekey>
				<themekey>surface water</themekey>
				<themekey>RTK</themekey>
				<themekey>inland waters</themekey>
				<themekey>AirSWOT</themekey>
				<themekey>discharge</themekey>
			</theme>
			<place>
				<placekt>None</placekt>
				<placekey>Willamette River</placekey>
				<placekey>Oregon</placekey>
				<placekey>Eugene</placekey>
				<placekey>Corvallis</placekey>
			</place>
		</keywords>
		<accconst>No access constraints as all data is open and non-proprietary</accconst>
		<useconst>The USGS shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data retrieved from the system. The USGS should be acknowledged as the data source in derived products.</useconst>
		<ptcontac>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntorgp>
					<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Oregon Water Science Center</cntorg>
				</cntorgp>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
					<address>2130 S.W. Fifth Avenue</address>
					<city>Portland</city>
					<state>OR</state>
					<postal>97201</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>503-251-3200</cntvoice>
				<cntfax>503-251-3470</cntfax>
				<cntemail>info-or@usgs.gov</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</ptcontac>
		<datacred>National Aeronautics and Space Administration</datacred>
		<native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1 (Build 4959) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native>
	</idinfo>
	<dataqual>
		<attracc>
			<attraccr>RTK-GPS surveys were open and closed daily to a locally placed benchmark near the McCartney launch. Additionally, a nearby National Geodetic Survey benchmark west of Albany, OR was surveyed to confirm RTK-GPS accuracy during the project. This dataset and metadata were reviewed by team members and an official USGS data release peer reviewer.</attraccr>
		</attracc>
		<logic>Location and elevation values were visually inspected in ArcMap and Excel to identify outliers and erroneous values. Additionally, water surface elevation values were confirmed with a network of pressure transducers placed every 2-3 kilometers along the river (published separately in the USGS Flood Event Viewer database; https://stn.wim.usgs.gov/FEV/)</logic>
		<complete>This is not a complete record of water surface elevation along the upper Willamette River. Specific reaches and locations were targeted for surveys as deemed appropriate and necessary for the project goals and field constraints.</complete>
		<posacc>
			<horizpa>
				<horizpar>Horizontal dilution of precision (HDOP) and horizontal precision values collected by the RTK-GPS during the survey are provided. The outputs are reliable and taken to the be the best indicator of horizontal error.</horizpar>
			</horizpa>
			<vertacc>
				<vertaccr>Vertical dilution of precision (VDOP) and vertical precision values collected by the RTK-GPS during the survey are provided. For these water-surface elevation profiles, tilt of the boat along sharp bends in the river influenced the elevation measurements, sometimes up to 30 centimeters but more typically less than 10 centimeters. Those values considered extraneously high were flagged and should not be considered for high-precision water surface elevation applications unless the user determines their own way to detrend the erroneous elevation values. Comparing the boat-based elevation profiles to the network of pressure transducers indicates that the combined internal error of the elevation has a range of +/- 0.22 meters and a standard deviation of 0.10 meters. </vertaccr>
			</vertacc>
		</posacc>
		<lineage>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Collect RTK-GPS data in field, including offset measurements.</procdesc>
				<procdate>20150330</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Export RTK-GPS data to CSV format.</procdesc>
				<procdate>20150415</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Compute boat height offset.</procdesc>
				<procdate>20151015</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Remove rod height and boat height offset from elevation values.</procdesc>
				<procdate>20151016</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Review dataset in ArcMap and identify elevation values to "flag."</procdesc>
				<procdate>20151105</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Export as final shapefile for review.</procdesc>
				<procdate>20151119</procdate>
			</procstep>
		</lineage>
	</dataqual>
	<spdoinfo>
		<direct>Point</direct>
		<ptvctinf>
			<sdtsterm>
				<sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
				<ptvctcnt>13112</ptvctcnt>
			</sdtsterm>
		</ptvctinf>
	</spdoinfo>
	<spref>
		<horizsys>
			<planar>
				<gridsys>
					<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
					<utm>
						<utmzone>10</utmzone>
						<transmer>
							<sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
							<longcm>-123.0</longcm>
							<latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
							<feast>500000.0</feast>
							<fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
						</transmer>
					</utm>
				</gridsys>
				<planci>
					<plance>coordinate pair</plance>
					<coordrep>
						<absres>0.6096</absres>
						<ordres>0.6096</ordres>
					</coordrep>
					<plandu>Meter</plandu>
				</planci>
			</planar>
			<geodetic>
				<horizdn>D_North_American_1983</horizdn>
				<ellips>GRS_1980</ellips>
				<semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
				<denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
			</geodetic>
		</horizsys>
	</spref>
	<eainfo>
		<detailed>
			<enttyp>
				<enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl>
				<enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the survey dataset. RTK-GPS survey conducted using a Trimble R8 GNSS system (http://www.trimble.com/Survey/trimbler8gnss.aspx) on the Oregon real-time GNSS network (http://www.oregon.gov/ODOT/HWY/THEORGN/Pages/Theorgn-Home.aspx).</enttypd>
				<enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
			</enttyp>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>FID</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>date</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Date of survey point</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>RTK-GPS output</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Date of survey point, in format of YYYYMMDD</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>time_utc</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Time of survey point</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Time (UTC) of survey point, in format of HH:MM:SS</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>northing</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Northing coordinate of survey point, in NAD83 UTM Zone 10N</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>RTK-GPS output</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>4886419.853</rdommin>
						<rdommax>4933516.393</rdommax>
						<attrunit>meter</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>easting</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Easting coordinate of survey point, in NAD83 UTM Zone 10N</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>RTK-GPS output</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>479509.876</rdommin>
						<rdommax>491108.752</rdommax>
						<attrunit>meter</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>wse_83elev</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Orthometric height of survey point, which was computed by subtracting survey rod height and boat height offset from elevation output of RTK-GPS.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>60.451</rdommin>
						<rdommax>111.348</rdommax>
						<attrunit>meter</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>wse_83elip</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>1983 ellipsoid height of survey point, which was computed by subtracting survey rod height and boat height offset from elipsoid output of RTK-GPS. The Oregon real-time GNSS network uses 1983 Geoid 9 for computing orthometric height.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>37.727</rdommin>
						<rdommax>88.08</rdommax>
						<attrunit>meter</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>wse_flag</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Flag for water surface elevation values that may be higher or lower than actual values as a result of tilt and roll of the boat during surveys (see vertical accuracy statement for more details).</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom>
						<edomv>0</edomv>
						<edomvd>Elevation value has more potential for being higher or lower than actual values as a result of tilt and roll of the boat during surveys; consider avoiding these elevation values for high-precision applications of water surface elevation.</edomvd>
						<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
					</edom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom>
						<edomv>1</edomv>
						<edomvd>Elevation value has less potential for being higher or lower than actual values as a result of tilt and roll of the boat during surveys.</edomvd>
						<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
					</edom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>gps_qual</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Quality of RTK-GPS survey point</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>RTK-GPS output</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom>
						<edomv>Fixed</edomv>
						<edomvd>RTK-GPS fixed at time of shot.</edomvd>
						<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
					</edom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>sats</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Number of satellites used in survey point</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>RTK-GPS output</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>5</rdommin>
						<rdommax>14</rdommax>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>hdop</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Horizontal dilution of precision of survey point</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>RTK-GPS output</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>0.81</rdommin>
						<rdommax>7.402</rdommax>
						<attrunit>unitless</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>vdop</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Vertical dilution of precision of survey point</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>RTK-GPS output</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>1.259</rdommin>
						<rdommax>6.447</rdommax>
						<attrunit>unitless</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>h_prec</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Horizontal precision of survey point</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>RTK-GPS output</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>0.016</rdommin>
						<rdommax>0.093</rdommax>
						<attrunit>meter</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>v_prec</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Vertical precision of survey shot</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>RTK-GPS output</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>0.018</rdommin>
						<rdommax>0.116</rdommax>
						<attrunit>meter</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
		</detailed>
		<overview>
			<eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes the tabular data associated with the data set. Please review the individual attribute descriptions for information on the values that appear as fields/table entries of the data set. Most values are direct outputs from the RTK-GPS used for the survey.</eaover>
			<eadetcit>The entity and attribute information was generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Additional details are provided within this metadata documentation.</eadetcit>
		</overview>
	</eainfo>
	<distinfo>
		<distrib>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntorgp>
					<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
				</cntorgp>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
					<address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
					<city>Denver</city>
					<state>CO</state>
					<postal>80225</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
			</cntinfo>
		</distrib>
		<distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items must be secured from the copyright owner whenever applicable. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although the data have been subjected to rigorous review and are substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, the data are released on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from authorized or unauthorized use. Although the data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Users of the data are advised to read all metadata and associated documentation thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</distliab>
		<stdorder>
			<digform>
				<digtinfo>
					<formname>Vector Digital Data Set (Point)</formname>
				</digtinfo>
				<digtopt>
					<onlinopt>
						<computer>
							<networka>
								<networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7TM786X</networkr>
							</networka>
						</computer>
					</onlinopt>
				</digtopt>
			</digform>
			<fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
		</stdorder>
	</distinfo>
	<metainfo>
		<metd>20160504</metd>
		<metc>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntper>Joseph F Mangano</cntper>
					<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>Hydrologist</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
					<address>2130 S.W. Fifth Avenue</address>
					<city>Portland</city>
					<state>OR</state>
					<postal>97201</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>503-251-3227</cntvoice>
				<cntfax>503-251-3470</cntfax>
				<cntemail>jmangano@usgs.gov</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</metc>
		<metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
		<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
	</metainfo>
	<Esri><CreaDate>20160506</CreaDate><CreaTime>06490600</CreaTime><SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce><DataProperties><itemProps><itemLocation><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\IGSWOAWWLTJOJO\E\users\jmangano\NASA\FINAL_DATASETS\Willamette2015_WSE_Profile_meta (1)</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></itemLocation></itemProps><copyHistory><copy source="E:\users\jmangano\NASA\FINAL_DATASETS\Willamette2015_WSE_Profile_meta" dest="\\IGSWOAWWLTJOJO\E\users\jmangano\NASA\FINAL_DATASETS\Willamette2015_WSE_Profile_meta (1)" date="20160506" time="06490600"></copy></copyHistory></DataProperties></Esri></metadata>
