<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-ntl.92.7" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0  http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
	<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
		<allow>
			<principal>uid=NTL, o=lter, dc=ecoinformatics, dc=org</principal>
			<permission>all</permission>
		</allow>
		<allow>
			<principal>public</principal>
			<permission>read</permission>
		</allow>
	</access>
	<dataset>
		<alternateIdentifier system="NTL-DEIMS">5654</alternateIdentifier>
		<shortName>LPPCHL1</shortName>
		<title>Landscape Position Project at North Temperate Lakes LTER: Chlorophyll 1998 - 2000</title>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Ben</givenName>
				<surName>Greenfield</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Thomas</givenName>
				<surName>Hrabik</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>University of Minnesota</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>1035 Kirby Dr</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Duluth</city>
      <administrativeArea>MN</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>55812</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">(218) 726-7626</phone>
			<phone phonetype="fax">(218) 726-8142</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>thrabik@d.umn.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Timothy</givenName>
				<surName>Kratz</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>10810 County Highway N</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Boulder Junction</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>54512</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">(715) 356-9494</phone>
			<phone phonetype="fax">(715) 356-6866</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>tkkratz@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>David</givenName>
				<surName>Lewis</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
    </address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">(608) 262-5905</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>dlewis2@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>David</givenName>
				<surName>Lewis</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <city>University Park</city>
      <administrativeArea>PA</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>16802</postalCode>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>dbl11@psu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Amina</givenName>
				<surName>Pollard</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Karen</givenName>
				<surName>Wilson</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <country>Canada</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>k.wilson@utoronto.ca</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<metadataProvider>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</metadataProvider>
		<pubDate>2005</pubDate>
		<language>english</language>
		<abstract>
			<para>Parameters characterizing the chemical limnology and spatial attributes of 49 lakes were
				surveyed as part of the Landscape Position Project. Most parameters are measured at or close
				to the deepest part of the lake. Chlorophyll is measured by collecting separate integrated
				samples from the epilimnion, metalimnion, and hypolimnion Sampling Frequency: generally
				monthly for one summer; for some lakes, one or two samples in one summer Number of sites: 51
			</para>
		</abstract>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>chlorophyll</keyword>
			<keyword>chlorophyll a</keyword>
			<keyword>primary production</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>LTER Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>NTL LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>North Temperate Lakes - LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>phaeophyton</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>NTL Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<intellectualRights>
			<section>
				<title>Data Policies</title>
				<para>Copyright Board of Regents, University of Wisconsin, Madison. This information is
					released to the public and may be used for academic, educational, or commercial purposes
					subject to the following restrictions: The Data User must realize that these data sets are
					being actively used by others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary
					to prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the NTL lead Principal
					Investigator, leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu, to check on other uses of the data. Where
					appropriate, the Data User may be encouraged to consider collaboration and/or
					co-authorship with original investigators.</para>
				<para>The Data User must realize that the data may be misinterpreted if taken out of
					context. We request that you provide the NTL lead Principal Investigator, ATTN: Data
					Access, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison, 680 North Park St.,
					Madison, WI 53706 with a copy of any manuscript using the data so that it may be reviewed
					and comments provided on the presentation of our data.</para>
				<para>The Data User must acknowledge use of the data by an appropriate citation (see
					Citation) of the NTL-LTER database. A generic citation for our databases is: name of data
					set, North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research program, NSF, contact person for
					data set, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison. The data set name and
					contact person for each data set can be found in the metadata header of the online data
					sets.</para>
				<para>The Data User must send two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the
					data to the address above. We would like to include such manuscripts in our LTER
					publications list.</para>
				<para>The Data User must not redistribute original data and documentation without permission
					from Emily Stanley, lead Principal Investigator, (ehstanley@wisc.edu).</para>
				<para>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation,
					complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is".
					The North Temperate Lakes LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or
					misinterpretation of data sets. Data users should be aware that we periodically update
					data sets.</para>
				<para>Our goal is to release all long term data associated with core research areas within 2
					years of collection. These data and accompanying metadata will be available for download
					from the NTL-LTER web site.</para>
				<para>By using these data, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement.
					Thank you for your cooperation. </para>
			</section>
		</intellectualRights>
		<distribution>
			<online>
				<url function="information">http://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/node/5654</url>
			</online>
		</distribution>
		<coverage>
			<geographicCoverage>
				<geographicDescription>Allequash Lake,Anderson Lake,Arrowhead Lake,Beaver Lake,Big Lake,Big Crooked Lake,Big Gibson Lake,Big Muskellunge Lake,Boulder Lake,Brandy Lake,Crampton Lake,Crystal Lake,Diamond Lake,Flora Lake,Heart Lake,Ike Walton Lake,Island Lake,Johnson Lake,Katherine Lake,Kathleen Lake,Katinka Lake,Lehto Lake,Little Crooked Lake,Little Muskie,Little Spider Lake,Little Sugarbush Lake,Little Trout Lake,Lower Kaubeshine Lake,Lynx Lake,McCullough Lake,Mid Lake,Minocqua Lake,Muskesin Lake,Nixon Lake,Partridge Lake,Randall Lake,Round Lake,Sanford Lake,Sparkling Lake,Statenaker Lake,Stearns Lake,Tomahawk Lake,Trout Lake,Upper Kaubeshine Lake,Verna Lake,Ward Lake,White Birch Lake,White Sand Lake,Wild Rice Lake,Wildcat Lake,Wolf Lake,Vilas County,WI,Iron County,WI,Oneida County,WI,Gogebic County,MI,USA
</geographicDescription>
				<boundingCoordinates>
					<westBoundingCoordinate>-90.044</westBoundingCoordinate>
					<eastBoundingCoordinate>-88.936</eastBoundingCoordinate>
					<northBoundingCoordinate>46.300</northBoundingCoordinate>
					<southBoundingCoordinate>45.855</southBoundingCoordinate>
				</boundingCoordinates>
			</geographicCoverage>
			<temporalCoverage>
				<rangeOfDates>
					<beginDate>
						<calendarDate>1998-05-28</calendarDate>
					</beginDate>
					<endDate>
						<calendarDate>2000-07-22</calendarDate>
					</endDate>
				</rangeOfDates>
			</temporalCoverage>
		</coverage>
		<maintenance>
			<description>
				<para>completed </para>
			</description>
		</maintenance>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Information Manager</positionName>
			<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
			<organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<publisher>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</publisher>
		<pubPlace>North Temperate Lakes</pubPlace>
		<methods>
			<methodStep>
				<description>
					<section>
						<para>Chlorophyll is measured by collecting separate integrated samples from the
							epilimnion, metalimnion, and hypolimnion </para>
					</section>
					<section>
						<para>A. Chlorophyll Extraction 1. Dim the lights and keep the sample tubes in the
							freezer: Because chlorophyll degrades when exposed to light and heat, this procedure
							and all others associated with analyzing chlorophyll should be carried out in dim
							light conditions. Only one sample tube should be out of the freezer at any one time
							while the pre-grinding or grinding procedure is occurring. Return each tube to the
							freezer as soon as its filter has been ground. 2. Pre-grind filters: Use the sharpened
							stainless steel spatula to chop up the filter into small pieces. This should take
							approximately 1 minute. 3. Grind filters: Grind filters using the tissue homogenizer.
							Place the homogenizer into the tube with the chopped filter. Turn on the homogenizer
							once it is in the tube and grind for at approximately one minute, moving tube up and
							down to ensure all chopped filter pieces are ground up. Be sure to turn off
							homogenizer before removing it from the tube. Rinse homogenizer with acetone after
							every sample. 4. Return the sample tubes to the freezer for 24 hours: Most protocols
							call for storing the grinded samples at 4 degree C. However, after storing duplicate
							samples in the freezer and refrigerator (after grinding) there was no significant
							difference in the chlorophyll results. Because past samples have been stored in the
							freezer, this is the current procedure being used. B. Centrifuging the Samples: The
							samples should be centrifuged as close as possible to 24 hours after extraction.
							Before centrifuging the samples, turn on the spectrophotometer vis light to allow the
							light to warm up for 60 minutes. 1. Loading the Marathon 21000 Fisher Scientific
							centrifuge: Making sure that the caps are on tight, put tubes with equal acetone
							volumes opposite each other in the centrifuge. If there is an odd tube remaining or a
							tube with a different volume, put a spare tube opposite the sample with the same
							volume of water to counterbalance the centrifuge. It is essential to load centrifuge
							buckets evenly to ensure proper balance. 2. Running the centrifuge: Run the centrifuge
							at 4000 RPMs for 15 minutes. This is programmed as Program 1 on the centrifuge. If the
							centrifuge is on Program 1, just press start and it will go automatically. If there is
							an imbalance in the centrifuge the centrifuge will shut down. In this case, stop the
							centrifuge and attempt to locate the imbalance. Sometimes this requires a placement
							shift in the center post of the bucket holders. 3. Unloading the centrifuge: Carefully
							take each sample tube out of the centrifuge with minimal mixing. If the filter paper
							is mixed with the liquid, it will be necessary to re-centrifuge the sample. Transport
							the samples to the freezer until it is time to process. C. Running a Sample: Ensure
							the spectrophotometer vis light has been on for at least 60 minutes. Exit from the
							small screen with the start-up results. Make sure the cuvette holder in the
							spectrophotometer is empty and clear of anything that could block the light waves. 1.
							Select the test: Click on Fix Wavelength, then click on Method on the top of the
							screen, choose LTERCHLA (the screen will not change). Exit from this small screen. 2.
							Run a blank and check that all cuvettes read near 0: Add acetone to a 1x1 mm, chemical
							resistant, macro, disposable cuvette and wipe it clean with a tissue then place it in
							the holder inside the spectrophotometer. Left click on Blank. No numbers will appear,
							this is just a calibration. Click on Read Sample on the top left of the screen. All of
							the readings at all wavelengths should be within .001 of 0 or under 0.0004. If this is
							not the case, remove the suspect cuvette and rinse, wipe, add acetone, and rerun it.
							Make sure that the correct program is being run by checking the wavelengths. The LTER
							samples should be run at 750, 665, 664, 647, and 630 nm. 3. Add sample to a cuvette:
							Before bringing the samples into the spectrophotometer room, turn off the overhead
							light. Carefully remove a sample from the rack and pipette approximately 2 mL of
							sample into a cuvette. Use caution not to suck up any filter paper into the pipette;
							tilt the sample to the side and submerge the pipette tip only just below the fluid
							level. If the pipette tip is getting close to the filter paper when removing the
							second mL of sample, stop pipetting and add the partial mL to the cuvette (it is
							possible to read approximately 1.5 mL of sample). 4. Check the 750 nm reading and run
							the sample: Insert the cuvette into the spec. making sure that the clear sides of the
							cuvette are facing left and right. The default reading on the spec is 750 nm. Click on
							Run Sample. Check to make sure that this reading is less than 0.010. If the reading is
							higher, remove the cuvette and re-wipe it with a tissue. If the reading is still high,
							pour the sample back into the tube and re-centrifuge it. 5. Rinse the pipette tip:
							Before adding another sample to a cuvette, the pipette tip should be rinsed with
							acetone. You should have 2 different sized beakers, one for waste and one for acetone
							rinse. Be sure that the pipette tip is firmly on the pipette (press it on the bottom
							of the rinse beaker). 6. Acidify the sample: Once the sample has been run, remove it
							from the spec and add 60 uL of 0.1 N HCl (30 uL per 1 mL of sample). Gently shake the
							sample and wait 90 seconds to run it. C. Running Multiple Samples: 1. It may be more
							efficient to run 2 samples before acidification and then run them both after
							acidification. If this is done, take caution to add the correct sample to the correct
							cuvette and not to mix up the samples when they are removed from the spec. for
							acidification. Recording the Results: 1. Record the results of each sample for every
							wavelength designated on spreadsheet before and after acidification. Be sure to
							include the lake, mL filtered, date of sample and date of analysis. Clean-up: 1. Rinse
							thoroughly and discard all used cuvettes and tubes of processed samples. 2. Dilute all
							samples to a solution of less than 20percent Acetone and disposed of down the drain.
							Fill the waste beaker with water and pour the waste down the sink with the water
							running. Leave the water running for several minutes 3. Rinse the beakers and pipette
							tips 3 times with tap water followed by 3 rinses with distilled water. &#194;&#160; </para>
					</section>
				</description>
			</methodStep>
		</methods>
		<project>
			<title>Landscape Position Project in North Temperate Lakes Study Area</title>
			<personnel>
				<individualName>
					<givenName>Thomas</givenName>
					<surName>Hrabik</surName>
				</individualName>
				<organizationName>University of Minnesota</organizationName>
				<address>
        <deliveryPoint>1035 Kirby Dr</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Duluth</city>
        <administrativeArea>MN</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>55812</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
				<phone phonetype="voice">(218) 726-7626</phone>
				<phone phonetype="fax">(218) 726-8142</phone>
				<electronicMailAddress>thrabik@d.umn.edu</electronicMailAddress>
				<role>project personnel</role>
			</personnel>
			<personnel>
				<individualName>
					<givenName>Timothy</givenName>
					<surName>Kratz</surName>
				</individualName>
				<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
				<address>
        <deliveryPoint>10810 County Highway N</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Boulder Junction</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>54512</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
				<phone phonetype="voice">(715) 356-9494</phone>
				<phone phonetype="fax">(715) 356-6866</phone>
				<electronicMailAddress>tkkratz@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
				<role>project personnel</role>
			</personnel>
			<personnel>
				<individualName>
					<givenName>David</givenName>
					<surName>Lewis</surName>
				</individualName>
				<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
				<address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      </address>
				<phone phonetype="voice">(608) 262-5905</phone>
				<electronicMailAddress>dlewis2@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
				<role>project personnel</role>
			</personnel>
			<abstract>
				<para>The importance of the position of a lake in the landscape relative to hydrologic flow
					has been a focus of the Long-Term Ecological Research Project, based at the UW-Madison
					Center for Limnology, for almost two decades. We have found that there are strong patterns
					in water chemistry, primary productivity, and morphology driven by ground and surface
					water inputs (Magnuson et. al. 1990, Kratz et al. 1997, Riera et al. in press). Also, lake
					size and physico-chemical conditions within a lake have been shown to influence community
					structure in fishes (Tonn and Magnuson 1982, Tonn et al.1990). However, we know much less
					about how landscape level traits, such as surface water connections, influence biotic
					diversity and community structure within lakes and whether the species pool changes across
					watersheds of North-Central Wisconsin (Hrabik and Magnuson 1999). The primary goal of our
					project is to conduct field experiments that contrast lake chemical and geographical
					properties and explore the role of those properties in shaping biotic diversity and
					community structure. </para>
			</abstract>
		</project>
		<dataTable>
			<entityName>landscape_position_chlorophyll</entityName>
			<entityDescription>Landscape Position Project: Chlorophyll</entityDescription>
			<physical>
				<objectName>landscapepositionchlorophyll</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
						<recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
							<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-ntl.92&amp;urlTail=ntl/data/5654_v1.csv</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<coverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Crystal Lake is located within the Northern Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County.
It is a seepage lake with predominantly sand substrate. It has a surface area of 36.7 hectare, 2.3 kilometers of highly developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 20.4 meters.
Crystal Lake represents one extreme in the groundwater input gradient, with a marked predominance of precipitation inputs. Groundwater accounts for only 5% of input water, yet, because groundwater is more concentrated chemically than precipitation, groundwater accounts for substantial amounts of incoming solutes. For example, about 50% of the silica budget comes into the lake via groundwater, exerting a major influence on primary production.
The lake is an oligotrophic, dimictic lake high in the landscape with minimal groundwater input, a light attenuation coefficient of 0.24 per meter (average ice-free Secchi depth of 8 m), a mean depth of 11.4 m, and a maximum depth of 20.4 m. Crystal Lake is circular with a shoreline development factor very close to 1.0. The littoral zone is fairly homogenous and is dominated by sandy substrate with low macrophyte and coarse woody habitat densities. The fish community has been historically dominated by pelagic yellow perch. However, yellow perch drastically declined after the detection of rainbow smelt in 1985.

</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.612233</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.612233</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>46.00275</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>46.00275</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Big Muskellunge Lake is located within the Northern Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County.
It is a seepage lake with predominantly sand and gravel substrate. It has a surface area of 396.3 hectare, 16.1 kilometers of moderately developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 21.3 meters.
</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.611783</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.611783</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>46.021067</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>46.021067</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Sparkling Lake is located within the Northern Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County.
It is a seepage lake with predominantly sand and gravel substrate. It has a surface area of 64 hectare, 4.3 kilometers of moderately developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 20 meters.
</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.701183</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.701183</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>46.007733</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>46.007733</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Allequash Lake is located within the Northern Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County. T41N-R7E, Sections 16, 17, 20, 21. 398 acres. (detailed lake description by the WDNR)
It is a drainage lake with predominantly sand and gravel substrate. It has a surface area of 168.4 hectare, 9.5 kilometers of mostly undeveloped shoreline and a maximum depth of 8 meters.
</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.620617</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.620617</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>46.038317</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>46.038317</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Trout Lake is located within the Northern Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County.
It is a drainage lake with predominantly gravel and sand substrate. It has a surface area of 1607.9 hectare, 25.9 kilometers of mostly undeveloped shoreline and a maximum depth of 35.7 meters.
</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.665017</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.665017</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>46.029267</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>46.029267</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
			</coverage>
			<attributeList>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>lake</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>lake name</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>lake name</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>lake name</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>sampledate</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>sample date</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>sample date</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>date</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<dateTime>
							<formatString>yyyy-MM-dd</formatString>
						</dateTime>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>rep</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>replicate number</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>replicate number</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>replicate number</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>top</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>depth of top of sample</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>top of vertically integrated depth</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
								<bounds>
									<minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
									<maximum exclusive="false">40</maximum>
								</bounds>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>bottom</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>depth of bottom of sample</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>bottom of vertically integrated depth</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
								<bounds>
									<minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
									<maximum exclusive="false">40</maximum>
								</bounds>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>volfiltered</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>volume of water filtered</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>total volume of water filtered</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>milliliter</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
								<bounds>
									<minimum exclusive="false">150</minimum>
									<maximum exclusive="false">5000</maximum>
								</bounds>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>chl</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>total chlorophyll</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>total chlorophyll</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microgramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
								<bounds>
									<minimum exclusive="false">-500</minimum>
									<maximum exclusive="false">1000</maximum>
								</bounds>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>phaeo</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>total phaeopigments</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>total degraded phaeopigments</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microgramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
								<bounds>
									<minimum exclusive="false">-500</minimum>
									<maximum exclusive="false">1000</maximum>
								</bounds>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>chl_plus_phaeo</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>chlorophyll plus phaeo</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>chlorophyll plus phaeo</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microgramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
								<bounds>
									<minimum exclusive="false">-500</minimum>
									<maximum exclusive="false">1000</maximum>
								</bounds>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
			</attributeList>
		</dataTable>
	</dataset>
	<additionalMetadata>
		<metadata>
			<ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1     http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
				<ns2:unit abbreviation="&#181;g/l" constantToSI="0" id="microgramPerLiter" multiplierToSI="0.000001" name="microgramPerLiter" parentSI="kilogramPerCubicMeter" unitType="massDensity">
					<ns2:description>micrograms / liter</ns2:description>
				</ns2:unit>
			</ns2:unitList>
		</metadata>
	</additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>