<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-ntl.224.8" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0  http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
	<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
		<allow>
			<principal>uid=NTL, o=lter, dc=ecoinformatics, dc=org</principal>
			<permission>all</permission>
		</allow>
		<allow>
			<principal>public</principal>
			<permission>read</permission>
		</allow>
	</access>
	<dataset>
		<alternateIdentifier system="NTL-DEIMS">5626</alternateIdentifier>
		<shortName>DODSON3</shortName>
		<title>Zooplankton of Small Lakes and Wetland Ponds in Wisconsin - North Temperate Lakes LTER 1996</title>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Stanley</givenName>
				<surName>Dodson</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
    </address>
		</creator>
		<metadataProvider>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</metadataProvider>
		<pubDate>2000</pubDate>
		<language>english</language>
		<abstract>
			<para>We sampled zooplankton communities from 54 small water bodies distributed throughout
				Wisconsin to evaluate whether a snap-shot of zooplankton community structure during early
				spring could be used for the purpose of differentiating lakes from wetlands. We collected a
				single set of zooplankton and water chemistry data during a one-month time window
				(synchronized from south to north across the state) from an open water site in each basin as
				a means to minimize and standardize sampling effort and to minimize cascading effects
				arising from predator-prey interactions with resident and immigrant aquatic insect
				communities. We identified 53 taxa of zooplankton from 54 sites sampled across Wisconsin.
				There was an average of 6.83 taxa per site. The zooplankton species were distributed with a
				great deal of independence. We did not detect significant correlations between number of
				taxa and geographic region or waterbody size. There was a significant inverse correlation
				between number of taxa and the concentration of calcium ion, alkalinity and conductivity.
				One pair of taxa, Lynceus brachyurus and Chaoborus americanus, showed a significant
				difference in average duration of sites of their respective occurrence. All other pairs of
				taxa had no significant difference in average latitude, waterbody surface area, total
				phosphorus, total Kjeldahl nitrogen, alkalinity, conductivity, calcium ion, sulfate,
				nitrate, silicate or chloride. Taxa were distributed at random among the sites - there were
				no statistically significant pairs of taxa occurring together or avoiding each other.
				Multivariate analysis of zooplankton associations showed no evidence of distinct
				associations that could be used to distinguish lakes from wetlands. Zooplankton community
				structure appears to be a poor tool for distinguishing between lakes and wetlands,
				especially at the relatively large scale of Wisconsin (dimension of about 500 km). The data
				suggest that a small body of water in Wisconsin could be classified as a wetland if it
				persists in the spring and summer for only about 4 months, and if it is inhabited by Lynceus
				brachyurus, Eubranchipus bundyi, and if Chaoborus americanus and Chydorus brevilabris are
				absent. Schell, Jeffery M., Carlos J. Santos-Flores, Paula E. Allen, Brian M. Hunker, Scott
				Kloehn, Aaron Michelson, Richard A. Lillie, and Stanley I. Dodson. 2001. Physical-chemical
				influences on vernal zooplankton community structure in small lakes and wetlands of
				Wisconsin, U.S.A. Hydrobiologia 445:37-50 Number of sites: 54 </para>
		</abstract>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>alkalinity</keyword>
			<keyword>calcium</keyword>
			<keyword>chloride</keyword>
			<keyword>conductance</keyword>
			<keyword>conductivity</keyword>
			<keyword>inorganic nutrients</keyword>
			<keyword>nitrate</keyword>
			<keyword>nitrogen</keyword>
			<keyword>ph</keyword>
			<keyword>phosphorus</keyword>
			<keyword>populations</keyword>
			<keyword>silica</keyword>
			<keyword>species richness</keyword>
			<keyword>sulfate</keyword>
			<keyword>total nitrogen</keyword>
			<keyword>total phosphorus</keyword>
			<keyword>zooplankton</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>LTER Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>Ca</keyword>
			<keyword>Cl</keyword>
			<keyword>lake characteristics</keyword>
			<keyword>N</keyword>
			<keyword>North Temperate Lakes - LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>NTL LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>P</keyword>
			<keyword>Si</keyword>
			<keyword>SO4</keyword>
			<keyword>species presence</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>NTL Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<intellectualRights>
			<section>
				<title>Data Policies</title>
				<para>Copyright Board of Regents, University of Wisconsin, Madison. This information is
					released to the public and may be used for academic, educational, or commercial purposes
					subject to the following restrictions: The Data User must realize that these data sets are
					being actively used by others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary
					to prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the NTL lead Principal
					Investigator, leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu, to check on other uses of the data. Where
					appropriate, the Data User may be encouraged to consider collaboration and/or
					co-authorship with original investigators.</para>
				<para>The Data User must realize that the data may be misinterpreted if taken out of
					context. We request that you provide the NTL lead Principal Investigator, ATTN: Data
					Access, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison, 680 North Park St.,
					Madison, WI 53706 with a copy of any manuscript using the data so that it may be reviewed
					and comments provided on the presentation of our data.</para>
				<para>The Data User must acknowledge use of the data by an appropriate citation (see
					Citation) of the NTL-LTER database. A generic citation for our databases is: name of data
					set, North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research program, NSF, contact person for
					data set, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison. The data set name and
					contact person for each data set can be found in the metadata header of the online data
					sets.</para>
				<para>The Data User must send two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the
					data to the address above. We would like to include such manuscripts in our LTER
					publications list.</para>
				<para>The Data User must not redistribute original data and documentation without permission
					from Emily Stanley, lead Principal Investigator, (ehstanley@wisc.edu).</para>
				<para>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation,
					complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is".
					The North Temperate Lakes LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or
					misinterpretation of data sets. Data users should be aware that we periodically update
					data sets.</para>
				<para>Our goal is to release all long term data associated with core research areas within 2
					years of collection. These data and accompanying metadata will be available for download
					from the NTL-LTER web site.</para>
				<para>By using these data, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement.
					Thank you for your cooperation. </para>
			</section>
		</intellectualRights>
		<distribution>
			<online>
				<url function="information">http://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/node/5626</url>
			</online>
		</distribution>
		<coverage>
			<geographicCoverage>
				<geographicDescription>Black Tern Bog - Vilas Co,Crystal Lake - Lincoln Co,Eldon Pond Amery,Emmons Creek Kettle,Frenchs Creek SWA Pond,Green Bush Kettle,Hwy 18 Helenville,Hwy 63 Northeast Spooner,Hwy 63 West Spooner,Hwy 70 South Spooner,Hwy Z Kettle,I-90 Pond,Jameison Pond - Columbia Co,Jimmy Hendricks Bog,Kostka 4 - Moss Pond,Kostka 5,Kostka A,Kostka B,Kostka C,Little Rock Frog Pond,Missouri Pond at Goose Lake SWA,Noranda Lake 15-16c,Noranda Lake 15-16d,Noranda Lake 22-12 NE,Noranda Lake 22-12 South -W,Noranda Lake 22-14,Noranda Lake 22-8,Noranda Lake 22-9a,Noranda Lake 22-9b,Noranda Lake I,Old Hwy 54 Pond,Patrick Marsh,Portage Jail,Rhinelander Paper Mill 1,Rhinelander Paper Mill 2,Rhinelander Paper Mill 3,Schneider 2,Schneider 3,Schneider 7,Siggelkow Pond,Spooner Tower Rd Pond,Starr School,Virgin Lake,Waterloo,White River Pond 1 North,White River Pond 2 South,Hwy 63 Southeast Spooner,McKenna Pond - Dane Co,Flaters North - Polk Co,Hwy 70 North Spooner,K-Mart Pond at Rice Lake,Noranda Lake 22-15,Prairie Chicken Pond,WI,USA
</geographicDescription>
				<boundingCoordinates>
					<westBoundingCoordinate>-92.964</westBoundingCoordinate>
					<eastBoundingCoordinate>-86.920</eastBoundingCoordinate>
					<northBoundingCoordinate>47.045</northBoundingCoordinate>
					<southBoundingCoordinate>42.457</southBoundingCoordinate>
				</boundingCoordinates>
			</geographicCoverage>
			<temporalCoverage>
				<rangeOfDates>
					<beginDate>
						<calendarDate>1996-04-24</calendarDate>
					</beginDate>
					<endDate>
						<calendarDate>1996-05-23</calendarDate>
					</endDate>
				</rangeOfDates>
			</temporalCoverage>
		</coverage>
		<maintenance>
			<description>
				<para>completed </para>
			</description>
		</maintenance>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Information Manager</positionName>
			<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
			<organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<publisher>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</publisher>
		<pubPlace>North Temperate Lakes</pubPlace>
		<methods>
			<methodStep>
				<description>
					<section>
						<para>Schell, Jeffery M., Carlos J. Santos-Flores, Paula E. Allen, Brian M. Hunker,
							Scott Kloehn, Aaron Michelson, Richard A. Lillie, and Stanley I. Dodson. 2001.
							Physical-chemical influences on vernal zooplankton community structure in small lakes
							and wetlands of Wisconsin, U.S.A. Hydrobiologia 445:37-50 </para>
					</section>
					<section>
						<para>Fifty-four ponds and wetlands were selected to represent a wide range in water
							duration (months of standing water during the ice-free period) from very short to
							permanent. Most were water bodies for which we had some long-term records (staff gage
							readings or personal observations) so as to assign an estimated average water
							duration. Ponds and wetlands were distributed statewide (Fig. 1) to enable us to
							account for geographic variations in possible indicator taxa. All sampling was
							completed within a one month time Figure 1. Location of the 54 Wisconsin lakes and
							wetlands surveyed in the spring of 1996. Code numbers of the ponds match site codes
							given in Table 2. The diagonal gray band represents the tension zone (Curtis 1959).
							Sample sites are distributed in three clusters: (1) the Northwestern cluster, near the
							Mississippi River, (2) the North Central cluster in the northern highlands above the
							Tension Zone, and (3) a South Central cluster mostly below the tension zone and east
							of the unglaciated corner of Wisconsin. period (April 24&#226;&#128;&#147;May 23, 1996) beginning in
							the South and finishing in the North. The narrow time window and sampling strategy
							employed was intended to minimize possibly confounding influences of temperature and
							light regimes and cascading biotic interactions on the community structure. Sampling
							in early Spring specifically was chosen over other periods because it represented the
							most stable circumstances for the aquatic insect community (sampled concurrently with
							zooplankton and topic of a separate paper), which was susceptible to rapid
							fluctuations due to immigration-emigration.We sampled in April&#226;&#128;&#147;May so that the bitoa
							present in any particular wetland basin whould represent the conditions that occurred
							during the previous year. The year 1993 was a very wet year and 1994&#226;&#128;&#147;95 were fairly
							average. We collected a single grab water sample from a central basin location using
							sample containers provided by the State Laboratory of Hygiene (SLH), Madison, WI. We
							conducted water sampling on the same date (just prior to) as microinvertebrate
							sampling to minimize effects of seasonal changes on water chemistry. Again, the logic
							being that the zooplankton community structure present would reflect water chemistry
							conditions leading up to the current conditions. Samples for alkalinity, pH,
							conductivity and dissolved silica were kept on ice until delivered to the SLH.
							Nutrient samples were preserved with sulfuric acid and dissolved calcium samples were
							preserved with nitric acid immediately upon collection. Analyses for Caplus2, SO4--2,
							Cl-, total Kjeldahl nitrogen (TKN), total phosphorus (TP) and Si (all in mgorl) were
							conducted according to agency protocols (Standard Methods per APHA, 1992). We
							collected zooplankton using a plankton net (15 cm diameter opening) equipped with
							number 10 mesh size or 120 microm netting). The selection of a relatively large mesh
							size was a necessary compromise to minimize clogging of the net due to the excessive
							amount of fine, particulate, suspended, organic materials present in many of the
							wetlands in the study. Naturally, we missed many of the smaller members of the
							zooplankton community, including many rotifers, as a result of using the coarser mesh
							net. We employed a standardized sampling strategy to collect 3 net sweeps from each
							basin. Each net sweep consisted of a 2 m horizontal tow, collected by tossing and
							retrieving the net in a central, open water area within each water basin. In some
							instances when the water was too shallow to permit a standard tow to be completed, the
							opening of the net was held vertically while being hand-swept the 2 m tow distance.
							The contents of one set of 3 tows or sweeps on one date represented the community for
							each basin. Contents of the net sweeps were transferred to storage containers and
							preserved in 4percent formalin. Samples were delivered to the Department of Zoology,
							UW-Madison for species analysis. The samples were scanned under the microscope and the
							micro-crustaceans and planktonic insects were sorted and identified, using the
							following authorities: Calanoida: Diaptomus:Wilson and Yeatman (1959). Cyclopoida and
							Harpacticoida: Acanthocyclops: Dodson (1994); all other taxa, Hudson et al. (1998).
							CLADOCERA: Bosmina: De Melo and Hebert (1994); Ceriodaphnia: Berner (1987 and pers.
							com.) and Negrea (1983); Chydorids: genera identified using Dodson and Frey (1991),
							while species were identified using a combination of Dodson and Frey (1991), and
							Smirnov (1971, 1996); Holopedium: Hebert (1997); Macrothricids (Acantholeberis,
							Ilyocryptus and Ophryoxus): Smirnov (1992) and Silva-Briano (1998); Daphnia: Hebert
							(1995); Diaphanosoma: Korinek (1981); Moina: Goulden (1968); Polyphemus: Rivier
							(1998); Scapholeberis: Dumont and Pensaert (1983); Simocephalus: Negrea (1983) and
							Hann (1995). ANOSTRACA: Eubranchipus: Pennak (1989). CONCHOSTRACA: Lynceus: Pennak
							(1989). INSECTA: Chaoborus: Cook (1954); Mochlonyx: Klink (1982). </para>
					</section>
				</description>
			</methodStep>
		</methods>
		<project>
			<title>North Temperate Lakes LTER</title>
			<personnel>
				<positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
				<organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
				<address>
        <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
				<electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
				<role>project personnel</role>
			</personnel>
			<abstract>
				<para>North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research studies the ecology of lakes as
					one of a network of sites established by the National Science Foundation. We are
					interested in how biophysical setting, climate, and changing land use and cover interact
					to shape lake characteristics and dynamics over time (past, present, future). Our primary
					study sites include a set of seven northern Wisconsin and four southern Wisconsin lakes
					and their surrounding landscapes. The project, which started in 1981, is administered by
					the Center for Limnology at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. Perception of Long-Term
					Change: How and why have the lake districts changed, and how will they change in the
					future? Climatic Forcing of Change: What are the major ecological and social responses of
					lake districts to climate change? Interacting Drivers, Scales of Space and Time, and
					Regional Change: How do multiple interacting drivers affect regional change in lake
					districts at multiple scales? Ecosystem Services: Past, Present and Future: What are the
					magnitudes, interactions and potential future flows of ecosystem services in lake
					districts? </para>
			</abstract>
		</project>
		<dataTable>
			<entityName>dodson_wdnr96_ponds</entityName>
			<entityDescription>Zooplankton - Wisconsin Small Lakes and Wetland Ponds  1996 Survey </entityDescription>
			<physical>
				<objectName>dodsonwdnr96ponds</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
						<recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
							<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-ntl.224&amp;urlTail=ntl/data/5626_1_v1.csv</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<attributeList>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>sitename</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>name of waterbody</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>name of waterbody</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>name of waterbody</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>sampledate</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>sample date</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>sample date</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>date</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<dateTime>
							<formatString>yyyy-MM-dd</formatString>
						</dateTime>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>town</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>town</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>town</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>town</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>map_range</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>range</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>range</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>range</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>section</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>section </attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>section </attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>section </definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>qq_q</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>quarter / quarter section</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>quarter / quarter section description</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>quarter / quarter section description</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>area</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>surface area</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>surface area of waterbody</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>hectare</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>habitat_type</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>habitat type</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>habitat type</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>habitat type</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>ca</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>calcium</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>calcium</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>cond</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>conductivity</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>conductivity</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microSiemenPerCentimeter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>ph</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>pH</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>pH</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>pH</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
								<bounds>
									<minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
									<maximum exclusive="false">14</maximum>
								</bounds>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>alk</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>alkalinity</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>alkalinity</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>cl</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>chloride</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>chloride</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>no3</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>nitrate</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>nitrate</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>so4</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>sulphate</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>sulphate</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>tkn</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>total Kjeldahl nitrogen</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>total Kjeldahl nitrogen</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>tp</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>total phosphorus</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>total phosphorus</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>si</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>silica</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>silica</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>duration</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>duration (months) surf water</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>duration  in months of surface water from spring thaw until drying or re-freezing</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>nominal month</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>total_taxa</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>total taxa present</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>total taxa present in this waterbody</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>site_code</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>site code</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>site code - cross ref to DNR data sheets</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>site code - cross ref to DNR data sheets</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>comments</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>comments</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>comments</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>comments</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
			</attributeList>
		</dataTable>
		<dataTable>
			<entityName>dodson_wdnr96_presence</entityName>
			<entityDescription>Zooplankton - Wisconsin 1996 Survey - Species Presence</entityDescription>
			<physical>
				<objectName>dodsonwdnr96presence</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
						<recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
							<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-ntl.224&amp;urlTail=ntl/data/5626_2_v1.csv</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<attributeList>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>sitename</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>name of waterbody</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>name of waterbody</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>name of waterbody</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>species</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>species / taxa name</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>species / taxa name</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>species / taxa name</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
			</attributeList>
		</dataTable>
	</dataset>
	<additionalMetadata>
		<metadata>
			<ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1     http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
				<ns2:unit abbreviation="mg/l" constantToSI="0" id="milligramPerLiter" multiplierToSI="0.001" name="milligramPerLiter" parentSI="kilogramPerCubicMeter" unitType="massDensity">
					<ns2:description>milligrams / liter</ns2:description>
				</ns2:unit>
				<ns2:unit abbreviation="uS/cm" constantToSI="0" id="microSiemenPerCentimeter" multiplierToSI="0.0001" name="microSiemenPerCentimeter" parentSI="siemenPerMeter" unitType="conductivityPerLength">
					<ns2:description>conductivity unit</ns2:description>
				</ns2:unit>
				<ns2:unit abbreviation="pH" id="pH" name="pH" unitType="">
					<ns2:description>pH</ns2:description>
				</ns2:unit>
				<ns2:unit id="nominal month" />
			</ns2:unitList>
		</metadata>
	</additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>