<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-ntl.225.8" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0  http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
	<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
		<allow>
			<principal>uid=NTL, o=lter, dc=ecoinformatics, dc=org</principal>
			<permission>all</permission>
		</allow>
		<allow>
			<principal>public</principal>
			<permission>read</permission>
		</allow>
	</access>
	<dataset>
		<alternateIdentifier system="NTL-DEIMS">5627</alternateIdentifier>
		<shortName>DODSON4</shortName>
		<title>Zooplankton Communities of Restored Depressional Wetlands in Wisconsin - North Temperate Lakes LTER 1998</title>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Stanley</givenName>
				<surName>Dodson</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
    </address>
		</creator>
		<metadataProvider>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</metadataProvider>
		<pubDate>2000</pubDate>
		<language>english</language>
		<abstract>
			<para>Wisconsin has lost approximately 2 million hectares of wetland since statehood (1848).
				Through the combined efforts of state and federal agencies and private groups focused
				primarily on wetland restoration for waterfowl habitat management or compensatory
				mitigation, a fairly substantial gain in wetland area has been achieved. Much of the wetland
				restoration effort in Wisconsin has occurred on formerly agricultural lands. However, due to
				the nature of the past disturbance and possible residual effects not corrected by simply
				returning surface waters to these lands, there is some question regarding the resultant
				wetland quality or biological integrity. In an effort aimed at developing tools to measure
				wetland gains in terms of quality or ecological integrity, the Wisconsin Department of
				Natural Resources (WDNR) initiated a study of biological communities on restored wetlands in
				Wisconsin. We report on the community of microcrustaceans and arthropods that can be
				collected with a plankton net in open water in wetlands. We examined zooplankton community
				structure in restored wetlands in terms of richness, taxonomic representation, and Daphnia
				sexual reproduction and related these metrics to attributes on wetlands representing
				least-disturbed conditions and agriculturally impacted wetlands. We sampled 56 palustrine
				wetlands distributed across Wisconsin. These wetland sites were categorized as agricultural,
				least-impacted, and restored (recently withdrawn from agricultural usage). The wetlands were
				reasonably homogeneous in many ways, so that taxon richness was not correlated with basin
				origin, presence of adjacent roads, presence or absence of fish, water chemistry, or the
				size of the open water. We identified a total of 40 taxa.. We conclude that restoration of
				wetland watersheds works. Withdrawal of the watershed from agricultural usage is followed by
				an increase in taxon richness, and the sites resembled least-impacted sites in about 6-7
				years. Dodson, S. I. and R. A. Lillie. 2001. Zooplankton communities of restored
				depressional wetlands in Wisconsin, USA. Wetlands 21:292-300. Number of sites: 58 </para>
		</abstract>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>communities</keyword>
			<keyword>diversity</keyword>
			<keyword>populations</keyword>
			<keyword>species richness</keyword>
			<keyword>zooplankton</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>LTER Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>Daphnia density</keyword>
			<keyword>Daphnia sex ratio</keyword>
			<keyword>NTL LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>North Temperate Lakes - LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>species presence</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>NTL Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<intellectualRights>
			<section>
				<title>Data Policies</title>
				<para>Copyright Board of Regents, University of Wisconsin, Madison. This information is
					released to the public and may be used for academic, educational, or commercial purposes
					subject to the following restrictions: The Data User must realize that these data sets are
					being actively used by others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary
					to prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the NTL lead Principal
					Investigator, leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu, to check on other uses of the data. Where
					appropriate, the Data User may be encouraged to consider collaboration and/or
					co-authorship with original investigators.</para>
				<para>The Data User must realize that the data may be misinterpreted if taken out of
					context. We request that you provide the NTL lead Principal Investigator, ATTN: Data
					Access, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison, 680 North Park St.,
					Madison, WI 53706 with a copy of any manuscript using the data so that it may be reviewed
					and comments provided on the presentation of our data.</para>
				<para>The Data User must acknowledge use of the data by an appropriate citation (see
					Citation) of the NTL-LTER database. A generic citation for our databases is: name of data
					set, North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research program, NSF, contact person for
					data set, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison. The data set name and
					contact person for each data set can be found in the metadata header of the online data
					sets.</para>
				<para>The Data User must send two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the
					data to the address above. We would like to include such manuscripts in our LTER
					publications list.</para>
				<para>The Data User must not redistribute original data and documentation without permission
					from Emily Stanley, lead Principal Investigator, (ehstanley@wisc.edu).</para>
				<para>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation,
					complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is".
					The North Temperate Lakes LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or
					misinterpretation of data sets. Data users should be aware that we periodically update
					data sets.</para>
				<para>Our goal is to release all long term data associated with core research areas within 2
					years of collection. These data and accompanying metadata will be available for download
					from the NTL-LTER web site.</para>
				<para>By using these data, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement.
					Thank you for your cooperation. </para>
			</section>
		</intellectualRights>
		<distribution>
			<online>
				<url function="information">http://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/node/5627</url>
			</online>
		</distribution>
		<coverage>
			<geographicCoverage>
				<geographicDescription>Amschler WPA,Badger 2,Betry 1,Betry 2,Bluff Creek Kettle,Bob Lake Central,Bob Lake West,Boe 1 W17,Boe 2 W18,Bong B-12,Bruins,Bruwalda 1 B42,Bruwalda 2 B43,Cherry Lake Sedge Meadow,Collins Marsh,DOT-Peters A B17,DOT-Peters B B18,Duffin,Falk Park Ephemeral,Flaters North WPA,Frenchs Creek West L06,Goose Pond West L15,Hwy 22 Traut Rd,Hwy 63 West-Northern,Hwy Z Kettle,Koberkick WPA,Kostka 1,Kostka 2 w07,Kostka 3,Lapham Peak Kettle,Lawin 1,Lawin 2,Lone Tree,Lundy Pond South w13,Maletzke B-28 (MA-4),Maletzke B-29 (MA-3 or MA-1),Marshmiller 1,Marshmiller 2,Muskego Park Hardwoods,Nordic Trails,Old World Wis,Older restoration 1 B36,Older restoration 2 B37,Red Cedar WPA,Schulenberg B30,Schulenberg B31,Scuppernong,Sonday Road,St. Croix Prairie WPA,Three Lakes WPA,Trego Kettle Creation 2 W24,Trego Kettle Creation 5 W26,Trego Natural 1 w23,Trego Natural 2 w25,Trego Natural 3 w27,Whitnall Park,WPL North,WPL South L14,WI,USA
</geographicDescription>
				<boundingCoordinates>
					<westBoundingCoordinate>-92.964</westBoundingCoordinate>
					<eastBoundingCoordinate>-86.920</eastBoundingCoordinate>
					<northBoundingCoordinate>47.045</northBoundingCoordinate>
					<southBoundingCoordinate>42.457</southBoundingCoordinate>
				</boundingCoordinates>
			</geographicCoverage>
			<temporalCoverage>
				<rangeOfDates>
					<beginDate>
						<calendarDate>1998-04-12</calendarDate>
					</beginDate>
					<endDate>
						<calendarDate>1998-04-29</calendarDate>
					</endDate>
				</rangeOfDates>
			</temporalCoverage>
		</coverage>
		<maintenance>
			<description>
				<para>completed </para>
			</description>
		</maintenance>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Information Manager</positionName>
			<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
			<organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<publisher>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</publisher>
		<pubPlace>North Temperate Lakes</pubPlace>
		<methods>
			<methodStep>
				<description>
					<section>
						<para>Dodson, S. I. and R. A. Lillie. 2001. Zooplankton communities of restored
							depressional wetlands in Wisconsin, USA. Wetlands 21:292-300. </para>
					</section>
					<section>
						<para>Field Sampling WDNR personnel collected zooplankton and water chemistry samples
							from each wetland during early spring (mid-April to early May) prior to desiccation.
							We classified each wetland according to its origin, setting, and type of current
							disturbance and subjectively estimated the percent land-use cover (row crops, pasture,
							urban, wooded, grassland, etc.) in the surface watershed of each wetland. We
							interviewed wildlife managers to determine the age of restored wetlands. We used a
							polar planimeter (maps scales varied among wetlands) to measure the surface area of
							each wetland. We recorded maximum water depth to the nearest cm with a meter stick
							during visits to each wetland in April&#226;&#128;&#147;May. The Wisconsin State Lab of Hygiene (WSLH)
							has established standard operating procedures (SOPs) for field collection,
							preservation, handling, and laboratory analysis that the WDNR must adhere to. The
							surface water chemistry analysis is referred to by the WSLH as non-compliance sampling
							(i.e., data not used for legal purposes) but which still must meet all regulatory
							holding times (be processed within a given number of days) or if times are exceeded,
							the analyses are not run (time limits for regulatory purposes are given in APHA
							(1989). Preservation for the automated alkalinity-pH-conductivity analysis calls for
							cooling to 4 degree C en route, refrigeration, and analysis within 14 days of
							collection (WSLH 1997). We collected water samples for pH, alkalinity, and
							conductivity measurements from a central basin location (undisturbed) within each
							wetland using a 250-ml plastic jar provided by the WSLH. Samples were placed in an
							iced cooler until delivered to the WSLH in Madison within one week of collection.
							Water duration was defined as the number of months of standing water during the
							growing season (March&#226;&#128;&#147;November). Duration determinations were made using longterm
							records, personal observations, or in a few cases, estimates based on the depth of
							water remaining in the basin in July. The presence of fish was noted when fish were
							captured or observed during sampling. However, there was no systematic sampling of
							zooplankton predators. We collected zooplankton samples from an undisturbed, central
							basin location within each wetland using a graduated 4-L grab bucket. The contents of
							the bucket were mixed and carefully filtered through a 200-micron-mesh net until the
							mesh began to clog or until a substantial quantity of zooplankton was visible in the
							net. Sample volume varied between 1 and 16 liters, depending of how fast the filter
							clogged. The quantity of sample filtered was recorded on a field sheet, and the sample
							was preserved in 95percent Ethanol. Laboratory Methods Water chemistry analyses were
							completed under contract with the Wisconsin State Laboratory of Hygiene using a
							standard protocol (WSLH 1997). Duplicative qualitative control limits for alkalinity
							are 1.08 percent less than 250 and 0.95 percent greater than 250. For conductivity,
							they are 1.69 percent less than 100 and 1.24 percent greater than 100. Each
							zooplankton sample was scrutinized to identify taxa of microcrustaceans and planktonic
							insects. Rotifers were not identified. When Daphnia occurred, they were all counted
							and scored according to gender. Taxa were identified at various levels according to
							procedures described by Schell et al. (2001). </para>
					</section>
				</description>
			</methodStep>
		</methods>
		<project>
			<title>North Temperate Lakes LTER</title>
			<personnel>
				<positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
				<organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
				<address>
        <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
				<electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
				<role>project personnel</role>
			</personnel>
			<abstract>
				<para>North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research studies the ecology of lakes as
					one of a network of sites established by the National Science Foundation. We are
					interested in how biophysical setting, climate, and changing land use and cover interact
					to shape lake characteristics and dynamics over time (past, present, future). Our primary
					study sites include a set of seven northern Wisconsin and four southern Wisconsin lakes
					and their surrounding landscapes. The project, which started in 1981, is administered by
					the Center for Limnology at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. Perception of Long-Term
					Change: How and why have the lake districts changed, and how will they change in the
					future? Climatic Forcing of Change: What are the major ecological and social responses of
					lake districts to climate change? Interacting Drivers, Scales of Space and Time, and
					Regional Change: How do multiple interacting drivers affect regional change in lake
					districts at multiple scales? Ecosystem Services: Past, Present and Future: What are the
					magnitudes, interactions and potential future flows of ecosystem services in lake
					districts? </para>
			</abstract>
		</project>
		<dataTable>
			<entityName>dodson_wdnr98_wetlands</entityName>
			<entityDescription>Zooplankton in Restored Wetlands in Wisconsin - 1998 Survey </entityDescription>
			<physical>
				<objectName>dodsonwdnr98wetlands</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
						<recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
							<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-ntl.225&amp;urlTail=ntl/data/5627_1_v1.csv</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<attributeList>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>sitename</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>restoration site</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>restoration site</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>restoration site</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>sampledate</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>sample date</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>sample date</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>date</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<dateTime>
							<formatString>yyyy-MM-dd</formatString>
						</dateTime>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>sitecode</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>site code</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>site code</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>site code</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>disturbance</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>disturbance</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>disturbance</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>disturbance</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>habitat_type</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>habitat type</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>habitat type</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>habitat type</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>history</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>history of site</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>history of site</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>history of site</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>site_group</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>site group</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>site group</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>site group</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>sex_ratio</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>daphnia ratio - males/females</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>sex ratio of daphnia  - males / females</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>sex ratio of daphnia  - males / females</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>daphnia</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>daphnia counted in sample</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>daphnia counted in sample</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>daphnia_density</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>daphnia density in sample</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>density of daphnia in sample</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>numberPerLiter</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>total_taxa</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>total taxa present</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>total taxa present in this wetland</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
			</attributeList>
		</dataTable>
		<dataTable>
			<entityName>dodson_wdnr98_presence</entityName>
			<entityDescription>Zooplankton in Restored Wetlands in Wisconsin - 1998 Survey - Species Presence</entityDescription>
			<physical>
				<objectName>dodsonwdnr98presence</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
						<recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
							<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-ntl.225&amp;urlTail=ntl/data/5627_2_v1.csv</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<attributeList>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>sitename</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>restoration site</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>restoration site</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>restoration site</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>species</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>species / taxa name</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>species / taxa name</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>species / taxa name</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
			</attributeList>
		</dataTable>
	</dataset>
</eml:eml>