<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.95.151301" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <title>Small Mammal Exclosure Study (SMES) Vegetation Line Intercept from Chihuahuan Desert Grassland and Shrubland at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico (1995-2005)</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>David</givenName>
        <surName>Lightfoot</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Sevilleta LTER, 167 Castetter Hall, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>dlightfo@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
        <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(505) 277.5355</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </metadataProvider>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>David</givenName>
        <surName>Lightfoot</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Sevilleta LTER, 167 Castetter Hall, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>dlightfo@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>data manager</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>David</givenName>
        <surName>Lightfoot</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Sevilleta LTER, 167 Castetter Hall, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>dlightfo@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>field crew</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Karen</givenName>
        <surName>Wright</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, Castetter Hall 167, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>karen@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>field crew</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Yang</givenName>
        <surName>Xia</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Sevilleta LTER UNM Biology Department, MSC03 2020 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-8119</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(505) 277.5355</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>yxia@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>field crew</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Michell</givenName>
        <surName>Thomey</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, Castetter Hall 167, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>mlthomey@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>field crew</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>2016-03-08</pubDate>
    <language>English</language>
    <abstract>
      <section>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>The purpose of this study is to determine whether or not the activities of small mammals regulate plant community structure, plant species diversity, and spatial vegetation patterns in Chihuahuan Desert shrublands and grasslands. What role if any do indigenous small mammal consumers have in maintaining desertified landscapes in the Chihuahuan Desert? Additionally, how do the effects of small mammals interact with changing climate to affect vegetation patterns over time? This is data for perennial plant vegetation canopy cover measured from all SMES study plots, fall 1995 and fall 2005. The purpose of this data is to provide ground-truth data for comparison with low-level aerial photographs of each study plot. Three, 29 meter lines were measured along three of six rows of the permanent vegetation measurement quadrats. Each line was measured at 10cm resolution for intercepts of perennial plant live canopy cover, and for bare ground. 10cm resolution is comparable to the resolution of the aerial photos. All plants were identified to the species level. These line-intercept measurements are taken once every ten years, at the same time that low-level aerial photographs are taken. These data will be compared to both decadal air photos, and annual measures ofvegetation from one-meter2 quadrats on each plot to provide information on vegetation change over time relative to the various animal exclosure treatments.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>populations</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>canopy cover</keyword>
      <keyword>transects</keyword>
      <keyword>deserts</keyword>
      <keyword>grasslands</keyword>
      <keyword>small mammals</keyword>
      <keyword>vegetation</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <section>
        <title>Data Policies</title>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER. A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url function="information">http://sevdeims-d.lternet.edu/data/sev-95</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Five Points Black Grama is on the transition between Chihuahuan Desert Scrub and Desert Grassland habitat. The site is subject to intensive research activity, including assessments of net primary productivity, phenology, and pollinator diversity, amongst other projects.&#160; It is the site of the unburned black grama (GU) component of the Burn NPP study. On August 4, 2009, a lightning-initiated fire began on the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge. By August 5, 2009, the fire had reached the Five Points Black Grama site.&#160; Portions of this site were burned, but not the entirety.&#160; See individual projects for further information on the effects of the burn. &#160;</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.736</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.736</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>The Rio Salado is an ephemeral tributary of the Rio Grande on the west side of the Sevilleta NWR, flowing west by northwest to east by southeast. Rio Salado Grassland &amp; Rio Salado Larrea are two study sites established in 1989. These sites were established&#160;as counterparts to sites at Five Points. Between 1989 and 1998, vegetation, litter decomposition, and ground dwelling arthropod and rodent populations were studied at both sites. Core studies at these sites were largely terminated in 1998, although rodent populations are still monitored at the Rio Salado Larrea site because the Small Mammal Exclosure Study's Larrea plots are co-located there. Rio Salado Grassland is the location Met Station 44.The Rio Salado study sites are accessed by taking the San Acacia exit, going west and then taking the frontage road back north to the Sevilleta NWR gate.&#160; After entering the refuge turn left after 0.2 mi and take this road 1.4 mi to a "T" in the road at the power lines.&#160; An earthen berm stops road travel here and the met station is located about 300 m west on the blocked road.&#160;</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.927</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.927</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>34.296</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>34.296</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>1503</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>1503</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1995-10-18</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2005-11-29</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>April 9, 2002: File created by Kristin Vanderbilt.Updated by Karen Wetherill, January 4, 2006. In 2006, the 1995 data codes were updated to reflect current Kartesz codes as found on the USDA plants website. In particular ATCA to ATCA2, ERPU to DAPU7, HIJA to PLJA, MAUR2 to MUAR2, MUPO to MUPO2, OPPH to OPPHP, SATR12 to SATR12, SCBR to SCBR2, SEMU to SEMU2, SPFL to SPFL2. Codes that could not be decipher and are still in the data set are LEER, OPVI, SCPO (could be SCPA6), and SPUK. Other mistakes such as site=L for Larrea were change to site= C. Negative intercepts (4) were NOT corrected.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">505 277-2535</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">505 277-2541</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>tech-support@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
        <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(505) 277.5355</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <publisher>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
        <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(505) 277.5355</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </publisher>
    <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <para>
              <literalLayout>Experimental Design: There are 2 study sites, the Five Points grassland site, and the Rio Salado creosotebush site. Each study site is 1 km by 0.5 km in area. Three rodent trapping webs and four replicate experimental blocks of plots are randomly located at each study site to measure vegetation responses to the exclusion of small mammals. Each block of plots is 96 meters on each side. Each block of plots consists of 4 experimental study plots, each occupying 1/4 ofeach block. The blocks of study plots are all oriented on a site in a X/Y coordinate system, with the top to the north. Treatments within each block include one unfenced control plot (Treatment: C), one plot fenced with hardware cloth and poultry wire to exclude rodents and rabbits (Treatment: R), and one plot fenced only with poultry wire to exclude rabbits (Treatment: L). The three treatments were randomly assigned to each of the four possible plots in each block independently, and their arrangements differ from block to block. Each of the three plots in a replicate block are separated by 20 meters. Each experimental measurement plot measures 36 meters by 36 meters. A grid of 36 sampling points are positioned at 5.8-meter intervals on a systematically located 6 by 6 point grid within each plot. A permanent one-meter by one-meter vegetation measurement quadrat is located at each of the 36 points. The 36 quadrats are numbered 1-36, starting with number 1 in the top left corner (north-west) of each plot (top being north), and running left (west) to right (east), then down (south) one row, and then right (east) to left (west), and so on. Quadrat/rebar number one is in the northwest corner of each plot, and numbers 1-6 are across the north side of the plot west to east,then quadrat/rebar number 7 is just south of quadrat/rebar number 6, and rebar numbers increase 7-12 east to west, and so on. 3-inch nails were originally placed in the top left (north-west) corner of each quadrat. These may be difficult to see. A 3-meter wide buffer area is situated between the grid of 36 points and the perimeter of each plot. How Data Were Collected: 100 meter measuring tapes were attached to the steel re-bar posts marking vegetation quads 1, 3, and 5 on each study plot. The measuring tapes were extended south to the re- bar posts marking quads 36, 34, and 32. Data were recorded for all intercepts of live perennial plant canopy foliage, and for bare ground. The start and end points for each intercept were recorded to the nearest 10 cm on the measuring tape. Intercepts less than 5 cm were ignored, and intercepts between 5 and 10 cm were recorded to the nearest 10 cm. Intercept measurements were only recorded for perennial plant species, and for bare soil. Annual plants and dead perennial plants were ignored.</literalLayout>
            </para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <qualityControl>
        <description>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>The data were entered in the field on to micro-cassette tape recorders. The taped recorded data were then entered on to MS Excel spreadsheets. A macro statement was used to subtract each observed intercept end measure from the start measure, to produce an intercept measure for each observation. Those data were then converted to space-formatted text files, and combined as one file. In 2006, the 1995 data codes were updated to reflect current Kartesz codes as found on the USDA plants website.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </description>
      </qualityControl>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>sev095_smeslineint_01122009.txt</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Data for SEV095</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>sev095_smeslineint_01122009_0.txt</objectName>
        <size>334566</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-sev/95/151301/e9d381b7c469656fd86f604ee165f935</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <coverage>
        <temporalCoverage>
          <rangeOfDates>
            <beginDate>
              <calendarDate>1995-10-18</calendarDate>
            </beginDate>
            <endDate>
              <calendarDate>2005-11-29</calendarDate>
            </endDate>
          </rangeOfDates>
        </temporalCoverage>
      </coverage>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>date</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>date</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The date on which data or a sample was collected.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>MM/DD/YY</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>-999</code>
            <codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>site</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>SITE</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The site at which data was collected.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>C</code>
                    <definition>Rio Salado creosote site</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>G</code>
                    <definition>Black grama site</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>block</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>block</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Block number in random block design.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Block number in random block design.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>plot</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>plot</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>plot from which data were collected</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>plot from which data were collected</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>trt</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>trt</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Plot treatment.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>C</code>
                    <definition>Control</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>L</code>
                    <definition>Lagomorph exclosure</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>R</code>
                    <definition>Rodent and Lagomorph exclosure</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>line</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>line</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Indicates the line at which data was collected.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Indicates the line at which data was collected.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>species</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>species</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The Kartez code for a plant species as designated by the USDA Plants Database.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>The Kartez code for a plant species as designated by the USDA Plants Database.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>start</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>start</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The point along a transect at which an individual plant or a substrate begins.</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">40000</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>intercept</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>intercept</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>End point for measurement.</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>centimeters</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>comments</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>comments</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>A special statement related to an observation.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>na</code>
                    <definition>not applicable</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
        <ns2:unit id="centimeters">
          <ns2:description />
        </ns2:unit>
      </ns2:unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>