<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.6.151654" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <title>Pinon Branch Demography Study at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico (1989-1993)</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Diane</givenName>
        <surName>Marshall</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
        <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(505) 277.5355</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </metadataProvider>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Douglas I.</givenName>
        <surName>Moore</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Sevilleta LTER, 167 Castetter Hall, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>dmoore@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>data manager</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>2016-03-03</pubDate>
    <language>English</language>
    <abstract>
      <section>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>This project was designed to investigate the response of plant growth and reproduction to short- and long-term variation in biotic and abiotic environmental variables. Several perennial taxa, including tree (Juniperus monsperma and Pinus edulis), shrub (Larrea tridentata) and bunch grasses (Oryzopsis hymenoides (now Achnaterum hymenoides) and Sporobolus contractus) species, were monitored at 1-3 sites differing in elevation and topography as well as edaphic variables and annual precipitation. The sites represented optimal or marginal/transitional zones for particular species. Demographic measurements were made biannually, after the 'wet' (fall) and 'dry' (spring) seasons. For tree and shrub species, estimates of growth and reproduction were based on branch demography, with ten branch tips from 10-20 individuals per species per site repeatedly measured from 1989-1993.&#194;&#160; For J. monsperma, P. edulis and L. tridentata, vegetative growth (i.e., branch growth) as well as reproduction were monitored. Additional measurements included needle length for P. edulis and leaf production, leaf size and branchlet production for L. tridentata. For grasses, basal diameter, leaf length and reproduction were monitored for 100 individuals per species per site. This project, SEV006, contains only data on pinon branch demography.&#194;&#160; Data on other variables and species is contained in SEV024, SEV025, SEV026, SEV027, and SEV028.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>populations</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>community structure</keyword>
      <keyword>demography</keyword>
      <keyword>seasonality</keyword>
      <keyword>census</keyword>
      <keyword>tree growth</keyword>
      <keyword>forests</keyword>
      <keyword>leaves</keyword>
      <keyword>trees</keyword>
      <keyword>logs</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <additionalInfo>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>1989: First Census - May 8,9,11 of 1989; Second Census - September 5 of 1989. 1990: First Census - This equals season&#194;&#160; 1 in the header for the data.&#194;&#160; The data were collected from 27 Apr 1990 to 17 May 1990. Second Census - This equals season&#194;&#160; 2 in the header for the data. The data were collected from 5 Sep 1990 - 20 Sep 1990.1991: First Census - 16 Apr 1991 - 15 May 1991. Second Census - 4 Aug 1991 - 13 Sep 1991. 1992: First Census - The first census was performed on the following dates: 15 Apr, 16 Apr, 22 Apr, 23 Apr, 27 Apr, 28 Apr, 29 Apr, 30 Apr, 1 May, 19 May, 21 May, 27 May, 28 May, 1 Jun, 2 Jun, 12 Jun 1992. Second Census - The second census was performed on 14-17 Sep, 22-24 Sep, 29 Sep, 5-7 Oct 1992. 1993: First Census - Goat Draw pinyon and juniper were measured on: 14 Apr; and 15 Apr 1993. Second Census - Goat Draw pinyon and juniper were measured on: 9 Sep; 10 Sep; and 13 Sep 1993. The data for the first census (May) were collected by Ann Evans (Asst. Professor/UNM), Troy Maddux (Head Plant Tech/LTER), Sam Loftin (Graduate Student/UNM), Marikay Ramsey (Head Animal Tech/LTER), Joran Viers (Plant Tech/LTER), Michelle Murillo (Plant Tech/LTER), Jennifer Franklin (Plant Tech/LTER), Amy Shortess (Plant Tech/LTER).&#194;&#160; The data for the second census (September) were collected by Troy Maddux (Head Plant Tech/LTER), Amy Shortess (Plant Tech/LTER), David Keller (Plant Tech/LTER).1991: The data for the first census&#194;&#160; (May) were collected by Roger Mongold (Plant Technician), Brad Swanson (Plant Technician), Joran Viers (Plant Technician), Kathleen McGee (Plant Technician), Sam Loftin (Graduate Student Technician), and Troy Maddux (Head Plant Technician).&#194;&#160; The data for the second census (May) were collected by Jim Stanton (Plant Technician), Susan Prichard (Plant Technician), and Troy Maddux (Head Plant Technician). &#194;&#160;1992: The data for the first census (Apr-Jun) were collected by Troy Maddux (Head Plant Technician) and the following plant technicians: Marilyn Altenbach, Michael Bradley, Melissa Chavez, Anthony Collier, Julie Knight, Ivan Ortiz, Amanda Persaud, Monica Valdez.&#194;&#160; The data for the second census (Aug-Oct) were collected by Troy Maddux (Head Plant Technician), Robin Abell (Plant Technician), and Tiffany Cotlar (Plant Technician).1993: SPRING CENSUS - Roger Stupf (Volunteer from Switzerland), Ursula Bonhage (Volunteer from Switzerland), Christian Heierli (Volunteer from Switzerland), Marilyn Altenbach (Field Crew Chief), Eric Scherff (Field Tech), Troy Maddux (Vegetation Studies Program Manager). FALL CENSUS - Cynthia Gregoire (Volunteer from Vermont), Marilyn Altenbach (Field Crew Chief), Eric Scherff (Field Tech).</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </additionalInfo>
    <intellectualRights>
      <section>
        <title>Data Policies</title>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER. A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url function="information">http://sevdeims-d.lternet.edu/data/sev-6</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>This site encompasses the upper reaches of Goat Draw and is dominated by pinon-juniper vegetation.&#160; Two pinon branch demography study sites were located here, each with 49 labeled trees, in a small canyon which drains the Los Pinos Mountains to the east.&#160; Vegetation is characterized as a pinon/juniper woodland with occasional occurrences of Quercus turbinella, Yucca spp. and Opuntia spp.&#160; Portions of the bird community assessment and plant phenology studies were also located within Goat Draw.</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>34.368</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>34.368</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>1976</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>1976</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1989-05-08</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>1993-09-13</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>I. Condensed log of activity of plant demography data:&#194;&#160; a. Individual documentations iniatiated 1989; Troy Maddux&#194;&#160; b. File (combined documentations) 31 August 1990; Troy Maddux&#194;&#160; c. Abstract (Written by Diane Marshall and Charles Wisdom) put in documentation 31 August 1990; Troy Maddux&#194;&#160; d. Documentation expanded 2 September 1990; Troy Maddux&#194;&#160; e. Concatenation of individual documentations iniatiated September 1990, completed 17 December 1990; Michelle Murillo&#194;&#160; f. File expanded into rdb file 17 December 1990; Michelle Murillo&#194;&#160; g. Rdb file checked, and errors eliminated 18 December 1990; Michelle Murillo&#194;&#160; h. KEYWORDS added 19 December 1990; James Brunt&#194;&#160; i. Random error checking completed 20 December 1990; Michelle Murillo&#194;&#160; j. File complete and archived 21 December 1990; Michelle Murillo &amp;amp; Greg Shore&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; Documentation changed to reflect changes in datafile structure; 1 March 91 T. Maddux &#194;&#160;II. Detailed log of alterations/modifications of plant demography data: This portion of the log contains details of all alterations and modifications applied to this file by Michelle Murillo. The file demography.dat was initiated in September 1990 by concatenating individual files into the demography.dat file. A generic header was devised to apply to all individual files. The header reads as such: date season site species station plant# branch# #1 #2 #3 #4 #5 #6 #7 #8, and the detailed description of the numbers 1-8 are listed in the documentation section of this file. The individual files were then modified to follow this header, which entailed rearranging of columns (generally the season, site, species, station, plant#, and branch#) and the addition of the date column. As the columns numbered 1-8 did not pertain to all individual files, non-applicables (na) were inserted where necessary. Other alterations included:&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; 1. Juniper 1989: Sepultura Canyon; addition of na's to presence/absence of male or female cones, depending on sex of tree, i.e. if tree was female then na's were inserted in the male column. Goat Draw; same as Sepultura Canyon&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; 2. juniper 1990: (Sepultura Canyon site has been discontinued) Goat Draw (season 1); orginal file contained x,y and --'s; which were converted to 0 (absence) and 1 (presence) and appropriate na's were inserted, depending on sex of tree Goat Draw (season 2); orginal file contained +'s for presence of cones; which were converted to 1 (presence) and appropriate na's were inserted depending on sex of tree.&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; NOTE: In 1989 width of branch was measured, and in 1990 this measurement was no longer taken. (The orginal data sheets for 1989-2 are unavailable at the time of archiving, assumption is that this measurement applies to season 2 also ).&#194;&#160; In 1990 the length of branchlet was measured which was not measured in 1989. (See documentation). &#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; NOTE: In 1989 (both seasons) the variable, number of branchlets, was not included. In 1990 the variable was added, but measurements of this variable was sporadic, occuring only in a few plants.&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; 3. grasses 1989/1990: All sites: addition of na's to branch#Error checking was done as follows:Two files, grasses 1990-season 1, and creosote 1990-season 1, had not been entered at the time of concatenation of individual files, and were therefore entered by Michelle Murillo. These two files were error checked by Michelle Murillo by visual checking of original data sheets with the files on 18 December 1990. On 17 December 1990, the expand program was applied to the demography.dat file and placed into the demography.rdb file. The rdb file was then checked for various errors, and the elimination of these errors were completed on 18 December 1990. On 19-20 December 1990, random error checking was conducted by using 'Tables for Statistical Data-Analysis'. One hundred and fifty entries were checked and approximiately 45 percent of the numbers were from 1989-season 2, and because the data sheets were unavailable, the entries were not error checked. On 23 December 1990, visual checking with the original data sheets was conducted for an overall check.File initiated June 1991: MLMseason 1 entered: MLMseason 2 entered: KPMBlack Butte, season 2 entered and error checked, 7 Jan 1992: MLMdata entry complete 25 October 1991:&#194;&#160; KPMdata error checking completed 8 November 1991:&#194;&#160; KPM Documentation updated (New people and times added) on 29 Jan 1992 and inserted into data file by Troy Maddux.&#194;&#160; 1992 log&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;* Put the 1992 data in the data base on 22 Oct 1992 Troy Maddux. THE FOLLOWING IS THE LOG FOR THE SPRING 1992 DEMOGRAPHY DATA &#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;* File initiated by Troy Maddux 24 Aug 1992&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;* Goat Draw PIED information entered by Michael Bradley&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;* and sent to Troy Maddux Wed Aug 19 15:31:03 1992 and these&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;* data added to this file by T. Maddux on 15 Oct 1992&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;* Black butte data added to this file 15 Oct 1992&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;* Many SPCO4 plants in plots 2 and 3 of Five Points had no&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;* data for the inflorescence # so this was added (it was 0)&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;* on 15 Oct 1992 by Troy Maddux&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;* Removed extra '0' from rs SPCO4 #531-534 - 16 Oct 1992, T.M.&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; * Pulled \doc from 1991 demography data to change for 1992 data 16 Oct 1992; T.M.&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;* Who and When data were collected was added 20 Oct 1992; T.M. &#194;&#160; THE FOLLOWING IS THE LOG FOR THE FALL 1992 DEMOGRAPHY DATA&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; *File initiated 16 Sep 1992 by Tiffany Cotlar&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;*Data file from Tiffany Cotlar and a data file from Robin Abell combined; also blank lines removed from both files; this was done by Troy Maddux on 20 Oct 1992.&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;*File initiated 16 Sep 1992 by Robin Abell&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;*PIED #'s 9,13,23,15,17,36,41,42 by Robin Abell 16 Sep 1992&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;*JUMO #'s 26,23,24,28,49,5,8,17,13,22,36,41,47,4,15,27,32,46,42&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;* by Robin Abell 16 Sep 1992&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;*LATR2 #'s (Five Points) 2,3,5,26 by Robin Abell 23 Sep 1992&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;*SPCO4 #'s (Station B) 61,92,93,94,95,99,101,103,104,105,108,109&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;* 109.1,110,110.1,111,112,112.1,122,125,126,127,130,148,149,402&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;* by Robin Abell 23 Sep 1992&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;*LATR2 #'s (Five Points) 90,92,96 by Robin Abell 24 Sep 1992&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;*LATR2#'s (Rio Salado) 1,14,17 by Robin Abell 1 Oct 1992&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;*changed typo: juno to JUMO; 20 Oct 1992, T.M.&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;*added additional field to grass data to make the field # correct 20 Oct 1992, TM.File submitted for archival 22 OCT 1992 - Troy MadduxFile initiated by Troy Maddux 22 Apr 1993 combining data entered by Ursula Bonhage, Roger Stupf, Christian Heierli, Marilyn Altenbach, andEric Scherff.----------------------------------------------------------------------*Data for:&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;*&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;PIED 28, 32, 36*&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;entered by Ursula Bonhage 14 Apr 1993.----------------------------------------------------------------------*Data for:*&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;PIED 4, 5, 8, 9, 13, 15* entered by M. Altenbach &amp;amp; E. Scherff 14 April 93.----------------------------------------------------------------------*Data for:*&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;pinyon 17,22,23,24 and* entered by&#194;&#160; M. Altenbach &amp;amp; 16 April 93.----------------------------------------------------------------------* Data entered for:*&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;PIED 26,27,41,42,46,47,49* by eric and marilyn on 13 and 14 April 1993----------------------------------------------------------------------* Documentation taken from 91-92 archive data set and modified for this data set.&#194;&#160; 18 Oct 1993, by Troy Maddux.* Filled in "Who" and "When" sections from the data sheets - Troy Maddux - 16 Nov 1993.----------------------------------------------------------------------****************************************&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;1993 FALL DATA ****************************************File for Black Butte orhy data created by Eric Scherff and Cynthia Gregoire on September 21, 1993. Data collected by Marilyn Altenbach and Eric Scherff on September 14, 1993 ****************************************File for Five Points Sporobolus information created by Cynthia Gregoire &amp;amp; Eric Scherff on 21 September 1993. Data collected by Marilyn Altenbach &amp;amp; Eric Scherff on 14 September 1993 and 15 September 1993. File appended by Eric Scherff and Cynthia Gregoire on 22 September 1993. Changed "nd" representing "no data" to "na" to be consistent with other data bases. - Troy Maddux - 8 Nov 1993.****************************************File for pinyons created by Eric Scherff on 10 September 1993 File appended by Eric Scherff on 15 September 1993 Data collected by M. Altenbach &amp;amp; E. Scherff on 9 September, 10 September, and 13 September.****************************************Different fall plant data put together into single archive file by Troy Maddux on 8 Nov 1993.****************************************Spring and Fall data put together in Archive File format 17 Nov 1993. by Troy Maddux - also changed nd's and dashes to na's.&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;****************************************9 Dec 1993 - Demography file contained all species - all but the pinyon information was taken from this file by Troy Maddux.****************************************10 Dec 1993 - Documentation section changed to reflect only pinyon and not other measured species (e.g. jumo, latr, orhy, and spco). Troy Maddux****************************************10 Feb 1994 - Documentation section compared to Doc. Manual and necessary changes made by Rosemary Vigil; Troy Maddux replaced four occurances of "na" with 0.****************************************14 March 1994. Separated the big demography-89-90 file into four parts; grass, pinyon, creosote, and juniper.&#194;&#160; Rupal Shah went through and separated the file and edited the documentation.* 3 Jan 1995 - replaced a couple of enigmatic X's with "na"'s - Troy Maddux.3/19/98 - Changed species codes to Kartesz. K. Taugher&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;- Added a final line to dataset of: "{END OF DATA}". K. Taugher&#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;- Updated metadata to reflect species code changes. K. Taugher9/23/09 - Added Kartesz reference. K. Taugher</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">505 277-2535</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">505 277-2541</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>tech-support@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
        <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(505) 277.5355</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <publisher>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
        <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(505) 277.5355</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </publisher>
    <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <para>
              <literalLayout>Tree Selection - Ten numbered pinon trees were randomly selected at each study site; five on the north slope of a canyon and five on the south slope.&#194;&#160; Numbers were assigned to trees which were then sampled by random selection. Branch Selection - Ten branches approximately 1.5 meters above the ground were chosen and assigned numbers (1-10). Tag Placement - Tags were placed about six centimeters from the tip of a selected branch. Blength - The length of the branch from the tag wire (or paint mark) to the branch apex. Fascicles - The length of the most distal cluster of leaves on the branch, the present year's cohort of leaves. Needle1 - The length, from tip to attachment point, of one needle in a cluster included in a length-with-fascicles measurement. Needle2 - A measurement of second needle in a cluster. Male - A measure of the length of a branch containing male cones. If the tagged branch diverged before reaching the apex, producing two or more male cones, the individual lengths were added together as one male cone branch length. Female - The number of female cones on a measured branch. Codes - The codes used for species in this study follow Kartesz abbreviation standards (Kartesz, J.T. 1994. A Synonymized Checklist of the Vascular Flora of the United States, Canada, and Greenland. Timber Press, Oregon). Codes consist of four-to-six characters and are alphanumeric .&#194;&#160; A comprehensive list of all plant species found on the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge and their associated codes can be found on the Sevilleta Information Management System (SIMS) at: /export/db/local/plant/lib/species_kartesz_codes_.lst.</literalLayout>
            </para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>sev6_pinyondemography_20160303.txt</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Data for pinyon demography study for years 1989-1993.</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>sev006_pinyondemography_20160303.csv</objectName>
        <size>86309</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-sev/6/151654/2ac759033019657fbaa67bc98983bfaa</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <coverage>
        <temporalCoverage>
          <rangeOfDates>
            <beginDate>
              <calendarDate>1989-01-01</calendarDate>
            </beginDate>
            <endDate>
              <calendarDate>1993-12-31</calendarDate>
            </endDate>
          </rangeOfDates>
        </temporalCoverage>
      </coverage>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>date</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>date</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The year in which data was collected.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>season</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>season</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The season in which the data were collected.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>1</code>
                    <definition>spring</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>2</code>
                    <definition>fall</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>-888</code>
            <codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>-999</code>
            <codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>site</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>site</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The site at which data was collected for sev006.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>gd</code>
                    <definition>Goat Draw</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>species</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>species</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The four-letter code representing the species sampled for sev006.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>PIED</code>
                    <definition>Pinus edulis</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>station</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>station</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The area within a site in which sampling was performed for sev006.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>1</code>
                    <definition>Lower station just above the windmill with a very steep north-facing slope and a gentle south-facing slope.</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>2</code>
                    <definition>Upper station up the wash from station 1.</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>plant#</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>plant#</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Identifies the individual measured. Individuals were numbered from 1 to 100 and, from these, twenty were randomly selected for demographic measurements.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Identifies the individual measured. Individuals were numbered from 1 to 100 and, from these, twenty were randomly selected for demographic measurements.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>branch#</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>branch#</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Identifies the branch on an individual plant. If a tagged branch died another branch was tagged using the same number followed by ".1" suffix. The suffix increased by ".1" every subsequent time a branch was replaced.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Identifies the branch on an individual plant. If a tagged branch died another branch was tagged using the same number followed by ".1" suffix. The suffix increased by ".1" every subsequent time a branch was replaced.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>blength</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>blength</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The length of the branch from the tag (or paint mark) to the branch apex.</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>na</code>
            <codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>fascicles</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>fascicles</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The length of the most distal cluster of leaves on a branch (i.e., that year's cohort of leaves).</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>na</code>
            <codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>needle1</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>needle1</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The length, from tip to attachment point, of one needle in the cluster measured for "fascicle" variable.</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>na</code>
            <codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>needle2</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>needle2</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The same measurement as "needle1" but performed on a second needle in the same cluster.</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>na</code>
            <codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>male</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>male</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The length of the branch containing the male cones. If the tagged branch diverged and produced two or more male cones, the individual lengths were added together.</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>na</code>
            <codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>female</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>female</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The number of female cones on a measured branch.</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>na</code>
            <codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>comments</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>comments</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>A special statement related to an observation.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>na</code>
                    <definition>not applicable</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
</eml:eml>