<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-mcm.43.6" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=MCM,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <shortName>limnets</shortName>
    <title>McMurdo Dry Valleys Community Respiration Rates : Quantifying the Activity of the Electron Transport System (ETS)</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>John</givenName>
        <surName>Priscu</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Montana State University</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>LRES, 334 Leon Johnson Hall</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Bozeman</city>
        <administrativeArea>MT</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>59717</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(406) 994-3250</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>jpriscu@montana.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
      <organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
      <onlineUrl>http://mcm.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </metadataProvider>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Inigo</givenName>
        <surName>San Gil</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>University Of New Mexico</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, MSC03 2020 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2625</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(505) 277-2541</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>isangil@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>data manager</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>2014-11-04</pubDate>
    <language>English</language>
    <abstract>
      <section>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>An important part of the McMurdo Long Term Ecological Research (LTER) is monitoring of spatial and temporal patterns, and processes that control net primary production (carbon dynamics) in perennial ice-covered lakes. One of the primary losses of carbon fixed by phytoplankton is through respiration, directly by the phytoplankton themselves and secondarily through the metabolic contributions of heterotrophic organisms such as bacterioplankton and protozoa. The coupling of low metabolic activity and supersaturated gases in the water column prohibits a direct measurement of respiration. Therefore, we measure the respiratory electron transport system (ETS) activity which drives oxidative phosphorylation, and hence oxygen consumption in all aerobic organisms (Packard 1985). This data set addresses this core area of research and estimates a community-wide respiration rate at specific depths in McMurdo Dry Valley lakes (Hoare, Fryxell and Bonney).</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>community respiration</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>Antarctica</keyword>
      <keyword>community respiration</keyword>
      <keyword>electron transport system</keyword>
      <keyword>ETS</keyword>
      <keyword>lake</keyword>
      <keyword>limnology</keyword>
      <keyword>respiration</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>Station Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>organic matter</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <additionalInfo>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>Energy of activation is an average of values ranging from 9300-16000 cal mol-1 (Ahmed and Kenner, 1977), and is supported by an experimentally derived value of 9720 cal mol-1 in Lake Bonney (Priscu, unpublished). If the absorbance of the kill sample is greater than the average of the live samples, ETS is reported as zero. &#194;&#160; Citations &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;Ahmed, S. I., and R. A. Kenner. 1977. A study of in vitro electron transport activity in marine phytoplankton as a functio n of temperature. &#194;&#160;Journal of Phycology 13: 116-121. &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; Christiansen, J.P., T.G. Owens, A.H. Devol, and T. Packard. 1980. Respiration physiological state in marine bacteria. Mari ne Biology 55: 267-276. &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; Kenner, R. A., and S. I. Ahmed. 1975. Measurements of electron transport activities in marine environments. Marine Biology &#194;&#160;33: 119-127. &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; Packard, T.T. 1985. Measurement of electron transport activity in microplankton. Advances in Aquatic Microbiology 3: 207-2 61. &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; Priscu, J.C., and C.R. Goldman. 1984. The effect of temperature on photosynthetic and respiratory electron transport syste m activity in the shallow and deep-living phytoplankton of a subalpine lake. Freshwater Biology 14:143-155. &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </additionalInfo>
    <intellectualRights>
      <section>
        <title>Data Policies</title>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>MCM LTER data may be used freely with the following restrictions: The Principal Investigator be sent a notice stating reasons for acquiring any data and a description of the publication intentions. The Principal Investigator of the data set be sent a copy of the report or manuscript prior to submission and be adequately cited in any resultant publications. A copy of any resultant publications should be sent to the McMurdo data manager and principal investigator. The end-user follow the guidelines set forth in the LTER Network Data Access Policy, Data Access Requirements, and General Data Use Agreement here: Definitions &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data Set&#226;&#8364; &#226;&#8364;&#8220; Digital data and its metadata derived from any research activity such as field observations, collections, laboratory analysis, experiments, or the post-processing of existing data and identified by a unique identifier issued by a recognized cataloging authority such as a site, university, agency, or other organization. &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data User&#226;&#8364; - individual to whom access has been granted to this Data Set, including his or her immediate collaboration sphere, defined here as the institutions, partners, students and staff with whom the Data User collaborates, and with whom access must be granted, in order to fulfill the Data User's intended use of the Data Set &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data Set Creator&#226;&#8364; - individual or institution that produced the Data Set &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data Set Owner&#226;&#8364; &#226;&#8364;&#8220; individual or institution that holds intellectual property rights to the dataset. Note that this may or may not be defined as a legal copyright. If no other party is designated in the metadata as Data Set Owner, it may be presumed that these rights are held by the Data Set Creator. &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data Set Distributor&#226;&#8364; - individual or institution providing access to the Data Sets. &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data Set Contact&#226;&#8364; - party designated in the accompanying metadata of the Data Set as the primary contact for the Data Set. Conditions of Use The re-use of scientific data has the potential to greatly increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines, and thus is fostered, supported and encouraged. Permission to use this dataset is granted to the Data User free of charge subject to the following terms: 1) Acceptable use. Use of the dataset will be restricted to academic, research, educational, government, recreational, or other not-for-profit professional purposes. The Data User is permitted to produce and distribute derived works from this dataset provided that they are released under the same license terms as those accompanying this Data Set. Any other uses for the Data Set or its derived products will require explicit permission from the dataset owner. 2 ) Redistribution. The data are provided for use by the Data User. The metadata and this license must accompany all copies made and be available to all users of this Data Set. The Data User will not redistribute the original Data Set beyond this collaboration sphere. 3 ) Citation. It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Data Set in any publications or in the metadata of any derived data products that were produced using the Data Set. Citation should take the following general form: Creator, Year of Data Publication, Title of Dataset, Publisher, Dataset identifier. For example: McKee, W. 2001. Vascular plant list on the Andrews Experimental Forest and nearby Research Natural Areas: Long-Term Ecological Research. Corvallis, OR: Forest Science Data Bank: SA002. [Database]. http://www.fsl.orst.edu/lter/data/abstract.cfm?dbcode=SA002. (21 October 2004) 4 ) Acknowledgement. The Data User should acknowledge any institutional support or specific funding awards referenced in the metadata accompanying this dataset in any publications where the Data Set contributed significantly to its content. Acknowledgements should identify the supporting party, the party that received the support, and any identifying information such as grant numbers. For example: Data sets were provided by the Forest Science Data Bank, a partnership between the Department of Forest Science, Oregon State University, and the U.S. Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station, Corvallis, Oregon. Significant funding for collection of these data was provided by the National Science Foundation Long-Term Ecological Research program (NSF Grant numbers BSR-90-11663 and DEB-96-32921). 5 ) Notification. The Data User will notify the Data Set Contact when any derivative work or publication based on or derived from the Data Set is distributed. The Data User will provide the data contact with two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the Data Set and will provide copies, or on-line access to, any derived digital products. Notification will include an explanation of how the Data Set was used to produce the derived work. 6 ) Collaboration. The Data Set has been released in the spirit of open scientific collaboration. Data Users are thus strongly encouraged to consider consultation, collaboration and/or co-authorship with the Data Set Creator. By accepting this Data Set, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. The Data Owner shall have the right to terminate this agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement. Disclaimer While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation contained in this Data Set, complete accuracy of data and metadata cannot be guaranteed. All data and metadata are made available "as is". The Data User holds all parties involved in the production or distribution of the Data Set harmless for damages resulting from its use or interpretation.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url function="information">http://mcmlter.org/content/community-respiration-rates-quantifying-activity-electron-transport-system-ets</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lake Bonney is a saline lake with permanent ice cover at the western end of Taylor Valley in the McMurdo Dry Valleys of Victoria Land, Antarctica. It is 7 kilometres or 4.3 mi long and up to 900 metres or 3,000 ft wide. A narrow channel only 50 metres or 160 ft wide. Lake Bonney at Narrows separates the lake into East Lake Bonney 3.32 square kilometres or 1.28 sq mi and West Lake Bonney, 0.99 square kilometres or 0.38 sq mi. The west lobe is flanked by Taylor glacier. Valley: Taylor Distance to Sea : 25 Maximum Length (km): 4.8 Maximum Width (km): 0.9 Maximum Depth (m): 37 Surface Area (km^2): 3.32 Ice Thickness Average Surface (m): 3 - 4.5 Volume (m^3 * 10^6): 54.7</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>162.353</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>162.536</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.6977</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.7244</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>57</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>57</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lake Bonney is a saline lake with permanent ice cover at the western end of Taylor Valley in the McMurdo Dry Valleys of Victoria Land, Antarctica. It is 7 kilometres or 4.3 mi long and up to 900 metres or 3,000 ft wide. A narrow channel only 50 metres or 160 ft wide. Lake Bonney at Narrows separates the lake into East Lake Bonney 3.32 square kilometres or 1.28 sq mi and West Lake Bonney, 0.99 square kilometres or 0.38 sq mi. Valley: Taylor Distance to Sea : 28 Maximum Length (km): 2.6 Maximum Width (km): 0.9 Maximum Depth (m): 40 Surface Area (km^2): 0.99 Ice Thickness Average Surface (m): 2.8-4.5 Volume (m^3 * 10^6): 10.1</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>162.269</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>162.355</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.7148</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.7273</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>57</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>57</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lake Hoare occupies a narrower portion of the Taylor Valley, dammed by the Canada Glacier. It would drain almost completely without this dam. There are a number of islands which may be related to an old terminal of Canada Glacier. The lake is fed primarily from direct runoff from the glacier, as well as meltwater streams. (Lake level rose ~1.5 m between 1972 and 1996). There are no surface outflows; the only known water loss is through ice ablation (evaporation, sublimation and physical scouring). Valley: Taylor Distance to Sea : 15 Maximum Length (km): 4.2 Maximum Width (km): 1 Maximum Depth (m): 34 Surface Area (km^2): 1.94 Ice Thickness Average Surface (m): 3.1 - 5.5 Volume (m^3 * 10^6): 17.5</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>162.784</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>162.936</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.6231</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.6393</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>73</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>73</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>The Lake Fryxell basin is formed by a moraine depression in a wider portion of the Taylor Valley. It has a number of moraine islands and shallower areas, as well as several relatively well developed deltas. The lake is fed by at least 10 meltwater streams with a total drainage catchment of 230 km2. The lake is dammed to the southwest by the Canada Glacier and is topographically closed. It is perennially ice covered; during summer months, an ice-free moat generally forms around much of the lake margin. Lake levels have risen ~2 m between 1971 and 1996. There are no surface outflows; the only known water loss is through ice ablation (evaporation, sublimation and physical scouring). Valley: Taylor Distance to Sea : 9 Maximum Length (km): 5.8 Maximum Width (km): 2.1 Maximum Depth (m): 20 Surface Area (km^2): 7.08 Ice Thickness Average Surface (m): 3.3 - 4.5 Volume (m^3 * 10^6): 25.2</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>163.049</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>163.26</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.5971</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.6227</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>18</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>18</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1993-10-31</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2001-12-30</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>In 2016, metadata was enhanced and completed for data preservation and export (San Gil) Data from this table was submitted to INSTAAR by John Priscu's team at Montana State University. The raw data files listed under 'file name' are the names of the original files submitted, which are stored in the /data1/data/lakes/lakebio/ directory on INSTAAR's Unix system. The 1993/94 and 1994/95 datasets are Microsoft Excel version 6.0 files, and the1995/96, 1996/97 and 1997/98 datasets are ascii text files. Upon arrival at INSTAAR, the data manager fine-tuned the location codes and limno runs to match those provided in the "locations, dates, codes for lake chemistry, biology samples" file. The file was imported into Microsoft Access on INSTAAR's Unix system, and can currently be found there. The file was then exported in ascii, comma delimited text and MS-DOS text (table layout) to present on the MCM LTER web site. Both of these files are linked to this web page above. Information for the metadata was obtained from the Metaets9697.rtf and Metaets9798.rtf files. The files were called up using Microsoft Word version 6.0. Text from these files was used to create this page in html format.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">505 277-2535</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">505 277-2541</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>tech-support@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
      <onlineUrl>http://mcm.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <publisher>
      <organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
      <onlineUrl>http://mcm.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </publisher>
    <pubPlace>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</pubPlace>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <para>
              <literalLayout>Lake water samples were collected at specific depths with a five-liter Niskin bottle during normal LTER limnological sampling. Sub-samples were decanted into three-1 L Nalgene bottles (2-light and 1-amber), two-500 mL amber Nalgene bottles, three-150 mL borosilicate glass bottles, two-20 mL scintillation vials, and one-30 mL serum vial. The two-one liter clear Nalgene bottles were used for the ETS experiment. Depending on the lake and depth at which each analysis was performed, 1000-2000 mL of lake water was filtered through a Whatman 47 mm GF/F filter. The filter was folded in half (organic material inside), placed in a glassine envelope, and stored at 0 degrees Celsius until analysis (&amp;lt;30 min). In an ice bath, the filter was combined with 3 mL of homogenization buffer and homogenized for 90 seconds with a glass/teflon tissue grinder. The mixture was decanted into a cone centrifuge tube; it was centrifuged in the cold for 3 minutes, vortexed for 30 seconds, and centrifuged for another 15 minutes. 0.5 mL of the extract was pipetted supernatant into three 1-cm quartz cuvettes (2 replicate, 1 control) and placed in an ice bath. The control sample was boiled for 10 minutes and cooled in an ice bath. 1.5 mL of substrate solution and 0.5 mL of INT solution was added to each cuvette, vortexed for 30 seconds, and incubated at 1-4C for one hour. The reaction was terminated in the cuvette with 0.5 mL of termination solution. The absorbance was measured at 490 nm with a spectrophotometer. Light absorption by the sample idirectly proportional to the moles of electrons transferred through the electron transport system (ETS). Community ETS (umol O2 L-1 hr-1) was calculated using the following equation: ETS = (AbsR - AbsC) a * b c * t where AbsR is the average absorbance of the replicate samples, AbsC is the absorbance of the control sample, a is ratio of the volume of homogenization buffer to the volume of lake water filtered, b is the ratio of the final volume of reaction mixture in each cuvette to the volume of extract supernatant, c is the extinction coefficient for formazan (31.8 Abs cm-1 umol O2-1), and t is the incubation period. Community ETS was adjusted to ambient lake temperature using the Arrhenius equation: ETSadj = ETS * e^(Ea (( 1 / (CI + 273 K)) - ( 1 / (CA + 273 K))) / R ) where Ea is the energy of activation (15,000 cal mol-1, Q10 = 2.66), CI is the incubation temperature (C), CA is the ambient lake water temperature at specific depth, and R is a gas constant (1.987 cal mol-1 K-1). A first order relationship exists between ETS activity and respiratory capacity in aquatic microorganisms (e.g., Kenner and Ahmed 1975, Christiansen et al. 1980). Our studies have revealed that 44% and 56% of measured ETS activity is from bacterioplankton and phytoplankton, respectively, in Lake Bonney (Takacs and Priscu, unpublished data). Using these relationships, in concert with published respiration:ETS ratios (Packard 1985), we derived a community respiration:ETS ratio of 0.61 for the water column of Lake Bonney. Individual respiration:ETS ratios for bacteria and phytoplankton were computed as 0.513 and 0.097, respectively.</literalLayout>
            </para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>LIMNO_RESPIRATION_ETS</entityName>
      <physical>
        <objectName>LIMNO_RESPIRATION_ETS.csv</objectName>
        <size>93574</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>28</numHeaderLines>
            <numFooterLines>1</numFooterLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-mcm/43/6/14435c9930ab85b7cfe4acad1445c960</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DATASET_CODE</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DATASET_CODE</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Code to ID the data table</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Code to ID the data table</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>LIMNO_RUN</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>LIMNO_RUN</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Code for lake's sampling location and date</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Code for lake's sampling location and date</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>LOCATION NAME</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>LOCATION NAME</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Name of lake where measurement was made</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Name of lake where measurement was made</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>LOCATION CODE</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>LOCATION CODE</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Code for site where measurement was made</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Code for site where measurement was made</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DATE_TIME</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DATE_TIME</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Date on which sample was gathered</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>mm/dd/yyyy</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DEPTH (m)</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DEPTH (m)</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Distance below ice from which sample was drawn</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">25</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Required entry</code>
            <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>ETS (umol O2/L*hr)</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>ETS (micromols of oxygen per liter per hour)</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Community Respiration Rate quantified by the Electron Transport System</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>microMolsPerliterPerhour</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.001</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Null</code>
            <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>ETS COMMENTS</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>ETS COMMENTS</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Helpful hints about the sample</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Helpful hints about the sample</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>RESPIRATION (umol O2/L*hr)</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>RESPIRATION (micromols of oxygen per liter per hour)</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Community Respiration Rate quantified by the Electron Transport System</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>microMolsPerliterPerhour</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.001</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Null</code>
            <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>RESPIRATION COMMENTS</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>RESPIRATION COMMENTS</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Helpful hints about the sample</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Helpful hints about the sample</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>FILE NAME</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>FILE NAME</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Name of file in which data was submitted</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Name of file in which data was submitted</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DEPTH MASL</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DEPTH MASL</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Depth referred to the Sea level. Distance below Mean Average Sea water level reference from which sample was drawn</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
        <ns2:unit id="microMolsPerliterPerhour">
          <ns2:description />
        </ns2:unit>
      </ns2:unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>