<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-ntl.87.13" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=NTL,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <alternateIdentifier system="NTL-DEIMS">5729</alternateIdentifier>
    <shortName>NTLPH07</shortName>
    <title>North Temperate Lakes LTER: Color - Trout Lake Area 1989 - current</title>
    <creator>
      <positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
      <organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
      <organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </metadataProvider>
    <pubDate>2012</pubDate>
    <language>english</language>
    <abstract>
      <para>Color is measured four times a year in the seven northern study lakes (Allequash, Big Muskellunge, Crystal, Sparkling, and Trout lakes, unnamed lakes 27-02 [Crystal Bog] and 12-15 [Trout Bog]) in water samples that are filtered in the field through 0.45 um nucleopore membrane filters. A spectrophotometer is used to quantify color in the lab as absorbance (unitless) at 1 nm intervals between the wavelengths of 200 and 800 nm (Note: Prior to August 2008, samples were initially run in 10cm cuvettes. Starting in Aug 2008, samples are initially run in 5cm cuvettes. Absorbance data are considered suspect for values greater than 2. Lakes with suspect data (typically, the bog lakes) are re-analyzed in the 200-400 nm range in 1 cm cuvettes. The data values are linear with respect to cuvette size. I.e, data from the 1cm cuvettes should be multiplied by 5 to be comparable with 5cm cuvette data and multiplied by 10 to be comparable with 10cm cuvette data. Data from 5cm cuvettes should be multiplied by 2 to be comparable with the older 10cm cuvette data. Sampling Frequency: 4 times annually Number of sites: 7
</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>NTL LTER</keyword>
      <keyword>North Temperate Lakes - LTER</keyword>
      <keyword>absorbance</keyword>
      <keyword>absorption</keyword>
      <keyword>lake color</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>NTL Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <section>
        <title>Data Policies</title>
        <para>Copyright Board of Regents, University of Wisconsin, Madison. This information is released to the public and may be used for academic, educational, or commercial purposes subject to the following restrictions: The Data User must realize that these data sets are being actively used by others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary to prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the NTL lead Principal Investigator, leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu, to check on other uses of the data. Where appropriate, the Data User may be encouraged to consider collaboration and/or co-authorship with original investigators.</para>
        <para>The Data User must realize that the data may be misinterpreted if taken out of context. We request that you provide the NTL lead Principal Investigator, ATTN: Data Access, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison, 680 North Park St., Madison, WI 53706 with a copy of any manuscript using the data so that it may be reviewed and comments provided on the presentation of our data.</para>
        <para>The Data User must acknowledge use of the data by an appropriate citation (see Citation) of the NTL-LTER database. A generic citation for our databases is: name of data set, North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research program, NSF, contact person for data set, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison. The data set name and contact person for each data set can be found in the metadata header of the online data sets.</para>
        <para>The Data User must send two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the data to the address above. We would like to include such manuscripts in our LTER publications list.</para>
        <para>The Data User must not redistribute original data and documentation without permission from Emily Stanley, lead Principal Investigator, (ehstanley@wisc.edu).</para>
        <para>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is". The North Temperate Lakes LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of data sets. Data users should be aware that we periodically update data sets.</para>
        <para>Our goal is to release all long term data associated with core research areas within 2 years of collection. These data and accompanying metadata will be available for download from the NTL-LTER web site.</para>
        <para>By using these data, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. Thank you for your cooperation.
</para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url function="information">http://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/node/5729</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Allequash Lake, Big Muskellunge Lake, Crystal Lake, Sparkling Lake, Trout Lake, and unnamed lakes 27-02 (Crystal Bog) and 12-15 (Trout Bog), Vilas County, WI, USA
</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-89.704</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.596</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>46.079</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>45.999</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1989-11-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2015-12-31</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>ongoing
</para>
      </description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">505 277-2535</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">505 277-2541</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>tech-support@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <positionName>NTL LTER Information Manager</positionName>
      <organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Street</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
      <organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <publisher>
      <organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </publisher>
    <pubPlace>North Temperate Lakes</pubPlace>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <para>We collect water samples for color at the deepest part of the lake four times per year: February under ice, spring mixis, August stratification, and fall mixis. The samples are surface water, filtered in the field through 0.45u polycarbonate membrane filters. We run a wavelength scan from 800 to 200nm, using a 5cm rectangular quartz cell in a Beckman Coulter Model DU800 spectrophotometer. Any samples that display absorbance values above 2AU are run again from 400 to 200nm using a 1cm quartz cuvette. Inititally the full range of wavelengths were run again and two values may be found in the database even if the original measurement with the large cuvette did not exceed 2AU. The user should discard values above 2AU and use values from the smaller cuvette instead. All values are given as measurements at the path lenth of the employed cuvette and need to be devided by the cuvette length for a comparable value at a pathlength of 1 cm.
The single beam Beckman Coulter DU800 spec is blanked first on a sample of DI water. Additional blank values are from a scan run on DI after that blanking as a check and are reported alongside the scans but are not subtracted from the scan values.

	Protocol Log: 1990 -- we began running color scans, using a 10cm cylindrical cell with a Kontron spectrophotometer.
	2001 -- we added scans in a 1cm cell for samples with high absorbance.
	July 2008 -- changed to Beckman Coulter DU800 spectrophotometer. At same time changed from 10cm to 5cm cell.
</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>North Temperate Lakes LTER</title>
      <personnel>
        <positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
        <organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Madison</city>
          <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
          <country>United States</country>
        </address>
        <electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>project personnel</role>
      </personnel>
      <abstract>
        <para>North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research studies the ecology of lakes as one of a network of sites established by the National Science Foundation. We are interested in how biophysical setting, climate, and changing land use and cover interact to shape lake characteristics and dynamics over time (past, present, future).
	Our primary study sites include a set of seven northern Wisconsin and four southern Wisconsin lakes and their surrounding landscapes. The project, which started in 1981, is administered by the Center for Limnology at the University of Wisconsin-Madison.
Perception of Long-Term Change: How and why have the lake districts changed, and how will they change in the future?
	Climatic Forcing of Change: What are the major ecological and social responses of lake districts to climate change?
	Interacting Drivers, Scales of Space and Time, and Regional Change: How do multiple interacting drivers affect regional change in lake districts at multiple scales?
	Ecosystem Services: Past, Present and Future: What are the magnitudes, interactions and potential future flows of ecosystem services in lake districts?
</para>
      </abstract>
    </project>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>color2_q1</entityName>
      <entityDescription>North Temperate Lakes LTER: Color</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>color2q1</objectName>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url function="download">https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-ntl/87/13/dfa0b1554851a03143f94b7da32e6040</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <coverage>
        <geographicCoverage>
          <geographicDescription>Location: Crystal Bog is located within the Northern Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County.
It is a small and shallow bog lake. It has a surface area of 0.5 hectare, mostly undeveloped shoreline and a maximum depth of 2.5 meters.
Bog lakes are isolated to a large extent from surrounding groundwater flow systems. However, they exhibit a similar pattern, across landscapes, to that exhibited by other lakes in general. The proportional input of groundwater to the bogs' hydrologic inputs increases with decreasing elevation in the landscape. More detailed studies of Crystal Bog reveal a complex interplay between conditions in the lake and in the surrounding wetland due to the groundwater flow regime and resulting chemical transfers.
&#160;
&#160;
&#160;
</geographicDescription>
          <boundingCoordinates>
            <westBoundingCoordinate>-89.606183</westBoundingCoordinate>
            <eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.606183</eastBoundingCoordinate>
            <northBoundingCoordinate>46.007583</northBoundingCoordinate>
            <southBoundingCoordinate>46.007583</southBoundingCoordinate>
          </boundingCoordinates>
        </geographicCoverage>
        <geographicCoverage>
          <geographicDescription>Location: Trout Bog is located within the Northern Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County.
It is a small bog lake. It has a surface area of 1.1 hectare, a mostly undeveloped shoreline and a maximum depth of 7.9 meters.
</geographicDescription>
          <boundingCoordinates>
            <westBoundingCoordinate>-89.686283</westBoundingCoordinate>
            <eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.686283</eastBoundingCoordinate>
            <northBoundingCoordinate>46.04125</northBoundingCoordinate>
            <southBoundingCoordinate>46.04125</southBoundingCoordinate>
          </boundingCoordinates>
        </geographicCoverage>
        <geographicCoverage>
          <geographicDescription>Location: Crystal Lake is located within the Northern Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County.
It is a seepage lake with predominantly sand substrate. It has a surface area of 36.7 hectare, 2.3 kilometers of mostly undeveloped (campground) developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 20.4 meters.
Crystal Lake represents one extreme in the groundwater input gradient, with a marked predominance of precipitation inputs. Groundwater accounts for only 5% of input water, yet, because groundwater is more concentrated chemically than precipitation, groundwater accounts for substantial amounts of incoming solutes. For example, about 50% of the silica budget comes into the lake via groundwater, exerting a major influence on primary production.
The lake is an oligotrophic, dimictic lake high in the landscape with minimal groundwater input, a light attenuation coefficient of 0.24 per meter (average ice-free Secchi depth of 8 m), a mean depth of 11.4 m, and a maximum depth of 20.4 m. Crystal Lake is circular with a shoreline development factor very close to 1.0. The littoral zone is fairly homogenous and is dominated by sandy substrate with low macrophyte and coarse woody habitat densities. The fish community has been historically dominated by pelagic yellow perch. However, yellow perch drastically declined after the detection of rainbow smelt in 1985.
&#160;
</geographicDescription>
          <boundingCoordinates>
            <westBoundingCoordinate>-89.612</westBoundingCoordinate>
            <eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.612</eastBoundingCoordinate>
            <northBoundingCoordinate>46.003</northBoundingCoordinate>
            <southBoundingCoordinate>46.003</southBoundingCoordinate>
            <boundingAltitudes>
              <altitudeMinimum>502</altitudeMinimum>
              <altitudeMaximum>502</altitudeMaximum>
              <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
            </boundingAltitudes>
          </boundingCoordinates>
        </geographicCoverage>
        <geographicCoverage>
          <geographicDescription>Location: Big Muskellunge Lake is located within the Northern Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County.
It is a seepage lake with predominantly sand and gravel substrate. It has a surface area of 396.3 hectare, 16.1 kilometers of moderately developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 21.3 meters.
&#160;
&#160;
&#160;
&#160;
&#160;
</geographicDescription>
          <boundingCoordinates>
            <westBoundingCoordinate>-89.611783</westBoundingCoordinate>
            <eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.611783</eastBoundingCoordinate>
            <northBoundingCoordinate>46.021067</northBoundingCoordinate>
            <southBoundingCoordinate>46.021067</southBoundingCoordinate>
            <boundingAltitudes>
              <altitudeMinimum>500</altitudeMinimum>
              <altitudeMaximum>500</altitudeMaximum>
              <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
            </boundingAltitudes>
          </boundingCoordinates>
        </geographicCoverage>
        <geographicCoverage>
          <geographicDescription>Location: Sparkling Lake is located within the Northern Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County.
It is a seepage lake with predominantly sand and gravel substrate. It has a surface area of 64 hectare, 4.3 kilometers of moderately developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 20 meters.
&#160;
&#160;
</geographicDescription>
          <boundingCoordinates>
            <westBoundingCoordinate>-89.701183</westBoundingCoordinate>
            <eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.701183</eastBoundingCoordinate>
            <northBoundingCoordinate>46.007733</northBoundingCoordinate>
            <southBoundingCoordinate>46.007733</southBoundingCoordinate>
            <boundingAltitudes>
              <altitudeMinimum>495</altitudeMinimum>
              <altitudeMaximum>495</altitudeMaximum>
              <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
            </boundingAltitudes>
          </boundingCoordinates>
        </geographicCoverage>
        <geographicCoverage>
          <geographicDescription>Location: Allequash Lake is located within the Northern Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County. T41N-R7E, Sections 16, 17, 20, 21. 398 acres. (detailed lake description by the WDNR)
It is a drainage lake with predominantly sand and gravel substrate. It has a surface area of 168.4 hectare, 9.5 kilometers of mostly undeveloped shoreline and a maximum depth of 8 meters.
&#160;
&#160;
&#160;
&#160;
</geographicDescription>
          <boundingCoordinates>
            <westBoundingCoordinate>-89.620617</westBoundingCoordinate>
            <eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.620617</eastBoundingCoordinate>
            <northBoundingCoordinate>46.038317</northBoundingCoordinate>
            <southBoundingCoordinate>46.038317</southBoundingCoordinate>
            <boundingAltitudes>
              <altitudeMinimum>494</altitudeMinimum>
              <altitudeMaximum>494</altitudeMaximum>
              <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
            </boundingAltitudes>
          </boundingCoordinates>
        </geographicCoverage>
        <geographicCoverage>
          <geographicDescription>Location: Trout Lake is located within the Northern Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County.
It is a drainage lake with predominantly gravel and sand substrate. It has a surface area of 1607.9 hectare, 25.9 kilometers of mostly undeveloped shoreline and a maximum depth of 35.7 meters.
&#160;
&#160;
</geographicDescription>
          <boundingCoordinates>
            <westBoundingCoordinate>-89.665017</westBoundingCoordinate>
            <eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.665017</eastBoundingCoordinate>
            <northBoundingCoordinate>46.029267</northBoundingCoordinate>
            <southBoundingCoordinate>46.029267</southBoundingCoordinate>
            <boundingAltitudes>
              <altitudeMinimum>492</altitudeMinimum>
              <altitudeMaximum>492</altitudeMaximum>
              <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
            </boundingAltitudes>
          </boundingCoordinates>
        </geographicCoverage>
      </coverage>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>sampledate</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>sample date</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>sample date</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>yyyy-MM-dd</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>lakeid</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>lake name abbreviation</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>lake name abbreviation</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>AL</code>
                    <definition>Allequash Lake</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>BM</code>
                    <definition>Big Muskellunge Lake</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>CB</code>
                    <definition>Bog 27-2  (Crystal Bog)</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>CR</code>
                    <definition>Crystal Lake</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>SP</code>
                    <definition>Sparkling Lake</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TB</code>
                    <definition>Bog 12-15  (Trout Bog)</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TR</code>
                    <definition>Trout Lake</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>year4</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>year</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>year</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>nominalYear</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>month</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>month</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>month</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>nominalMonth</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>wavelength</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>wavelength </attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>wavelength </attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>nanometer</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">200</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">800</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>cuvette</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>cuvette size</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>cuvette size, path length</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>value</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>absorbance </attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>absorbance at the cuvette path length. To arrive at absorption per one centimeter this value needs to be divided by the path length of the cuvette.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>color_flag</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>data flag for absorbance value</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>data flag for absorbance value</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>K</code>
                    <definition>Data suspect</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
        <ns2:unit abbreviation="" id="nominalMonth" name="nominalMonth" unitType="">
          <ns2:description />
        </ns2:unit>
      </ns2:unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>