<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-mcm.7018.4" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=MCM,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <shortName>Mt. Fleming met</shortName>
    <title>McMurdo Dry Valleys Mt. Fleming Meteorological Station Measurements</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Andrew</givenName>
        <surName>Fountain</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Portland State University</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Department of Geology, Cramer Hall 1721 SW Broadway</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>97207</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(503) 725-3386</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>andrew@pdx.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
      <organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
      <onlineUrl>http://mcm.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </metadataProvider>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Maciej</givenName>
        <surName>Obryk</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Portland State University</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Dept. of Geology</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>97207</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">5037253386</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>mobryk@pdx.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>field crew</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Inigo</givenName>
        <surName>San Gil</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>University Of New Mexico</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, MSC03 2020 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2625</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(505) 277-2541</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>isangil@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>data manager</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>2014-11-05</pubDate>
    <language>English</language>
    <abstract>
      <section>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>As part of the Long Term Ecological Research in the McMurdo Dry Valleys of Antarctica, meteorological data was collected from various locations throughout Beacon, Taylor, Wright and Victoria Valleys. These files contain data for the Mt. Fleming meteorology station.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>humidity</keyword>
      <keyword>meteorology</keyword>
      <keyword>radiation</keyword>
      <keyword>soil</keyword>
      <keyword>temperature</keyword>
      <keyword>wind</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>Station Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <additionalInfo>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>&#194;&#160;Meteorological data is collected year-round at each of the stations in the McMurdo Dry Valleys of Antarctica. After retrieving this data (usually every January), the parameters that are recorded are processed from level 0 (raw) to level 1 (processed, provided on the web). The raw data file descriptions and task lists summarize what was done to get from level 0 to level 1 for all station found at the following address: &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; http://mcmlter.lternet.edu/data/meteorology/tasks/task_lists.htm &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </additionalInfo>
    <intellectualRights>
      <section>
        <title>Data Policies</title>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>MCM LTER data may be used freely with the following restrictions: The Principal Investigator be sent a notice stating reasons for acquiring any data and a description of the publication intentions. The Principal Investigator of the data set be sent a copy of the report or manuscript prior to submission and be adequately cited in any resultant publications. A copy of any resultant publications should be sent to the McMurdo data manager and principal investigator. The end-user follow the guidelines set forth in the LTER Network Data Access Policy, Data Access Requirements, and General Data Use Agreement here: Definitions &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data Set&#226;&#8364; &#226;&#8364;&#8220; Digital data and its metadata derived from any research activity such as field observations, collections, laboratory analysis, experiments, or the post-processing of existing data and identified by a unique identifier issued by a recognized cataloging authority such as a site, university, agency, or other organization. &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data User&#226;&#8364; - individual to whom access has been granted to this Data Set, including his or her immediate collaboration sphere, defined here as the institutions, partners, students and staff with whom the Data User collaborates, and with whom access must be granted, in order to fulfill the Data User's intended use of the Data Set &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data Set Creator&#226;&#8364; - individual or institution that produced the Data Set &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data Set Owner&#226;&#8364; &#226;&#8364;&#8220; individual or institution that holds intellectual property rights to the dataset. Note that this may or may not be defined as a legal copyright. If no other party is designated in the metadata as Data Set Owner, it may be presumed that these rights are held by the Data Set Creator. &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data Set Distributor&#226;&#8364; - individual or institution providing access to the Data Sets. &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data Set Contact&#226;&#8364; - party designated in the accompanying metadata of the Data Set as the primary contact for the Data Set. Conditions of Use The re-use of scientific data has the potential to greatly increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines, and thus is fostered, supported and encouraged. Permission to use this dataset is granted to the Data User free of charge subject to the following terms: 1) Acceptable use. Use of the dataset will be restricted to academic, research, educational, government, recreational, or other not-for-profit professional purposes. The Data User is permitted to produce and distribute derived works from this dataset provided that they are released under the same license terms as those accompanying this Data Set. Any other uses for the Data Set or its derived products will require explicit permission from the dataset owner. 2 ) Redistribution. The data are provided for use by the Data User. The metadata and this license must accompany all copies made and be available to all users of this Data Set. The Data User will not redistribute the original Data Set beyond this collaboration sphere. 3 ) Citation. It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Data Set in any publications or in the metadata of any derived data products that were produced using the Data Set. Citation should take the following general form: Creator, Year of Data Publication, Title of Dataset, Publisher, Dataset identifier. For example: McKee, W. 2001. Vascular plant list on the Andrews Experimental Forest and nearby Research Natural Areas: Long-Term Ecological Research. Corvallis, OR: Forest Science Data Bank: SA002. [Database]. http://www.fsl.orst.edu/lter/data/abstract.cfm?dbcode=SA002. (21 October 2004) 4 ) Acknowledgement. The Data User should acknowledge any institutional support or specific funding awards referenced in the metadata accompanying this dataset in any publications where the Data Set contributed significantly to its content. Acknowledgements should identify the supporting party, the party that received the support, and any identifying information such as grant numbers. For example: Data sets were provided by the Forest Science Data Bank, a partnership between the Department of Forest Science, Oregon State University, and the U.S. Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station, Corvallis, Oregon. Significant funding for collection of these data was provided by the National Science Foundation Long-Term Ecological Research program (NSF Grant numbers BSR-90-11663 and DEB-96-32921). 5 ) Notification. The Data User will notify the Data Set Contact when any derivative work or publication based on or derived from the Data Set is distributed. The Data User will provide the data contact with two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the Data Set and will provide copies, or on-line access to, any derived digital products. Notification will include an explanation of how the Data Set was used to produce the derived work. 6 ) Collaboration. The Data Set has been released in the spirit of open scientific collaboration. Data Users are thus strongly encouraged to consider consultation, collaboration and/or co-authorship with the Data Set Creator. By accepting this Data Set, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. The Data Owner shall have the right to terminate this agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement. Disclaimer While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation contained in this Data Set, complete accuracy of data and metadata cannot be guaranteed. All data and metadata are made available "as is". The Data User holds all parties involved in the production or distribution of the Data Set harmless for damages resulting from its use or interpretation.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url function="information">http://mcmlter.org/content/mt-fleming-meteorological-station-measurements</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>The met station at Mt. Fleming</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>160.271</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>160.271</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.5327</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.5327</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>351</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>351</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1995-01-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2014-12-31</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>On 2013, the data manager (Inigo San Gil) added the this station to the list of MCM met stations available through the MCMLTER Database and Infomration Management System (DEIMS)</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">505 277-2535</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">505 277-2541</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>tech-support@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
      <onlineUrl>http://mcm.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <publisher>
      <organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
      <onlineUrl>http://mcm.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </publisher>
    <pubPlace>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</pubPlace>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <para>
              <literalLayout>The Mt. Fleming meteorological station was added to the McMurdo Dry Valley network in the 1995-1996 field season. It was established on the shore of Mt. Fleming in Victoria Valley, one of the largest lakes in the dry valleys, recently discovered to have a 19 m ice cover over a hypersaline brine of undetermined depth. The station was set up to sample sensors every 30 seconds and send summary statistics (for example, averages and maximums) to solid-state storage modules every 15 minutes. This has resulted in approximately 20 values being recorded for final storage in every output interval. Sampling and Averaging Intervals For Sampling frequency and Data Logger output and averaging intervals please visit: http://mcmlter.lternet.edu/data/meteorology/methods/Interval_Dates.pdf Seasonal Task Summary To view the data post-processing steps for each season please visit: http://mcmlter.lternet.edu/data/meteorology/tasks/task_lists.htm Details from Task List For File FLMM_201112_SM001.DAT (01/08/2011 11:00 to 12/14/2011 15:15). Program Name: flm201011v1.dld Sampling every 30 seconds. Cr10X 1 minutes and 12 secs behind. Adjusted time at 12/14/2011 1442. Swapped wind monitor, RH head, CR10X and pressure. Installed FGR-115RC radio, wavelink PRO890-12-40F02N4 12 dbi antenna, Crydom solid-state relay DC60S3 and SC32B. Antenna pointed at Lake Vanda. No connection Loaded new program, FLMM_201112v1.dld at 12/14/2011 @ 1515. For second file (FLMM_201112_SM002-003.DAT: Cr10X 2 minutes and 10 secs behind. Adjusted time at 01/26/2011 1420. Swapped out pressure with old sensor. Was not sure new one was working, which it was. Need to replace again next season. Loaded new program, FLMM_201112_v2.dld at 12/14/2011 @ 1515. Corrected mistaking in radio timing. Moved wire from C8 to C7, wrong location for turning the SwCtrl12V. Rotated radio antenna 10 degrees CW. Still no success connecting with the hub at Vanda Second air temp is still not working. Need to check program.</literalLayout>
            </para>
          </section>
        </description>
        <instrumentation>1995-1996 - 1999-2000: Campbell Scientific 207 temp/rh probe. 1999-2000 - present: Campbell Scientific 107 temp probe.</instrumentation>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>FLMM_AIRT</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Mt Fleming Station Air Temperature spreadsheet description and units</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>FLMM_AIRT.csv</objectName>
        <size>4749859</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>27</numHeaderLines>
            <numFooterLines>1</numFooterLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-mcm/7018/4/9af8581db5dfe4f162fc47afde6df0c2</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <methods>
        <methodStep>
          <description>
            <section>
              <para>
                <literalLayout>For File FLMM_201112_SM001.DAT (01/08/2011 11:00 to 12/14/2011 15:15). Program Name: flm201011v1.dld Sampling every 30 seconds. Cr10X 1 minutes and 12 secs behind. Adjusted time at 12/14/2011 1442. 2. Swapped wind monitor, RH head, CR10X and pressure. 3. Installed FGR-115RC radio, wavelink PRO890-12-40F02N4 12 dbi antenna, Crydom solid-state relay DC60S3 and SC32B. Antenna pointed at Lake Vanda. No connection 4. Loaded new program, FLMM_201112v1.dld at 12/14/2011 @ 1515. For second file (FLMM_201112_SM002-003.DAT: 1. Cr10X 2 minutes and 10 secs behind. Adjusted time at 01/26/2011 1420. 2. Swapped out pressure with old sensor. Was not sure new one was working, which it was. Need to replace again next season.. 3. Loaded new program, FLMM_201112_v2.dld at 12/14/2011 @ 1515. Corrected mistaking in radio timing. Moved wire from C8 to C7, wrong location for turning the SwCtrl12V. Rotated radio antenna 10 degrees CW. Still no success connecting with the hub at Vanda 4. Second air temp is still not working. Need to check program.</literalLayout>
              </para>
            </section>
          </description>
          <instrumentation>1995-1996 - 1999-2000: Campbell Scientific 207 temp/rh probe. 1999-2000 - present: Campbell Scientific 107 temp probe.</instrumentation>
        </methodStep>
      </methods>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DATASET_CODE</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DATASET_CODE</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Code for given set of information for Mt. Fleming meteorology station</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Code for given set of information for Mt. Fleming meteorology station</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>METLOCID</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>METLOCID</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Location code for Mt. Fleming meteorology station</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Location code for Mt. Fleming meteorology station</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DATE_TIME</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DATE_TIME</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Date/time of sample (New Zealand DST, +13 UTC)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>MM/DD/YYYY HH24:MI</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>AIRT2M</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>AIRT2M</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Average air temperature at 2 m above ground</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.01</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Null</code>
            <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>AIRTMAX</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>AIRTMAX</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Maximum air temperature at 2 m above ground</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.01</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Null</code>
            <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>AIRTMIN</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>AIRTMIN</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Minimum air temperature at 2 m above ground</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.01</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Null</code>
            <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>AIRT_COMMENTS</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>air temperature comments</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Noted comments by the investigator about the particular measure of air temperature</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Noted comments by the investigator about the particular measure of air temperature</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>AIRT1_3M</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>AIRT1_3M</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>differential of air temperature between 3m and 1m above ground</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.01</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Null</code>
            <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>FLMM_RH</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Mt. Fleming station relative humidity spreadsheet description and units</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>FLMM_RH.csv</objectName>
        <size>4014548</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>27</numHeaderLines>
            <numFooterLines>1</numFooterLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-mcm/7018/4/a78cf22d77a9c769354c8a6f7cca16b9</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <methods>
        <methodStep>
          <description>
            <section>
              <para>
                <literalLayout>sampled every 30 seconds</literalLayout>
              </para>
            </section>
          </description>
        </methodStep>
      </methods>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DATASET_CODE</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DATASET_CODE</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Code for given set of information for Mt. Fleming meteorology station</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Code for given set of information for Mt. Fleming meteorology station</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>METLOCID</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>METLOCID</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Location code for Mt. Fleming meteorology station</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Location code for Mt. Fleming meteorology station</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DATE_TIME</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DATE_TIME</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Date/time of sample (New Zealand DST, +13 UTC)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>MM/DD/YYYY HH24:MI</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>RH</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>RH</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Relative humidity at 3 meters</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.01</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Null</code>
            <codeExplanation>See comments</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>RH_COMMENTS</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>relative humidity comments</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Noted comments by the investigator about the particular measure of relative humidity</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Noted comments by the investigator about the particular measure of relative humidity</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>FLMM_WIND</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Mt. Fleming station wind measurement spreadsheet description and units</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>FLMM_WIND.csv</objectName>
        <size>5737962</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>27</numHeaderLines>
            <numFooterLines>1</numFooterLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-mcm/7018/4/c50d396bff6815fd0d962417e76ccaf0</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DATASET_CODE</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DATASET_CODE</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Code for given set of information for Mt. Fleming meteorology station</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Code for given set of information for Mt. Fleming meteorology station</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>METLOCID</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>METLOCID</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Location code for Mt. Fleming meteorology station</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Location code for Mt. Fleming meteorology station</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DATE_TIME</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DATE_TIME</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Date/time of sample (New Zealand DST, +13 UTC)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>MM/DD/YYYY HH24:MI</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>WDIR</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>WDIR</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Average wind direction</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>degreesfromnorth</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Null</code>
            <codeExplanation>See comments</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>WDIRSTD</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>WDIRSTD</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Standard deviation of wind direction</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>degreesfromnorth</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Null</code>
            <codeExplanation>See comments</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>WSPD</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>WSPD</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Wind speed</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>metersPerSecond</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Null</code>
            <codeExplanation>See comments</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>WSPDMAX</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>WSPDMAX</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Maximum wind speed</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>metersPerSecond</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Null</code>
            <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>WSPDMIN</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>WSPDMIN</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Minimum wind speed</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>metersPerSecond</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Null</code>
            <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>WIND_COMMENTS</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>WIND_COMMENTS</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Noted comments by the investigator about the particular measure of WIND</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Noted comments by the investigator about the particular measure of WIND</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>FLMM_PRESSTA</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Mt. Fleming station atmospheric pressure spreadsheet description and units</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>FLMM_PRESSTA.csv</objectName>
        <size>3870907</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>27</numHeaderLines>
            <numFooterLines>1</numFooterLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-mcm/7018/4/725475b6623dc8d00b03130a6e3bee9a</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DATASET_CODE</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DATASET_CODE</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Code for given set of information for Mt. Fleming meteorology station</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Code for given set of information for Mt. Fleming meteorology station</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>METLOCID</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>METLOCID</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Location code for Mt. Fleming meteorology station</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Location code for Mt. Fleming meteorology station</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DATE_TIME</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DATE_TIME</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Date/time of sample (New Zealand DST, +13 UTC)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>MM/DD/YYYY HH24:MI</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>PRESSTA</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>PRESSTA</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Atmospheric Pressure (mbar)</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>millibar</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.4</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Null</code>
            <codeExplanation>see comments</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>PRESSTA_COMMENTS</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Atmospheric Pressure comments</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Noted comments by the investigator about the particular measure of atmospheric pressure</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Noted comments by the investigator about the particular measure of atmospheric pressure</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
        <ns2:unit abbreviation="%" constantToSI="0" id="percent" multiplierToSI="100" name="percent" parentSI="numberPerNumber" unitType="dimensionless">
          <ns2:description>ratio of two quantities as percent composition (1:100)</ns2:description>
        </ns2:unit>
        <ns2:unit abbreviation="" id="degreesfromnorth" name="degreesfromnorth" unitType="">
          <ns2:description />
        </ns2:unit>
      </ns2:unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>