<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-mcm.39.8" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=MCM,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <shortName>Limno Runs</shortName>
    <title>McMurdo Dry Valleys Limno Runs - Locations, Dates, Codes for Lake Chemistry, Biology Samples</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Berry</givenName>
        <surName>Lyons</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Ohio State University</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Byrd Polar Research Center. 108 Scott Hall. 1090 Carmack Rd</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <administrativeArea>OH</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>43210</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>lyons.142@osu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
      <organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
      <onlineUrl>http://mcm.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </metadataProvider>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Kathleen</givenName>
        <surName>Welch</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Ohio State University</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Byrd Polar Center</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <administrativeArea>OH</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>43210</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>welch.189@osu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>lab crew</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Amy</givenName>
        <surName>Chiuchiolo</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Montana State University</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>LRES, 334 Leon Johnson Hall</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Bozeman</city>
        <administrativeArea>MT</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>59717</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(406) 994-2360</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(406) 994-5863</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>achiuchiolo@montana.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>field crew</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>2014-11-04</pubDate>
    <language>English</language>
    <abstract>
      <section>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>This table is is a summary of "limon runs" - usually 2 or 3 per austral summer season, but may be one or, during extended seasons, over five per season. A limno run represents a complete set of samples from a lake - a useful code for tracking provenance used in the data lifecycle and chain of command too</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>date</keyword>
      <keyword>lake</keyword>
      <keyword>limnology</keyword>
      <keyword>location</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>Station Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <additionalInfo>
      <para>
        <literalLayout />
      </para>
    </additionalInfo>
    <intellectualRights>
      <section>
        <title>Data Policies</title>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>MCM LTER data may be used freely with the following restrictions: The Principal Investigator be sent a notice stating reasons for acquiring any data and a description of the publication intentions. The Principal Investigator of the data set be sent a copy of the report or manuscript prior to submission and be adequately cited in any resultant publications. A copy of any resultant publications should be sent to the McMurdo data manager and principal investigator. The end-user follow the guidelines set forth in the LTER Network Data Access Policy, Data Access Requirements, and General Data Use Agreement here: Definitions &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data Set&#226;&#8364; &#226;&#8364;&#8220; Digital data and its metadata derived from any research activity such as field observations, collections, laboratory analysis, experiments, or the post-processing of existing data and identified by a unique identifier issued by a recognized cataloging authority such as a site, university, agency, or other organization. &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data User&#226;&#8364; - individual to whom access has been granted to this Data Set, including his or her immediate collaboration sphere, defined here as the institutions, partners, students and staff with whom the Data User collaborates, and with whom access must be granted, in order to fulfill the Data User's intended use of the Data Set &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data Set Creator&#226;&#8364; - individual or institution that produced the Data Set &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data Set Owner&#226;&#8364; &#226;&#8364;&#8220; individual or institution that holds intellectual property rights to the dataset. Note that this may or may not be defined as a legal copyright. If no other party is designated in the metadata as Data Set Owner, it may be presumed that these rights are held by the Data Set Creator. &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data Set Distributor&#226;&#8364; - individual or institution providing access to the Data Sets. &#226;&#8364;&#339;Data Set Contact&#226;&#8364; - party designated in the accompanying metadata of the Data Set as the primary contact for the Data Set. Conditions of Use The re-use of scientific data has the potential to greatly increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines, and thus is fostered, supported and encouraged. Permission to use this dataset is granted to the Data User free of charge subject to the following terms: 1) Acceptable use. Use of the dataset will be restricted to academic, research, educational, government, recreational, or other not-for-profit professional purposes. The Data User is permitted to produce and distribute derived works from this dataset provided that they are released under the same license terms as those accompanying this Data Set. Any other uses for the Data Set or its derived products will require explicit permission from the dataset owner. 2 ) Redistribution. The data are provided for use by the Data User. The metadata and this license must accompany all copies made and be available to all users of this Data Set. The Data User will not redistribute the original Data Set beyond this collaboration sphere. 3 ) Citation. It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Data Set in any publications or in the metadata of any derived data products that were produced using the Data Set. Citation should take the following general form: Creator, Year of Data Publication, Title of Dataset, Publisher, Dataset identifier. For example: McKee, W. 2001. Vascular plant list on the Andrews Experimental Forest and nearby Research Natural Areas: Long-Term Ecological Research. Corvallis, OR: Forest Science Data Bank: SA002. [Database]. http://www.fsl.orst.edu/lter/data/abstract.cfm?dbcode=SA002. (21 October 2004) 4 ) Acknowledgement. The Data User should acknowledge any institutional support or specific funding awards referenced in the metadata accompanying this dataset in any publications where the Data Set contributed significantly to its content. Acknowledgements should identify the supporting party, the party that received the support, and any identifying information such as grant numbers. For example: Data sets were provided by the Forest Science Data Bank, a partnership between the Department of Forest Science, Oregon State University, and the U.S. Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station, Corvallis, Oregon. Significant funding for collection of these data was provided by the National Science Foundation Long-Term Ecological Research program (NSF Grant numbers BSR-90-11663 and DEB-96-32921). 5 ) Notification. The Data User will notify the Data Set Contact when any derivative work or publication based on or derived from the Data Set is distributed. The Data User will provide the data contact with two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the Data Set and will provide copies, or on-line access to, any derived digital products. Notification will include an explanation of how the Data Set was used to produce the derived work. 6 ) Collaboration. The Data Set has been released in the spirit of open scientific collaboration. Data Users are thus strongly encouraged to consider consultation, collaboration and/or co-authorship with the Data Set Creator. By accepting this Data Set, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. The Data Owner shall have the right to terminate this agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement. Disclaimer While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation contained in this Data Set, complete accuracy of data and metadata cannot be guaranteed. All data and metadata are made available "as is". The Data User holds all parties involved in the production or distribution of the Data Set harmless for damages resulting from its use or interpretation.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url function="information">http://mcm.lternet.edu/content/limno-runs-locations-dates-codes-lake-chemistry-biology-samples</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lake Bonney is a saline lake with permanent ice cover at the western end of Taylor Valley in the McMurdo Dry Valleys of Victoria Land, Antarctica. It is 7 kilometres or 4.3 mi long and up to 900 metres or 3,000 ft wide. A narrow channel only 50 metres or 160 ft wide. Lake Bonney at Narrows separates the lake into East Lake Bonney 3.32 square kilometres or 1.28 sq mi and West Lake Bonney, 0.99 square kilometres or 0.38 sq mi. The west lobe is flanked by Taylor glacier. Valley: Taylor Distance to Sea : 25 Maximum Length (km): 4.8 Maximum Width (km): 0.9 Maximum Depth (m): 37 Surface Area (km^2): 3.32 Ice Thickness Average Surface (m): 3 - 4.5 Volume (m^3 * 10^6): 54.7</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>162.353210449219</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>162.536209106445</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.697700500488</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.724441528320</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>57</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>57</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lake Brownworth is&#160;a meltwater lake west of&#160;Wright Lower Glacier&#160;at the east end of&#160;Wright Valley.&#160;It was named by the&#160;Advisory Committee on Antarctic Names&#160;for&#160;Frederick S. Brownworth Jr.,</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>162.718856811523</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>162.823226928711</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.417655944824</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.442016601563</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>5</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>5</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lake Chad is in the Lake Hoare basin, Taylor Valley, west of Lake Hoare and east of the Suess Glacier. Wharton, House and McKay streams flow from the Suess Glacier directly into Lake Chad and then the overflow from Lake Chad flows into Lake Hoare. Valley: Taylor Distance to Sea : 24 Maximum Length (km): 1 Maximum Width (km): 0.2 Maximum Depth (m): 5.5 Surface Area (km^2): 0.15 Ice Thickness Average Surface (m): 3.5 - 4.5</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>162.745544433594</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>162.785705566406</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.640029907227</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.644386291504</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Narrows between Lake Chad and Lake Hoare is a short spillway approximately 5m long between Lake Chad and Lake Hoare. Wharton, House and McKay streams flow into Lake Chad from the Suess Glacier. The overflow from Lake Chad then flows into the west end of Lake Hoare. There are many microbial mats in this area between the Hoare and Chad moats and around the spillway. Valley: Taylor Distance to Sea : 24 Maximum Length (km): 0.005</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>162.774902343750</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>162.793258666992</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.639038085938</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.641983032227</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Don Juan Pond is located in the west end of the Wright Valley. It is wedged between the Asgard Range and the Dias. On the west end there is a small tributary and a feature that has been described as a rock glacier. Don Juan Pond is a shallow (i.e. flat bottom) hyper-saline pond. The salinity is high enough that it doesn't freeze even in winter. Therefore, unlike other lakes and ponds in the dry valleys, it has no ice cover. It has been described as a groundwater discharge zone. The dominant ions in solution are calcium and chloride. The area around Don Juan Pond is covered with sodium chloride and calcium chloride salts that have been precipitated as the water evaporated. Area and volume of Don Juan Pond varies over time. According to the USGS topo map published in 1977, the area was approximately 0.25 sq. km. However, in recent years the size of the pond has shrunk considerably. The pond has changed over the past 5 years although this is mostly anecdotal. The maximum depth in 93-94 was described as "a foot deep." In Jan 97, it was approximately 10cm deep; in Dec 98 the pond was almost dry everywhere except for an area 10's of sq meters. Most of the water that was left was restricted to depressions around large boulders in the pond. Valley: Wright Distance to Sea : 60 Maximum Length (km): 0.75 Maximum Width (km): 0.35 Maximum Depth (m): 0.1</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>161.190994262695</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>161.190994262695</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.561897277832</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.561897277832</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>200</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>200</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>The Lake Fryxell basin is formed by a moraine depression in a wider portion of the Taylor Valley. It has a number of moraine islands and shallower areas, as well as several relatively well developed deltas. The lake is fed by at least 10 meltwater streams with a total drainage catchment of 230 km2. The lake is dammed to the southwest by the Canada Glacier and is topographically closed. It is perennially ice covered; during summer months, an ice-free moat generally forms around much of the lake margin. Lake levels have risen ~2 m between 1971 and 1996. There are no surface outflows; the only known water loss is through ice ablation (evaporation, sublimation and physical scouring). Valley: Taylor Distance to Sea : 9 Maximum Length (km): 5.8 Maximum Width (km): 2.1 Maximum Depth (m): 20 Surface Area (km^2): 7.08 Ice Thickness Average Surface (m): 3.3 - 4.5 Volume (m^3 * 10^6): 25.2</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>163.048782348633</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>163.259582519531</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.597076416016</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.622711181641</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>18</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>18</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lake Garwood is located in the Garwood Valley, adjacent to McMurdo Sound on the east side. It is fed by the Garwood River, which contains meltwater from Garwood Glacier, as well as Joyce Glacier, which melts into Lake Colleen, which in turn flows into the Garwood River. Valley: Garwood Distance to Sea : 0.01</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>164.276672363281</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>164.310836791992</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-78.030540466309</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-78.034614562988</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>10</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>10</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lake Hoare occupies a narrower portion of the Taylor Valley, dammed by the Canada Glacier. It would drain almost completely without this dam. There are a number of islands which may be related to an old terminal of Canada Glacier. The lake is fed primarily from direct runoff from the glacier, as well as meltwater streams. (Lake level rose ~1.5 m between 1972 and 1996). There are no surface outflows; the only known water loss is through ice ablation (evaporation, sublimation and physical scouring). Valley: Taylor Distance to Sea : 15 Maximum Length (km): 4.2 Maximum Width (km): 1 Maximum Depth (m): 34 Surface Area (km^2): 1.94 Ice Thickness Average Surface (m): 3.1 - 5.5 Volume (m^3 * 10^6): 17.5</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>162.784423828125</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>162.935836791992</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.623085021973</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.639259338379</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>73</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>73</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lake Joyce lies in the Pearse Valley against the Taylor Glacier.&#160;Valley: Pearse&#160;Distance to Sea : 44&#160;Maximum Length (km): 1&#160;Maximum Width (km): 1&#160;Maximum Depth (m): 35&#160;Surface Area (km^2): 0.83&#160;Ice Thickness Average Surface (m): 3.9 - 5.6&#160;Volume (m^3 * 10^6): 4.9</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>161.608886718750</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>161.662445068359</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.715972900391</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.726486206055</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>301</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>301</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lake Miers lies in the Miers Valley. Valley: Miers Distance to Sea : 20 Maximum Length (km): 1.5 Maximum Width (km): 0.7 Maximum Depth (m): 21 Surface Area (km^2): 1.3 Ice Thickness Average Surface (m): 3.4 - 6 Volume (m^3 * 10^6): 2.9</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>163.812332153320</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>163.886840820313</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-78.094047546387</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-78.101478576660</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>240</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>240</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>A lake with an area of 1 square mile which occupies the north portion of Pyramid Trough, Scott Coast. Named by New Zealand Geographic Board (NZGB) (1994) in association with Pyramid Trough.</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>162.718856811523</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>162.823226928711</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.417655944824</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.442016601563</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lake Vanda is located in the Wright Valley, adjacent to the Taylor Valley. It is fed primarily by the Onyx River, which has its origin at Lake Brownworth, and ultimately at the Lower Wright Glacier located ~27 km east of the lake. The lake has no outflow. Valley: Wright Distance to Sea : 47 Maximum Length (km): 8 Maximum Width (km): 2 Maximum Depth (m): 75 Surface Area (km^2): 5.2 Ice Thickness Average Surface (m): 2.8 - 4.2 Volume (m^3 * 10^6): 160</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>161.391906738281</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>161.691970825195</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.518882751465</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.542304992676</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>143</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>143</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lake Bonney is a saline lake with permanent ice cover at the western end of Taylor Valley in the McMurdo Dry Valleys of Victoria Land, Antarctica. It is 7 kilometres or 4.3 mi long and up to 900 metres or 3,000 ft wide. A narrow channel only 50 metres or 160 ft wide. Lake Bonney at Narrows separates the lake into East Lake Bonney 3.32 square kilometres or 1.28 sq mi and West Lake Bonney, 0.99 square kilometres or 0.38 sq mi. Valley: Taylor Distance to Sea : 28 Maximum Length (km): 2.6 Maximum Width (km): 0.9 Maximum Depth (m): 40 Surface Area (km^2): 0.99 Ice Thickness Average Surface (m): 2.8-4.5 Volume (m^3 * 10^6): 10.1</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>162.269104003906</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>162.354934692383</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.714805603027</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.727287292480</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>57</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>57</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1994-01-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2014-12-31</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>metadata enhanced in 2016 using the Drupal Ecological Information Management System (DEIMS)</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">505 277-2535</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">505 277-2541</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>tech-support@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
      <onlineUrl>http://mcm.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <publisher>
      <organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
      <onlineUrl>http://mcm.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </publisher>
    <pubPlace>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</pubPlace>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <para>
              <literalLayout>Two 10-cm-diameter sampling holes are drilled through the ice by auger at the deepest site of each lake and then melted out to a diameter of ~30 cm. One hole is used for&#194;&#160; water column PAR profiles and the primary productivity incubation; the other hole is used for discrete water sampling (Van Dorn or Niskin bottles) and CTD deployment and&#194;&#160; is protected with an opaque cover. &#194;&#160; Discrete water samples are collected at specific depths relative to the water level in the borehole in each lake to capture important vertical characteristics. Appendix 6.1 in the Limnology Methods Manual lists the target depths at which samples are collected. However, due to environmental conditions (ice thickness, bottom depth in area of sample hole caused by lake level variation) the samples immediately beneath the ice and nearest to the bottom cannot always be replicated. &#194;&#160;Consequently, the top sample is collected ~0.5m below the bottom of the ice cover, and the bottom sample as close to the bottom of the lake as possible without disturbing the sediment. &#194;&#160;</literalLayout>
            </para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>LIMNO_RUN_CODING</entityName>
      <physical>
        <objectName>LIMNO_RUN_CODING.csv</objectName>
        <size>32812</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>21</numHeaderLines>
            <numFooterLines>1</numFooterLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-mcm/39/8/e66763e5892b06aca2d5ee762680795c</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DATASET_CODE</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DATASET_CODE</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Code to identify the data containing entity - LIMNO_RUN_CODING</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Code to identify the data containing entity - LIMNO_RUN_CODING</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Limno_Run</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Limno_Run</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Code for lake's sampling location and date</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Code for lake's sampling location and date</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Location_Name</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Location_Name</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Name of lake where measurement was made</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Name of lake where measurement was made</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Location_Code</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Location_Code</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Code for site where measurement was made</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Code for site where measurement was made</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>STARTING_DATE</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>STARTING_DATE</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Date on which sampling began</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>MM/DD/YYYY</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Required entry</code>
            <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>ENDING_DATE</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>ENDING_DATE</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Date on which sampling ended</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>MM/DD/YYYY</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Required entry</code>
            <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>LAT</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Latitude</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Point Latitude of the whole where measurement was made</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.0001</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Null</code>
            <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>LON</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Longitude</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Point Longitude of the whole where measurement was taken</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.0001</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>Null</code>
            <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>COMMENTS</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>COMMENTS</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Comments about the particular limno run</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Comments about the particular limno run</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
</eml:eml>