<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-arc.1384.8" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=ARC,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <shortName>1996gshtbm</shortName>
    <title>Plant biomass in heath tundra experimental plots, 1996, Arctic LTER, Toolik Lake, Alaska.</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Gaius</givenName>
        <surName>Shaver</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>7 M B L St</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Woods Hole</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.mbl.edu/ecosystems/staff/shaver/</onlineUrl>
    </creator>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>James</givenName>
        <surName>Laundre</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Laboratory,Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Woods Hole</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>jlaundre@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>associated researcher</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>2015-12-14</pubDate>
    <language>English</language>
    <abstract>
      <section>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>Plant biomass in arctic heath experimental plots. Plots set up in 1989 with nitrogen, phosphorus, nitrogen plus phosphorus and a shade treatment were harvested for above ground biomass. Root mass was also measured on a smaller subsample.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>tundra</keyword>
      <keyword>productivity</keyword>
      <keyword>primary production</keyword>
      <keyword>populations</keyword>
      <keyword>phosphorus</keyword>
      <keyword>organic matter</keyword>
      <keyword>nitrogen</keyword>
      <keyword>inorganic nutrients</keyword>
      <keyword>disturbance</keyword>
      <keyword>biomass</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <section>
        <title>Data Policies</title>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>The re-use of scientific data has the potential to greatly increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines, and thus is fostered, supported and encouraged. Permission to use this dataset is granted to the Data User free of charge subject to the following terms: 1) Acceptable use. Use of the dataset will be restricted to academic, research, educational, government, recreational, or other not-for-profit professional purposes. The Data User is permitted to produce and distribute derived works from this dataset provided that they are released under the same license terms as those accompanying this Data Set. Any other uses for the Data Set or its derived products will require explicit permission from the dataset owner. 2 ) Redistribution. The data are provided for use by the Data User. The metadata and this license must accompany all copies made and be available to all users of this Data Set. The Data User will not redistribute the original Data Set beyond this collaboration sphere. 3 ) Citation. It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Data Set in any publications or in the metadata of any derived data products that were produced using the Data Set. Citation should take the following general form: Creator, Year of Data Publication, Title of Dataset, Publisher, Dataset identifier. For example: Shaver, G. 1989. Above ground biomass in acidic tussock tundra experimental site, 1989, Arctic LTER, Toolik, Alaska. Arctic LTER, Marine Biological Lab, Woods Hole, Ma 02543. 1989gsttbm http://ecosystems.mbl.edu/arc/terrest/biomass/index.shtml 4 ) Acknowledgement. The Data User should acknowledge any institutional support or specific funding awards referenced in the metadata accompanying this dataset in any publications where the Data Set contributed significantly to its content. Acknowledgements should identify the supporting party, the party that received the support, and any identifying information such as grant numbers. For example: Data sets were provided by the Arctic LTER. This material is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation under Grants #DEB-981022, 9211775, 8702328; #OPP-9911278, 9911681, 9732281, 9615411, 9615563, 9615942, 9615949, 9400722, 9415411, 9318529; #BSR 9019055, 8806635, 8507493. 5 ) Notification. The Data User will notify the Data Set Contact when any derivative work or publication based on or derived from the Data Set is distributed. The Data User will provide the data contact with two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the Data Set and will provide copies, or on-line access to, any derived digital products. Notification will include an explanation of how the Data Set was used to produce the derived work. 6 ) Collaboration. The Data Set has been released in the spirit of open scientific collaboration. Data Users are thus strongly encouraged to consider consultation, collaboration and/or co-authorship with the Data Set Creator. By accepting this Data Set, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. The Data Owner shall have the right to terminate this agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement. Disclaimer While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation contained in this Data Set, complete accuracy of data and metadata cannot be guaranteed. All data and metadata are made available "as is". The Data User holds all parties involved in the production or distribution of the Data Set harmless for damages resulting from its use or interpretation.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url function="information">http://arc-lter.ecosystems.mbl.edu/1996gshtbm</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Arctic LTER Experimental Plots: Heath Tundra - Block 1, Northeast corner near Toolik Field Station, North Slope, Alaska.</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-149.587</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-149.587</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>68.6417</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>68.6417</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>724</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>724</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1996-07-24</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>1996-08-01</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>Log of changes: 5Mar00 Separated comma delimited data from Excel file. JL 27Oct04 completed the variable description and update the file name to 1996. JL For Archival Use: DATE RECEIVED: Sept 1996 DATA FILE ENTERED BY: Jim Laundre DATA FILE VALIDATION: NAME: Jim Laundre, Gus Shaver DATE: 8Oct91 Version 2: Added attribute table. Jiml Version 3: Added LTERNET Data Access server proxy for Excel and comma delimited data files. Version 4: Upadte LTERNET Data Access server proxy link for Excel and comma delimited data files. Changed from knb to das in url. Version 5: Updated the metadata form to new version and eml to 2.1.0 JimL 9Jul2012 Version 6: Taxonomic coverage data updated. Updated metadata to newer form (with sites sheet). CH March 2013. Version 7: Checked keywords against the LTER network preferred list and replaced non-preferred terms. Jim L 27Jan14 Version 8: Changed Distrubution URL since the LTER network DAS system is being discontinued. JimL 9Apr2015 Version 9: Changed Distrubution URL since the LTER network DAS system is being discontinued. JimL 9Apr2015</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">505 277-2535</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">505 277-2541</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>tech-support@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Arctic_LTER</givenName>
        <surName>Information Manager</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>7 M B L St.</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Woods Hole</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02536</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 548-3705</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>arc_im@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <pubPlace>Arctic LTER</pubPlace>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <para>
              <literalLayout>The Arctic LTER heath plots are located in a dry dwarf-shrub, fruticose-lichen tundra near the north end of Toolik Lake. They are laid out in three blocks of randomized 5x20 m plots. Each block contains the following treatments: control (CT), nitrogen plus phosphorus (NP), nitrogen (N) and phosphorus (P). Shade (SH) and shade plus nitrogen and phosphorus (SHNP) are replicated in only 2 blocks (SHNP was not harvested). The plots were established in June 1998. Nitrogen and/or phosphorus plots receive an annual treatment of 10 g/m2 nitrogen (as NH4NO3) and/or 5 g/m2 phosphorous (as triple superphosphate). Shade houses, simple &amp;#039;A&amp;#039; frames covered with 50% light reducing shade cloth, are covered annually in late May or early June and uncovered at the end of August or early September. Calculations: Units; Tissue mass data are expressed in g/quadrat (400 cm2). Multiply by 25 to get g/m2. Reference Citations: Shaver, G. R., and F. S. Chapin. 1991. Production biomass relationships and element cycling in contrasting arctic vegetation types. Ecological Monographs 61:1-31. Sampling Description. In N, P, NP, and CT plots, five quadrats (20 cm x 20 cm) were located at random along a 10 m transect that was about 40 cm from the south edge of the east end. In the shade plots, quadrats were located haphazardly in the eastern third of each shade frame by tossing a knife, spinning, into the plot and taking a quadrat at the point of the knife. Each quadrat was harvested to a depth of about 10 to 15 cm, which included most roots. Aboveground biomass was considered &amp;quot;within&amp;quot; the quadrat if it was associated with a meristem that was within the quadrat. All vascular plants were sorted to species while mosses and lichens were lumped. Categories included: new above, old above, and below ground stems/rhizomes. Leaves and stems for the new or old category were not separated. Only the green mass of the mosses and the total live mass of the lichens were sorted. Coarse roots (greater than 1 mm in diameter) were separated in all quadrats. To estimate fine root mass, a 50-100 g sample of homogenized loose soil from each quadrat in block 1 was taken and all the fine roots were separated, dried and weighed. Weights of the total soil, the subsample and the dried roots were recorded. All samples were dried at 50-70 degrees C for several days and weighed to nearest milligram. Samples were then returned to Woods Hole for archiving and future nutrient analysis. Details are given in Shaver and Chapin (Ecological Monographs, 61(1), 1991, pg. 1.)</literalLayout>
            </para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>1996gshtbm_csv</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Plant biomass in heath tundra experimental plots, 1996, Arctic LTER, Toolik Lake, Alaska.</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>1996gshtbm.csv</objectName>
        <size>26127</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-arc/1384/8/d23099e9bae706637082d0b0c4f0ae5c</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Treatment</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Treatment</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Experimental treatment plot. See methods for description.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Experimental treatment plot. See methods for description.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Growth Form</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Growth Form</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The growth form</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>The growth form</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Species</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Species</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The species categroy. Only major species were categorized. All others were lumped under 'Other' category.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>The species categroy. Only major species were categorized. All others were lumped under 'Other' category.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Tissue</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Tissue</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The tissue type</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>The tissue type</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>B1CTQ1</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>B1CTQ1</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Oven dried weight (gm) of sample collected in a quadrat. (Code of variable name: B for block and the number following the B is the block number and then treatment code. Q stands for quadrat with the number following the Q being the quadrat number).</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>B1CTQ2</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>B1CTQ2</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Oven dried weight (gm) of sample collected in a quadrat. (Code of variable name: B for block and the number following the B is the block number and then treatment code. Q stands for quadrat with the number following the Q being the quadrat number).</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>B1CTQ3</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>B1CTQ3</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Oven dried weight (gm) of sample collected in a quadrat. (Code of variable name: B for block and the number following the B is the block number and then treatment code. Q stands for quadrat with the number following the Q being the quadrat number).</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>B1CTQ4</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>B1CTQ4</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Oven dried weight (gm) of sample collected in a quadrat. (Code of variable name: B for block and the number following the B is the block number and then treatment code. Q stands for quadrat with the number following the Q being the quadrat number).</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>B1CTQ5</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>B1CTQ5</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Oven dried weight (gm) of sample collected in a quadrat. (Code of variable name: B for block and the number following the B is the block number and then treatment code. Q stands for quadrat with the number following the Q being the quadrat number).</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>B2CTQ1</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>B2CTQ1</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Oven dried weight (gm) of sample collected in a quadrat. (Code of variable name: B for block and the number following the B is the block number and then treatment code. Q stands for quadrat with the number following the Q being the quadrat number).</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>B2CTQ2</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>B2CTQ2</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Oven dried weight (gm) of sample collected in a quadrat. (Code of variable name: B for block and the number following the B is the block number and then treatment code. Q stands for quadrat with the number following the Q being the quadrat number).</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>B2CTQ3</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>B2CTQ3</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Oven dried weight (gm) of sample collected in a quadrat. (Code of variable name: B for block and the number following the B is the block number and then treatment code. Q stands for quadrat with the number following the Q being the quadrat number).</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>B2CTQ4</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>B2CTQ4</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Oven dried weight (gm) of sample collected in a quadrat. (Code of variable name: B for block and the number following the B is the block number and then treatment code. Q stands for quadrat with the number following the Q being the quadrat number).</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>B2CTQ5</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>B2CTQ5</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Oven dried weight (gm) of sample collected in a quadrat. (Code of variable name: B for block and the number following the B is the block number and then treatment code. Q stands for quadrat with the number following the Q being the quadrat number).</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>B3CTQ1</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>B3CTQ1</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Oven dried weight (gm) of sample collected in a quadrat. (Code of variable name: B for block and the number following the B is the block number and then treatment code. Q stands for quadrat with the number following the Q being the quadrat number).</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>B3CTQ2</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>B3CTQ2</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Oven dried weight (gm) of sample collected in a quadrat. (Code of variable name: B for block and the number following the B is the block number and then treatment code. Q stands for quadrat with the number following the Q being the quadrat number).</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>B3CTQ3</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>B3CTQ3</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Oven dried weight (gm) of sample collected in a quadrat. (Code of variable name: B for block and the number following the B is the block number and then treatment code. Q stands for quadrat with the number following the Q being the quadrat number).</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>B3CTQ4</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>B3CTQ4</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Oven dried weight (gm) of sample collected in a quadrat. (Code of variable name: B for block and the number following the B is the block number and then treatment code. Q stands for quadrat with the number following the Q being the quadrat number).</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>B3CTQ5</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>B3CTQ5</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Oven dried weight (gm) of sample collected in a quadrat. (Code of variable name: B for block and the number following the B is the block number and then treatment code. Q stands for quadrat with the number following the Q being the quadrat number).</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Average gm/quad</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Average gm/quad</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Average gm/quad Average of all quadrats for that species and tissue type.</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Std. Err. gm/quad</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Std. Err. gm/quad</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Standard Error of the mean for species and tissue type.</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Count</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Count</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Number of quadrats</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>number</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Average gm/m2</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Average gm/m2</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Average of all quadrats expressed as g/m2</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Std. Err. gm/m2</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Std. Err. gm/m2</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Standard error of the mean in g/m2.</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>#N/A</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
    <otherEntity>
      <entityName>1996gshtbm_excel</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Excel file with metadata and data sheets. Plant biomass in heath tundra experimental plots, 1996, Arctic LTER, Toolik Lake, Alaska.</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>1996gshtbm.xls</objectName>
        <size>419328</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <externallyDefinedFormat>
            <formatName>application/vnd.ms-excel</formatName>
          </externallyDefinedFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-arc/1384/8/cf615793a28e58df017be03e93aa7610</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <entityType>document</entityType>
    </otherEntity>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
        <ns2:unit abbreviation="" constantToSI="0" id="gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared" multiplierToSI="0.00004" name="gramPerFourHundredthMeterSquared" parentSI="kilogramsPerSquareMeter" unitType="arealMassDensity">
          <ns2:description>grams per 0.04 square meter</ns2:description>
        </ns2:unit>
        <ns2:unit abbreviation="number" constantToSI="0" id="number" multiplierToSI="1" name="number" parentSI="dimensionless" unitType="dimensionless">
          <ns2:description>dimensionless number, i.e., ratio, count</ns2:description>
        </ns2:unit>
        <ns2:unit abbreviation="g/m&#178;" constantToSI="0" id="gramPerMeterSquared" multiplierToSI="0.001" name="gramPerMeterSquared" parentSI="kilogramsPerSquareMeter" unitType="arealMassDensity">
          <ns2:description>grams per square meter</ns2:description>
        </ns2:unit>
      </ns2:unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>