<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.92.167872" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <title>Small Mammal Exclosure Study (SMES) Termite Mud Casing Data from Chihuahaun Desert Grassland and Shrubland at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico (1996-2005)</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>David</givenName>
        <surName>Lightfoot</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Sevilleta LTER, 167 Castetter Hall, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>dlightfo@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
        <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(505) 277.5355</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </metadataProvider>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>David</givenName>
        <surName>Lightfoot</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Sevilleta LTER, 167 Castetter Hall, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>dlightfo@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>data manager</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Terri</givenName>
        <surName>Koontz</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, Castetter 167, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>tkoontz@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>data manager</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Yang</givenName>
        <surName>Xia</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Sevilleta LTER UNM Biology Department, MSC03 2020 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-8119</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(505) 277.5355</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>yxia@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>data manager</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>2016-08-03</pubDate>
    <language>English</language>
    <abstract>
      <section>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>The purpose of this study is to determine whether or not the activities of small &#194;&#160;mammals regulate plant community structure, plant species diversity, and spatial vegetation patterns in Chihuahuan Desert shrublands and grasslands. What role if any do indigenous small mammal consumers have in maintaining desertified landscapes in the Chihuahuan Desert? Additionally, how do the effects of small mammals interact with changing climate to affect vegetation patterns over time? This is data for amounts of termite mud casing measured on each of the SMES study plots. Three-dimensional measurements were made from all termite mud casing present on each of the 36 one-meter2 quadrats twice each year when vegetation was measured.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>disturbance</keyword>
      <keyword>populations</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>deserts</keyword>
      <keyword>grasslands</keyword>
      <keyword>termites</keyword>
      <keyword>small mammals</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <additionalInfo>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>Additional Information on the personnel associated with the Data Collection / Data Processing Sevilleta Field Crew Employee History Megan McClung, April 2013-present, Stephanie Baker, October 2010-Present, John Mulhouse, August 2009-Present, Amaris Swann, August 25, 2008-January 2013, Maya Kapoor, August 9, 2003-January 21, 2005 and April 2010-March 2011, Terri Koontz, February 2000-August 2003 and August 2006-August 2010, Yang Xia, January 31, 2005-April 2009, Karen Wetherill, February 7, 2000-August 2009, Michell Thomey, September 3, 2005-August 2008, Jay McLeod, January 2006-August 2006, Charity Hall, January 31, 2005-January 3, 2006, Tessa Edelen, August 15, 2004-August 15, 2005, Seth Munson, September 9, 2002-June 2004, Caleb Hickman, September 9, 2002-November 15, 2004, Heather Simpson, August 2000-August 2002, Chris Roberts, September 2001-August 2002, Mike Friggens, 1999-September 2001, Shana Penington, February 2000-August 2000.</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </additionalInfo>
    <intellectualRights>
      <section>
        <title>Data Policies</title>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER. A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url function="information">http://sevdeims-d.lternet.edu/data/sev-92</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Five Points Black Grama is on the transition between Chihuahuan Desert Scrub and Desert Grassland habitat. The site is subject to intensive research activity, including assessments of net primary productivity, phenology, and pollinator diversity, amongst other projects.&#160; It is the site of the unburned black grama (GU) component of the Burn NPP study. On August 4, 2009, a lightning-initiated fire began on the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge. By August 5, 2009, the fire had reached the Five Points Black Grama site.&#160; Portions of this site were burned, but not the entirety.&#160; See individual projects for further information on the effects of the burn. &#160;</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.736</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.736</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>The Rio Salado is an ephemeral tributary of the Rio Grande on the west side of the Sevilleta NWR, flowing west by northwest to east by southeast. Rio Salado Grassland &amp; Rio Salado Larrea are two study sites established in 1989. These sites were established&#160;as counterparts to sites at Five Points. Between 1989 and 1998, vegetation, litter decomposition, and ground dwelling arthropod and rodent populations were studied at both sites. Core studies at these sites were largely terminated in 1998, although rodent populations are still monitored at the Rio Salado Larrea site because the Small Mammal Exclosure Study's Larrea plots are co-located there. Rio Salado Grassland is the location Met Station 44.The Rio Salado study sites are accessed by taking the San Acacia exit, going west and then taking the frontage road back north to the Sevilleta NWR gate.&#160; After entering the refuge turn left after 0.2 mi and take this road 1.4 mi to a "T" in the road at the power lines.&#160; An earthen berm stops road travel here and the met station is located about 300 m west on the blocked road.&#160;</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.927</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.927</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>34.296</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>34.296</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>1503</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>1503</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1996-04-16</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2005-10-19</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <purpose>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>The purpose of this study is to determine whether or not the activities of small &#194;&#160;mammals regulate plant community structure, plant species diversity, and spatial vegetation patterns in Chihuahuan Desert shrublands and grasslands. What role if any do indigenous small mammal consumers have in maintaining desertified landscapes in the Chihuahuan Desert? Additionally, how do the effects of small mammals interact with changing climate to affect vegetation patterns over time? This study will provide long-term experimental tests of the roles of consumers on ecosystem pattern and process across a latitudinal climate gradient. The following questions or hypotheses will be addressed. 1) Do small mammals influence patterns of plant species composition and diversity, vegetation structure, and spatial patterns of vegetation canopy cover and biomass in Chihuahuan Desert shrublands and grasslands? Are small mammals keystone species that determine plant species composition and physiognomy of Chihuahuan Desert communities? Do small mammals have a significant role in maintaining the existence of shrub islands and spatial heterogeneity of creosotebush shrub communities? &#194;&#160; 2) Do small mammals affect the taxonomic composition and spatial pattern of vegetation similarly or differently in grassland communities as compared to shrub communities? How do patterns compare between grassland and shrubland sites, and how do these relatively small scale patterns relate to overall landscape vegetation patterns? 3) Do small mammals interact with short-term (annual) and &#194;&#160;long-term (decades) climate change to affect temporal changes in vegetation spatial patterns and species composition? 4) Do small mammals interact with other herbivore and granivore consumers enough to affect the species composition and abundance&#226;&#8364;&#8482;s of other consumers such as ants and grasshoppers?</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </purpose>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>Notes: &#194;&#160;2 measurements were taken in 1995, 3 from 1996 on, and data entry program calculates volume, 1996 on. 07/07/03 &#194;&#160;- 1996 Measurements: Checked data for missing data points, doubles, and errors. Missing data points were recorded using periods (.), duplicates of data points were removed, and errors were corrected. &#194;&#160;If a data point contained a measurement of zero and a measurement with an observation, the zero observation was removed. - Removed Species, Comments, and Per fields. &#194;&#160;Tape field was changed to ID#. If there were no observations made in the previously named Tape field, observations from the Per field were moved to the new ID# field. &#194;&#160;EC field was added and NA was recorded in this field for this year and any comments made were put in this field. &#194;&#160;Date MM/DD/YY field was changed to just DATE. Other changes in the fields include PLT to PLOT, BLK to BLOCK, M1 to LENGTH, M2 to WIDTH, and M3 to HEIGHT. - Volume was not calculated for this year. &#194;&#160;Periods (.) were put in this field to indicate this. &#194;&#160; &#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; - Terri Koontz 07/14/03 &#194;&#160;- Modified metadata to correct format. &#194;&#160;- Terri Koontz 07/07/03 &#194;&#160;- 1997 Measurements: Date MM/DD/YY field was changed to just DATE and the AREA field was changed to VOL. &#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; - Missing plots are Site G BLOCK 1 PLOT 2 TRT R and Site G BLOCK 2 PLOT 1 TRT L. &#194;&#160;These plots are from the fall field season. &#194;&#160;All plots are present for spring field season.&#194;&#160; - Any empty cells were filled in with either a period for missing data or an NA for not applicable. - Quads 9-16 were originally classified as TRT C in the fall at the Grass Site for BLOCK 4 PLOT 1. &#194;&#160;Changed the TRT to TRT R. - For the fall field season at the Grass Site, BLOCK 2 PLOT 4 TRT R QUAD 7 was classified as Creosote, changed to&#194;&#160;Grass Site.&#194;&#160; - Fall field season data has an ID# with S97, should have been F97. &#194;&#160;Error not corrected in the data. - Terri Koontz 07/07/03 &#194;&#160;- 1998 Measurements: Checked data for missing data points, doubles, and errors. Missing data points were recorded using periods (.), duplicates of data points were removed, and errors were corrected. &#194;&#160;If a data point contained a measurement of zero and a measurement with an observation, the zero observation was removed. - Date MM/DD/YY field was changed to just DATE and the AREA field was changed to VOL. &#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; - Any empty cells were filled in with either a period for missing data or an NA for not applicable. - Quads 21-24 were originally classified as TRT C in the Spring at the Grass Site for BLOCK 4 PLOT 3, changed the TRT to TRT L. - Quads 9-17 were originally classified as TRT C in the Spring at the Creosote Site for BLOCK 2 PLOT 2, changed the TRT to TRT L. - Terri Koontz 07/30/03 &#194;&#160;- Quads 10-14 were originally classified as TRT C in the spring at the Creosote Site for BLOCK 3 PLOT 4, changed TRT to TRT L. - Terri Koontz 07/07/03 &#194;&#160;- 1999 Measurements: Checked data for missing data points, doubles, and errors. Missing data points were recorded using periods (.), duplicates of data points were removed, and errors were corrected. &#194;&#160;If a data point contained a measurement of zero and a measurement with an observation, the zero observation was removed. - Date MM/DD/YY field was changed to just DATE and the AREA field was changed to VOL. &#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; - Any empty cells were filled in with either a period for missing data or an NA for not applicable. - Spring Field Season Changes For BLOCK 1 PLOT 2 TRT R and BLOCK 2 PLOT 1 TRT L all quads Classified as Creosote Site, changed to Grass Site. For quads 1-18 at the Creosote Site for BLOCK 2 PLOT 1 TRT C, originally classified as PLOT 4, changed to PLOT 1. For Creosote Site BLOCK 4 PLOT 2 TRT C: Quads 1-4, 28-35 originally PLOT 1 changed to PLOT 2 Quads 5-19 originally PLOT 3 changed to PLOT 2 For Creosote Site BLOCK 3 PLOT 2 TRT R, originally classified as BLOCK 2 and PLOT 3, changed to BLOCK 3 and PLOT 2. - Fall Field Season Changes For quads 1-18 at the Creosote Site for BLOCK 1 PLOT 4 TRT R, originally classified as PLOT 3, changed to PLOT 4. - Terri Koontz 07/07/03 &#194;&#160;- &#194;&#160;2000 Measurements: Checked data for missing data points, doubles, and errors. Missing data points were recorded using periods (.), duplicates of data points were removed, and errors were corrected. &#194;&#160;If a data point contained a measurement of zero and a measurement with an observation, the zero observation was removed. - Date MM/DD/YY field was changed to just DATE and the AREA field was changed to VOL. &#194;&#160;&#194;&#160; - Any empty cells were filled in with either a period for missing data or an NA for not applicable. - Spring Field Season Changes For Grass Site BLOCK 1 PLOT 4 TRT C Quads 1-30, originally classified as BLOCK 2, changed to BLOCK 1. For Grass Site BLOCK 3 PLOT 4 TRT C, originally classified as BLOCK 4 PLOT 3, changed to BLOCK 3 PLOT 4. - Fall Field Season Changes For Creosote Site BLOCK 2 PLOT 2 TRT L, date changed from 10/09/00 to 11/09/00 for quads 26-36. For Grass Site BLOCK 1 PLOT 4 TRT C, date changed from 10/06/00 to 11/06/00 for quads 23-29. - Terri Koontz 07/22/03 &#194;&#160;- 2001 Measurements: Checked data for missing data points, doubles, and errors. Missing data points were recorded using periods (.), duplicates of data points were removed, and errors were corrected. &#194;&#160;If a data point contained a measurement of zero and a measurement with an observation, the zero observation was removed. - Date MM/DD/YY field was changed to just DATE and AREA was changed to VOL. - Missing at the Grass Site for Fall field season all quads from BLOCK 3 PLOT 4 TRT C. - Spring Field Season Changes For Creosote BLOCK 3 PLOT 4 TRT L QUADS 18-36, originally recorded as TRT R, changed to TRT L. - Fall Field Season Changes Changed dates to reflect that data was measured in 2001 and not in the 1970s. Changed in the ID# field &#226;&#8364;&#732;1&#226;&#8364;&#8482; to SMESVQF01CR1, &#226;&#8364;&#732;2&#226;&#8364;&#8482; to SMESVQF01CR2, and &#226;&#8364;&#732;3&#226;&#8364;&#8482; to SMESVQF01CR3. For Creosote BLOCK 2 PLOT 3 TRT R QUADS 34 and 36, originally BLOCK 1 PLOT 3 TRT R, changed BLOCK 1 to BLOCK 2.&#194;&#160; For Grass BLOCK 4 PLOT 2 TRT C QUADS 13-36, originally recorded as Creosote Site, changed to Grass Site. - Any empty cells were filled in with either a period for missing data or an NA for not applicable. - Terri Koontz 03/17/06 &#194;&#160;- Checked data for missing data points, doubles, and errors. Missing data points were recorded using -999 (human Error), duplicates of data points were removed, and errors were corrected. &#194;&#160;If a data point contained a measurement of zero and a measurement with an observation, the zero observation was removed. - Date MM/DD/YY field was changed to just DATE. BLOCK field was changed to BLK. - AREA was changed to VOL. - Changed dates to reflect that data was measured in 2002 and not in the 1970s. - Changed to "1" in the EC field with comments. - Any empty cells were filled in with -999 (human Error) for missing data or an NA for not applicable. - Yang Xia 03/23/06 &#194;&#160;- For the Spring field season at the Creosote site, Plots missing are BLK 1 Plot 1 Trt C and BLK 3 Plot 3 Trt C. These plots are added to the dataset as missing values. - Metadata was modified to correct format. - Yang Xia 03/24/06 &#194;&#160;- changed start date from september 1995 to May 1995 in the research Hypotheses, since the data collection was starting on 05/02/95.&#194;&#160; - Yang Xia 05/03/06 &#194;&#160;- Checked data for missing data points, doubles, and errors. Missing data points were recorded using -999 (human Error), duplicates of data points were removed, and errors were corrected. If a data point contained a measurement of zero and a measurement with an observation, the zero observation was removed. - Date MM/DD/YY field was changed to just DATE. BLOCK field was changed to BLK; AREA was changed to VOL. - Changed dates to reflect that data was measured in 2003 and not in the 1970s. - Changed to "1" in the EC field with comments. - Any empty cells were filled in with -999 (human Error) for missing data or an NA for not applicable. - Yang Xia 06/08/06 &#194;&#160;- Metadata was modified to correct format. - Yang Xia 06/13/06 &#194;&#160;- Checked data for missing data points, doubles, and errors. Missing data points were recorded using -999 (human Error), duplicates of data points were removed, and errors were corrected. &#194;&#160;If a data point contained a measurement of zero and a measurement with an observation, the zero observation was removed. - Date MM/DD/YY field was changed to just DATE. BLOCK field was changed to BLK; AREA was changed to VOL. - Changed dates to reflect that data was measured in 2004 and not in the 1970s and 1990s. - Changed to "1" in the EC field with comments. - Any empty cells were filled in with -999 (human Error) for missing data or an NA for not applicable. - Yang Xia 06/20/06 &#194;&#160;- Modified metadata to correct format. - For Creosote Site in the Spring, changed BLOCK 4 PLOT 1 TRT C QUAD 17-21 to BLOCK 4 PLOT 1 TRL L QUAD 17-21. - For Grassland in the Spring, changed BLOCK 4 PLOT 1 TRT C QUAD 31-36 TO BLOCK 4 PLOT 1 TRT R QUAD 31-36. - Yang Xia 06/30/06 &#194;&#160;- Checked data for missing data points, doubles, and errors. Missing data points were recorded using -999 (human Error), duplicates of data points were removed, and errors were corrected. If a data point contained a measurement of zero and a measurement with an observation, the zero observation was removed. - Date MM/DD/YY field was changed to just DATE; BLOCK field was changed to BLK; AREA was changed to VOL; and TAPEID was changed to ID#. - Any empty cells were filled in with -999 (human Error) for missing data or an NA for not applicable. - Yang Xia 07/07/06 &#194;&#160;- Modified metadata to correct format. - An NA for not applicable in the EC field in 2005. - Yang Xia</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">505 277-2535</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">505 277-2541</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>tech-support@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
        <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(505) 277.5355</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <publisher>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
        <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(505) 277.5355</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </publisher>
    <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <para>
              <literalLayout>Experimental Design: There are 2 study sites, the Five Points grassland site, and the Rio Salado creosotebush site. Each study site is 1 km by 0.5 km in area. Three rodent trapping webs and four replicate experimental blocks of plots are randomly located at each study site to measure vegetation responses to the exclusion of small mammals. Each block of plots is 96 meters on each side. Each block of plots consists of 4 experimental study plots, each occupying 1/4 of each block. The blocks of study plots are all oriented on a site in a X/Y coordinate system, with the top to the north. Treatments within each block include one unfenced control plot (Treatment: C), one plot fenced with hardware cloth and poultry wire to exclude rodents and rabbits (Treatment: R), and one plot fenced only with poultry wire to exclude rabbits (Treatment: L). The three treatments were randomly assigned to each of the four possible plots in each block independently, and their arrangements differ from block to block. Each of the three plots in a replicate block are separated by 20 meters. Each experimental measurement plot measures 36 meters by 36 meters. A grid of 36 sampling points are positioned at 5.8-meter intervals on a systematically located 6 by 6 point grid within each plot. A permanent one-meter by one-meter vegetation measurement quadrat is located at each of the 36 points. The 36 quadrats are numbered 1-36, starting with number 1 in the top left corner (north-west) of each plot (top being north), and running left (west) to right (east), then down (south) one row, and then right (east) to left (west), and so on Quadrat/rebar number one is in the northwest corner of each plot, and numbers 1-6 are across the north side of the plot west to east, then quadrat/rebar number 7 is just south of quadrat/rebar number 6, and rebar numbers increase 7-12 east to west, and so on. 3-inch nails were originally placed in the top left (north-west) corner of each quadrat. These may be difficult to see. A 3-meter wide buffer area is situated between the grid of 36 points and the perimeter of each plot. While measuring vegetation on each quad, &#194;&#160;all occurrences of termite mud casing observed on the quad were measured. Termite mud casing on plant litter and dead standing plant material on the quadrat was looked for. There was usually a number of separate occurrences of casing. Each one was measured as a separate observation. A tape measure was used to measure the length, diameter, and height, for each occurrence of casing in units of one centimeter. The minimum measurement for each dimension was one centimeter. Most casing was flat on the surface, covering leaf litter, stems, rabbit feces, etc. In some situations, the casing would cover something vertical such as standing dead plant stems. For the height measurement, the vertical height of the mud casing perpendicular to the length and width, not from the ground surface was measured. In situations where there were many vertical mud cases covered stems, for example a dead clump of grass, the height, length, and width of the entire clump, not each stem was measured. If there were lots of individual occurrences of mud casing on a single quadrat (say about 10 or more) then a pooled visual estimate of all of the mud casing with one set of three dimension measures (e.g., length 20, diameter 20, height 5) was recorded and this information was placed in the comments.&#194;&#160;</literalLayout>
            </para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>sev092_smestermite_03042011.txt</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Data for SEV092</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>sev092_smestermite_03042011_0.txt</objectName>
        <size>970496</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-sev/92/167872/0c43a7832a5ec427b396fca9c3fc04c3</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <coverage>
        <temporalCoverage>
          <rangeOfDates>
            <beginDate>
              <calendarDate>1996-04-16</calendarDate>
            </beginDate>
            <endDate>
              <calendarDate>2005-10-19</calendarDate>
            </endDate>
          </rangeOfDates>
        </temporalCoverage>
      </coverage>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DATE</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DATE</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Date of data collection</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>MM/DD/YYYY</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>.</code>
            <codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>site</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>SITE</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The site at which data was collected.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>C</code>
                    <definition>Rio Salado creosote site</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>G</code>
                    <definition>Black grama site</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>BLOCK</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>BLOCK</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Experimental block.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Experimental block.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>PLOT</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>PLOT</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Plot within study design.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Plot within study design.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>TRT</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>TRT</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Treatment that was prescribed to the plot.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>C</code>
                    <definition>Control</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>L</code>
                    <definition>Lagomorph exclosure</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>R</code>
                    <definition>Rodent and Lagomorph exclosure</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>QUAD</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>QUAD</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Quadrat that data were recorded from.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Quadrat that data were recorded from.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>LENGTH</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>LENGTH</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Length of termite mud casing.</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>centimeters</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>WIDTH</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>WIDTH</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Diameter of termite mud casing.</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>centimeters</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>HEIGHT</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>HEIGHT</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Height of termite mud casing.</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>centimeters</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>VOL</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>VOL</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Volume = l*w*h</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>cubic centimeters</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>ID#</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>ID#</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Identification code that is given with each data point to identify data collector, year, and season data were collected.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Identification code that is given with each data point to identify data collector, year, and season data were collected.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>EC</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>EC</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Code to indicate if there are comments associated with a data point.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Code to indicate if there are comments associated with a data point.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
        <ns2:unit id="centimeters">
          <ns2:description />
        </ns2:unit>
        <ns2:unit id="cubic centimeters">
          <ns2:description />
        </ns2:unit>
      </ns2:unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>