<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      version="3.5"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-5.xsd">
   <recordInfo>
      <recordIdentifier source="CoBA">OSGC-000-000-019-916</recordIdentifier>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2013-11-21</recordCreationDate>
      <recordChangeDate encoding="w3cdtf">2015-10-09</recordChangeDate>
      <recordContentSource>NCAR Library and Archives</recordContentSource>
      <recordOrigin>Human prepared. Transformed from a record in the OpenSky metadata
                framework.</recordOrigin>
      <recordOrigin>This record was transformed using the following
                files: osm-main-to-mods.xsl, osm-common-to-mods.xsl, and
                osm-article-to-mods.xsl.</recordOrigin>
      <languageOfCataloging>
         <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
         <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
      </languageOfCataloging>
   </recordInfo>
   <titleInfo>
      <title>Response of tropical deep convection to localized heating perturbations: Implications for aerosol-induced convective invigoration</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal"
         valueURI="8415"
         authorityURI="https://people.ucar.edu"
         authority="UCAR People Database"
         usage="primary">
      <namePart type="given">Hugh</namePart>
      <namePart type="family">Morrison</namePart>
      <displayForm>Hugh Morrison</displayForm>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text" authority="marcrelator">author</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
      <affiliation>University Corporation For Atmospheric Research (UCAR):National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR):NCAR Earth System Laboratory (NESL):Mesoscale and Microscale Meteorology Division (MMM):Physical Meteorology Group (PMG)</affiliation>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         valueURI="6983"
         authorityURI="https://people.ucar.edu"
         authority="UCAR People Database">
      <namePart type="given">Wojciech</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">W.</namePart>
      <namePart type="family">Grabowski</namePart>
      <displayForm>Wojciech W. Grabowski</displayForm>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text" authority="marcrelator">author</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
      <affiliation>University Corporation For Atmospheric Research (UCAR):National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR):NCAR Earth System Laboratory (NESL):Mesoscale and Microscale Meteorology Division (MMM):Physical Meteorology Group (PMG)</affiliation>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="marcgt">article</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2013-11-01</dateIssued>
      <publisher>American Meteorological Society</publisher>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="rfc5646">en</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract lang="eng">A cloud-system-resolving model is used to investigate the effects of localized heating/cooling perturbations on tropical deep convection, in the context of the aerosol "invigoration effect." This effect supposes that a reduction of droplet collision-coalescence in polluted conditions leads to lofting of cloud water in convective updrafts and enhanced freezing, latent heating, and buoyancy. To specifically isolate and test this mechanism, heating perturbations were applied to updrafts with corresponding cooling applied in downdrafts. Ensemble simulations were run with either perturbed or unperturbed conditions and large-scale forcing from a 7.5-day period of active monsoon conditions during the 2006 Tropical Warm Pool–International Cloud Experiment. In the perturbed simulations there was an initial invigoration of convective updrafts and surface precipitation, but convection returned to its unperturbed state after about 24 h because of feedback with the larger-scale environment. This feedback led to an increase in the horizontally averaged mid-/upper-tropospheric temperature of about 1 K relative to unperturbed simulations. When perturbed conditions were applied to only part of the domain, gravity waves rapidly dispersed buoyancy anomalies in the perturbed region to the rest of the domain, allowing convective invigoration from the heating perturbations to be sustained over the entire simulation period. This was associated with a mean mesoscale circulation consisting of ascent (descent) at mid-/upper levels in the perturbed (unperturbed) region. In contrast to recent studies, it is concluded that the invigoration effect is intimately coupled with larger-scale dynamics through a two-way feedback, and in the absence of alterations in the larger-scale circulation there is limited invigoration beyond the convective adjustment time scale.</abstract>
   <subject authority="osm-keyword">
      <topic>Convective-scale processes</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="osm-keyword">
      <topic>Cumulus clouds</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="osm-keyword">
      <topic>Heating</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="osm-keyword">
      <topic>Cloud resolving models</topic>
   </subject>
   <relatedItem type="host">
      <titleInfo>
         <title>Journal of the Atmospheric Sciences</title>
      </titleInfo>
      <part>
         <detail type="volume">
            <number>70</number>
         </detail>
         <detail type="issue">
            <number>11</number>
         </detail>
         <extent unit="page">
            <start>3533</start>
            <end>3555</end>
            <list>3533-3555</list>
         </extent>
      </part>
   </relatedItem>
   <extension>
      <osm:classification xmlns:osm="http://nldr.library.ucar.edu/metadata/osm">Refereed</osm:classification>
   </extension>
   <extension>
      <osm:collaboration xmlns:osm="http://nldr.library.ucar.edu/metadata/osm">UCAR only</osm:collaboration>
   </extension>
   <extension>
      <osm:collectionKey xmlns:osm="http://nldr.library.ucar.edu/metadata/osm">articles</osm:collectionKey>
   </extension>
   <relatedItem type="isReferencedBy">
      <identifier type="uri">http://dx.doi.org/10.1175/JAS-D-13-027.1</identifier>
   </relatedItem>
   <identifier type="uri" displayLabel="Legacy citable URL">http://nldr.library.ucar.edu/repository/collections/OSGC-000-000-019-916</identifier>
   <identifier type="doi">10.1175/JAS-D-13-027.1</identifier>
   <accessCondition type="use and reproduction">Copyright 2013 American Meteorological Society (AMS). Permission to use figures, tables, and brief excerpts from this work in scientific and educational works is hereby granted provided that the source is acknowledged. Any use of material in this work that is determined to be "fair use" under Section 107 or that satisfies the conditions specified in Section 108 of the U.S. Copyright Law (17 USC, as revised by P.L. 94-553) does not require the Society's permission. Republication, systematic reproduction, posting in electronic form on servers, or other uses of this material, except as exempted by the above statements, requires written permission or license from the AMS. Additional details are provided in the AMS Copyright Policies, available from the AMS at 617-227-2425 or amspubs@ametsoc.org. Permission to place a copy of this work on this server has been provided by the AMS. The AMS does not guarantee that the copy provided here is an accurate copy of the published work.</accessCondition>
</mods>
