<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-cwt.2012.4" scope="system" system="cwt-lter" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 http://gce-lter.marsci.uga.edu/lter/files/schemas/eml-201/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><title>Population differentiation and biogeography of desmognathus monticola.</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Erin D.</givenName><surName>Casey</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Biological Sciences</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Eastern Illinois University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>600 Lincoln Avenue</deliveryPoint><city>Charleston</city><administrativeArea>Illinois</administrativeArea><postalCode>61920</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(217) 581-2112</phone><electronicMailAddress>erincasey13@hotmail.com</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://coweeta.ecology.uga.edu</onlineUrl></creator><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Mark E.</givenName><surName>Mort</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Biological Sciences</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Eastern Illinois University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>600 Lincoln Avenue</deliveryPoint><city>Charleston</city><administrativeArea>Illinois</administrativeArea><postalCode>61920</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(217) 581-2112</phone><electronicMailAddress>cfmem2@eiu.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://coweeta.ecology.uga.edu</onlineUrl></creator><abstract><para>Members of the Desmognathus complex have geographically isolated populations throughout their range and reproductive isolation between populations has been documented for most species. It is generally thought that geographic and the associated behavioral isolation has played a major role in the diversification of this genus (Tilley et al. 1978, Tilley et al. 1990). Desmognathus monticola does not appear to adhere to the typical pattern of geographic isolation observed elsewhere in the genus. The range of D. monticola has been proposed to extend between southern Pennsylvania and Georgia with a disjunct, state-endangered population recently reported in the Red Hills of Alabama (Conant and Collins 1991). The initial question presented is whether the entire range of D. monticola consists of disjunct, isolated populations, or if the Alabama population is unique in being isolated from a continuous northern range. To date, insufficient fieldwork has limited the documentation of the entire range of the species and it is possible that the Alabama population may not, in fact, be disjunct. If it is truly disjunct, then two hypotheses can be proposed. This population could be a recent derivative from the main range or an ancestral group that was isolated during the glaciation of the Appalachian Mountains. These hypotheses have not yet been tested. Establishment of a network of population relatedness will provide needed insights into this question. Additionally, D. monticola populations have no documented reproductive behavioral isolation between populations (Mabry pers. com). Lack of behavioral isolation in D. monticola as compared to its congeners may indicate that it is a recently derived species. To date, studies of Desmognathus have employed enzyme electrophoresis to examine genetic diversity, but little variation has been reported using isozyme data (Tilley et al. 1978). Similarly, our preliminary allozyme studies on D. monticola have revealed little genetic variation. Thus, a hypervariable DNA technique, such as Intersimple Sequence Repeats (ISSRs), is necessary to examine the genetic diversity within and among populations of this species. ISSR data are dominant/recessive markers that are scored as band present or absent (Gupta et al. 1994, Zietkiewicz et al. 1994). It is possible to construct a similarity matrix, examine the degree of differences both within and between populations, and establish a dendrogram of population relatedness (neighbor-joining and/or UPGMA tree).</para><para>Field sampling: I will locate D. monticola populations throughout the proposed range from Pennsylvania to Georgia. To determine if the Alabama population is truly disjunct, it will be necessary to search for other populations in suitable habitat between Alabama and the southern extent of its range. Topographic maps will be examined to find potential locations of D. monticola populations. For all populations located, I will collect a small amount of tail tissue (less than 10mg) from 20 individuals. Vouchers will be documented using a digital camera. To assist in subsequent population location, GPS coordinates will be recorded for each population. | DNA Extraction and Genetic Analyses: DNA will be extracted using the Promega Wizard Kit (Promega Corporation, Madison). ISSR reactions will be conducted in 25mL volumes using standard methods (Wolfe and Liston 1998). DNA will be electrophoresed on 1% agarose gels, stained using ethidium bromide, and bands will be viewed using ultraviolet light. All ISSR reactions will be replicated to test for the presence or absence of each band. Pictorial documentation of bands will be taken using Kodak EDAS Package, and scoring and sizing of bands will be conducted using Kodak 1D Image Analysis Software Package (Eastman Kodak Corporation, Rochester). Similarity matrices will be constructed and these data will be analyzed using NTSYS (Applied Biostatistics, Inc.) | Interpretation of population data: A network of relatedness between populations will be established based on ISSR analyses. If populations between the southern range of the species and the Alabama population are found, then a continuous range will be indicated and bands will be studied to determine polymorphism, and presence of band subsets. If the Alabama population is disjunct, then it will be possible to examine its position in the resulting dendrogram. A basal position may indicate it is ancestral. However, if it is clustered with the Appalachian populations, I will conclude it is a more recently derived population. In addition to cluster analyses, careful inspection of the ISSR bands lend insights into the origin of this population. For example, a shared subset of bands found in the Appalachian populations would indicate a recently derived population. A high proportion of unique bands may indicate a more ancestral population, as sufficient time has passed for the accumulation of mutations (Soltis and Bloom 1991).

Study_Sampling_Frequency: Samples will be taken over a period of approximately two weeks.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>Coweeta</keyword><keyword>LTER</keyword><keyword>Desmognathus monticola</keyword><keyword>Evolutionary Biology</keyword><keyword>ISSR</keyword><keyword>Genetics</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>Must adhere to the Coweeta LTER Data Policy (See http://coweeta.uga.edu/policies/data).</para></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://coweeta.uga.edu/summaries/Csummary2012_b.html</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Exact location is still unknown, but I will be collecting in and around Henson Creek, Shope Fork, and Coweeta creek</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate /><eastBoundingCoordinate /><northBoundingCoordinate /><southBoundingCoordinate /></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2001-05-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2002-05-01</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><positionName>Coweeta LTER Information Manager</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(828) 524-2128</phone></contact><project scope="document"><title>Coweeta Long Term Ecological Research</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Ted</givenName><surName>Gragson</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>tgragson@earthlink.net</electronicMailAddress><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>James</givenName><surName>Vose</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>jvose@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Brian</givenName><surName>Kloeppel</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>kloeppel@sparc.ecology.uga.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><abstract><para>The Coweeta LTER Research Program has evolved since 1980 from a site-based to a site- and region-based project examining the effects of disturbance

and environmental gradients on biogeochemical cycling, and the underlying

watershed ecosystem processes that regulate and respond to those cycles. 

The objective for the 2002-2008 research is to advance scientific

understanding of the spatial, temporal, and decision-making components of

land use and land-use change in the southern Appalachian Mountains over the

last 200 years, and forecast patterns into the future 30 years.  This will

be accomplished by addressing ecological and socioeconomic aspects of

land-use change while continuing long-term studies of environmental

gradients and natural disturbance regimes.  The result will be a more

complete understanding of ecological dynamics in the southern Appalachian

Mountains that makes possible the development of reasonable forecasts of

its future ecological state. | The guiding hypothesis for the proposed research is that the frequency, intensity, and extent of land use represents human decision-making in

response to socioeconomic and bio-geophysical conditions with consequences

that cascade through ecosystems.  The research activities are organized

into three initiatives: (1) Characterization of the Socio-Natural Template,

(2) Ecosystem Responses to the Socio-Natural Template, and (3) Forecasting

Ecosystem Responses to Changes in the Socio-Natural Template.  The

integrated scientific research will provide both a description as well as

an explanation of the underlying causes of land use and the consequences of

land-use change for southern Appalachian ecosystems and society.  It thus

recognizes the complexity of land use as a process and the research needs

as defined in the LTER Program and the broader scientific community.</para></abstract><funding><para>National Science Foundation. Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed in the material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation.</para></funding></project><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=cwt,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access></dataset></eml:eml>