<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-luq.102.1" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 C:/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><shortName>LUQMetadata102</shortName><title>Leaf miners (Acrocercops sp.)larvae performance on young leaves of Manilkara bidentata</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Maria del Pilar</givenName><surName>Angulo</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of Puerto Rico</organizationName><positionName>Graduate Student</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Biology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>PO Box 23360</deliveryPoint><city>R&#195;&#173;o Piedras</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00931</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(787)764-0000(3653)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(787)771-1481</phone><electronicMailAddress>manilkara1@hotmail.com</electronicMailAddress></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Maria del Pilar</givenName><surName>Angulo</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of Puerto Rico</organizationName><positionName>Graduate Student</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Biology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>PO Box 23360</deliveryPoint><city>R&#195;&#173;o Piedras</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00931</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(787)764-0000(3653)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(787)771-1481</phone><electronicMailAddress>manilkara1@hotmail.com</electronicMailAddress></metadataProvider><language>english</language><abstract><para><literalLayout>Manilkara bidentata is attacked by a specialist leaf miner(Acrocercops sp.(microlepidoptera:gracillariidae).  More than one larvae can be found per mine within a leaf. The purposes of this study is to determine the effect of group feeding for this species since larval density within a leaf vary from 1-14 larvae per mine (Angulo-Sandoval personal observation). This variation allows to determine the effect of larval density on the amount of leaf damage, larval survivorship and larval growth. Leaves with mines varied in area from 10 to 224 cm2 (mean = 85.7 cm2) and the number of larvae per leaf ranged from 1 to 14 (mean = 5.7 larvae/mine). There was no relation between the size of the leaf and the number of larvae found within the leaf.  There was a relationship between the number of larvae in a blotch mine and amount of damaged tissue. Herbivory increases from approximately 10% for one larva per leaf to 50% in leaves with eight larvae. In leaves with more than eight larvae, herbivory decreased . There was an effect of initial larval density on percent larval survivorship.Survivorship was high (70%) in leaves with one to three larvae. In intermediate density (4-8 larvae per mine) 50% of larvae survived and in high densities (9 - 14 larvae per mine), only 22% survived. Even though there was a decrease in larvae number in high densities, the final number of larvae remained higher, compared with low or intermediate densities. A linear relationship was found between number of larvae present in the leaf and the time it took the larvae to complete their larval stage. Larvae in high density (&amp;gt; 9 larvae per mine) tended to develop faster (3-8 days) than larvae in low densities (5 - 10 days). Larval size upon emergence ranged from 8 to 12 mm (mean= 9.27) but there was no effect of larval density on the final larval size. The total number of surviving larvae varied according to the initial larval number and was highest in mines with eight individuals of which on average 4.7 survived. The number of surviving larvae was less than three for all other clutch sizes. Even though eight larvae appears to be the optimum clutch size, most females produced smaller clutches (4- 6 larvae per leaf).All larvae that emerged built a cocoon and 90% emerged as butterflies.</literalLayout></para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>Acrocercops sp</keyword><keyword>Manilkara bidentata</keyword><keyword>disturbance</keyword><keyword>el verde</keyword><keyword>group behavior</keyword><keyword>herbivory</keyword><keyword>larvae density</keyword><keyword>DISTURBANCE</keyword><keyword>EL VERDE</keyword><keyword>HERBIVORY</keyword><keyword>PEER REVIEWED JOURNAL</keyword><keyword>TABONUCO</keyword><keyword>Population Dynamics</keyword><keyword>Disturbance Regime</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><title>ADEQUATE ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><para><literalLayout>The scientists, the LEF-LTER Program, and the                                     USDA International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITF) must                                     receive adequate acknowledgement for the use of data by other                                     scientists, and the LEF LTER program must receive two copies of                                     any publication using that data. One copy will be placed at the                                     IITF library and one copy will stay with the LEF LTER Data                                     Manager. A suggested format for this acknowledgement will be                                     distributed along with the requested data.</literalLayout></para><section><title>Acknowledgements for NSF Support.</title><para><literalLayout>The following paragraph should be                                         included in the acknowledgements of all publications funded                                         in any way by current and future LTER grants:</literalLayout><literalLayout>This research was performed under grant                                         #DEB-0218039 from the National Science Foundation to the                                         Institute of Tropical Ecosystem Studies (IEET), University                                         of Puerto Rico, and the International Institute of Tropical                                         Forestry (IITFR) as part of the Long-Term Ecological                                         Research Program in the Luquillo Experimental Forest.                                         Additional support was provided by the Forest Service (U.S.                                         Department of Agriculture) and the University of Puerto                                         Rico.</literalLayout></para></section></section></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb102/metadata/lterdb102.htm#DATA</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>The Luquillo Experimental Forest (LEF) covers                                 11,231 hectares and reaches 1079 m above sea level. It has a warm                                 and wet climate and includes a variety of tropical habitats and                                 forest types and streams, and a high diversity of plants and                                 animals. A key feature of these ecosystems is disturbance.                                 Hurricanes, landslides, and human disturbance have shaped the                                 forest, and research by LUQ has stimulated a new appreciation of the                                 significance of large-scale disturbances in tropical forested                                 ecosystems and the key role of plants and animals in shaping the                                 response to these events. Hurricanes occurring one and 10 years                                 after LUQ began in 1988 provided landscape-scale natural experiments                                 which are still followed closely.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-65.92</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-65.7</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>18.35</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>18.23</southBoundingCoordinate><boundingAltitudes><altitudeMinimum>20</altitudeMinimum><altitudeMaximum>1060</altitudeMaximum><altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits></boundingAltitudes></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Mitch</givenName><surName>Aide</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of Puerto Rico</organizationName><positionName>Professor</positionName><address scope="document"><city>R&#195;&#173;o Piedras</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00931-3360</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(603)862-2698</phone><electronicMailAddress>maide@upracd.upr.clu.edu</electronicMailAddress></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>Luquillo Experimental Forest LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>University of Puerto Rico, Rio Piedras</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>P. O. Box 21910</deliveryPoint><city>San Juan</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00931-1910</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(787) 764 - 0000 (ext. 4940)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(787) 772 -1481</phone><electronicMailAddress>nbrokaw@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://luq.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></publisher><methods><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Study area. The study was conducted in a 16 hectare plot, in the Luquillo Experimental Forest (LEF), within the Caribbean National Forest in northeastern Puerto Rico (180o 20' N, 65o 49' W)(Waide and Reagan 1996). The study area is near El Verde Research Station (350 m) on the northwest slope of the LEF. The forest is classified as subtropical wet forest and the dominant tree species are Dacryodes excelsa, Prestoea montana, Casearia arborea, Inga laurina, Manilkara bidentata, and Sloanea berteriana (Zimmerman et al. 1994). Average height of the forest canopy is 20 m with few emergent trees (Waide and Reagan 1996). Mean annual precipitation is 3460 mm (McDowell and Estrada-Pino 1988), and although January to April is the period of lowest precipitation, monthly means are usually greater than 100 mm /month (Brown et al. 1983) and evapotranspiration is lower than precipitation throughout the year (Waide and Reagan 1996). Mean monthly temperatures range between 21-25o C (Brown et al. 1983).</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep></methods><project scope="document"><title>Herbivory</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Maria del Pilar</givenName><surName>Angulo</surName></individualName><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><abstract><para><literalLayout>Long-term experiments associated with herbivory, a process which under certain circumstances may be an important regulator of detrital processing, has started at El Verde only since 2002. In addition to continuing long-term vegetation measurements will be conducted to determine long-term patterns of herbivory in two ways. As in most tropical forests, herbivores mainly eat young leaves (Coley &amp;amp; Barone 1996), which flush during May and June in the tabonuco forest or following disturbance (Angulo-Sandoval &amp;amp; Aide 2000). We will measure percent herbivory on new leaves of focal species marked each year in May and June. The second measurement will be of inputs of green leaf litter and insect frass to the forest floor. These measures will be used to gauge the changes in rates of herbivory during recovery from disturbance, with the ultimate goal of evaluating the role of herbivory in succession.  In addition, herbivory manipulations (autotroph-based food web) will be conducted within the main treatments of the Canopy Trimming Experiment. This experiment will employ small-scale mesocosms and removal of organisms to isolate the potential effects of food web components thought to influence ecosystem processes. Because of the intense maintenance requirements of these manipulations, they will be conducted for only two years.  "Canopy herbivory and soil processes in a temperate and tropical forest".  one to determine the importance of food availability on herbivory, leaf phenology and leaf damage; another to dermine the effect of group feeding for a specific species, and a last one to determine the effect of plant density on herbivory.</literalLayout></para></abstract><funding><para><literalLayout>LTER</literalLayout></para></funding></project><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=LUQ,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access></dataset></eml:eml>