<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.187.167478" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Pinon Juniper Net Primary Production Quadrat Data from the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico: 1999-2001</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Esteban</givenName>
      <surName>Muldavin</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>New Mexico Natural Heritage Program, Biology Department Castetter Hall 167, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>muldavin@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">9896</userId>
  </creator>
  <metadataProvider>
    <positionName>, </positionName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuqeurque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
  </metadataProvider>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Kristin</givenName>
      <surName>Vanderbilt</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, MSC03 2020, 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>vanderbi@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">11054</userId>
    <role>data manager</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <pubDate>2010</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>This three-year study at the Sevilleta LTER was designed to monitor net  primary production (NPP) across two distinct ecosystems: pinon/juniper  woodland (P) and juniper savannah woodland (J). Net primary production (NPP) is a fundamental ecological variable that measures rates of carbon consumption and fixation.  Estimates of NPP are important in understanding energy flow at a community level as well as spatial and temporal responses of the community to a wide range of ecological processes. While measures of both below- and above-ground biomass are important in estimating NPP, this study focused on estimating above-ground biomass production (ANPP).To measure ANPP (i.e., the change in plant biomass,   represented by  stems, flowers, fruit and foliage, over time), the   vegetation  variables in this dataset, including species  composition and   the  cover and height of individuals, were sampled twice  yearly (spring   and  fall) at permanent 1m x 1m plots. The data from these plots was  used   to  build regressions correlating biomass and volume  via weights  of   select harvested species obtained in SEV157, "Net Primary   Productivity   (NPP) Weight Data." In addition, volumetric measurements were obtained from permanent plots to build regressions correlating biomass and volume.Spring measurements were  taken in April or May  when shrubs  and  spring annuals reached peak  biomass. Fall  measurements were  taken  in either September or October  when summer  annuals reached  peak  biomass but prior to killing frosts.  Winter  measurements were taken  in  February before the onset of  spring growth.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>primary production</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>community patterns</keyword>
    <keyword>plant communities</keyword>
    <keyword>plant ecology</keyword>
    <keyword>vegetation dynamics</keyword>
    <keyword>plant species composition</keyword>
    <keyword>species richness</keyword>
    <keyword>plant cover</keyword>
    <keyword>net primary productivity</keyword>
    <keyword>annual net primary production</keyword>
    <keyword>plant biomass</keyword>
    <keyword>aboveground biomass</keyword>
    <keyword>population and community properties</keyword>
    <keyword>seasonality</keyword>
    <keyword>permanent plots</keyword>
    <keyword>plant growth</keyword>
    <keyword>aboveground production</keyword>
    <keyword>harvesting</keyword>
    <keyword>deserts</keyword>
    <keyword>forests</keyword>
    <keyword>plants</keyword>
    <keyword>foliage</keyword>
    <keyword>grasses</keyword>
    <keyword>herbs</keyword>
    <keyword>forbs</keyword>
    <keyword>shrubs</keyword>
    <keyword>vegetation</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>Employee History:Mike Friggens: 1999 to September 2001, Karen Wetherill: February 7, 2000 to August 2009, Terri Koontz: February 2000 to August 2003  and August 2006 to August 2010, Shana Penington: February 2000 to August 2000, Heather Simpson: August 2000 to August 2002, Chris Roberts: September 2001 to August 2002.</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/2485</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Cerro Montosa Pinyon-Juniper site has been the location of major Sevilleta LTER research since 1989. Meteorological trends, net primary productivity, rodent and ground-dwelling arthropod populations, mycorrhizal responses to fertilizer, pinyon-juniper fruit and nut production, and pinyon mortality are all being investigated at this site. Previous studies have included analyses of pinyon tree rings for regional climate reconstruction.Vegetation: The vegetation is New Mexico Pinyon-Juniper Woodland, dominated by Colorado pinyon (Pinus edulis) and one-seed juniper (Juniperus monosperma), and accompanied by gray oak (Quercus grisea).  There is a diverse shrub component, including scrub live oak (Q. turbinella), mountain mahogany (Cercocarpus montanus), broom snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae), sacahuista (Nolina microcarpa), red barberry (Mahonia haematocarpa), Apache plume (Fallugia paradoxa), tree cholla (Opuntia imbricata), skunkbush (Rhus trilobata), and banana yucca (Yucca baccata).  Grass diversity is also high, and open spaces between trees are dominated by blue grama (Bouteloua gracilis), with hairy and sideoats grama (B. hirsuta and B. curtipendula) and black grama (B. eriopoda) also being significant. Other common grasses include purple threeawn (Aristida purpurea), wolftail (Lycurus phleoides), mountain and ring muhly (M. montanus and M. torreyi), and New Mexican porcupinegrass (Heterostipa neomexicana). Common forbs include small-flowered milkvetch (Astragalus nuttallianus), white sagebrush (Artemesia ludoviciana), Fendler&#8217;s arabis (Arabis fendleri), Fendler&#8217;s sandmat (Chamaesyce fendleri), New Mexico thistle (Cirsium neomexicanum), false pennyroyal (Hedeoma oblongifolia), bastard sage (Eriogonum wrightii), ping&#252;e rubberweed (Hymenoxys richardsonii), large four o&#8217;clock (Mirabilis multiflora), Fendler's penstemon (Penstemon fendleri), and globemallows (Sphaeralcea hastulata and S. wrightii). , </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.368</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.368</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1976</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1976</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>1999-02-01</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2001-10-01</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <maintenance>
    <description>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>January 7, 2008  KRW Data from the P and J sites from 1999 to 2002 were extracted from the  ongoing npp database and put in its own table in navicat.  Palmtop/pj_npp. NPP data from 1999-2001  was QAQC'd in MySQL. I checked for duplicates and missing quads.  These most often happened when a  recorder mislabeled a particular quad.  I also checked every plant code against the USDA Plants  database online at http://plants.usda.gov/.  All plant codes that have had nomenclature changes  were updated.  All previously unknown plants that have since been identified were also updated.   All unknown plants that will never be identified were left in the database.  All types were  corrected.  A list of codes not in the USDA list are that are still in the data are as follows NONE  = no plants in quad, and UKFO57 = unknowns that will never be identified, UKFO80 = unknown that has  not yet been identified. A list of the updates and the reason for the change are in the table  below along with comments where identifications were questionable.</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </description>
  </maintenance>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Douglas I.</givenName>
      <surName>Moore</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Sevilleta LTER, 167 Castetter Hall, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>dmoore@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">9661</userId>
  </contact>
  <publisher>
    <positionName>, </positionName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque, NM  </city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
  </publisher>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Collecting the Data: Vegetation data is collected on a palm top computer. Excel   spreadsheets are used for data entry and file names should  begin with   the overall study (npp), followed by the date (mm.dd.yy) and  the   initials of the recorder (.abc). Finally, the site abbreviation  should   be added (i.e., c, g, b, p). The final format should be as  follows:   npp.mm.dd.yy.abcg.xls. File names should be in lowercase. A 1-m2 PVC-frame  is placed over the fiberglass stakes that mark the   diagonal corners of  each quadrat. When measuring cover it is important   to stay centered over  the vegetation in the quadrat to prevent errors   caused by angle of view  (parallax). Each PVC-frame is divided into  100  squares with nylon  string. The dimensions of each square are 10cm x   10cm and represent 1  percent of the total area. The cover (area) and height of each individual live (green)    vegetative unit that falls within the one square meter quadrat is    measured. A vegetative unit consists of an individual size class (as    defined by a unique cover and height) of a particular species within a    quadrat. Cover is quantified by counting the number of 10cm x 10cm    squares filled by each vegetative unit. Niners and plexidecs are additional tools that help accurately    determine the cover a vegetative unit. A niner is a small, hand-held PVC    frame that can be used to measure canopies. Like the larger PVC frame    it is divided into 10cm x 10cm squares, each square representing 1%  of   the total cover.  However, there are only nine squares within the   frame,  hence the name &#8220;niner.&#8221; A plexidec can help determine the cover   of  vegetative units with covers less than 1%. Plexidecs are clear   plastic  squares that are held above vegetation.  Each plexidec   represents a  cover of 0.5% and has smaller dimensions etched onto the   surface that  correspond to 0.01%, 0.05%, 0.1%, and 0.25% cover. It is extremely important that cover and height measurements remain    consistent over time to ensure that regressions based on this data    remain valid. Field crew members should calibrate with each other to    ensure that observer bias does not influence data collection. Cover Measurements: Grasses-To determine the cover of a grass clump,    envision a perimeter around the central mass or densest portion of the    plant, excluding individual long leaves, wispy ends, or more open upper    regions of the plant. Live foliage is frequently mixed with dead   foliage  in grass clumps and this must be kept in mind during   measurement as our  goal is to measure only plant biomass for the   current season. In  general, recently dead foliage is yellow and dead   foliage is gray.  Within reason, try to include only yellow or green   portions of the plant  in cover measurement while excluding portions of   the plant that are  gray. This is particularly important for   measurements made in the winter  when there is little or no green   foliage present. In winter, sometimes  measurements will be based mainly   on yellow foliage. Stoloniferous stems  of grasses that are not rooted   should be ignored. If a stem is rooted  it should be recorded as a   separate observation from the parent plant. Forbs-The cover of forbs is measured as the    perimeter of the densest portion of the plant. If the forb is an annual    it is acceptable to include the inflorescence in this measurement. If    the forb is a perennial, do not include the inflorescence as part of  the   cover measurement. Measure all foliage that was produced during  the   current season, including any recently dead (yellow) foliage.  Avoid   measuring gray foliage that died in a previous season. Cacti-For cacti that consist of a series of pads or jointed stems (Opuntia phaecantha, Opuntia imbricata)    measure the length and width of each pad to the nearest cm instead of cover and    height. Cacti that occur as a dense ball/clump of stems (Opuntia leptocaulis) are measured using the same protocol as shrubs. Pincushion or hedgehog cacti (Escobaria vivipara, Schlerocactus intertextus, Echinocereus fendleri) that occur as single (or clustered) cylindrical stems are measured as a single cover. Yuccas-Make separate observations for the leaves and    caudex (thick basal stem). Break the observations into sections of    leaves that are approximately the same height and record the cover as    the perimeter around this group of leaf blades. The caudex is measured    as a single cover. The thick leaves of yuccas make it difficult to make  a   cover measurement by centering yourself over the caudex of the  plant.   The cover of the caudex may be estimated by holding a niner  next to it   or using a tape measure to measure to approximate the area. Height Measurements: Height is recorded as a whole number in centimeters. All heights are    vertical heights but they are not necessarily perpendicular to the    ground if the ground is sloping. Annual grasses and all forbs-Measure the height from    the base of the plant to the top of the inflorescence (if present).    Otherwise, measure to the top of the green foliage. Perennial grasses-Measure the height from the base    of the plant to the top of the live green foliage. Do not include the    inflorescence in the height measurement. The presence of live green    foliage may be difficult to see in the winter. Check carefully at the    base of the plant for the presence of green foliage. If none is found it    may be necessary to pull the leaf sheaths off of several plants   outside  the quadrat. From this you may be able to make some   observations about  where green foliage is likely to occur. Perennial shrub and sub-shrubs-Measure the height    from the base of the green foliage to the top of the green foliage,    ignoring all bare stems. Do not measure to the ground unless the foliage    reaches the ground. Plants rooted outside but hanging into a quadrat-Do not measure the height from the ground. Measure only the height of the portion of the plant that is within the quadrat. Foliage canopy cover: Cover and height are recorded for all separate vegetative units that   fall within an infinite vertical column that is defined by the inside   edge of the PVC-frame.  A vegetative unit consists of an individual   species with a unique cover and height. This includes vegetation that is   rooted outside of the frame but has foliage that extends into the   vertical column defined by the PVC-frame. As mentioned above, cover is quantified by counting the number or   fraction of 10 cm x 10 cm squares intercepted by each vegetative unit.   It is possible to obtain a total percent cover greater than 100 for a   quadrat because vegetative units often overlap (especially in shrubs and   succulents).  For perennial plants, cover is based only on the   vegetative portion of the plant (stem and leaf).  For annual plants,   cover is based on both vegetative and reproductive (inflorescence)   portions of the plant. If the cover of a vegetative unit is less than 1, the increments used   are as follows: 0.01, 0.05, 0.1, 0.25, 0.5, and 0.75.  If cover is   between 1 and 5, increments of 0.5 are used and, if greater than 5,   increments of 1 are used.&#160; Finally, if the cover is greater than 15, the   total canopy cover is divided into smaller units and the cover and   heights of each observation measured separately.  This reduces the size   of harvest samples.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
  </methods>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>sev187_pjnppquadrat_04122010.txt</entityName>
    <entityDescription>ANPP quadrat data for the years 1999-2001.</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>sev187_pjnppquadrat_04122010.txt</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url>http://sev.lternet.edu/sites/default/files/data/sev-187/sev187_pjnppquadrat_04122010.txt</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1999-02-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2001-10-01</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>year</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>year</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The year in which data was collected.  </attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>season</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>season</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The season in which data was collected.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1 </code>
                  <definition> winter</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>2 </code>
                  <definition> spring</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3 </code>
                  <definition> fall</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>site</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>site</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The site at which data was collected.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>P </code>
                  <definition> pinon-juniper site</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>web</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>web</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The number of the web being sampled, which can range from 1-5 depending on site and project.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The number of the web being sampled, which can range from 1-5 depending on site and project.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>plot</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>plot</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The plot at which data was collected.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The plot at which data was collected.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>quad</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>quad</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The quadrat at which data was collected.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The quadrat at which data was collected.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>species</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>species</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The Kartez code for a plant species as designated by the USDA Plants Database. </attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The Kartez code for a plant species as designated by the USDA Plants Database. </definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>obs</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>obs</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The sequential number given to a specific vegetative unit within a quadrat.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The sequential number given to a specific vegetative unit within a quadrat.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>cover</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>cover</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The percent cover of an observation (or vegetative unit) for a given species.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0.01</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">100</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>height</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>height</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The height of an observation (or vegetative unit) for a given species.  For grasses, this is the average height of green foliage.  For herbs, it includes the inflorescence, if applicable.  </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>count</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>count</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The number of records within a vegetative unit for a given species.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The number of records within a vegetative unit for a given species.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>comments</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>comments</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>A special statement related to an observation.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>na </code>
                  <definition> not applicable</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>phen</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>phen</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The reproductive condition of a plant.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>V</code>
                  <definition>Vegetative only</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>F</code>
                  <definition>Reproductive (budding, flowering, or fruiting)</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
    <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
<ns2:unit abbreviation="" id="percentage" name="percentage" unitType=""><ns2:description /></ns2:unit>

    </ns2:unitList>
  </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>