<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-nwt.34.8" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1    http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.1/eml.xsd">
	<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
		<allow>
			<principal>uid=NWT,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
			<permission>all</permission>
		</allow>
		<allow>
			<principal>public</principal>
			<permission>read</permission>
		</allow>
	</access>
<dataset scope="document">
	<title>Snow depth data for saddle snowfence, 1992 - ongoing.</title>
	<creator>
		<individualName>
			<salutation>Dr.</salutation>
			<givenName>Donald (Skip)</givenName>
			<surName>Walker</surName>
		</individualName>
		<address>
	<deliveryPoint>Institute of Arctic Biology</deliveryPoint>
	<deliveryPoint>University of Alaska Fairbanks</deliveryPoint>
	<deliveryPoint>311 Irving</deliveryPoint>
	<deliveryPoint>PO Box 757000</deliveryPoint>
	<city>Fairbanks</city>
	<administrativeArea>Alaska</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99775-6780</postalCode>
	<country>UNITED STATES</country>
</address>
		<phone phonetype="business">(907)474-2460</phone>
	</creator>
	<metadataProvider>
		<organizationName>Niwot Ridge LTER</organizationName>
		<positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
		<address>
		<deliveryPoint>INSTAAR, University of Colorado</deliveryPoint>
		<deliveryPoint>1560 30th Street</deliveryPoint>
		<deliveryPoint>UCB 450</deliveryPoint>
		<city>Boulder</city>
		<administrativeArea>CO</administrativeArea>
		<postalCode>80309-0450</postalCode>
		<country>USA</country>
	</address>
		<phone phonetype="voice">303-492-2594</phone> 
		<electronicMailAddress>lternwt@colorado.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		<onlineUrl>http://niwot.colorado.edu/</onlineUrl>
	</metadataProvider>
	<associatedParty id="12010" scope="system" system="FLS"> 
		<individualName>
			<givenName>Hope</givenName>
			<surName>Humphries</surName> 
		</individualName> 
		<address>
		<deliveryPoint>INSTAAR, University of Colorado</deliveryPoint> 
		<deliveryPoint>1560 30th Street</deliveryPoint> 
		<deliveryPoint>UCB 450</deliveryPoint> 
		<city>Boulder</city> 
		<administrativeArea>CO</administrativeArea> 
		<postalCode>80309-0450</postalCode>
	</address> 
		<phone phonetype="voice">(303) 492-2594</phone> 
		<electronicMailAddress>hope.humphries@colorado.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		<role>Data Contact</role> 
	</associatedParty>
	<associatedParty id="12020" scope="system" system="FLS"> 
		<organizationName>Niwot Ridge LTER</organizationName>
		<positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
		<address>
		<deliveryPoint>INSTAAR, University of Colorado</deliveryPoint>
		<deliveryPoint>1560 30th Street</deliveryPoint>
		<deliveryPoint>UCB 450</deliveryPoint>
		<city>Boulder</city>
		<administrativeArea>CO</administrativeArea>
		<postalCode>80309-0450</postalCode>
		<country>USA</country>
	</address>
		<phone phonetype="voice">303-492-2594</phone> 
		<electronicMailAddress>lternwt@colorado.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		<onlineUrl>http://niwot.colorado.edu/</onlineUrl>
		<role>Data Contact</role> 
	</associatedParty>
<pubDate>1993</pubDate>
<abstract>
<para>
	A snowfence was built in 1993 on the Niwot Ridge Saddle grid 
	to determine the effects of changes in snowpack on a number of variables. The 
	study area was 60m x 125m. Snow depths were measured at each of 147 points 
	within the snowfence experiment area and at 6 control locations outside of but 
	near the snowfence experiment area. Of the 147 points, 84 were located on the 
	leeward (east) side of the snowfence, 56 were located on the windward (west)
	side of the snowfence, and 7 were located along the snowfence itself. These 
	measurements were made weekly to biweekly. Sampling locations were each 
	given a unique point indentification number in order that these data could 
	be incorporated into the Saddle GIS. The snowfence was oriented in a 
	north/south direction and was 60 m long. Each of the point identification 
	numbers had a coordinate within the experiment area. The first number of 
	the coordinate was the distance in m from the snowfence in an east/west 
	direction, negative numbers being west of the snowfence and positive 
	numbers being east of the fence. The second number in the coordinate 
	was the distance in m from the southern terminus of the snowfence in 
	a northerly direction. Point identification numbers and coordinates for 
	the windward drift were: 200 (-40,0), 201 (-40,10), 202 (-40,20), 
	203 (-40,30), 204 (-40,40), 205 (-40,50), 206 (-40,60), 207 (-35,0), 
	208 (-35,10), 209 (-35,20), 210 (-35,30), 211 (-35,40), 212 (-35,50), 
	213 (-35,60), 214 (-30,0), 215 (-30,10), 216 (-30,20), 217 (-30,30), 
	218 (-30,40), 219 (-30,50), 220 (-30,60), 221 (-25,0), 222 (-25,10), 
	223 (-25,20), 224 (-25,30), 225 (-25,40), 226 (-25,50), 227 (-25,60), 
	228 (-20,0), 229 (-20,10), 230 (-20,20), 231 (-20,30), 232 (-20,40), 
	233 (-20,50), 234 (-20,60), 235 (-15,0), 236 (-15,10), 237 (-15,20), 
	238 (-15,30), 239 (-15,40), 240 (-15,50), 241 (-15,60), 242 (-10,0), 
	243 (-10,10), 244 (-10,20), 245 (-10,30), 246 (-10,40), 247 (-10,50), 
	248 (-10,60), 249 (-5,0), 250 (-5,10), 251 (-5,20), 252 (-5,30), 
	253 (-5,40), 254 (-5,50), 255 (-5,60). Point identification numbers 
	and coordinates for the leeward drift were: 256 (5,0), 257 (5,10), 
	258 (5,20), 259 (5,30), 260 (5,40), 261 (5,50), 262 (5,60), 263 (10,0), 
	264 (10,10), 265 (10,20), 266 (10,30), 267 (10,40), 268 (10,50), 
	269 (10,60), 270 (15,0), 271 (15,10), 272 (15,20), 273 (15,30), 
	274 (15,40), 275 (15,50), 276 (15,60), 278 (20,0), 279 (20,10),
	280 (20,20), 281 (20,30), 282 (20,40), 283 (20,50), 284 (20,60), 
	285 (25,0), 286 (25,10), 287 (25,20), 288 (25,30), 289 (25,40), 
	290 (25,50), 291 (25,60), 292 (30,0), 293 (30,10), 294 (30,20), 
	295 (30,30), 296 (30,40), 297 (30,50), 298 (30,60), 299 (35,60), 
	300 (35,10), 301 (35,20), 302 (35,30), 303 (35,40), 304 (35,50), 
	305 (35,0), 306 (40,0), 307 (40,10), 308 (40,20), 309 (40,30), 
	310 (40,40), 311 (40,50), 312 (40,60), 313 (45,0), 314 (45,10), 
	315 (45,20), 316 (45,30), 317 (45,40), 318 (45,50), 319 (45,60), 
	320 (50,0), 321 (50,10), 322 (50,20), 323 (50,30), 324 (50,40), 
	325 (50,50), 326 (50,60), 327 (55,0), 328 (55,10), 329 (55,20), 
	330 (55,30), 331 (55,40), 332 (55,50), 333 (55,60), 334 (60,0), 
	335 (60,10), 336 (60,20), 337 (60,30), 338 (60,40), 339 (60,50), 
	340 (60,60). Point identification numbers and coordinates for
	the points directly along the fence were: 341 (0,0), 342 (0,10), 
	343 (0,20), 344 (0,30), 345 (0,40), 346 (0,50), 346 (0,60). Point 
	identification numbers and locations for the control points were: 
	113 (approximately 10 m south of the -30,0 coordinate) in the 
	Acomastylidetum rossii vegetation association, 114 (approximately 
	11 m south of the -25,0 coordinate) in the Acomastylidetum rossii 
	vegetation association, 115 (approximately 8 m south of the 55,0
	coordinate) in the Kobresietum myosuroidis vegetation association, 
	116 (approximately 5 m north of the 50,60 coordinate) in the Kobresietum 
	myosuroidis vegetation association, 117 (approximately 3 m north of the 
	-23,60 coordinate) in the Rhodiolo integrifoliae vegetation association, 
	118 (approximately 5 m north of the -21,60 coordinate) in the Rhodiolo 
	integrifoliae vegetation association. Control points are indicated by a
	'C' in column 2.</para>
	<para>NOTE: This LTER data portal display does not contain important maintenance/log information. 
		Please be sure to view the EML file (a text file that contains XML tags) which is included in 
		the zip archive (click on "Download zip archive") for legacy maintenance/log information 
		pertaining to each dataset. The EML file name will have the following format:
		knb-lter-nwt.[3 digit dataset number].[version number].xml. Most web browsers can 
		parse the EML so it's easier to read. Scroll down to the "maintenance" tag.</para>
</abstract>
<keywordSet>
	<keyword>snow depth</keyword>
	<keyword>snow pack</keyword>
	<keyword>snow accumulation</keyword>
	<keyword>windward drift</keyword>
	<keyword>leeward drift</keyword>
	<keyword>control plot</keyword>
	<keyword>altered snow regime</keyword>
	<keyword>snowfence</keyword>
	<keyword>saddle grid</keyword>
	<keyword>climatology</keyword>
	<keyword>meteorology</keyword>
	<keyword>hydrology</keyword>
	<keyword>snow effects</keyword>
	<keyword>disturbance</keyword>
	<keyword>Niwot Ridge LTER</keyword>
	<keyword>NWT</keyword>
</keywordSet>
	<intellectualRights>
		<section>
			<title>Niwot LTER Data Policy</title>
			<para> The following acknowledgment should accompany any publication or 
				citation of these data: <itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para> Logistical support and/or data were provided by the 
							NSF-supported Niwot Ridge (NWT) Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) 
							project and the University of Colorado (CU) Mountain Research Station (MRS). </para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para> The user of NWT LTER data agrees to provide proper 
							acknowledgment with each usage of the data. Citation of 
							the name(s) of the investigator(s) responsible for the 
							data set, in addition to the generic statement above, 
							constitutes proper acknowledgment. Author(s) (including NWT investigators) 
							of published material that makes use of previously unpublished 
							NWT data agree to provide the NWT data manager with a PDF of 
							that material as soon as it becomes available. The user of NWT 
							data agrees not to resell or redistribute shared data.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Disclaimer</title>
			<para> The NSF-supported NWT LTER project shall not be held liable for 
				improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained 
				herein, nor assumes liability for misuse, manipulation or distribution 
				of the data. These data  
				are not legal documents and are not intended to be used as such. 
				The information contained in these data is dynamic and may change 
				over time. The user of these data should be aware that, 
				while efforts have been taken to ensure that these data are of the 
				highest quality, there is no guarantee of perfection for the data 
				contained herein and the possibility of errors exists. It is the 
				responsibility of the data user to use the data appropriately and 
				in a manner consistent with the limitations of data in 
				general and these data in particular. Users assume responsibility 
				to determine the usability of the dataset. NWT LTER gives no warranty, expressed or implied, as to 
				the accuracy, reliability, or completeness of these data. It is 
				strongly recommended that these data be directly acquired from 
				the NWT LTER server and not indirectly through other sources 
				that may have changed the data in some way. Although these data 
				have been processed successfully on computer systems at CU, no 
				warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the utility of 
				the data on other systems for general or scientific purposes, 
				nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. 
				This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and 
				aggregate use with other data.  </para>
		</section>
	</intellectualRights>
<distribution scope="document">
	<online>
		<url function="download">http://niwot.colorado.edu/data_csvs/snfcsnow.dw.data.csv</url>
	</online>
</distribution>
<coverage scope="document">
<temporalCoverage scope="document">
<rangeOfDates>
<beginDate>
<calendarDate>1992-10-30</calendarDate>
</beginDate>
<endDate>
<calendarDate>2012-11-27</calendarDate>
</endDate>
</rangeOfDates>
</temporalCoverage>
<geographicCoverage scope="document">
	<geographicDescription>The southern terminus of the 60-m fence is to be 25 m west of
		Saddle grid stake #28 and 25 m east of Saddle grid stake #27; the snowfence
		study area thus included or touched Saddle grid stakes #27, 28, 29, 37, 38, 
		and 39. Original data are stored in Research Laboratory #3.
	</geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates>
<westBoundingCoordinate>-105.643  </westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>-105.3753 </eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>40.0615   </northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>39.9932   </southBoundingCoordinate>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
</coverage>
<maintenance>
<description>
<para>
	The documentation for this file was created by Susan Kindig in May of 1993,
	with additional information being supplied by Rick Ingersoll and Brad
	Lewis. Data for 30 October 1992 to 7 May 1993 were added to the data
	section at this time and the file was placed under sccs control.
	[RCI 2 June 1993] Data for 29 May 1993 were appended on 2 June 1993.
	[RCI 2 June 1993] All data beginning 30 October 1992 were double-
	entered using EasyEntry programs (see "The Management of NWT LTER Data
	on the PC") and then processed on a Sun SPARC 2 (see "The Management of
	NWT LTER Data on culter").[RCI 14 June 1993] Data for 22 June 1993 
	were appended to the data section on 29 June 1993.[RCI 29 June 1993]
	Data for 2 and 19 July 1993 were appended to the data section on 
	23 July 1993.[RCI 23 July 1993] Data for 30 July 1993 were appended to the
	data section on 27 August 1993.[RCI 27 August 1993] Data for 2 
	November 1993 were appended to the data section on 4 November 1993.
	[RCI 4 November 1993] Data for 20 November 1993 were appended to the 
	data section on 23 November 1993.[RCI 23 November 1993] Data for 11
	December 1993 were appended to the data section on 14 December 1993.
	[RCI 14 December 1993] Data for 30 December 1993 were appended to the
	data section on 7 January 1994.[RCI 7 January 1994] Data for 15 January
	1994 were appended to the data section on 28 January 1994.[RCI 28
	January 1994] Data for 3 and 4 February 1994 were appended to the
	data section on 8 February 1994.[RCI 8 February 1994] Data for 26
	February and 17 March 1994 were appended to the data section on
	5 April 1994.[RCI 5 April 1994] Data for 18 April 1994 were appended
	to the data section on 29 April 1994.[RCI 29 April 1994] The snow
	depth for point identification number 263 on 2 November 1993 was changed
	from 290 cm to 115 cm (because the original measurement had been in cm
	but had been thought to be in inches) on 16 May 1994.[RCI 16 May 1994]
	Data for 9 April 1994 were inserted into the data section on 18 May
	1994.[RCI 18 May 1994] Data for 2 June 1994 were appended to the 
	data section on 7 June 1994.[RCI 7 June 1994] The locations of the
	point identification codes 117 and 118 were transposed as originally
	provided. This error was pointed out by Brad Lewis on 24 August 1994
	and the location codes in the comments section were corrected on that
	date.[RCI 24 August 1994] Data for 25 August 1994 were appended to
	the data section on 26 August 1994.[RCI 26 August 1994] Data for
	14 May 1994 were inserted into the data section on 1 September 1994.
	[RCI 1 September 1994] Data for 27 October 1994 were appended to the
	data section on 7 November 1994.[RCI 7 November 1994] Data for 4
	November 1994 were appended to the data section on 10 November 1994.
	[RCI 10 November 1994] Data for 11 and 17 1994 November were appended 
	to the data section on 29 November 1994.[RCI 29 November 1994] 
	Data for 30 November and 7 December 1994 were appended to the data
	section on 14 December 1994.[RCI 14 December 1994] Data for 15 December
	1994 were appended to the data section on 19 December 1994.[RCI 19
	December 1994] Data for 21 December 1994 were appended to the data
	section on 4 January 1995.[RCI 4 January 1995] Data for 30 December 
	1994 were appended to the data section on 17 January 1995.[RCI 17
	January 1995] Data for 5 and 13 January 1995 were appended to the
	data section on 20 January 1995.[RCI 20 January 1995] Data for 19 
	January 1995 were appended to the data section on 23 January 1995.
	[RCI 23 January 1995] Data for 26 January and 3 February 1995 were
	appended to the data section on 8 February 1995.[RCI 8 February
	1995] Data for 16 February 1995 were appended to the data section on
	27 February 1995.[RCI 27 February 1995] Data for 23 February 1995
	were appended to the data section on 1 March 1995.[RCI 1 March 1995]
	Data for 2 and 9 March 1995 were appended to the data section on 13 
	March 1995.[13 March 1995] Data for 23 March 1995 were appended to
	the data section on 4 April 1995.[RCI 4 April 1995] Data for 30 March
	1995 were appended to the data section on 6 April 1995.[RCI 6 April 
	1995] Data for 17 April 1995 were appended to the data section on 25 
	April 1995.[RCI 25 April 1995] Data for 28 April 1995 were appended 
	to the data section on 5 May 1995.[RCI 28 April 1995] Data for 12
	May 1995 were appended to the data section on 17 May 1995.[RCI 17 May
	1995] Data for 19 May 1995 were appended to the data section on 23
	May 1995.[RCI 23 May 1995] Data for 2 June 1995 were appended to the
	data section on 6 June 1995.[RCI 6 June 1995] Data for 5 June 1995
	were appended to the data section on 7 June 1995.[RCI 7 June 1995]
	Data for 12 June 1995 were appended to the data section on 15 June
	1995.[RCI 15 June 1995] Data for 15 and 23 June 1995 were appended
	to the data section on 3 July 1995.[RCI 3 July 1995] Data for 30
	June 1995 were appended to the data section on 7 July 1995.[RCI 7
	July 1995] Data for 7, 11, and 17 July 1995 were appended to the
	data section on 19 July 1995.[RCI 19 July 1995] Data for 26 July
	1995 were appended to the data section on 9 August 1995.[MAH 9
	August 1995] A comment from the 26 July 1995 hard copy data form
	was added to the comments section on 10 August 1995.[MAH 10 August
	1995] Data for 24 July and 22 August 1995 were appended to the
	data section on 1 September 1995.[MAH 1 September 1995] Data for
	14 September 1995 and 01 October 1995 were appended to the data 
	section on 20 October 1995.[MAH 20 October 1995] Data for 29 December
	1995, and for 10 and 17 January 1996 were appended to the data
	section, and the missing value indicator listed in the header section
	for column 3 was changed to 999 on 23 January 1996.[MAH 23 January
	1996] Data for 21 January 1996 were appended to the data section
	on 8 February 1996.[MAH 8 February 1996] Data for 21 February 1996
	were appended to the data section on 5 March 1996.[MAH 5 March 1996]
	Data for 28 February 1996 were appended to the data section on 13
	March 1996.[MAH 13 March 1996] Data for 13 March 1996 were appended
	to the data section on 20 March 1996.[MAH 20 March 1996] The references
	to Walker et al. (1994) and Brooks et al. (1995) were added to the 
	citations section on 2 May 1996.[MAH 2 May 1996] Comments regarding
	routine measurements along the snowfence were added to the abstract
	and comment sections, and data for 27 March 1996 and 3 April 1996
	were appended to the data section on 9 May 1996. Also, it was discovered
	by data management personnel that all records for coordinates -15,40 
	were incorrectly listed with the point identification number of 238
	instead of 239. A script to correct the error was run on the data, and the 
	corrected data were used to replace the erroneous data on 9 May 1996.[MAH
	9 May 1996] Data for 7 and 22 May 1996 were appended to the data section
	on 29 May 1996.[MAH 29 May 1996] Data for 7 and 14 June 1996 were appended
	to the data section on 2 July 1996.[MAH 2 July 1996] Data for 3 and 10
	July were appended to the data section on 22 July 1996.[MAH 22 July 1996]
	Data for 26 June 1996 were inserted to the data section, and data for
	16, 24, and 30 July 1996 were appended to the data section on 18 October
	1996.[MAH 18 October 1996] Data for 3 and 18 October 1996 were appended 
	to the data section on 12 November 1996.[MAH 12 November 1996] Data for
	28 October 1996 were appended to the data section on 20 November 1996.[MAH
	20 November 1996] Data for 21 November 1996 were appended to the data section
	on 16 December 1996.[MAH 16 December 1996] Data for 28 January 1996, 14
	February 1996, 11 and 30 December 1996, 16 and 23 January 1997, and 5
	February 1997 were inserted and/or appended to the data section on 13 
	February 1997.[MAH 13 February 1997] Data for 13 February 1997 were appended
	to the data section on 24 February 1997.[MAH 24 February 1997] Data for 7 
	March 1997 were appended to the data section on 26 March 1997.[MAH 26 March 
	1997] Data for 29 April 1997 were appended to the data section on 7 May
	1997.[MAH 7 May 1997] Data for 12 May 1997 were appended to the data section
	on 9 June 1997.[MAH 9 June 1997] Data for 21 May 1997 were appended to the
	data section on 26 June 1997.[MAH 26 June 1997] Data for 26 June 1997 were
	appended to the data section on 12 September 1997.[MAH 12 September 1997]
	Data for 29 October 1997 were appended to the data section on 26 November
	1997.[MAH 26 November1997] Data for 29 October 1997, 10 and 25 November 1997, 
	4 December 1997, and 2 January 1998 were appended to the data section on 14 
	January 1998.[MAH 14 January 1998] Data for 21 March, 5 April, 29 May, 9 and
	19 June, 7 July, and 19 December 1997, and 9 January 1998 were inserted into
	the data section on 17 February 1998.[MAH 17 February 1998] Data for 17 March
	1998 were appended to the data section on 7 April 1998.[MAH 7 April 1998] Data
	for 9 April 1998 were appended to the data section on 12 June 1998.[MAH 12
	June 1998] Data for 18 and 27 May 1998 were appended to the data section on
	17 June 1998.[MAH 17 June 1998] Data for 26 June 1998 were appended to the data
	section on 6 October 1998.[MAH 6 October 1998] Data for 14 July 1998, 17 November
	1998, 01 and 15 December 1998, 19 January 1999, and 01 February 1999 were
	appended to the data section on 26 February 1999.[MAH 26 February 1999] Data
	for 15 and 24 February 1999 were appended to the data section on 25 March
	1999.[MAH 25 March 1999]. Data for 19 April, 29 April, 01 June, 24 June, 30
	June, and 02 December 1999, as well as 20 January, 15 February, 24 February,
	18 April, 10 May, 30 May, and 09 June 2000 were appended to the data section
	on 19 July 2000.[MAH 19 July 2000] Data for 29 March 1999 as well as the
	control points for 1 December 1999 were inserted into the data section on 21
	September 2000.[MAH 21 September 2000] Data for 27 December 1999 as well as
	the control points were inserted into the data section on 5 February 
	2001.[TMA 5 February 2001] Control point data for 17 November 1998 and 15 
	December 1998 were inserted into the data section on 28 February 2001.[TMA
	28 February 2001]  Data for the period 13 December 2000 to 25 June 2001
	were appended to the data section along with the control point data on 
	30 July 2001.[TMA 30 July 2001] Point data and Control Point data for 10 
	December 2001 were appended to the data section on 12 February 2002.[TMA
	12 February 2002] Point data and Control Point data for the period 17 January
	2002 to 19 February 2002 were appended to the data section on 25 March 2002.
	[TMA 25 March 2001] Data for 21 March through 17 June 2002 were appended
	to the data section.[TMA 25 September 2002] Data for 11 November 2002 through
	13 February 2003 were appended to the data section.[TMA 25 March 2003] Data
	for 13 March 2003 were appended to the data section.[TMA 21 April 2003]
	Data for 3 April through 22 December 2003 were appended to the data section.
	[TMA 6 February 2004] Data for 10 February 2004 through 01 June 2004 were
	appended to the data section.[TMA 19 January 2005] Data for 14 June 2004 through
	19 April 2005 were appended to the data section.[TMA 20 May 2005] Data for 26
	May 2005 through 06 March 2006 were appended to the data section.[TMA 22 May
	2007]. Data for 26 January 2005 were inserted and 31 March 2006 through 12 April
	2007 were appended to the data section.[TMA 22 May 2007] Data for 20 April through
	25 October 2007 were appended to the data section.[TMA 05 June 2008] 
	Data for January through December 2008 were appended to the data section.
	[HCH 09 March 2009] Data for 20 January 2009 through 25 May 2010 were appended
	to the data section. All data were edited to reformat the date to yyyy/mm/dd
	and a column was added to indicate control points as a 'C'.[HCH 09 April 2012]
	Title, keywords, comments, cols, and data format edited.[HCH 06 July 2013]
</para>
	<para>begin 30 October 1992, ongoing, weekly to biweekly.</para>
</description>
</maintenance>
	<contact>
		<organizationName>Niwot Ridge LTER</organizationName>
		<positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
		<address>
<deliveryPoint>Institute of Arctic and Alpine Research (INSTAAR)</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>University of Colorado</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>1560 30th Street</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>UCB 450</deliveryPoint>
<city>Boulder</city>
<administrativeArea>CO</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>80309-0450</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
		<phone phonetype="voice">303-492-2594</phone> 
		<electronicMailAddress>lternwt@colorado.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		<onlineUrl>http://niwot.colorado.edu/</onlineUrl>
	</contact>
	<publisher>
		<organizationName>Niwot Ridge LTER</organizationName>
		<positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
		<address>
<deliveryPoint>Institute of Arctic and Alpine Research (INSTAAR)</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>University of Colorado</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>1560 30th Street</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>UCB 450</deliveryPoint>
<city>Boulder</city>
<administrativeArea>CO</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>80309-0450</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
		<phone phonetype="voice">303-492-2594</phone> 
		<electronicMailAddress>lternwt@colorado.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		<onlineUrl>http://niwot.colorado.edu/</onlineUrl>
	</publisher>
	<methods>
		<methodStep>
			<description>
				<para>Citations:</para>
				<para>Walker, D.A., B.E. Lewis, W.B. Krantz, E.T. Price, and 
					R.D. Tabler. 1994. Hierarchic studies of snow-ecosystem interactions: 
					A 100-year snow-alteration experiment. Pp. 407-414 In: Ferrik, M. (ed.). 
					Proceedings of the Fiftieth Annual Eastern and Western Snow Conference, 
					Quebec City, Quebec, Canada, 8-10 June 1993. 441 pp.</para>
				<para>Brooks, P.D., M. W. Williams, D. A. Walker, and S. K. Schmidt. 1995. 
					The Niwot Ridge snow fence experiment: Biogeochemical responses to changes 
					in the seasonal snowpack. Pp. 293-302 In Tonnessen, K. A., M. W. Williams, 
					and M. Tranter (eds.). Biogeochemistry of Seasonally Snow Covered Basins. 
					International Association of Hydrological Sciences, Wallingford, UK, IAHS-AIHS 
					Publication no. 228. 465 pp.</para>
				<section>
					<para>Snow depth measurements at the control points were not
						initiated until 9 January 1993.</para><para>
						Prior to the spring of 1995, two distinct lenticular drifts formed,
						a large leeward and a smaller windward drift. As a result of the
						unusually heavy snows during the spring of 1995, these two drifts
						actually merged to form a single large drift that engulfed the 
						snowfence itself. Consequently snow depths were recorded at the
						fence during the spring of 1995, and these measurements were originally
						listed in the comments section of this file. In the spring of
						1996 it was determined that measurements should be routinely taken
						along the snowfence. The entry and processing programs were changed
						accordingly and the 1995 snow depths were inserted into the data section. 
						The hard copy data form for 26 July 1995 contained the following
						comment written by Lee Turner "Put down 26 July 95 as the last day
						with any snow in the snowfence area".</para><para>
						The hard copy data form for 31 January 1996 contained the following
						comment written by Lee Turner "snow fell with no wind, 30" of fresh
						powder".</para><para>
						Notes on the hard copy data form for 28 January 1996 indicated that
						an ice lens was present at coordinates 10,40 (ID #267) and 20,40 
						(ID #282).</para><para>
						A note on the hard copy data form for 14 February 1996 indicated 
						that the measurements at coordinates 20,60 (ID #284), 20,50 (ID #283), 
						and 20,40 (ID #282) may not be correct. After consultation with L. Turner 
						it was determined that there may have been an ice lens at those coordinates.
						A note on the hard copy data form for 7 July 1997 indicated that the 
						fence drift had melted out 100% on 7 July 1997.</para>
				</section>
			</description>
		</methodStep>
	</methods>
<dataTable scope="document">
<entityName>snfcsnow.dw.data.csv</entityName>
	<entityDescription>Snow depth data for saddle snowfence, 1992 - ongoing. </entityDescription>
<physical scope="document">
<objectName>snfcsnow.dw.data.csv</objectName>
<dataFormat>
<textFormat>
	<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
	<numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
	<recordDelimiter>\r</recordDelimiter>
	<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
	<simpleDelimited>
		<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
		<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
</simpleDelimited>
</textFormat>
</dataFormat>
	<distribution> 
		<online>
			<url function="download">http://niwot.colorado.edu/data_csvs/snfcsnow.dw.data.csv</url> 
		</online>
	</distribution>
</physical>
<attributeList>
	<attribute>
		<attributeName>point identification number</attributeName>
		<attributeLabel>point identification number</attributeLabel>
		<attributeDefinition>point identification number</attributeDefinition>
		<storageType>integer</storageType>
		<measurementScale>
			<ratio>
				<unit>
					<standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
				</unit>
				<numericDomain>
					<numberType>integer</numberType>
					<bounds>
						<minimum exclusive="false">113</minimum>
						<maximum exclusive="false">347</maximum>
					</bounds>
				</numericDomain>
			</ratio>
		</measurementScale>
		<missingValueCode>
			<code>NaN</code>
			<codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
		</missingValueCode>
	</attribute>
	<attribute>
		<attributeName>control point</attributeName>
		<attributeLabel>control point</attributeLabel>
		<attributeDefinition>control point</attributeDefinition>
		<storageType>string</storageType>
		<measurementScale>
			<nominal>
				<nonNumericDomain>
					<textDomain>
						<definition>control point</definition>
					</textDomain>
				</nonNumericDomain>
			</nominal>
		</measurementScale>
		<missingValueCode>
			<code>NaN</code>
			<codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
		</missingValueCode>
	</attribute>
	<attribute>
		<attributeName>date</attributeName>
		<attributeLabel>date</attributeLabel>
		<attributeDefinition>date</attributeDefinition>
		<storageType>date</storageType>
		<measurementScale>
			<dateTime>
				<formatString>YYYY-MM-DD</formatString>
				<dateTimePrecision>1</dateTimePrecision>
				<dateTimeDomain>
					<bounds>
						<minimum exclusive="false">1992-10-30</minimum>
					</bounds>
				</dateTimeDomain>
			</dateTime>
		</measurementScale>
		<missingValueCode>
			<code>NaN</code>
			<codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
		</missingValueCode>
	</attribute>
	<attribute>
		<attributeName>snow depth</attributeName>
		<attributeLabel>snow depth</attributeLabel>
		<attributeDefinition>snow depth</attributeDefinition>
		<storageType>integer</storageType>
		<measurementScale>
			<ratio>
				<unit>
					<standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
				</unit>
				<numericDomain>
					<numberType>integer</numberType>
					<bounds>
						<minimum exclusive="false">000</minimum>
					</bounds>
				</numericDomain>
			</ratio>
		</measurementScale>
		<missingValueCode>
			<code>NaN</code>
			<codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
		</missingValueCode>
	</attribute>
</attributeList>
</dataTable>
</dataset>
</eml:eml>