<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="msb-tempbiodev.1111161.0" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=MACROECO,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <title>
Tree Growth in Gentry Subplots for Six Experimental Sites (NWT, CWT, HJA, HFR, LUQ, and BCI)
</title>
    <creator>
      <organizationName>University of Arizona - Enquist Lab</organizationName>
      <onlineUrl>
http://eeb37.biosci.arizona.edu/~brian/Department_of_Ecology_and_Evolutionary_Biology/Enquist_Lab.html
</onlineUrl>
    </creator>
    <pubDate>2014-12-09</pubDate>
    <language>English</language>
    <abstract>
      <section>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>
Patterns of biodiversity, such as the increase toward the tropics and the peaked curve during ecological succession, are fundamental phenomena for ecology. Such patterns have multiple, interacting causes, but temperature emerges as a dominant factor across organisms from microbes to trees and mammals, and across terrestrial, marine, and freshwater environments. However, there is little consensus on the underlying mechanisms, even as global temperatures increase and the need to predict their effects becomes more pressing. The purpose of this project is to generate and test theory for how temperature impacts biodiversity through its effect on biochemical processes and metabolic rate. A combination of standardized surveys in the field and controlled experiments in the field and laboratory measure diversity of three taxa -- trees, invertebrates, and microbes -- and key biogeochemical processes of decomposition in seven forests distributed along a geographic gradient of increasing temperature from cold temperate to warm tropical. This dataset contains growth records of plants (trees, shrubs, and liana) using the measures of diameter at breast height and/or diameter and ground height at five Gentry subplots at each experimental site. These plots were installed by the Enquist Lab and the University of Arizona as part of this macrosystems biodiversity and latitude project supported by the National Science Foundation under Cooperative Agreement DEB#1065836.
</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Trees</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Growth</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Diameter Breast Height</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Diameter Ground Height</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">DBH</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">DGH</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">HJ Andrews</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Coweeta</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Harvard Forest</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Luquillo</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Niwot Ridge</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Macrosystems</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Biodiversity</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Latitude</keyword>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <section>
        <title>Data Policies</title>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>http://www.lternet.edu/policies/data-access</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url function="information">
http://macroeco2.lternet.edu/content/tree-growth-gentry-subplots-six-experimental-sites-nwt-cwt-hja-hfr-luq-and-bci
</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <contact>
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">505 277-2535</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">505 277-2541</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>tech-support@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Brian</givenName>
        <surName>Enquist</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>University of Arizona - Enquist Lab</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>benquist@email.arizona.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <pubPlace>Experimental Macroecology Data</pubPlace>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <para>
              <literalLayout>
Annual measurements within each Gentry plot We use a revised CTFS protocol to measure stems within each 2 x 100m transect (Condit 1998). Determining which individuals are within the transect - General rule: If the center of the plant's base is within the 2m boundary of the line, the plant is within the transect. - For example, consider a tree with multiple stems that lies directly on the transect line. If the basal center point for all the stems is within the transect, all stems, including those that lie outside the transect line, are measured. However, if the center point of all stems comprising the individual is outside of the transect, none of the stems are measured, and the individual is considered to be outside of the plot. There are species-specific cases to this rule. Ground-skimming conifer branches: Some firs have extensive networks of low-lying branches that dive into and then out of the ground. To avoid retagging the same individuals, we only tag firmly-rooted, vertical stems. Junipers: We associate large clumps of bush like junipers as single individuals. As with all ground measurements, we only measure and tag the largest stem of each individual. Determining separate individuals Stems are considered to be part of the same individual if there are above or belowground connections among multiple stems. Belowground connections can be checked by minor digging, but no deeper than one fingers-length, (approx. 10cm). We also assume that there are belowground connections if all stems appear to emerge from a single location, i.e. the angle at which each stem emerges from the ground points to a central location of germination for the individual. Multiple stems are denoted as a single individual by recording the largest stem or "main stem" tag number with the tag numbers of each secondary stem. Determining if and where to measure General rule: Measure DBH (diameter at breast height) for all stems greater than or equal to 1cm diameter at 1.3m from the ground. Measure DGH (diameter at ground height) for all stems below 1cm DBH, but greater than or equal to 1cm basal diameter at the ground. -	Always measure DBH at 1.3m from on the upslope side of the individual. -	If scars or any malformations occur at 1.3m, move the DBH measurement above or below 1.3cm. -	If a tree is buttressed, measure 1.3cm from the top of the buttress. -	If a stem has bends and curves, measure 1.3m from ground including curvature, i.e. do not measure vertically, but rather measure 1.3m along the stem. -	Measure DGH from the lowest accessible point on the stem without major alterations to the natural environment, i.e. do not dig up litter extensively or move debris. If the individual has multiple stems, only measure the largest stem. -	Lianas, Vines and hemi-epiphytes are measured if the original rooting point is in the transect, and live stems are found climbing into the canopy. Painting: Use white or orange tree paint to mark where DBH measurements were taken on trees, shrubs, and vines. Note: some sites do not allow tree paint (Luquillo and BCI), in which case, carefully notated descriptions will be used for re-measurement. Notations include: -	POM (point of measurement): distance in cm from the ground to the location of diameter measurement. Note if different from 130 cm. -	DTN (distance to nail): distance in cm from location of diameter measurement to the nail used to tag the individual. Value will be positive if nail is above POM, and value will be negative if nail is below POM. Nails should always be 20cm from point of measurement. Palms: Measure a single DBH for palms that have woody trunks at 1.3m from ground. For all other palms, take three measurements: DGH, diameter at highest point of woody stem (see below), and distance from ground to the highest diameter measurement. The woody stem is defined as any part of the palm stem that is below the location of where fronds separate from the main stem. Large herbs: With large herbs, always measure a ground measurement of the largest stem (frond, petiole, etc.) in a clump. Examples include ginger, heliconia, ferns, devil's club, etc. Tagging each stem All trees above 10cm (Luquillo) and 5cm (all other sites) DBH are tagged 20 cm above the point of measurement (POM, 1.3m) by nailing a tag to the tree with an aluminum nail. All stems below 5cm DBH are tagged by tying a tag to the stem with either grafting tape (Luquillo) or metal wire (all other sites). We nail the tags to each tree so that the nail has a downward angle to ensure the tag falls away from the stem. We do not drive nails very deeply into the tree to allow for several years of growth. We use enough wire/grafting tape to allow for ~5 years of potential growth. Tags that are attached too tightly can constrict growth or cause the tree to swallow the wire. All tags are placed on the stem containing the POM, i.e. above live branches but below the POM, and below live branches above the POM. This ensures that the measurement is taken on the tagged stem. Images Tagging exceptions: -	Palms can be nailed, but need to also have grafting tape run through the tag and tied around the trunk. -	Some trees cannot be nailed regardless of their size, examples include Cecropia and Schefflera. -	Herbaceous clumps are tagged with grafting tape that encompasses the entire individual, not just a single stem. Note: Trees above 1cm DBH that were previously tagged are not retagged. This reduces confusion that may occur by adding new tags to individuals with existing tags, especially at sites that currently follow CTFS protocol. Checking the measurements As with any large resampling, there are always mistakes. To minimize mistakes that make it into each year's resampling data, we thoroughly look over the data sheet for mistakes before leaving each site. Some common mistakes include not recording measurements, missed species ids, misplaced measurements (i.e. recording a DBH instead of a DGH), etc. We attempt to find these mistakes by carefully looking over each measurement. When a mistake is found, we highlight the row corresponding to the stem from which the mistake may have occurred. We are then able to assess these errors by returning to the field to confirm/remeasure any stems under question.
</literalLayout>
            </para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>
Tree Growth in Gentry Subplots for Six Experimental Sites (NWT, CWT, HJA, HFR, LUQ, and BCI)
</entityName>
      <entityDescription>
This dataset contains growth records of plants using the measures of diameter at breast height and/or diameter and ground height at the five Gentry plots at each macrosystems site.
</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>MacrosystemsGentryPlotPlantGrowthDataFINAL.csv</objectName>
        <size>4628775</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/msb-tempbiodev/1111161/0/bab1a867ad4784acfe4a6fc662e9f369</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <coverage>
        <temporalCoverage>
          <rangeOfDates>
            <beginDate>
              <calendarDate>2011-08-01</calendarDate>
            </beginDate>
            <endDate>
              <calendarDate>2014-08-06</calendarDate>
            </endDate>
          </rangeOfDates>
        </temporalCoverage>
      </coverage>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>sample_id</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>sample_id</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>sample_id</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>sample_id</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Site</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Site</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The research site where measurements were taken</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>The research site where measurements were taken</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Site_code</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Site_code</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Includes site name and associated Gentry number, ie NWTT1 represents Gentry 1 at Niwot Ridge. For a better understanding of a Gentry plot, view Plant Sampling Methodolgy: (i) Gentry Plot 0.1ha Methodology
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
Includes site name and associated Gentry number, ie NWTT1 represents Gentry 1 at Niwot Ridge. For a better understanding of a Gentry plot, view Plant Sampling Methodolgy: (i) Gentry Plot 0.1ha Methodology
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Date</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Date</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Eight digit date of when measurements were first taken for each stem. Previous to 10/16/2013 date was recorded as month_year.
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>YYYYMMDD</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Year2_date</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Year 2 sample date</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Eight digit date when year 2 measurements were made at each site. Previous to 10/16/2013 date was recorded as month_year.
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>YYYYMMDD</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Year3_date</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Year 3 sample date</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Eight digit date when year 3 measurements were made at each site
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>YYYYMMDD</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>year</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>year</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
The year of the project that the stem was first measured
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
The year of the project that the stem was first measured
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Latitude</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Latitude</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Taken in the center of each Gentry plot using a handheld GPS Garmin 62stc (estimated position error of 5-10m) and converted to decimal with a WGS84 projection
</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Longitude</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Longitude</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Longitude Taken in the center of each Gentry plot using a handheld GPS Garmin 62stc (estimated position error of 5-10m) and converted to decimal with a WGS84 projection
</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Elevation</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Elevation</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Taken in the center of each Gentry plot using a handheld GPS Garmin 62stc (estimated position error of 5-10m) in feet with a WGS84 projection and converted to meters.
</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Line</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Line</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Line. Each Gentry plot has 10 50m transects, denoted as lines 1-10. All transect lines are from south to north
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
Line. Each Gentry plot has 10 50m transects, denoted as lines 1-10. All transect lines are from south to north
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Main_Stem</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Main_Stem</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
. Largest stem of a multi-stemmed individual. All multi-stemmed individuals were measured if &gt;1 cm DBH and the largest individual was tagged for Niwot and Coweeta 2011. At all other sites individual stems were tagged and measured separately follow CTFS protocol.
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
. Largest stem of a multi-stemmed individual. All multi-stemmed individuals were measured if &gt;1 cm DBH and the largest individual was tagged for Niwot and Coweeta 2011. At all other sites individual stems were tagged and measured separately follow CTFS protocol.
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>LTER_Tag</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>LTER_Tag_#</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
LTER_Tag_#. Long Term Ecological Research tag number. We used the existing tag any time a tree was already tagged in our plots.
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
LTER_Tag_#. Long Term Ecological Research tag number. We used the existing tag any time a tree was already tagged in our plots.
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>ENQ_Tag_#</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>ENQ_Tag_#</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
ENQ_Tag_#. All multi-stemmed individuals were measured if greater than 1 cm DBH and the largest individual was tagged for Niwot and Coweeta 2011. All other sites individual stems were tagged and measured separately follow CTFS protocol.
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
ENQ_Tag_#. All multi-stemmed individuals were measured if greater than 1 cm DBH and the largest individual was tagged for Niwot and Coweeta 2011. All other sites individual stems were tagged and measured separately follow CTFS protocol.
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Distance_m</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Distance_m</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Distance_m. The distance the plant is from the start of the 50m transect measured in meters
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
Distance_m. The distance the plant is from the start of the 50m transect measured in meters
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>location_2012</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>location_2012</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Determed in 2012 by dividing the 2 m transect into 5ths. While facing north, plant location was determined as on the left left (LL), left (L), center (C), right (R), or right right (RR) of the trensect.
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
Determed in 2012 by dividing the 2 m transect into 5ths. While facing north, plant location was determined as on the left left (LL), left (L), center (C), right (R), or right right (RR) of the trensect.
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Habit</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Habit</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Habit. Plant life form, eg Tree, Shrub, Liana as determined by the USDA growth habit (usda.gov). All Plants listed as Tree Shrub were considered Shrubs
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
Habit. Plant life form, eg Tree, Shrub, Liana as determined by the USDA growth habit (usda.gov). All Plants listed as Tree Shrub were considered Shrubs
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Morpho</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Morpho</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Semi-descriptive name used before correct species determination is known
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
Semi-descriptive name used before correct species determination is known
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Family</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Family</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Family taxon. Matched with family names used in Tropicos.org
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
Family taxon. Matched with family names used in Tropicos.org
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Genus</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Genus</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Genus matched with current genera found in Tropicos.org
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
Genus matched with current genera found in Tropicos.org
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Species</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Species</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Species matched with species names used in Tropicos.org
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
Species matched with species names used in Tropicos.org
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Taxon</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Taxon</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Genus-species identifier.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Genus-species identifier.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Authority</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Authority</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Person(s) that originally named and described species
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
Person(s) that originally named and described species
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Determiner</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Determiner</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Researcher that identified specimen in this study</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Researcher that identified specimen in this study</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Year1_DBH</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Year1_DBH</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Year1_DBH. Year1 describes the first visit to each site ranging from August 2011 until September 2012. Diameter at Breast Height in centimeters using a cloth DBH tape
</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Year2_DBH</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Year2_DBH</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Year2_DBH. Year2 describes the second visit to each site ranging from August 2012 until September 2013. Diameter at Breast Height in centimeters using small cm DBH tape. An X indicates that the stem is dead.
</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Year3_DBH</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Year3_DBH</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Year3_DBH. Year3 describes the third visit to each site ranging from August 2013 until September 2014. Diameter at Breast Height in centimeters using small cm DBH tape. An X indicates that the stem is dead.
</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Year1_DGH</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Year1_DGH</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Year1_DGH_1. Year1 describes the first visit to each site ranging from August 2011 until September 2012. Diameter at Ground Height measured in millimeters using digital calipers at Niwot and Coweeta in 2011 and converted to cm. All other sites use a small DBH tape.
</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Year2_DGH</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Year2_DGH</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Year2_DGH. Year2 describes the second visit to each site ranging from August 2012 until September 2013. Diameter at Ground Height measured in millimeters using a small cm DBH tape
</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Year3_DGH</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Year3_DGH</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Year3_DGH. Year3 describes the third visit to each site ranging from August 2013 until September 2014. Diameter at Ground Height measured in millimeters using a small cm DBH tape
</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Mortality_Date</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Mortality_Date</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Mortality_Date. The date on which individuals/stems were found dead
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>MM_YYYY</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>error</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>error</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
error. Each type of error that was made in the data was assigned a specific number which denotes the error made and the corrections, if any, that were made to the data. a-Mainstem # was forgotten in the data sheet. Corrected by inserting the mainstem # if there were no distance or location measurements and there was a DBH measurement (both indicating that it was a stem and not a new plant). b-A secondary stem tag number was not included. Corrected by inserting the missing tag number. Ex. If secondary stems have tag numbers 1,2,3,blank,5,6 in the data sheet, we would insert # 4 for the missing tag number. c-The distance of the plant along the 50 m transect was corrected. d-The location on the transect for year2 was considerably different from year1's location. Ex. Year1 - Right, Year2 - L or LL; last year - Center, this year - RR or LL. These errors were not corrected because it is unknown which location is correct. e-change morpho f-A measurement error were 6s were written instead of 9s and vica versa. Corrected by switching the 6 for a 9 or a 9 for a 6. These switches were only made when the following year's measurements verified that this mistake was made the previous year. Ex. Year1 DBH - 9.2, Year2 DBH - 6.3. Year1 DBH would be changed to 6.2 g-In Year1 the measurement was a DGH, but in subsequent years, it became a DBH because of the change in protocol, therefore it is not necessarily indicative of growth. Year1's protocol stated that a DBH measure of less than 2.5 cm was to be measured as a DGH. Year2's protocol stated that only plants with a DBH less than 1 cm were to be measured as a DGH h- The year 1 measurement was incorrect. Verified in the field by compaing year 1 measurement to year 2 measurement. Not corrected i- the year 1 measurement was recorded as a DGH, but it should have been recorded in the year 1 DBH column or vica versa (recorded DBH should be DGH). This was verified in the field in year 2. Corrected by moving the year 1 DGH measurement to the year 1 DBH column in year 2. j- Year 1's tag number was recorded incorrectly. Corrected in the filed in year 2 by replacing the incorrect tag number with the correct tag number k- A single stem has 2 tags (1 tag from the LTER site and 1 Enquist tag). Both tag numbers are left in the data sheet. l-the stem is within the transect but was not recorded (i.e. forgotten or not inclueded in the yr 1 protocol), but is included in year 2 m-The species was recorded in the data sheet with only the genus Nyssa. It should have included the species, Nyssa sylvatica. Corrected in the data sheet by including the species. n- The species name was accepted by USDA but not tropicos. The species with this error code are the only ones in the data set that do not have approved names from tropicos. o- Decimal was forgotten in yr 1 measurement. Corrected by verifying the true DBH or DGH in year 2 and then inserting the decimal point for the year 1 measurement p- the stem was recorded in the wrong line number in year 1. corrected by replacing the incorrect line number with the correct one q- after reassessing in year 2, the stem is outside of the transect or should not be measured according to the protocol r- The decimal point on a DGH measurement was put in the wrong spot and/or additional numbers were accidentaly typed into the PDA. Corrected by moving the decimal or removing a number so that year 2's measurement is close to year 1 measurement. The original measurement for year 2 is recored in the notes s- At Luquillo on year 2, Seth, an El Verde field tech, helped us identify seedlings from photos we took in the field. If he provided a species code but was still uncertain of the species or failed to identify the species, the row is assigned the error code "s" t- If we identified an individual but had uncertainty in its identification, the individual is assigned an error code "t" u - The tag was removed from the yr 2 measurement because the stem should never have been included in the transect according to the protocol (ex. Multiple stems tagged of one liana) v - The point of measurement in yr 1 was much higher than the standard 1.3 meters above ground. Yr 2 measurements were taken at 1.3 meters so differences between year 1 and year 2 DBH measurements may not indicate growth. w - The year 2 DGH measurement was below 1 cm DGH so the tag was removed from the individual. x-changed species identification
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
error. Each type of error that was made in the data was assigned a specific number which denotes the error made and the corrections, if any, that were made to the data. a-Mainstem # was forgotten in the data sheet. Corrected by inserting the mainstem # if there were no distance or location measurements and there was a DBH measurement (both indicating that it was a stem and not a new plant). b-A secondary stem tag number was not included. Corrected by inserting the missing tag number. Ex. If secondary stems have tag numbers 1,2,3,blank,5,6 in the data sheet, we would insert # 4 for the missing tag number. c-The distance of the plant along the 50 m transect was corrected. d-The location on the transect for year2 was considerably different from year1's location. Ex. Year1 - Right, Year2 - L or LL; last year - Center, this year - RR or LL. These errors were not corrected because it is unknown which location is correct. e-change morpho f-A measurement error were 6s were written instead of 9s and vica versa. Corrected by switching the 6 for a 9 or a 9 for a 6. These switches were only made when the following year's measurements verified that this mistake was made the previous year. Ex. Year1 DBH - 9.2, Year2 DBH - 6.3. Year1 DBH would be changed to 6.2 g-In Year1 the measurement was a DGH, but in subsequent years, it became a DBH because of the change in protocol, therefore it is not necessarily indicative of growth. Year1's protocol stated that a DBH measure of less than 2.5 cm was to be measured as a DGH. Year2's protocol stated that only plants with a DBH less than 1 cm were to be measured as a DGH h- The year 1 measurement was incorrect. Verified in the field by compaing year 1 measurement to year 2 measurement. Not corrected i- the year 1 measurement was recorded as a DGH, but it should have been recorded in the year 1 DBH column or vica versa (recorded DBH should be DGH). This was verified in the field in year 2. Corrected by moving the year 1 DGH measurement to the year 1 DBH column in year 2. j- Year 1's tag number was recorded incorrectly. Corrected in the filed in year 2 by replacing the incorrect tag number with the correct tag number k- A single stem has 2 tags (1 tag from the LTER site and 1 Enquist tag). Both tag numbers are left in the data sheet. l-the stem is within the transect but was not recorded (i.e. forgotten or not inclueded in the yr 1 protocol), but is included in year 2 m-The species was recorded in the data sheet with only the genus Nyssa. It should have included the species, Nyssa sylvatica. Corrected in the data sheet by including the species. n- The species name was accepted by USDA but not tropicos. The species with this error code are the only ones in the data set that do not have approved names from tropicos. o- Decimal was forgotten in yr 1 measurement. Corrected by verifying the true DBH or DGH in year 2 and then inserting the decimal point for the year 1 measurement p- the stem was recorded in the wrong line number in year 1. corrected by replacing the incorrect line number with the correct one q- after reassessing in year 2, the stem is outside of the transect or should not be measured according to the protocol r- The decimal point on a DGH measurement was put in the wrong spot and/or additional numbers were accidentaly typed into the PDA. Corrected by moving the decimal or removing a number so that year 2's measurement is close to year 1 measurement. The original measurement for year 2 is recored in the notes s- At Luquillo on year 2, Seth, an El Verde field tech, helped us identify seedlings from photos we took in the field. If he provided a species code but was still uncertain of the species or failed to identify the species, the row is assigned the error code "s" t- If we identified an individual but had uncertainty in its identification, the individual is assigned an error code "t" u - The tag was removed from the yr 2 measurement because the stem should never have been included in the transect according to the protocol (ex. Multiple stems tagged of one liana) v - The point of measurement in yr 1 was much higher than the standard 1.3 meters above ground. Yr 2 measurements were taken at 1.3 meters so differences between year 1 and year 2 DBH measurements may not indicate growth. w - The year 2 DGH measurement was below 1 cm DGH so the tag was removed from the individual. x-changed species identification
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Dendrometer</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Dendrometer</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Dendrometer. Denotes individuals with dendrometers. This will be updated, as of 6/2012 individuals have not been identified.
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>D</code>
                    <definition>Dendrometer Present</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>yes</code>
                    <definition>Dendrometer Present</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>No D</code>
                    <definition>No dendrometer present</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Year2_recorder</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Year2_recorder</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
The name of the person that was recording the data on the HP Ipaq
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
The name of the person that was recording the data on the HP Ipaq
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Year2_Tagger</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Year2_Tagger</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The name of the person who was tagging new stems</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>The name of the person who was tagging new stems</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Year2_measurer</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Year2_measurer</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
The name of the person who was taking DBH measurements
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
The name of the person who was taking DBH measurements
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DTN</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DTN</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
DTN. Distance of the point of measurement (POM) to the nail/tree tag measured in cm. This was primarily used for site we were unable to mark the POM with tree paint.
</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>POM</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>POM</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
POM. Distance of the point of measurement (POM) to the ground measured in cm. This was primarily used for odd shaped trees where the normal DBH height of 130cm use not used and were tree paint was not also used.
</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Year1_notes</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Year1_notes</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Year1 describes the first visit to each site ranging from August 2011 until September 2012. Often includes morpho/multistem and other location info. G=the switch made from measuring all stems less than 2.5 at DBH at ground to measuring them at DBH if they reach DBH. This follows CTFS protocol.
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
Year1 describes the first visit to each site ranging from August 2011 until September 2012. Often includes morpho/multistem and other location info. G=the switch made from measuring all stems less than 2.5 at DBH at ground to measuring them at DBH if they reach DBH. This follows CTFS protocol.
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Year2_Notes</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Year2_Notes</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Year2 describes the second visit to each site ranging from August 2012 until September 2013. Often includes morpho/multistem and other location info. G=the switch made from measuring all stems less than 2.5 at DBH at ground to measuring them at DBH if they reach DBH. This follows CTFS protocol.
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
Year2 describes the second visit to each site ranging from August 2012 until September 2013. Often includes morpho/multistem and other location info. G=the switch made from measuring all stems less than 2.5 at DBH at ground to measuring them at DBH if they reach DBH. This follows CTFS protocol.
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Year3_Notes</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Year3_Notes</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Year3 describes the third visit to each site ranging from August 2013 until September 2014. Often includes morpho/multistem and other location info. G=the switch made from measuring all stems less than 2.5 at DBH at ground to measuring them at DBH if they reach DBH. This follows CTFS protocol.
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
Year3 describes the third visit to each site ranging from August 2013 until September 2014. Often includes morpho/multistem and other location info. G=the switch made from measuring all stems less than 2.5 at DBH at ground to measuring them at DBH if they reach DBH. This follows CTFS protocol.
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Year1_Total_Plot_Biomass</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Year1_Total_Plot_biomass</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Year1 describes the first visit to each site ranging from August 2011 until September 2012. Biomass will be calculated using associated formula
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
Year1 describes the first visit to each site ranging from August 2011 until September 2012. Biomass will be calculated using associated formula
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Sampled</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Sampled</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Denotes individuals in which Lindsey Sloat collected a sample from Coweeta in 2012. Samples were pressed, identified, and stored in the attic of the Coweeta dorms. These samples include the most common species in Coweeta so that a measuring crew can quickly learn local species
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
Denotes individuals in which Lindsey Sloat collected a sample from Coweeta in 2012. Samples were pressed, identified, and stored in the attic of the Coweeta dorms. These samples include the most common species in Coweeta so that a measuring crew can quickly learn local species
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Angle</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Angle</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
The angle at which a secondary brach points at the point of measurement (1.3 m), ie 0 is a branch that points North at 1.3 m and 90 is a branch that points East at 1.3 m
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
The angle at which a secondary brach points at the point of measurement (1.3 m), ie 0 is a branch that points North at 1.3 m and 90 is a branch that points East at 1.3 m
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>location_2011</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>location_2011</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Determined in 2011 by dividing the 2m transect into 3rds while facing north and determining left, right, or center plant location
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
Determined in 2011 by dividing the 2m transect into 3rds while facing north and determining left, right, or center plant location
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Cloth_tape</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Cloth_tape</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
In year 2, the DBH of some trees was measured with the cloth DBH tape and the small cm DBH tape to determine if there was a consistent difference between DBH measurements with the small cm DBH tape and the cloth DBH tape
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
In year 2, the DBH of some trees was measured with the cloth DBH tape and the small cm DBH tape to determine if there was a consistent difference between DBH measurements with the small cm DBH tape and the cloth DBH tape
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>RUFINO_HABIT</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>RUFINO_HABIT</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>
Rufino, the field technician at BCI, reported the habit of stems within the gentry plots, however, his classification system is still unclear.
</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>
Rufino, the field technician at BCI, reported the habit of stems within the gentry plots, however, his classification system is still unclear.
</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>vnum</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>vnum</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>vnum</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>vnum</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>WoodDensity</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>WoodDensity</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Wood Density</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Wood Density</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
</eml:eml>