<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata><Source>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/metadata/CO2_and_CH4_Production_and_CH4_Oxidation_in_Low_Temperature_Soil_Incubations_from_Flat_and_High_Centered_Polygons_Barrow_Alaska_2012.xml</Source>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1288688</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/CO2_CH4_prod_CH4_oxidation_low_temp_soil_incubations/data</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/CO2_CH4_prod_CH4_oxidation_low_temp_soil_incubations/documentation</onlink>
        <origin>David Graham (grahamde@ornl.gov)</origin>
        <origin>Jianqiu Zheng (zhengj@ornl.gov)</origin>
        <origin>Taniya RoyChowdhury (rctaniya@gmail.com)</origin>
        <title>CO2 and CH4 Production and CH4 Oxidation in Low Temperature Soil Incubations from Flat- and High-Centered Polygons, Barrow, Alaska, 2012</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The dataset consists of respiration and methane production rates and methane oxidation potential obtained from soil microcosm studies carried out under controlled temperature and incubation conditions. Soils cores collected in 2012 represent the flat- and high-centered polygon active layers and permafrost (when present) from the NGEE Arctic Intensive Study Site 1, Barrow, Alaska.</abstract>
      <purpose>Data presented here will improve our understanding of the temperature controls on the temporal variation in microbially mediated carbon loss potentials from soils impacted by a characteristic microtopographic feature in the Arctic tundra ecosystems. Such an understanding will in turn help parameterize fine-scale models that constrain soil biogeochemistry, particularly relevant to methane cycle under water saturated and oxic conditions.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20120412</begdate>
          <enddate>20120412</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>complete</progress>
      <update>n/a</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Intensive site 1</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-156.596662</westbc>
        <eastbc>-156.596662</eastbc>
        <northbc>71.282767</northbc>
        <southbc>71.282767</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Barrow, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Area B</placekey>
        <placekey>Area C</placekey>
        <placekey>Intensive Site 1</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>internal</accconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Jianqiu Zheng</cntper>
          <cntorg>Biosciences Division, Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1 Bethel Valley Rd</address>
          <city>Oak Ridge</city>
          <state>Tennessee</state>
          <postal>37830</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntemail>zhengj@ornl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <tool>
      <toolcont>
        <cntinfo>
          <cntaddr>
            <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          </cntaddr>
        </cntinfo>
      </toolcont>
    </tool>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>field</methtype>
        <methdesc>Headspace CO2 and CH4 gases in the microcosms were analyzed at regular intervals for up to 60 days of incubation. &amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Headspace gas was analyzed with a SRI 8610C gas chromatograph equipped with a methanizer and Flame Ionization Detector (FID) with a 1.82 m by 0.32 cm HayeSep D packed column (SRI Instruments, Torrance, CA). H2 gas and air flow rates for the FID were maintained at 25 mL min-1 and 250 mL min-1, respectively. Helium flow was maintained at 20 mL min-1 as the carrier gas. Detector and oven temperatures were 40 and 300 degrees C, respectively. &amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Headspace gas samples (0.5 mL) were injected onto the on-column injector and analyzed isothermally. All gas sample analyses were performed after calibration with standard gases (+/- 99.99 %; Scotty Specialty Gas Calibration Standards, Sigma-Aldrich). Every 10 measurements were bracketed by replicate working standards. The linear response of the detector was verified over the range 1-100 ppmv for both CO2 and CH4. The limit of detection for CH4 was determined at 1 ppmv and for CO2 at 10 ppmv. CO2 and CH4 concentrations were calculated from the linear regression analysis of five-point standard curves. &amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Gas production rates were calculated as the change in headspace gas concentrations (adjusted for headspace volume and ambient temperature and pressure) and dissolved gas concentrations with time. Dissolved gas concentrations were calculated based on headspace concentrations, soil water content, and Henry's constant for CH4 and CO2 equilibrium adjusted for temperature and soil pH.</methdesc>
      </method>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Data Center Support</cntper>
          <cntorg>Next-Generation Ecosystem Experiments (NGEE) Arctic Project, Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1 Bethel Valley Road</address>
          <city>Oak Ridge</city>
          <state>TN</state>
          <postal>37831-6290</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntemail>support@ngee.ornl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160928</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Jianqiu Zheng</cntper>
          <cntorg>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1 Bethel Valley Rd</address>
          <city>OAK RIDGE</city>
          <state>Tennessee</state>
          <postal>37830</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>865-241-2408</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>zhengj@ornl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FDGC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata and
			Biological Data Profile</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FDGC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
  <ome>
    <ome_status>approved</ome_status>
    <taskname>BGC</taskname>
  </ome>
</metadata>
