<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata><Source>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/metadata/Active_Layer_Soil_Carbon_and_Nitrogen_Mineralization_Barrow_Alaska_2012.xml</Source>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1185213</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/vegetation_dynamics/Active_Layer_Soil_Carbon_and_Nutrient_Mineralization_User_Guidance_Document.pdf</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/vegetation_dynamics/Schadel_et_al_2015_NGEE_Arctic_Barrow_Soil_Incubations_2012.csv</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/vegetation_dynamics/Treat_et_al_2015_NGEE_Arctic_Barrow_Soil_Incubations_2012.csv</onlink>
        <origin>Colleen Iversen (iversencm@ornl.gov)</origin>
        <origin>Holly Vander Stel (vanderstelhm@ornl.gov)</origin>
        <origin>Richard Norby (norbyrj@ornl.gov)</origin>
        <origin>Victoria Sloan (victoria.l.sloan@gmail.com)</origin>
        <origin>Joanne Childs (childsj@ornl.gov)</origin>
        <origin>Deanne Brice (bricedj@ornl.gov)</origin>
        <origin>Jason Keller (jkeller@chapman.edu)</origin>
        <origin>Ariane Jong (jong102@mail.chapman.edu)</origin>
        <origin>Mallory Ladd (laddmp@ornl.gov)</origin>
        <origin>Stan Wullschleger (wullschlegsd@ornl.gov)</origin>
        <pubdate>20150701</pubdate>
        <title>Active Layer Soil Carbon and Nutrient Mineralization, Barrow, Alaska, 2012</title>
        <geoform>Laboratory Analysis</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Global Change Biology (2015) 21, 2787-2803, doi: 10.1111/gcb.12875</pubplace>
          <publish>Wiley</publish>
        </pubinfo>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This data set consists of bulk soil characteristics as well as carbon and nutrient mineralization rates of active layer soils manually collected from the field in August, 2012, frozen, and then thawed and incubated across a range of temperatures in the laboratory for 28 day periods in 2013-2015. The soils were collected from four replicate polygons each in areas A-D of Intensive Site 1 at the Next-Generation Ecosystem Experiments (NGEE) Arctic site near Barrow, Alaska, in center, edge, and trough microtopography in each polygon. Data included are i) bulk soil characteristics including carbon, nitrogen, gravimetric water content, bulk density, and pH in 5-cm depth increments and also by soil horizon, ii) carbon, nitrogen, and phosphorus mineralization rates for soil horizons incubated aerobically (and in one case both aerobically and anaerobically) for 28 days at temperatures that included 2, 4, 8, and 12 degrees C. http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1185213&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
[These data are a portion of a larger dataset. Additional soil and incubation data are forthcoming when published as part of another paper that includes additional replicate analyses. 2015/10/29]</abstract>
      <purpose>Atmospheric warming, which is expected to occur  more rapidly in the Arctic compared with lower-latitudes, may lead to permafrost degradation, potentially increasing feedbacks of carbon (C) to the atmosphere, and increased nutrient availability for plants. While C stored in permafrost  has been the focus of much research, we were interested in  feedbacks from warming of the active  layer that thaws each year. Microbial processing of organic matter in the active layer is controlled by the  balance among soil organic matter content, moisture, and temperature, which are influenced by landscape position and plant community composition. We collected active layer soil across a gradient of microtopographic positions in polygonal tundra in Barrow, Alaska. We hypothesized that C, N, and P mineralization would be greatest in the warmest soils with the greatest soil organic matter content.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20120731</begdate>
          <enddate>20120803</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>ongoing</progress>
      <update>as needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Intensive site 1</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-156.596662</westbc>
        <eastbc>-156.596662</eastbc>
        <northbc>71.282767</northbc>
        <southbc>71.282767</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Barrow Environmental Observatory</placekey>
        <placekey>NGEE Arctic</placekey>
        <placekey>Area B</placekey>
        <placekey>Area C</placekey>
        <placekey>Area A</placekey>
        <placekey>Barrow, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Area D</placekey>
      </place>
      <stratum>
        <stratkey>active layer</stratkey>
      </stratum>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Soil characteristics and soil carbon and nutrient mineralization</themekt>
        <themekey>soil carbon content</themekey>
        <themekey>soil nitrogen content</themekey>
        <themekey>soil pH</themekey>
        <themekey>soil gravimetric water content</themekey>
        <themekey>soil bulk density</themekey>
        <themekey>soil carbon mineralization rates</themekey>
        <themekey>soil nitrogen mineralization rates</themekey>
        <themekey>soil phosphorus mineralization rates</themekey>
        <themekey>soil organic matter depth</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>public</accconst>
    <datacred>Claire Treat, University of Alaska, Fairbanks (ctreat@usgs.gov); Christina Schadel, Northern Arizona University (Christina.Schaedel@nau.edu); A. Shafer Powell, Oak Ridge National Laboratory (powellas@ornl.gov)</datacred>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Colleen Iversen</cntper>
          <cntorg>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>One Bethel Valley Road</address>
          <city>Oak Ridge</city>
          <state>Tennessee</state>
          <postal>37831</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>865 241 3961</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>iversencm@ornl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <tool>
      <toolcont>
        <cntinfo>
          <cntaddr>
            <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          </cntaddr>
        </cntinfo>
      </toolcont>
    </tool>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <qattracc>
        <attraccv>We have not conducted uncertainty analyses, but we have completed quality assurance/control checks. These data have also been used in wider meta-analyses, and have been compared against other sites.</attraccv>
      </qattracc>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Three of us checked the data in the electronic file against the raw data sheets.</logic>
    <complete>Some data are missing due to sample loss at time of field collection, or due to laboratory mishap. These cells were left blank.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>both</methtype>
        <methdesc>At peak growing season in late July, 2012, we manually collected soil cores to the permafrost boundary across gradients of polygonal tundra and microtopographic position on the Barrow Environmental Observatory. Soil samples were collected using a 5.08-cm diameter hammer corer or a tundra knife (to sample 10 cm by 10 cm soil columns) when soil was too wet to retrieve an intact soil sample. Cores were collected in each of four polygon types (poorly defined, low, flat, and high-centered), from the trough, edge, or center microtopographic locations within each polygon (n = 4 polygon types by 4 replicate polygons of each type by 3 microtopographic positions = 48 total soil cores). Upon removal from the soil, the depth of the organic layer was determined as the boundary where soil became largely mineral in texture. The cores were then sectioned into 5 cm increments, placed in separate bags, and kept on blue ice while in the field. When the organic/mineral transition fell within a 5 cm increment, the organic matter and mineral soil were treated separately. Cores were frozen at -20 degrees C before shipping to Oak Ridge National Laboratory, where they were frozen at -20 degrees C until processing. &amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Given the large number of soil depth increments, processing and month-long soil incubations were performed serially on each replicate polygon (in January 2013, June and September of 2014, and January 2015). For each replicate, core increments were first thawed overnight at 4 degrees C,then plant material (green moss, fine roots, and rhizomes) was removed and soils were homogenized by hand (organic horizons) or by sieving the soil through an 8-mm sieve (mineral horizons). The 5-cm depth increments were subsampled for a series of soil characteristics. One subsample was used to determine pH using 1:4 or 1:2 ratios of field-moist soil to distilled water for organic and mineral soils, respectively (Beckman 350 pH Meter, Fullerton, CA).  A second subsample was used for determination of initial extractable ammonium, nitrate, and phosphate by shaking a 1:10 ratio of field-moist soil to 2 M KCl for 1 hour at low speed on a reciprocal shaker. After settling overnight at 4 degrees C, the extractant was filtered through Whatman No.1 filter papers pre-leached with distilled water and frozen at -20 degrees C until analysis for nitrogen and phosphorus on an autoanalyzer (Lachat QuickChem QC8500 Automated Ion Analyzer, Loveland, CO). A third subsample was used to determine soil gravimetric water content by drying the soil to a constant mass (3 days) at 70 degrees C. Dried gravimetric water content samples were ground to a fine powder (SPEX SamplePrep 2010 Geno/Grinder,  Metuchen, NJ), re-dried, and carbon and nitrogen content were determined on an elemental analyzer (Costech ECS 4010 Elemental Analyzer, Valencia, CA).&amp;#xD;
To assess soil C and nutrient mineralization response to warming, we incubated soils from three horizons at three temperatures for 28 days. After initial subsamples were complete, we combined 5-cm depth increments into soil horizons: organic, mineral, and deep organic (DO) defined as organic-rich soil near the permafrost boundary. We re-sampled these soils for initial horizon pH, nitrogen and phosphorus, gravimetric water content, and carbon and nitrogen as described above, and then approximately 5 g of soil were sealed into 160-ml serum bottles, which were flushed with compressed air to ensure at least 6 cycles of gas through the headspace. Air filled serum bottles served as blanks (6 bottles per replicate) and were incubated with the samples (2 bottles per temperature treatment). (Note: the first replicate in January 2013 was incubated both aerobically and anaerobically; the anaerobic incubations were flushed with nitrogen gas rather than compressed air.). Bottles were then stored in incubators (Thermo Scientific Precision Model 815 Incubator, Marietta, OH) held at a constant temperature of 4, 8 or 12 degrees C. The bottles were sampled on days 1, 3, 7, 14 and 28 of the incubation via gas chromatography (SRI Instruments Greenhouse Gas GC System with 8610C Chassis, Torrance CA). A 1 ml syringe was inserted to the septum and the plunger was pumped vigorously to ensure the air within the bottle was mixed uniformly. A fixed volume of sample (0.4 ml) was injected into the gas chromatograph and the methane and carbon dioxide peak areas were recorded. Samples were then flushed with air for 6 cycles and returned to the incubators. For each day of gas chromatography sampling, a set of carbon dioxide (and methane, for anaerobic incubations) standards was run to create a standard curve between carbon content and peak area.  Following gas chromatograph injection on day 28, the bottle seals were broken, and soil was subsampled for pH, extractable ammonium, nitrate, and phosphate using methods described above.  &amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Carbon mineralization rate was calculated (in both microgram C g soil-1 hour-1 and microgram C g C-1 hour-1) for both the incubation time between each sampling day and the total mineralization over the 28 day study. Nutrient mineralization rate was calculated (microgram nutrient g soil day-1) as the difference between initial and final nutrient content, standardized for soil dry weight.</methdesc>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>These data correspond to a data file provided for data submitted for two publications (Treat et al., 2015 and Schadel et al., 2015) that focused solely on carbon cycling, with specific parameters of interest, and included only one replicate each of the full data set collected in this effort. These data will be updated and additional categories will become available for the full data set (e.g., ammonification, nitrification, and phosphorus mineralization rates and initial pool sizes). &amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Treat, C.C., S.M. Natali, J. Ernakovich, C.M. Iversen, M. Lupascu, A.D. McGuire, R.J. Norby, T.R. Chowdhury, A. Richter, H. Santruckova, C. Schadel, E.A.G. Schuur, V.L. Sloan, M.R. Turetsky, M.P. Waldrop. 2015. A pan-Arctic synthesis of CH4 and CO2 production from anoxic soil incubations. Global Change Biology 21: 2787-2803. doi: 10.1111/gcb.12875&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Schadel C, M.K.F. Bader, E.A.G. Schuur,  R. Bracho, P. Capek, S. De-Baets, K. Diakova, J. Ernakovich, C. Estop-Aragones, I. P. Hartley, C.M. Iversen, E. Kane, C. Knoblauch, M. Lupascu, S. Natali, R. J. Norby, J. Donnell, T. Roy Chowdhury, H. Santruckova, G. Shaver, V.L. Sloan, C. Treat, M. Waldrop, K. Wickland. 2015. Dominant role of landscape hydrology in controlling the permafrost carbon feedback. Nature Climate Change, submitted.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20151013</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
    <cntinfo>
                                <cntperp>
                                        <cntper>Data Center Support</cntper>
                                        <cntorg>Next-Generation Ecosystem Experiments (NGEE) Arctic Project, Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
                                </cntperp>
                                <cntaddr>
                                        <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
                                        <address>1 Bethel Valley Road</address>
                                        <city>Oak Ridge</city>
                                        <state>TN</state>
                                        <postal>37831-6290</postal>
                                        <country>USA</country>
                                </cntaddr>
                                <cntvoice></cntvoice>
                                <cntfax></cntfax>
                                <cntemail>support@ngee.ornl.gov</cntemail>
                        </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20151030</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Colleen Iversen</cntper>
          <cntorg>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Staff Scientist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>One Bethel Valley Road</address>
          <city>Oak Ridge</city>
          <state>Tennessee</state>
          <postal>37831</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>865 241 3961</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>iversencm@ornl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FDGC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata and
			Biological Data Profile</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FDGC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
  <ome>
    <datause>These data provide a characterization of the active layer soil processes in different polygonal types in Barrow, Alaska.</datause>
    <ome_status>approved</ome_status>
    <taskname>V</taskname>
  </ome>
</metadata>
