<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata><Source>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/metadata/Plant_Root_Characteristics_and_Dynamics_in_Arctic_Tundra_Ecosystems_1960_2012.xml</Source>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/vegetation_dynamics/V_Plant Root Characteristics and Dynamics in Arctic Tundra Ecosystems 1960-2012_User_Guidance_Document_v1.pdf</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/vegetation_dynamics/Plant_roots_in_arctic_tundra_Supporting_Information_Table_S1_20140729.pdf</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/vegetation_dynamics/Plant_roots_in_arctic_tundra_20140827.xlsx</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/vegetation_dynamics/Plant_roots_in_arctic_tundra_20140827.csv</onlink>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1114222</onlink>
        <origin>Colleen Iversen (iversencm@ornl.gov)</origin>
        <pubdate>20140831</pubdate>
        <title>Plant Root Characteristics and Dynamics in Arctic Tundra Ecosystems, 1960-2012</title>
        <geoform>publication</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>New Phytologist</pubplace>
          <publish>Wiley-Blackwell</publish>
        </pubinfo>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Plant roots play a critical role in ecosystem function in arctic tundra, but root dynamics in these ecosystems are poorly understood. To address this knowledge gap, we synthesized available literature on tundra roots, including their distribution, dynamics, and contribution to ecosystem carbon and nutrient fluxes, and we highlighted key aspects of their representation in terrestrial biosphere models. Across all tundra ecosystems, belowground plant biomass exceeded aboveground biomass, with the exception of polar desert tundra. Roots were shallowly-distributed in the thin layer of soil that thaws annually, and were often found in surface organic soil horizons. Root traits including distribution, chemistry, anatomy, and resource partitioning play an important role in controlling plant species competition, and therefore ecosystem carbon and nutrient fluxes, under changing climatic conditions, but have only been quantified for a small fraction of tundra plants. Further, the annual production and mortality of fine roots are key components of ecosystem processes in tundra, but extant data are sparse. Tundra root traits and dynamics should be the focus of future research efforts.  Better representation of the dynamics and characteristics of tundra roots will improve the utility of models for evaluating the responses of tundra ecosystems to changing environmental conditions. http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1114222; DOI: 10.5440/1114222.</abstract>
      <purpose>We undertook this review to better understand the response of tundra ecosystems to rapidly changing environmental conditions in the Arctic. Our primary goals were to highlight current knowledge of roots and their role in key ecosystem processes in arctic tundra, and to identify priority areas for future research. Within each of several focused sections, ranging from the distribution and dynamics of tundra roots to the contribution of roots to ecosystem C and nutrient cycling, we touched on four key themes: (1) how tundra root traits and processes may differ from those observed in other biomes, (2) the relationships between belowground and aboveground tundra plant traits, (3) the response of roots to changing edaphic and environmental conditions, and (4) priorities for future research on fine roots in tundra ecosystems. Additionally, we compared current experimental and observational knowledge with the representation of tundra roots in models used to simulate C and nutrient cycling in the Arctic. Our goal was to determine to what extent different model conceptualizations and parameterizations are needed to accurately represent the range of root traits and processes of species found in arctic tundra ecosystems.&amp;#xD;
	  &amp;#xD;
We systematically identified and compiled data on root traits and root-soil interactions in arctic tundra. We defined arctic tundra as low-growing vegetation north of the Arctic treeline, encompassing five bioclimatic subzones ranging from the cold and barren subzone A to the warmer and more vegetated subzone E. Because data on roots in arctic tundra are scarce, we also included data from sites with similar plant species or plant communities (e.g., subarctic tundra in Abisko, Sweden, and subalpine tundra in Eagle Creek, Alaska). Data were compiled from various sources, including primary literature, books, and theses.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>19600101</begdate>
          <enddate>20120101</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>ongoing</progress>
      <update>as needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Arctic tundra region</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-165.767</westbc>
        <eastbc>149.7</eastbc>
        <northbc>80.634</northbc>
        <southbc>58.717</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Meade River, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Hidden Pond, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Eagle Summit, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Betty Pingo, Prudhoe Bay, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Pituffik (Thule), Greenland</placekey>
        <placekey>Rea Point, Melville Island, Western Queen Elizabeth Islands</placekey>
        <placekey>Agapa Settlement, Western Taimyr</placekey>
        <placekey>Komperdell Alm, Austria</placekey>
        <placekey>Disko Island, Greenland</placekey>
        <placekey>Eastern Taimyr</placekey>
        <placekey>Truelove, Devon island, Northwest Territories, Canada</placekey>
        <placekey>Adventdalen, Svalbard</placekey>
        <placekey>Sagavanirktok River, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Malloch Dome, Ellef Ringnes Island, Western Queen Elizabeth Islands</placekey>
        <placekey>Coldfoot, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Kevo, Finland</placekey>
        <placekey>Eagle Creek, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Toolik Lake, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Taimyr, USSR</placekey>
        <placekey>Latnjajaure, Sweden</placekey>
        <placekey>Rylekaerene, Greenland</placekey>
        <placekey>Northwestern Finland</placekey>
        <placekey>Somerset Island, Canadian high arctic</placekey>
        <placekey>Koryakskaya Zemlya</placekey>
        <placekey>Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Komi, ASSR</placekey>
        <placekey>Fairbanks, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Mt. Paras, Signaldalen, Troms, Norway</placekey>
        <placekey>Atkasook, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Bonanza Creek Experimental Forest, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Abisko Scientific Research Station, Sweden</placekey>
        <placekey>Everett Pond, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Devon Island, Canada</placekey>
        <placekey>Pyasina River, Tareya station, Western Taimyr</placekey>
        <placekey>Sagwon, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Western Taimyr</placekey>
        <placekey>Smith Lake, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Kamasjaure, Sweden</placekey>
        <placekey>Timberline, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Dempster, Yukon, Canada</placekey>
        <placekey>Caribou-Poker Creeks Research Watershed</placekey>
        <placekey>Ny-London, Blomstrandhalvoya, Spitsbergen, Norway</placekey>
        <placekey>Zackenberg Research Station, Northeastern Greenland</placekey>
        <placekey>Spitsbergen, Svalbard, Norway</placekey>
        <placekey>Harp, USSR</placekey>
        <placekey>Ogoturuk Creek, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Stordalen, Sweden</placekey>
        <placekey>La Perouse Bay, Manitoba, Canada</placekey>
        <placekey>Imnavait Creek, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Truelove Lowland, Devon island, Northwest Territories, Canada</placekey>
        <placekey>Bathurst Island, Canadian high arctic</placekey>
        <placekey>Zackenberg, Northeast Greenland</placekey>
        <placekey>Anaktuvuk Pass, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Barrow, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Sagwon Hills, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Snowden Mountain, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Cornwallis Island, Canadian High Arctic</placekey>
        <placekey>Atigun River, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Prudhoe Bay, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Skirhasjohka valley, Fennoscandia</placekey>
        <placekey>Prince of Wales, Canadian high arctic</placekey>
        <placekey>Brandalpynten, Knudsenheia peninsula, Spitsbergen, Norway</placekey>
        <placekey>Sibik, Eastern Siberia</placekey>
        <placekey>Sag River, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Stordalen mire, Abisko, Sweden</placekey>
        <placekey>Circle Hot Springs, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Cape Abernethy, King Christian Island, Western Queen Elizabeth Islands</placekey>
        <placekey>Samoylov, Lena Delta, Northern Siberia</placekey>
        <placekey>Ny-Alesund, Spitsbergen, Norway</placekey>
        <placekey>Bol'shoy Lyakhovsky Island</placekey>
        <placekey>Tanana River floodplain, Fairbanks, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Alexandra Fiord, Ellesmere Island, Nunavut, Canada</placekey>
        <placekey>Cape Thompson, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Eight Mile Lake, Healy, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Hardangervidda, Norway</placekey>
        <placekey>Churchhill, Manifoba, Canada</placekey>
        <placekey>King Christian Island, Canada</placekey>
        <placekey>Imnavait Creek watershed, Northern Foothills, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Kevo Sub-Arctic Research Institute, Finland</placekey>
        <placekey>Sagwon Bluff, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Old Man, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Abisko, Sweden</placekey>
        <placekey>Washington Creek, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Vorkuta city, Komi ASSR</placekey>
      </place>
      <stratum>
        <stratkey>Root zone</stratkey>
      </stratum>
      <theme>
        <themekt>root biomass</themekt>
        <themekey>Author_year</themekey>
        <themekey>Mycorrhizae</themekey>
        <themekey>PFT</themekey>
        <themekey>Project</themekey>
        <themekey>Root_depth_distribution</themekey>
        <themekey>Experimental_Manipulation</themekey>
        <themekey>Aerenchyma</themekey>
        <themekey>Soil_cores</themekey>
        <themekey>Longitude_Decimal</themekey>
        <themekey>Species</themekey>
        <themekey>Notes</themekey>
        <themekey>Ecosystem</themekey>
        <themekey>Study_Description</themekey>
        <themekey>B_A</themekey>
        <themekey>Journal_Book_Thesis</themekey>
        <themekey>Root_production</themekey>
        <themekey>Carbon_cycling</themekey>
        <themekey>Isotopic_tracer_stable_isotope</themekey>
        <themekey>Minirhizotrons</themekey>
        <themekey>Ingrowth_cores</themekey>
        <themekey>Review_Paper</themekey>
        <themekey>Soil monolith_Excavation</themekey>
        <themekey>Average_root diameter_mm</themekey>
        <themekey>Polygonal_topography</themekey>
        <themekey>Polar_desert</themekey>
        <themekey>Pot_Tiller</themekey>
        <themekey>Year_Initial</themekey>
        <themekey>Location_Place</themekey>
        <themekey>Root_morphology</themekey>
        <themekey>Elevation_m</themekey>
        <themekey>Maximum_rooting_depth_cm</themekey>
        <themekey>Study</themekey>
        <themekey>Publication_year</themekey>
        <themekey>Fineroot_Leaf</themekey>
        <themekey>Latitude_Decimal</themekey>
        <themekey>Root_standing_crop</themekey>
        <themekey>Nutrient_cycling</themekey>
        <themekey>Root_turnover_decomposition</themekey>
        <themekey>Environmental_forcing</themekey>
        <themekey>Degraded_permafrost</themekey>
        <themekey>Aboveground_biomass_g_m2</themekey>
        <themekey>Belowground_biomass_g_m2</themekey>
        <themekey>Year_Final</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>public</accconst>
    <useconst>No use constraints are associated with this data.</useconst>
    <datacred>Victoria L. Sloan, Patrick F. Sullivan, Eugenie S. Euskirchen, A. David McGuire, Richard J. Norby, Anthony P. Walker, Jeffrey M. Warren, Stan D. Wullschleger, The Next-Generation Ecosystem Experiments (NGEE Arctic) project is supported by the Office of Biological and Environmental Research in the U.S. Department of Energy Office of Science. Oak Ridge National Laboratory is managed by UT-Battelle, LLC, for the U.S. Department of Energy under contract DE-AC05-00OR22725.</datacred>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Colleen Iversen</cntper>
          <cntorg>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>One Bethel Valley Road</address>
          <city>Oak Ridge</city>
          <state>Tennessee</state>
          <postal>37831</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>865 241 3961</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>iversencm@ornl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <tool>
      <toolcont>
        <cntinfo>
          <cntaddr>
            <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          </cntaddr>
        </cntinfo>
      </toolcont>
    </tool>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <qattracc>
        <attraccv>No formal uncertainty assessments were conducted and no estimates of uncertainty are reported.</attraccv>
      </qattracc>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Data are considered of good quality in the context of the information presented in the abstract.  Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</logic>
    <complete>Data are considered complete in the context of the information presented in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>field</methtype>
        <methdesc>We undertook this review to better understand the response of tundra ecosystems to rapidly changing environmental conditions in the Arctic. Our primary goals were to highlight current knowledge of roots and their role in key ecosystem processes in arctic tundra, and to identify priority areas for future research. Additionally, we compared current experimental and observational knowledge with the representation of tundra roots in models used to simulate C and nutrient cycling in the Arctic.&amp;#xD;
		We systematically identified and compiled data on root traits and root-soil interactions in arctic tundra. We defined arctic tundra according to Walker et al. (2005): low-growing vegetation north of the Arctic treeline. Because data on roots in arctic tundra are scarce, we also included data from sites with similar plant species or plant communities (e.g., subarctic tundra in Abisko, Sweden and subalpine tundra in Eagle Creek, Alaska). Data were compiled from various sources, including primary literature, books, and theses.&amp;#xD;
		Our main focus in this literature review was on fine plant roots, which are an important component of ecosystem C and nutrient budgets because of their high respiration rates, high nutrient content, short lifespan relative to larger-diameter woody roots, and their role in stimulating microbial activity through the release of water and soluble exudates. Fine roots have generally been defined as less than 2 mm in diameter (Pregitzer, 2002), and we used that definition here because it was most appropriate to the available literature. Recently, the definition of fine roots has evolved to a more functional characterization, where fine roots are short-lived, non-woody roots whose main function is the uptake of nutrients and water from the soil (Guo et al., 2008). This functional definition is more relevant for understanding root processes and their representation in large-scale models, and we discuss how a next generation of measurements might improve our functional understanding of roots in tundra ecosystems.&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
References:&amp;#xD;
Guo DL, Li H, Mitchell RJ, Han WX, Hendricks JJ, Fahey TJ, Hendrick RL. 2008. Fine root heterogeneity by branch order: exploring the discrepancy in root turnover estimates between minirhizotron and carbon isotopic methods. New Phytologist 177: 443-456. doi: 10.1111/j.1469-8137.2007.02242.x&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Pregitzer, K. S. (2002), Fine roots of trees-a new perspective. New Phytologist, 154: 267-270. doi: 10.1046/j.1469-8137.2002.00413_1.x&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Walker, D. A., Raynolds, M. K., Daniels, F., J.A., Einarsson, E., Elvebakk, A., Gould, W. A., Katenin, A. E., Kholod, S. S., Markon, C. J., Melnikov, E. S., Moskalenko, N. G., Talbot, S. S., Yurtsev, B. A. and The other members of the CAVM Team (2005), The Circumpolar Arctic vegetation map. Journal of Vegetation Science, 16: 267-282. doi: 10.1111/j.1654-1103.2005.tb02365.x</methdesc>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>We systematically identified and compiled data on root traits and root-soil interactions in arctic tundra. We defined arctic tundra according to Walker et al. (2005): low-growing vegetation north of the Arctic treeline. Because data on roots in arctic tundra are scarce, we also included data from sites with similar plant species or plant communities (e.g., subarctic tundra in Abisko, Sweden and subalpine tundra in Eagle Creek, Alaska). Data were compiled from various sources, including primary literature, books, and theses.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
                 <cntinfo>
                                <cntperp>
                                        <cntper>Data Center Support</cntper>
                                        <cntorg>Next-Generation Ecosystem Experiments (NGEE) Arctic Project, Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
                                </cntperp>
                                <cntaddr>
                                        <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
                                        <address>1 Bethel Valley Road</address>
                                        <city>Oak Ridge</city>
                                        <state>TN</state>
                                        <postal>37831-6290</postal>
                                        <country>USA</country>
                                </cntaddr>
                                <cntvoice></cntvoice>
                                <cntfax></cntfax>
                                <cntemail>support@ngee.ornl.gov</cntemail>
                        </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150114</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Colleen Iversen</cntper>
          <cntorg>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Staff Scientist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>One Bethel Valley Road</address>
          <city>Oak Ridge</city>
          <state>Tennessee</state>
          <postal>37831</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>865 241 3961</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>iversencm@ornl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FDGC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata and
			Biological Data Profile</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FDGC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
  <ome>
    <datause>This review identifies information that is currently available for better testing and parameterization of root processes represented in arctic models, and these data can serve as the beginning of a tundra root trait database that could be expanded for future model benchmarking.</datause>
    <ome_status>approved</ome_status>
    <taskname>V</taskname>
  </ome>
</metadata>
