<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata><Source>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/metadata/Ground_Water_Levels_for_NGEE_Areas_A_B_C_and_D_Barrow_Alaska_2012_2014.xml</Source>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1183767</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/hydrology_and_geomorphology/Water_Levels_Barrow_Area_D_FINAL_Liljedahl_20150324.xlsx</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/hydrology_and_geomorphology/Water_Levels_Barrow_Area_B_FINAL_Liljedahl_20150324.xlsx</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp:/ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/hydrology_and_geomorphology/Water_Levels_Barrow_Area_A_FINAL_Liljedahl_20150324.xlsx</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/hydrology_and_geomorphology/Water_Levels_Barrow_Area_C_South_FINAL_Liljedahl_20150324.xlsx</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/hydrology_and_geomorphology/Water_Levels_Barrow_Area_C_North_FINAL_Liljedahl_20150324.xlsx</onlink>
        <origin>Anna Liljedahl (akliljedahl@alaska.edu)</origin>
        <origin>Cathy Wilson (cjw@lanl.gov)</origin>
        <title>Ground Water Levels for NGEE Areas A, B, C and D, Barrow, Alaska, 2012-2014</title>
        <geoform>In situ Field Measurements</geoform>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Ice wedge polygonal tundra water levels were measured at a total of 45 locations representing polygon centers and troughs during three summers. Early season water levels, which were still affected by ice and snow, are represented by manual measurements only. Continuous (&lt;hourly) measurements followed through early fall (~mid-Sep). The data set contains inundation depth (cm), absolute water level and local ground surface elevation (masl). Dataset DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1183767</abstract>
      <purpose>To understand spatiotemporal variations in water levels in ice wedge polygon tundra terrain.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20120501</begdate>
          <enddate>20150930</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>complete</progress>
      <update>n/a</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Intensive site 1</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-156.596662</westbc>
        <eastbc>-156.596662</eastbc>
        <northbc>71.282767</northbc>
        <southbc>71.282767</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Area D</placekey>
        <placekey>Area C</placekey>
        <placekey>Area B</placekey>
        <placekey>Area A</placekey>
        <placekey>Barrow Environmental Observatory (BEO)</placekey>
        <placekey>North Slope, Alaska</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Hydrology</themekt>
        <themekey>Water level</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>public</accconst>
    <datacred>Alexander Kholodov, Andrew Chamberlain, Hanna Lee, Ronald Daanen, Lily Cohen, Sarah Hayes, Go Iwahana, Anna Iverson, Hanna Lee, Tristan Weiss, Andrew Hoffman, Stan Wullschleger, Larry Hinzman, UMIAQ</datacred>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Anna Liljedahl</cntper>
          <cntorg>University of Alaska Fairbanks</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>PO Box 755910</address>
          <city>Fairbanks</city>
          <state>Alaska</state>
          <postal>99775</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>907-474-1951</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>akliljedahl@alaska.edu</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <tool>
      <toolcont>
        <cntinfo>
          <cntaddr>
            <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          </cntaddr>
        </cntinfo>
      </toolcont>
    </tool>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <qattracc>
        <attraccv>Note that the soft ground (moss), especially in troughs, makes it difficult to determine the true elevation of the ground surface within ~2 cm. &amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Manual measurements of water level were conducted periodically during all three seasons in order to establish a reference for calibration of the data loggers.&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
The well names and respective APPROXIMATE x and y coordinates are provided.</attraccv>
      </qattracc>
    </attracc>
    <logic>2012 and 2014 elevation surveys were conducted by placing survey rod on ground, reading elevation for ground surface, then reading distance from ground to mark to find mark elevation. 2013 elevation surveys were conducted by placing bottom of survey rod level with mark, reading elevation for mark, then measuring distance from ground to mark to find ground elevation.&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Latitude and longitude for all wells determined using DGPS EXCEPT wells CP1 and C-d, where a handheld GPS was used</logic>
    <complete>Area A: Wells QA1 and QA2 were not installed until the spring of 2013; hence, no 2012 data is available at these locations.  The diver in Well A14 was damaged during June 2013 during a freeze event and accordingly only manual measurements are presented. The diver in Well QA2 was damaged during June 2014 by being frozen into the thaw layer and accordingly only manual measurements are presented.&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Area B: The early-June 2013 cold event destroyed the Diver sensors in wells B70 and B71 (due to ice formation) and because of the water table being exceptionally low in these troughs, no manual measurements are available for the 2013 season. Well B67 is located in the center of a high-center ice wedge polygon. Hence the well was dry down to the frost table for most of the time during all three seasons, despite montly instrument adjustments as thaw progressed during the summer. Precipitation events, however, were observed to cause short-term accumulation of water in the well. The elevation of this water level is poorly calibrated for the 2013 season, as it was difficult to make a manual measurement of the water table at great depth during the periods of data collection, and should be considered approximate to ~ 5 cm. However, the 2014 data for the well is well calibrated due to an exceptionally high water period in late June of 2014. Instrument malfunction occurred in Well B64 during the 2014 season and accordingly only manual measurements are presented. Well QB1 was not installed until the spring of 2013; hence, no 2012 data is available at this location.&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Area C: Well CP1 was installed during the spring of 2013 and accordingly no data exists at this well for the 2012 season. Damage of an unknown nature seems to have occured to the Diver in Well C43 in July of 2014, resulting in a partially corrupted datafile, and accordingly only manual measurements are presented after July 10 of 2014 for that season. Well C39 was dry throughout July of 2012 to the depth of the Odyssey free weight and hence no data was collected during this period. The Odyssey in Well C31 produced questionable readings; the data for the 2012 season is accordingly incomplete and may contain erroneous data. Well C33 was installed in 2013 and the Diver used to measure water levels for the 2013 seasons was damaged by freezing. Accordingly, no data exists for 2012 and manual measurements are all that are available for 2013. Wells C-b, C-c, QC1, QC2, and QC3 were installed in 2013. All except for QC3 contained Divers through the 2013 season. However, the diver in C-b was damaged during this time. Well QC3 only contained a Diver during the 2014 season. Accordingly, no 2012 data is presented for any of these wells, and only 2014 Diver data for C-b and QC3.&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Area D: no issues to report.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>field</methtype>
        <methdesc>Manual measurements of water levels along with seasonally installed non-vented pressure transducers that were calibrated to manual measurements. &amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Wells were installed in early May 2012 and 2013 using a SiPRE corer or a 2 in auger. The wells were made by 1 1/4 in or 2 in diameter white PVC pipe  about 5 ft long with 1/4 in diameter holes drilled about 0.5 to 1 in apart in three transects along the side walls. The well was anchored about 1 ft into the permafrost by three bolts sticking out of the side of the PVC pipe about 0.5 to 1 cm. Manual water levels were measured as the distance from a mark near the top of the pipe to the water surface. The mark was made with a saw (~ 2cm long horizontal cut). Divers and Odyssey loggers were hung inside the pipe using a nylon string.&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Water level elevations are given as absolute elevation (meters above sea level) via a detailed level surveying (September of 2012, 2013, and 2014, and July of 2013) of each well to a known benchmark. The elevation survey was made using the digital level TopCon DL-502. Note that the soft ground (moss), especially in troughs, makes it difficult to determine the true elevation of the ground surface within ~2 cm. Well names are given in Table 1 and all surveyed elevations are given in Table 2. The averaged surveyed elevation for respective mark on each well was used to produce the presented continuous water level dataset.&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Water level fluctuations were determined using Odyssey conductivity loggers (2012) and Schlumberger "Diver" non-vented pressure transducers (2013 and 2014). Odysseys remained installed for the duration of the 3 seasons, while Divers were installed during June of 2013 and 2014. Divers were manually lowered on a sub-monthly basis (June and July) as the active layer thaw progressed and removed in September of 2013 and 2014. Manual measurements of water level were conducted periodically during all three seasons in order to establish a reference for calibration of the data loggers. &amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Water level elevations are given as absolute elevation (meters above sea level) via a detailed level surveying (September of 2012, 2013, and 2014, and July of 2013) of each well to a known benchmark.</methdesc>
      </method>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Data Center Support</cntper>
          <cntorg>Next-Generation Ecosystem Experiments (NGEE) Arctic Project, Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1 Bethel Valley Road</address>
          <city>Oak Ridge</city>
          <state>TN</state>
          <postal>37831-6290</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntemail>support@ngee.ornl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160202</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Anna Liljedahl</cntper>
          <cntorg>University of Alaska Fairbanks</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Research Assistant Professor</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>PO Box 755910</address>
          <city>Fairbanks</city>
          <state>Alaska</state>
          <postal>99775</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>907-474-1951</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>akliljedahl@alaska.edu</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FDGC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata and
			Biological Data Profile</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FDGC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
  <ome>
    <datause>The data is represented via a time series for respective well and its geographical location.</datause>
    <ome_status>approved</ome_status>
    <taskname>HG</taskname>
  </ome>
</metadata>
