<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata><Source>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/metadata/CT_Scans_of_Cores_Metadata_Barrow_2015.xml</Source>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1170517</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/hydrology_and_geomorphology/Kneafsey_ice_core_CTscans_2015</onlink>
        <origin>Tim Kneafsey (tjkneafsey@lbl.gov)</origin>
        <title>CT Scans of Cores Metadata, Barrow, Alaska 2015</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Individual ice cores were collected from Barrow Environmental Observatory in Barrow, Alaska, throughout 2013 and 2014. Cores were drilled along different transects to sample polygonal features (i.e. the trough, center and rim of high, transitional and low center polygons).  Most cores were drilled around 1 meter in depth and a few deep cores were drilled around 3 meters in depth. Three-dimensional images of the frozen cores were constructed using a medical X-ray computed tomography (CT) scanner. TIFF files can be uploaded to ImageJ (an open-source imaging software) to examine soil structure and densities within each core. doi:10.5440/1170517; http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1170517</abstract>
      <purpose>Data were collected to gain an increased understanding of the soil structure and hydrology of the Barrow site to build more accurate climate models to incorporate feedback loops of projected permafrost loss.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20130401</begdate>
          <enddate>20130630</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>ongoing</progress>
      <update>as needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>AB Trans, BD Trans, DTLB, Site 0, EC</descgeog>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Intensive site 0</placekey>
        <placekey>BD Transect</placekey>
        <placekey>AB Transect</placekey>
        <placekey>EC</placekey>
        <placekey>DTLB</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekt>X-ray</themekt>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>CT-computed Tomography</themekt>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>internal</accconst>
    <datacred>Tim Kneafsey (Geological Staff Scientist, Hydrogeology Department Head, Earth Sciences Division, LBNL), Craig Ulrich (Scientific Engineering Associate, LBNL)</datacred>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Tim Kneafsey</cntper>
          <cntorg>LBNL</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, 1 Cyclotron</address>
          <city>Berkeley</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>94720</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>510.486.4414</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>tjkneafsey@lbl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <tool>
      <toolcont>
        <cntinfo>
          <cntaddr>
            <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          </cntaddr>
        </cntinfo>
      </toolcont>
    </tool>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>both</methtype>
        <methdesc>Ice cores were collected from Barrow Environmental Observatory in Barrow, Alaska, in 2013 as part of the Next Generation Ecosystem Experiment (NGEE). Each core was drilled from a different location at varying depths. A few days after drilling, the cores were stored in coolers packed with dry ice and flown to Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory (LBNL) in Berkeley, CA. 3-dimensional images of the cores were constructed using a medical X-ray computed tomography (CT) scanner at 120kV. Images were reconstructed to resolutions of 2.56 pixels per millimeter.</methdesc>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Please refer to Excel metadata file to determine the date in which each core was scanned.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
    <cntinfo>
                                <cntperp>
                                        <cntper>Data Center Support</cntper>
                                        <cntorg>Next-Generation Ecosystem Experiments (NGEE) Arctic Project, Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
                                </cntperp>
                                <cntaddr>
                                        <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
                                        <address>1 Bethel Valley Road</address>
                                        <city>Oak Ridge</city>
                                        <state>TN</state>
                                        <postal>37831-6290</postal>
                                        <country>USA</country>
                                </cntaddr>
                                <cntvoice></cntvoice>
                                <cntfax></cntfax>
                                <cntemail>support@ngee.ornl.gov</cntemail>
                        </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150327</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Tim Kneafsey</cntper>
          <cntorg>LBNL</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Geological Staff Scientist, Hydrogeology Department Head</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, 1 Cyclotron</address>
          <city>Berkeley</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>94720</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>510.486.4414</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>tjkneafsey@lbl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FDGC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata and
			Biological Data Profile</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FDGC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
  <ome>
    <datause>The core structures may be correlated to polygonal patterned ground to scale up modeling of this Arctic landscape. The data could also be used to understand the hydrologic behaviors of this landscape. Specific coordinates, polygonal type and other important information to geolocate and characterize each core is available in the metadata Excel file online.</datause>
    <ome_status>approved</ome_status>
    <taskname>HG</taskname>
  </ome>
</metadata>
