<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata><Source>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/metadata/Digital_Elevation_Model_0_25_m_Barrow_Environmental_Observatory_Alaska_2013.xml</Source>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/landscape_characterization/2013_DEM_Barrow</onlink>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1224720</onlink>
        <origin>Cathy Wilson (cjw@lanl.gov)</origin>
        <origin>Garrett Altmann (gla@lanl.gov)</origin>
        <title>Digital Elevation Model, 0.25 m, Barrow Environmental Observatory, Alaska, 2013</title>
        <geoform>software and tools</geoform>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This 0.25m horizontal resolution digital elevation model, DEM, was developed from Airborne Laser Altimetry flown by Aerometric Inc, now known as Quantum Spatial, Inc. on 12 July, 2013. One Mission was flown and the data jointly processed with LANL personnel to produce a 0.25m DEM covering a region approximately 2.8km wide and 12.4km long extending from the coast above North Salt Lagoon to south of Gas Well Road. This DEM encompasses a diverse range of hydrologic, geomorphic, geophysical and biological features typical of the Barrow Peninsula. Vertical accuracy at the 95% confidence interval was computed as 0.143m. The coordinate system, datum, and geoid for this DEM are UTM Zone 4N, NAD83 (2011), NAVD88 (GEOID09). Dataset DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1224720</abstract>
      <purpose>0.25m LiDAR dataset acquired for an area near Barrow, Alaska on 12 July, 2013. Data were collected to improved characterization of key landscape elevation features such as polygonal terrain and hydrologic drainage features. This DEM encompasses a diverse range of hydrologic, geomorphic, geophysical and biological features typical of the Barrow Peninsula.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20130712</begdate>
          <enddate>20130712</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>complete</progress>
      <update>n/a</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Barrow, Alaska</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>584100</westbc>
        <eastbc>587100</eastbc>
        <northbc>7918600</northbc>
        <southbc>7906100</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Barrow, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Arctic Coastal Plain</placekey>
        <placekey>Barrow Environmental Observatory (BEO)</placekey>
        <placekey>Intensive site 0</placekey>
        <placekey>Intensive site 1</placekey>
        <placekey>DTLB-1</placekey>
        <placekey>DTLB-2</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Land Surface</themekt>
        <themekey>Topography</themekey>
        <themekey>TERRAIN ELEVATION</themekey>
        <themekey>DIGITAL ELEVATION/TERRAIN MODEL (DEM)</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>LIDAR</themekt>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Laser backscatter</themekt>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Elevation</themekt>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>internal</accconst>
    <useconst>Use of this data recommends the user collaborates with the NGEE LiDAR data PI, Cathy Wilson, and involve her as a co-author on presentations and publications resulting from its use. LA-UR-15-28483 (Los Alamos Unlimited Release Unclassified Document number)</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Cathy Wilson</cntper>
          <cntorg>Los Alamos National Laboratory</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>SM-30 Bikini Atoll Rd, MS-J495</address>
          <city>Los Alamos</city>
          <state>NM</state>
          <postal>87545</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>505-667-0202</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>cjw@lanl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <tool>
      <toolcont>
        <cntinfo>
          <cntaddr>
            <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          </cntaddr>
        </cntinfo>
      </toolcont>
    </tool>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <qattracc>
        <attraccv>Vertical accuracy at the 95% confidence interval was computed as 0.143m. The coordinate system, datum, and geoid for this DEM are UTM Zone 4N, NAD83 (2011), NAVD88 (GEOID09).</attraccv>
      </qattracc>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Aerometric provided further QC procedures involving the comparison of LiDAR data points with field-survey data to remove any atmospheric bias encountered during data collection.  This process involves statistically comparing the LiDAR "bare-earth" surface to collected ground survey data, determining and applying a vertical offset, and generating final statistics to determine the vertical accuracy of the data.  Contact data PI to obtain Aerometric statistical summary of the vertical accuracy results [file: Barrow_LiDAR_Vertical_Accuracy_Results.xls].</logic>
    <complete>No data missing.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>field</methtype>
        <methdesc>LiDAR data acquisition was completed on July 12, 2013. One mission was flown. The LiDAR data for this project was collected with the Aerometric Leica ALS-70 LiDAR system. All flight planning and acquisition was completed using Leica FPES. Aerometric used the following sensor acquisition settings. The flight altitude (above ground level) was 700 meters, laser pulse rate was 350 kHz, mirror scan frequency was 58 Hz, scan angle (+/-) was 40 degrees, side lap was 50 %, and ground speed was 150 kts.&amp;#xD;
The LiDAR data for this project was acquired in one mission. Airborne GPS and IMU data was collected during acquisition for use in determining the sensor's position. The mission included the acquisition of all planned project lines and cross flights. The cross flights were flown perpendicular to the planned flight lines and their data used in the in-situ calibration of the sensor. The mission was processed using Leica IPAS-TC software to determine both the airborne GNSS trajectory, and the blending of inertial data. Aerometric operated a GPS base station on location during the acquisition of this data. The position of the base station and raw GPS data were computed by Aerometric for use in processing.&amp;#xD;
The airborne GNSS/IMU post processed data along with the LiDAR raw measurements were processed using Leica IPAS-TC 3.1. This software was used to match the raw LiDAR measurements with the computed positions and attitudes of the LiDAR sensor. The result was a point cloud of LiDAR measured points referenced to the ground control system. One LAS 1.2 file was generated per flightline.</methdesc>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>We used 285 checkpoints acquired by UMIAQ to compute the vertical accuracy. The computed RMSE at the 95th percentile confidence interval was 0.143 meters, meeting the general LiDAR data vertical accuracy specifications. A mosaic was created using the 142 geotiff files produced by Aerometric to create a single 0.25 horizontal resolution DEM dataset.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20151020</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Data Center Support</cntper>
          <cntorg>Next-Generation Ecosystem Experiments (NGEE) Arctic Project, Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1 Bethel Valley Road</address>
          <city>Oak Ridge</city>
          <state>TN</state>
          <postal>37831-6290</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntemail>support@ngee.ornl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20151120</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Garrett Altmann</cntper>
          <cntorg>Los Alamos National Lab</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>SM-30 Bikini Atoll Rd, MS J-495</address>
          <city>Los Alamos</city>
          <state>NM</state>
          <postal>87545</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>505-606-1963</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>gla@lanl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FDGC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata and
			Biological Data Profile</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FDGC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
  <ome>
    <datause>This 0.25m DEM was produced in geotiff format using the UTM Zone 4N coordinate system with the NAD83 horizontal datum, and the NAVD88 (GEOID09) vertical datum.</datause>
    <ome_status>approved</ome_status>
    <taskname>LC</taskname>
  </ome>
</metadata>
