<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata><Source>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/metadata/Compiled_Multi_Lab_Geochemistry_Synoptic_Survey_LANL_ORNL_LBNL_Barrow_Alaska_2012.xml</Source>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1164833</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/biogeochemistry/Multilab_GeochemCompiled_2013-10.xlsx</onlink>
        <origin>Heather Throckmorton (hthrockmorton@lanl.gov)</origin>
        <origin>Brent Newman (bnewman@lanl.gov)</origin>
        <title>Compiled Multi-Lab Geochemistry Synoptic Survey (LANL, ORNL, LBNL), Barrow, Alaska; 2012</title>
        <geoform>software and tools</geoform>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Polygonal ground is a signature characteristic of the Arctic, and permafrost thaw can potentially generate substantial feedbacks to Arctic ecosystems and climate. This study describes the first comprehensive spatial examination of active layer biogeochemistry that extends across high- and low-centered polygons and their features, including depth. Water chemistry measurements were made on active layer water samples collected near Barrow, Alaska during summer, 2012. Several significant differences in chemistry were observed between high- and low-centered polygons suggesting polygon types may be useful for landscape-scale geochemical classification. However, differences were found for polygon features (centers and troughs) for analytes that were not significant for type, suggesting that finer scale features control biogeochemistry in a different way than polygon type. Depth variations were also significant, demonstrating important multi-dimensional aspects of polygonal ground biogeochemistry. These results have major implications for understanding how polygonal ground ecosystems function, and how they may respond to future change. DOI 10.5440/1164833; http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1164833.</abstract>
      <purpose>To assess the effects of microtopography and depth on ground water geochemistry in arctic polygonal terrain.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20120718</begdate>
          <enddate>20120914</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>complete</progress>
      <update>n/a</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-157.829589841</westbc>
        <eastbc>-155.85205077858</eastbc>
        <northbc>71.356926683007</northbc>
        <southbc>70.89493473556</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Barrow, Alaska</placekey>
      </place>
      <stratum>
        <stratkey>Cryosphere: polygons</stratkey>
      </stratum>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Anions</themekt>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Cations</themekt>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Carbon</themekt>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Dissolved oxygen</themekt>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Soil pore water</themekt>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Geochemistry</themekt>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>internal</accconst>
    <datacred>ORNL; LLNL; LANL</datacred>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Heather Throckmorton</cntper>
          <cntorg>Los Alamos National Lab</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Bikini Atoll Rd.</address>
          <city>Los Alamos</city>
          <state>New Mexico</state>
          <postal>87545</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntemail>hthrockmorton@lanl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <tool>
      <toolcont>
        <cntinfo>
          <cntaddr>
            <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          </cntaddr>
        </cntinfo>
      </toolcont>
    </tool>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <logic>Biases among the three different laboratories in sampling, processing, preservation and/or laboratory analyses were assessed to verify that samples could be directly compared across laboratories. &amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Outliers were determined using Grubbs Test for Outliers, and removed.&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Correlation table (Samples NOT included as follows): &amp;#xD;
LANL: estuary/ drainage samples&amp;#xD;
LANL TOC&amp;#xD;
ORNL: all cations&amp;#xD;
ORNL: HCl sample NGALL0002_00&amp;#xD;
ORNL high Cl points for anions (Cl, NO3, PO4, SO4): outliers- NGALL0005_00 and NGALL0006_00&amp;#xD;
LBL outlier for cations: TP2_1_25CM&amp;#xD;
Also trace analytes excluded</logic>
    <complete>NA</complete>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>both</methtype>
        <methdesc>Surface waters were collected as grab samples. Collection of subsurface water samples was often challenging, and multiple methods were used for sampling (see Supplementary Information). Samples were classified by three factors: polygon feature (center or trough of a polygon); polygon type (high-centered- or low-centered polygon); and depth. A few low-center rims were sampled, but not enough for robust statistics. Troughs form the surface drainage network in both high- and low-centered polygons. One hundred and twenty one samples were collected from early July through mid-September, 2012. Sample locations are shown in Figure 1. Standard water chemistry preservation and analytical techniques were used, and determinations were made for 54 different analytes.</methdesc>
      </method>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
    <cntinfo>
                                <cntperp>
                                        <cntper>Data Center Support</cntper>
                                        <cntorg>Next-Generation Ecosystem Experiments (NGEE) Arctic Project, Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
                                </cntperp>
                                <cntaddr>
                                        <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
                                        <address>1 Bethel Valley Road</address>
                                        <city>Oak Ridge</city>
                                        <state>TN</state>
                                        <postal>37831-6290</postal>
                                        <country>USA</country>
                                </cntaddr>
                                <cntvoice></cntvoice>
                                <cntfax></cntfax>
                                <cntemail>support@ngee.ornl.gov</cntemail>
                        </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150106</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Heather Throckmorton</cntper>
          <cntorg>Los Alamos National Laboratory</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Postdoctoral researcher</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Bikini Atoll Rd.</address>
          <city>Los Alamos</city>
          <state>New Mexico</state>
          <postal>87545</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>505-606-1641</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>hthrockmorton@lanl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FDGC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata and
			Biological Data Profile</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FDGC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
  <ome>
    <ome_status>approved</ome_status>
    <taskname>BGC</taskname>
  </ome>
</metadata>
