<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata><Source>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/metadata/Representativeness_based_Sampling_Network_Design_for_the_State_of_Alaska.xml</Source>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1108686</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/landscape_characterization/Hoffman_LandscapeEcology_2013/</onlink>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10980-013-9902-0</onlink>
        <origin>Jitendra Kumar (jkumar@climatemodeling.org)</origin>
        <origin>William W. Hargrove (hnw@geobabble.org)</origin>
        <origin>Richard T. Mills (rmills@ornl.gov)</origin>
        <origin>Forrest M. Hoffman (forrest@climatemodeling.org)</origin>
        <pubdate>20130601</pubdate>
        <title>Representativeness-based Sampling Network Design for the State of Alaska</title>
        <geoform>GIS Products</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Landscape Ecology</pubplace>
          <publish>Springer</publish>
        </pubinfo>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This data set collection consists of data products described in Hoffman et. al., 2013.&amp;#xD;
Hoffman, Forrest M., Jitendra Kumar, Richard T. Mills, and William W. Hargrove. October 1, 2013. Representativeness-based Sampling Network Design for the State of Alaska. Landscape Ecology, 28(8):1567-1586. doi:10.1007/s10980-013-9902-0&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Abstract:&amp;#xD;
Resource and logistical constraints limit the frequency and extent of environmental observations, particularly in the Arctic, necessitating the development of a systematic sampling strategy to maximize coverage and objectively represent environmental variability at desired scales. A quantitative methodology for stratifying sampling domains, informing site selection, and determining the representativeness of measurement sites and networks is described here. Multivariate spatiotemporal clustering was applied to down-scaled general circulation model results and data for the State of Alaska at 4 km2 resolution to define multiple sets of ecoregions across two decadal time periods. Maps of ecoregions for the present (2000-2009) and future (2090-2099) were produced, showing how combinations of 37 characteristics are distributed and how they may shift in the future. Representative sampling locations are identified on present and future ecoregion maps. A representativeness metric was developed, and representativeness maps for eight candidate sampling locations were produced. This metric was used to characterize the environmental similarity of each site. This analysis provides model-inspired insights into optimal sampling strategies, offers a framework for up-scaling measurements, and provides a down-scaling approach for integration of models and measurements. These techniques can be applied at different spatial and temporal scales to meet the needs of individual measurement campaigns. doi.org/10.5440/1108686</abstract>
      <purpose>Resource and logistical constraints limit the frequency and extent of environmental observations, particularly in the Arctic, necessitating the development of a systematic sampling strategy to maximize coverage and objectively represent environmental variability at desired scales. A quantitative methodology for stratifying sampling domains, informing site selection, and determining the representativeness of measurement sites and networks is described here. Multivariate spatiotemporal clustering was applied to down-scaled general circulation model results and data for the State of Alaska at 4 km2 resolution to define multiple sets of ecoregions across two decadal time periods. Maps of ecoregions for the present (2000-2009) and future (2090-2099) were produced, showing how combinations of 37 characteristics are distributed and how they may shift in the future. Representative sampling locations are identified on present and future ecoregion maps. A representativeness metric was developed, and representativeness maps for eight candidate sampling locations were produced. This metric was used to characterize the environmental similarity of each site. This analysis provides model-inspired insights into optimal sampling strategies, offers a framework for up-scaling measurements, and provides a down-scaling approach for integration of models and measurements. These techniques can be applied at different spatial and temporal scales to meet the needs of individual measurement campaigns.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20130601</begdate>
          <enddate>20130601</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>complete</progress>
      <update>n/a</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>State of Alaska</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-180</westbc>
        <eastbc>-129.3</eastbc>
        <northbc>71.4</northbc>
        <southbc>50.9</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Alaska</placekey>
      </place>
      <stratum>
        <stratkey>Landscape</stratkey>
      </stratum>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Ecoregions</themekt>
        <themekey>Ecoregions</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>public</accconst>
    <useconst>Appropriate credits/co-authorship to the authors along with citation of the original paper.</useconst>
    <datacred>Next Generation Ecosystem Experiments (NGEE) - Arctic; Biological and Environmental Research Division of US Department of Energy</datacred>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Jitendra Kumar</cntper>
          <cntorg>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>One Bethel Valley Road, PO Box 2008, MS-6301</address>
          <city>Oak Ridge</city>
          <state>TN</state>
          <postal>37831</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>864-574-9467</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jkumar@climatemodeling.org</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <tool>
      <toolcont>
        <cntinfo>
          <cntaddr>
            <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          </cntaddr>
        </cntinfo>
      </toolcont>
    </tool>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <qattracc>
        <attraccv>No formal uncertainty assessments were conducted and no estimates of uncertainty are reported.</attraccv>
      </qattracc>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Data are considered of good quality in the context of the information presented in the abstract.  Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</logic>
    <complete>Data are considered complete in the context of the information presented in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>field</methtype>
        <methdesc>Methods applied for development of this data set has been described in the Hoffman et. al., 2013.&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Hoffman, Forrest M., Jitendra Kumar, Richard T. Mills, and William W. Hargrove. October 1, 2013. Representativeness-based Sampling Network Design for the State of Alaska. Landscape Ecology, 28(8):1567-1586. doi:10.1007/s10980-013-9902-0</methdesc>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Hoffman, F.M., J. Kumar, R.T. Mills, and W. W. Hargrove</origin>
            <pubdate>20131001</pubdate>
            <title>Representativeness-based Sampling Network Design for the State of Alaska</title>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
      </method>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
                       <cntinfo>
                                <cntperp>
                                        <cntper>Data Center Support</cntper>
                                        <cntorg>Next-Generation Ecosystem Experiments (NGEE) Arctic Project, Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
                                </cntperp>
                                <cntaddr>
                                        <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
                                        <address>1 Bethel Valley Road</address>
                                        <city>Oak Ridge</city>
                                        <state>TN</state>
                                        <postal>37831-6290</postal>
                                        <country>USA</country>
                                </cntaddr>
                                <cntvoice></cntvoice>
                                <cntfax></cntfax>
                                <cntemail>support@ngee.ornl.gov</cntemail>
                        </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150204</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Jitendra Kumar</cntper>
          <cntorg>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>One Bethel Valley Road, PO Box 2008, MS-6301</address>
          <city>Oak Ridge</city>
          <state>TN</state>
          <postal>37831</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>865-574-9467</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jkumar@climatemodeling.org</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FDGC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata and
			Biological Data Profile</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FDGC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
  <ome>
    <ome_status>submit</ome_status>
  </ome>
</metadata>
