<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata><Source>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/metadata/CO2_and_CH4_fluxes_for_8_polygon_geomorphic_types_Barrow_Alaska_2008_2010.xml</Source>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/CO2_CH4_fluxes_across_polygon_geomorphic_types/data</onlink>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1156852</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/CO2_CH4_fluxes_across_polygon_geomorphic_types/documentation</onlink>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/gcb.12757</onlink>
        <origin>Mark J. Lara (mjlara@alaska.edu)</origin>
        <origin>Craig E. Tweedie (ctweedie@utep.edu)</origin>
        <pubdate>20140909</pubdate>
        <title>CO2 and CH4 Fluxes across Polygon Geomorphic Types, Barrow, Alaska, 2006-2010</title>
        <geoform>In situ Field Measurements</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Global Change Biology</pubplace>
          <publish>Wiley</publish>
        </pubinfo>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Carbon flux data are reported as Net Ecosystem Exchange (NEE), Gross Ecosystem Exchange (GEE), Ecosystem Respiration (ER), and Methane (CH4) flux. Measurements were made at 82 plots across various polygon geomorphic classes at research sites on the Barrow Environmental Observatory (BEO), the Biocomplexity Experiment site on the BEO, and the International Biological Program (IBP) site a little west of the BEO. ArcView GIS files available of the Land Cover Type Classifications. Dataset doi:10.5440/1156852&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
This product is a compilation of data from 27 plots as presented in Lara et al. (2012), data from six plots presented in Olivas et al. (2010); and from 49 plots described in (Lara et al. 2014).  Measurements were made during the peak of the growing seasons during 2006 to 2010.&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
At each of the measurement plots (except Olivas et al., 2010) four different thicknesses of shade cloth were used to generate CO2 light response curves. Light response curves were used to normalize photosynthetically active radiation that is diurnally variable to a peak growing season average ~400 umolm-2sec-1. At the Olivas et al. (2010) plots, diurnal patterns were characterized by repeated sampling.  CO2 measurements were made using a closed-chamber photosynthesis system and CH4 measurements were made using a photo-acoustic multi-gas analyzer.&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
In addition, plot-level measurements for thaw depth (TD), water table depth (WTD), leaf area index (LAI), and normalized difference vegetation index (NDVI) are summarized by geomorphic polygon type.&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Lara et al. 2014&amp;#xD;
Lara MJ, McGuire AD, Euskirchen ES, Tweedie CE, Hinkel KM, Skurikhin AN, Romanovsky VE, Grosse G, Bolton WR, Genet H (2014) Polygonal tundra geomorphological change in response to warming alters future CO2 and CH4 flux on the Barrow Peninsula. Global Change Biology. DOI: 10.1111/gcb.12757&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Lara et al. 2012&amp;#xD;
Lara MJ, Villarreal S, Johnson DR, Hollister RD, Webber PJ, Tweedie CE (2012) Estimated change in tundra ecosystem function near Barrow, Alaska between 1972 and 2010. Environmental Research Letters, 7. http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/7/1/015507 &amp;#xD;
 &amp;#xD;
Olivas et al. 2010&amp;#xD;
Olivas PC, Oberbauer SF, Tweedie C, Oechel WC, Lin D, Kuchy A (2011) Effects of Fine-Scale Topography on CO2 Flux Components of Alaskan Coastal Plain Tundra: Response to Contrasting Growing Seasons. Arctic Antarctic and Alpine Research, 43, 256-266. http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2009JG001254</abstract>
      <purpose>Data were collected to characterize plant community/geomorphic type ecosystem function, to estimate/model the impact of plant community/landscape change over time.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20060725</begdate>
          <enddate>20100810</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>complete</progress>
      <update>n/a</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>BEO, Biocomplexity Experiment, and International Biological Program, Barrow</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>71.329029927053</westbc>
        <eastbc>-156.69490813938</eastbc>
        <northbc>-156.49715423313</northbc>
        <southbc>71.250616415666</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>North Slope, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Arctic</placekey>
        <placekey>Barrow Environmental Observatory (BEO)</placekey>
        <placekey>Barrow, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>International Biological Program research site</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Net Ecosystem Exchange</themekt>
        <themekey>NEE</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Gross Ecosystem Exchange</themekt>
        <themekey>GEE</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Ecosystem Respiration</themekt>
        <themekey>ER</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Methane Flux</themekt>
        <themekey>CH4 flux</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Carbon Dioxide equivalence</themekt>
        <themekey>C-CO2eq</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Thaw Depth</themekt>
        <themekey>TD</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Water Table Depth</themekt>
        <themekey>WTD</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Normalized Difference Vegetation Index</themekt>
        <themekey>NDVI</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>public</accconst>
    <useconst>No use constraints are associated with this data.</useconst>
    <datacred>Support: NGEE-arctic, Department of Energy; and IPY-BTF, National Science Foundation</datacred>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Mark J. Lara</cntper>
          <cntorg>University of Alaska Fairbanks</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>902 Koyukuk Dr.</address>
          <city>Fairbanks</city>
          <state>Alaska</state>
          <postal>99775</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>9152404277</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>mjlara@alaska.edu</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <tool>
      <toolcont>
        <cntinfo>
          <cntaddr>
            <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          </cntaddr>
        </cntinfo>
      </toolcont>
    </tool>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <qattracc>
        <attraccv>Data uncertainty is estimated in the manuscript Lara et al. 2014 in review.</attraccv>
      </qattracc>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Data are considered of good quality in the context of the information presented in the abstract.  Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.&amp;#xD;
Specific to carbon fluxes:&amp;#xD;
QA/QC of CO2 fluxes closely followed that noted in Oberbauer et al. 2007&amp;#xD;
QA/QC of CH4 fluxes closely followed that noted in Sachs et al. 2010 and Lund et al. 2009 &amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Lund et al. 2009&amp;#xD;
Lund M, Christensen T R, Mastepanov M, Lindroth A and Strom L 2009. Effects of N and P fertilization on the greenhouse gas exchange in two northern peatlands with contrasting N deposition rates. Biogeosciences. 6 2135-2144.&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Oberbauer et al. 2007&amp;#xD;
Oberbauer S F et al. 2007. Tundra CO2 fluxes in response to experimental warming across latitudinal and moisture gradients. Ecological Monograph. 77(2) 221-238. &amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
Sachs et al. 2010&amp;#xD;
Sachs T, Giebels M, Boike J and Kutzbach L. 2010. Environmental controls on CH4 emission from polygonal tundra on the microsite scale in the Lena river delta, Siberia. Global Change Biology. 16(11) 3096-3110.</logic>
    <complete>Data are considered complete in the context of the information presented in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>field</methtype>
        <methdesc>Land-atmosphere CO2 fluxes were measured using a LI-COR 6200 Photosynthesis System (LI-COR Inc., Lincoln, NB, USA), and four different thicknesses of shade cloth from which ecosystem light response curves were generated. Calculations of net ecosystem CO2 exchange (NEE), ecosystem respiration (ER), and gross ecosystem exchange (GEE) were made following Oberbauer et al (2007). Methane (CH4) flux was measured using a photo-acoustic multi-gas analyzer (INNOVA 1312 AirTech Instruments A/S, Denmark; sensu Lund et al 2009, Sachs et al 2010) and processed following (Lund et al 2009). (see data quality for citations)</methdesc>
      </method>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Data Center Support</cntper>
          <cntorg>Next-Generation Ecosystem Experiments (NGEE) Arctic Project, Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1 Bethel Valley Road</address>
          <city>Oak Ridge</city>
          <state>TN</state>
          <postal>37831-6290</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntemail>support@ngee.ornl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160527</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Mark Lara</cntper>
          <cntorg>University of Alaska Fairbanks</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Post doctoral research fellow</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>902 Koyukuk Dr.</address>
          <city>Fairbanks</city>
          <state>Alaska</state>
          <postal>99775</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>9152404277</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>mjlara@alaska.edu</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FDGC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata and
			Biological Data Profile</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FDGC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
  <ome>
    <datause>GPS coordinates are provided for each of the 82 measured plot. In addition a category for each tundra geomorphic unit is provided. These data can add to other datasets collected to better characterize carbon fluxes, water table depths, thaw depth, and leaf area index by geomorphic type.</datause>
    <ome_status>approved</ome_status>
    <taskname>BGC</taskname>
  </ome>
</metadata>
