<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata><Source>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/metadata/Subsurface_Temperature_Moisture_Thermal_Conductivity_and_Heat_Flux_Barrow_Area_A_B_C_D.xml</Source>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1126515</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/hydrology_and_geomorphology/romanovsky_subsurface</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/hydrology_and_geomorphology/view/</onlink>
        <origin>Vladimir Romanovsky (veromanovsky@alaska.edu)</origin>
        <origin>William Cable (wlcable@alaska.edu)</origin>
        <title>Subsurface Temperature, Moisture, Thermal Conductivity and Heat Flux, Barrow, Area A, B, C, D</title>
        <geoform>In situ Field Measurements</geoform>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Subsurface temperature data are being collected along a transect from the center of the polygon through the trough (and to the center of the adjacent polygon for Area D).  Each transect has five 1.5m vertical array thermistor probes with 16 thermistors each.  This dataset also includes soil pits that have been instrumented for temperature, water content, thermal conductivity, and heat flux at the permafrost table. Area C has a shallow borehole of 2.5 meters depth is instrumented in the center of the polygon.  doi:10.5440/1126515, http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1126515</abstract>
      <purpose>These data are being collected to better understand the thermal dynamics of the active layer and permafrost.  The data could also be used as supporting measurements for other research and modeling activities.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20120909</begdate>
          <enddate>20140930</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>ongoing</progress>
      <update>annually</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Intensive site 1</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-156.596662</westbc>
        <eastbc>-156.596662</eastbc>
        <northbc>71.282767</northbc>
        <southbc>71.282767</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Area D</placekey>
        <placekey>Area B</placekey>
        <placekey>Area A</placekey>
        <placekey>Area C</placekey>
        <placekey>Barrow, Alaska</placekey>
      </place>
      <stratum>
        <stratkey>Active Layer; Permafrost</stratkey>
      </stratum>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Subsurface Temperature Transect</themekt>
        <themekey>VATP</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Soil moisture</themekt>
        <themekey>VWC</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Thermal Conductivity</themekt>
        <themekey>ThermCond</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Permafrost Heat Flux</themekt>
        <themekey>HeatFlux</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Soil Temperature</themekt>
        <themekey>Tsoil</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Shallow Borehole Temperature</themekt>
        <themekey>Tdeep</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>internal</accconst>
    <useconst>No use constraints are associated with this data.</useconst>
    <datacred>Bob Busey (rcbusey@alaska.edu)</datacred>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Vladimir Romanovsky</cntper>
          <cntorg>University of Alaska Fairbanks, Geophysical Institute</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>903 Koyukuk Dr.</address>
          <city>Fairbanks</city>
          <state>AK</state>
          <postal>99712</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>907-474-7459</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>veromanovsky@alaska.edu</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <tool>
      <toolcont>
        <cntinfo>
          <cntaddr>
            <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          </cntaddr>
        </cntinfo>
      </toolcont>
    </tool>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <qattracc>
        <attraccv>No formal uncertainty assessments were conducted and no estimates of uncertainty are reported.</attraccv>
      </qattracc>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Data are considered of good quality in the context of the information presented in the abstract.  Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</logic>
    <complete>Data are considered complete in the context of the information presented in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>field</methtype>
        <methdesc>Instrumentation was installed in September of 2012 and consists of:&amp;#xD;
* 5 Vertical Array Thermistor Probes with 16 thermistors each (see http://permafrost.gi.alaska.edu/content/thermistor-probe-construction).  These probes are arranged in a transect across the polygon.&amp;#xD;
* 1 Shallow Borehole is instrumented with a thermistor string (see http://permafrost.gi.alaska.edu/content/thermistor-string-construction).&amp;#xD;
* 2 Soil Pits in the active layer containing:&amp;#xD;
** 3 additional thermistors.&amp;#xD;
** 3 Hydra Probes (http://www.stevenswater.com/catalog/stevensProduct.aspx?SKU='93640').&amp;#xD;
** 3 Thermal Conductivity Probes (http://www.east30sensors.com/conductivity.php).&amp;#xD;
** 1 Heat Flux Plate installed on the permafrost table (http://www.hukseflux.com/product/hfp01).&amp;#xD;
* These sensors are all connected to a CR1000 in conjunction with the meteorological measurements.</methdesc>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Instruments are measured every 10 minutes and hourly averages are computed and stored on the datalogger.  The exception to this is the Thermal Conductivity probes which are measured daily and the raw data is stored for offline processing.</procdesc>
        <procdate>continuous</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data are collected hourly using Loggernet and the data are then automatically imported into Vista Data Vision for immediate viewing via the internet (http://lapland.gi.alaska.edu/vdv/index.html).  At this point the data have not been inspected or QCed so they should be considered provisional.</procdesc>
        <procdate>hourly</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>The thermal conductivity data are processed automatically using a Matlab script and then added to the Vista Data Vision database.</procdesc>
        <procdate>daily</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>As needed the data in the Vista Data Vision database are visually inspected and QCed.  Data can then be downloaded from the Vista Data Vision interface using the NGEE login.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Annually or more frequently if needed, output files are generated from the database.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
                 <cntinfo>
                                <cntperp>
                                        <cntper>Data Center Support</cntper>
                                        <cntorg>Next-Generation Ecosystem Experiments (NGEE) Arctic Project, Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
                                </cntperp>
                                <cntaddr>
                                        <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
                                        <address>1 Bethel Valley Road</address>
                                        <city>Oak Ridge</city>
                                        <state>TN</state>
                                        <postal>37831-6290</postal>
                                        <country>USA</country>
                                </cntaddr>
                                <cntvoice></cntvoice>
                                <cntfax></cntfax>
                                <cntemail>support@ngee.ornl.gov</cntemail>
                        </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150506</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>William Cable</cntper>
          <cntorg>University of Alaska Fairbanks, Geophysical Institute</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Research Professional</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>903 Koyukuk Dr.</address>
          <city>Fairbanks</city>
          <state>AK</state>
          <postal>99712</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>303-351-1105</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>wlcable@alaska.edu</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FDGC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata and
			Biological Data Profile</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FDGC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
  <ome>
    <datause>The data are supplied in a ascii csv file with header.  It should be noted that the time is in UTC and not local time.  Units of the variables are given in the header of the file. Empty cells indicate a gap in data, bad data that has been removed, or data that doesn't exist.  No gap filling has been done.</datause>
    <ome_status>approved</ome_status>
    <taskname>HG</taskname>
  </ome>
</metadata>
