<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata><Source>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/metadata/Soil_Physicochemical_Characteristics_from_Ice_Wedge_Polygons_Barrow_Alaska_Ver_1.xml</Source>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/BGC_soil_core_descriptions_2012-2013_physicochemical_properties/documentation</onlink>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1109232</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/BGC_soil_core_descriptions_2012-2013_physicochemical_properties/data</onlink>
        <origin>Taniya RoyChowdhury (rctaniya@gmail.com)</origin>
        <origin>David Graham (grahamde@ornl.gov)</origin>
        <title>Soil Physicochemical Characteristics from Ice Wedge Polygons, Barrow, Alaska, Ver. 1</title>
        <geoform>Laboratory Analysis</geoform>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This dataset provides details about soil cores (active layer and permafrost) collected from ice-wedge polygons during field expeditions to Barrow Environmental Observatory, Alaska in April, 2012 and 2013. Core information available are exact core locations; soil horizon descriptions and characteristics; and fundamental soil physico-chemical properties. In February 2016, two columns  (carbon and carbon:nitrogen in soil layer) were added to the data but no existing data values changed. See documentation. The new filename is version 2. In July 2016, data for two soil cores were added. The new filename is version 3. doi:10.5440/1109232, http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1109232</abstract>
      <purpose>This dataset can contribute towards creating an extensive database of soil properties of the intensive study sites (Areas A, B, C) of NGEE-Arctic; the detailed metadata will also be valuable to all studies based in the Arctic that have soil as an integral component; e.g. Soil Biogeochemistry, Microbiology, Hydrology to list a few.&amp;#xD;
&amp;#xD;
BGC1.3       Representative soil property data for subsurface modules</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20120412</begdate>
          <enddate>20130416</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>ongoing</progress>
      <update>as needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Intensive site 1</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-156.596662</westbc>
        <eastbc>-156.596662</eastbc>
        <northbc>71.282767</northbc>
        <southbc>71.282767</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Area B</placekey>
        <placekey>Intensive site 1</placekey>
        <placekey>Barrow, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Area C</placekey>
        <placekey>Area A</placekey>
        <placekey>North Slope, Alaska</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Soil characteristics</themekt>
        <themekey>SOIL PH</themekey>
        <themekey>SOIL CLASSIFICATION</themekey>
        <themekey>SOIL COLOR</themekey>
        <themekey>SOIL MOISTURE/WATER CONTENT</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>public</accconst>
    <useconst>No use constraints are associated with this data.</useconst>
    <datacred>Elizabeth Herndon (herndonem@ornl.gov)</datacred>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Taniya RoyChowdhury</cntper>
          <cntorg>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1 Bethel valley Road, MS 6038</address>
          <city>Oak Ridge</city>
          <state>TN</state>
          <postal>37831</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>865-241-2408</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>roychowdhurt@ornl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <tool>
      <toolcont>
        <cntinfo>
          <cntaddr>
            <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          </cntaddr>
        </cntinfo>
      </toolcont>
    </tool>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <qattracc>
        <attraccv>Yes. Standard deviations were obtained for each replicated measurement (n = 3) and values of standard deviations will be included</attraccv>
      </qattracc>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Yes, data is checked for inconsistent values and there are none found.</logic>
    <complete>Data are considered complete in the context of the information presented in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>lab</methtype>
        <methdesc>Intact frozen soil cores were processed and sampled under sterile and anoxic conditions in a vinyl anaerobic chamber (Coy Laboratory Products Inc., MI, U.S.A.) with a N2 atmosphere containing at least 1.00 % H2 and less than 1 ppm O2. Soil cores were extruded from their PVC liners and placed on sterilized photo papers upon frozen blue ice packs to limit thawing. A sterilized stainless steel spatula was used to scrape the partially thawed outer surface (1 - 2 mm) of a core, removing any sloughed material or soil displaced during drilling (Kieft, 2007). Soil horizons were visually diagnosed based on moist soil Munsell color, presence of undecomposed (Oa) or intermediately decomposed (Oe) plant-derived organic matter and presence or absence of permafrost affected soil or ice wedge segregations (Table 1). Soil cores were then divided by horizons and subsequent homogenization and subsampling was carried out one horizon at a time. The remaining soil horizons were kept intact and frozen at -20 deg C. Each soil horizon was divided into 5 to 10 cm thick sections, placed in a sterilized plastic container, and homogenized at constant room temperature under anoxic conditions allowing for minimal thawing. An oscillating power tool with sterilized cutting blades was used for all sediment processing and homogenization and containers were kept on blue icepacks. Homogenized subsamples were used for soil physico-chemical property determination and microcosm set-up.</methdesc>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Kieft, T.L., Phelps, T.J., Fredrickson, J.K.,</origin>
            <pubdate>2007</pubdate>
            <title>Drilling, coring, and sampling subsurface environments: in Manual of Environmental Microbiology, Hurst, C.J., Crawford, R.L., Garland, J.L., Lipson, D.A., Mills, A.L., and Stetzenbach, L.D. (eds) : ASM Pres</title>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
      </method>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Data Center Support</cntper>
          <cntorg>Next-Generation Ecosystem Experiments (NGEE) Arctic Project, Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1 Bethel Valley Road</address>
          <city>Oak Ridge</city>
          <state>TN</state>
          <postal>37831-6290</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntemail>support@ngee.ornl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20160822</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Taniya RoyChowdhury</cntper>
          <cntorg>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Postdoctoral Research Associate</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1 Bethel valley Road, MS 6038</address>
          <city>Oak Ridge</city>
          <state>TN</state>
          <postal>37831</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>865-241-2408</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>roychowdhurt@ornl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FDGC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata and
			Biological Data Profile</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FDGC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
  <ome>
    <datause>As a reference dataset or for meta-analyses of polygonal Tundra soil properties</datause>
    <ome_status>approved</ome_status>
    <taskname>BGC</taskname>
  </ome>
</metadata>
