<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata><Source>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/metadata/Frost_Tables_Barrow_Alaska_NGEE_Areas_B_C_and_D_for_2012_2013_2014_Final_Version_20150312.xml</Source>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/hydrology_and_geomorphology/FINAL_Frost_Tables_NGEE_Area_C_Liljedahl_v20150325.xlsx</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/hydrology_and_geomorphology/FINAL_Frost_Tables_NGEE_Area_B_Liljedahl_v20150325.xlsx</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/hydrology_and_geomorphology/FINAL_Frost_Tables_NGEE_Area_D_Liljedahl_v20150325.xlsx</onlink>
        <origin>Anna Liljedahl (akliljedahl@alaska.edu)</origin>
        <title>Frost Tables, Barrow, Alaska, NGEE Areas B, C and D for 2012, 2013, 2014, Final Version, 20150312</title>
        <geoform>In situ Field Measurements</geoform>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This dataset represent spatially intensive thaw depth surveys with individual point measurements spaced ~0.5 m apart. The three ~10x10m grids cover an ice wedge and a portion of its two neighboring polygons. The file contains thaw depth, frost table elevation, ground surface elevation, active layer depth and surface water inundation across three seasons (2012, 2013 and 2014) at Barrow NGEE Areas B, C and D.</abstract>
      <purpose>To improve understanding of fine scale spatial variability in the measured variables with ice wedge polygon type.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20120901</begdate>
          <enddate>20150930</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>complete</progress>
      <update>n/a</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Area B, C and D</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>585821</westbc>
        <eastbc>585968</eastbc>
        <northbc>7910563</northbc>
        <southbc>7910285</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Area B</placekey>
        <placekey>North Slope, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Barrow, Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Area C</placekey>
        <placekey>Area D</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekt>thaw depth</themekt>
        <themekey>water level</themekey>
        <themekey>active layer</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>internal</accconst>
    <datacred>Yes. See file.</datacred>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Anna Liljedahl</cntper>
          <cntorg>University of Alaska Fairbanks</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>PO Box 755910</address>
          <city>Fairbanks</city>
          <state>Alaska</state>
          <postal>99775</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>907-474-1951</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>akliljedahl@alaska.edu</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <tool>
      <toolcont>
        <cntinfo>
          <cntaddr>
            <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          </cntaddr>
        </cntinfo>
      </toolcont>
    </tool>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <qattracc>
        <attraccv>Reference elevation survey point was surveyed prior and after each grid survey. See water level dataset.</attraccv>
      </qattracc>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Basic QA/QC check.</logic>
    <complete>No.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>field</methtype>
        <methdesc>FIELD MEASUREMENTS: Elevations are given as absolute elevation (meters above sea level) via a detailed level surveying  of each gridpoint to a known benchmark. A permanent wooden stake marked each grid corner, which was surveyed with a Differential GPS system by Craig Ulrich in Sep. 2012. The start of each transect, which was located 0.5 (Area B and D) or 1 m (Area C) apart, was also marked with a wooden stake. During each survey, a meter tape was secured to each transect's end-point and an elevation/thaw depth was measured every 0.5 m along the meter tape. The elevation survey was made using the digital level TopCon DL-502. The known benchmark/reference elevation was surveyed at the beginning and at the end of each survey. Note that the ground elevation, especially moss-covered, is difficult to determine within ~5 cm. A pointed 1.25 m long and 1 cm diameter metal probe was used to determine thaw depth. The ground surface elevation was surveyed with the digital level and rod, while the thaw depth and water level was measured locally with the rod (water) and probe (thaw). Each grid surveys took 1.5 to 6 h.</methdesc>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>DATA PROCESSING: All values were processed to represent absolute elevation (meter above sea level). Water surface elevation measurements were averaged within respective polygon feature. The value is only reported at locations where surface inundation was observed. The location coordinates (x and y) were presented as relative values in the field, but translated into UTM coordinates using linear interpolation from the DGPS grid corner coordinates.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20150312</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
    <cntinfo>
                                <cntperp>
                                        <cntper>Data Center Support</cntper>
                                        <cntorg>Next-Generation Ecosystem Experiments (NGEE) Arctic Project, Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
                                </cntperp>
                                <cntaddr>
                                        <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
                                        <address>1 Bethel Valley Road</address>
                                        <city>Oak Ridge</city>
                                        <state>TN</state>
                                        <postal>37831-6290</postal>
                                        <country>USA</country>
                                </cntaddr>
                                <cntvoice></cntvoice>
                                <cntfax></cntfax>
                                <cntemail>support@ngee.ornl.gov</cntemail>
                        </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150511</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Anna Liljedahl</cntper>
          <cntorg>University of Alaska Fairbanks</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Research Assistant Professor</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>PO Box 755910</address>
          <city>Fairbanks</city>
          <state>Alaska</state>
          <postal>99775</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>907-474-1951</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>akliljedahl@alaska.edu</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FDGC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata and
			Biological Data Profile</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FDGC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
  <ome>
    <datause>Data can be used as a time series for a particular point or as a gridded product for a particular date.</datause>
    <ome_status>approved</ome_status>
    <taskname>HG</taskname>
  </ome>
</metadata>
