<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata><Source>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/metadata/Hydraulic_Conductivity_Measurements_Barrow_2014.xml</Source>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/hydrology_and_geomorphology/Hydraulic Conductivity Methods Barrow 2014.pdf</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ngee.ornl.gov/data/outgoing/hydrology_and_geomorphology/Hydraulic_Conductivity_Summary_WEB.xlsx</onlink>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1170518</onlink>
        <origin>Katie McKnight (kmcknight@berkeley.edu)</origin>
        <origin>Tim Kneafsey (tjkneafsey@lbl.gov)</origin>
        <origin>Jil Geller (jtgeller@lbl.gov)</origin>
        <origin>Craig Ulrich (culrich@lbl.gov)</origin>
        <title>Hydraulic Conductivity Measurements Barrow 2014</title>
        <geoform>Laboratory Analysis</geoform>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Six individual ice cores were collected from Barrow Environmental Observatory in Barrow, Alaska, in May of 2013 as part of the Next Generation Ecosystem Experiment (NGEE). Each core was drilled from a different location at varying depths. A few days after drilling, the cores were stored in coolers packed with dry ice and flown to Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory (LBNL) in Berkeley, CA. 3-dimensional images of the cores were constructed using a medical X-ray computed tomography (CT) scanner at 120kV. Hydraulic conductivity samples were extracted from these cores at LBNL Richmond Field Station in Richmond, CA, in February 2014 by cutting 5 to 8 inch segments using a chop saw. Samples were packed individually and stored at freezing temperatures to minimize any changes in structure or loss of ice content prior to analysis.  &amp;#xD;
Hydraulic conductivity was determined through falling head tests using a permeameter [ELE International, Model #: K-770B] (Appendix A). Samples were placed in a latex membrane via a membrane stretcher while frozen. Use of a membrane stretcher made the membranes easier to secure and minimized contact with the sample. A clear polycarbonate sleeve, fabricated with a stainless steel ring at the bottom to keep the sleeve from floating, was placed around the sample inside the permeameter to minimize deformation during analysis. The permeameter was filled with water and 1.0 PSI of air was applied for confining pressure during sample defrost. Outflow valves were left open to allow for incremental thawing and samples were left to thaw for approximately 12 hours. &amp;#xD;
After approximately 12 hours of thaw, initial falling head tests were performed. When the flow was significantly too fast or too slow, the analysis was stopped and the burette size was adjusted accordingly (i.e. a larger diameter burette was used for flows that were faster than desired or a smaller diameter burette was used for flows that were slower than desired). Two to four measurements were collected on each sample and collection stopped when the applied head load exceeded 25% change from the original load. Analyses were performed between 2 to 3 times for each sample. The final hydraulic conductivity calculations were computed using methodology of Das et al., 1985. doi:10.5440/1170518; http://dx.doi.org/10.5440/1170518</abstract>
      <purpose>Data were collected to understand hydraulic conductivity rates of thawed soils of varying compositions within the study site to incorporate into climate models.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20140703</begdate>
          <enddate>20140717</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>ongoing</progress>
      <update>as needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>AB Trans, BD Trans, DTLB</descgeog>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>AB Transect</placekey>
        <placekey>BD Transect</placekey>
        <placekey>DTLB</placekey>
        <placekey>Barrow, Alaska</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Hydraulic Conductivity</themekt>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Hydrology</themekt>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Falling Head Test</themekt>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>internal</accconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Tim Kneafsey</cntper>
          <cntorg>LBNL</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, 1 Cyclotron</address>
          <city>Berkeley</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>94720</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>510.486.4414</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>tjkneafsey@lbl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <tool>
      <toolcont>
        <cntinfo>
          <cntaddr>
            <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          </cntaddr>
        </cntinfo>
      </toolcont>
    </tool>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <qattracc>
        <attraccv>CT scans of DTLB38_2 and AB117_3 indicate they are both ataxitic with chunks of mineral and ice distributed throughout the core, compared to the other samples that are generally mineral, with ice intrusions. These samples are also among the deepest samples.  AB117_3 may have had other disturbances when a second membrane had to be installed over the sample after a hole in the original membrane was discovered.  Creases and/or significant shrinkage occurred in DTLB19_1, DTLB40_2, DTLB38_2, AB117_3 during tests. Such occurrences could lead to error in hydraulic conductivity measurements.</attraccv>
      </qattracc>
    </attracc>
    <logic>A literature review is currently being performed to compare collected hydraulic conductivity estimates and methods with existing data of similar samples. This report will be available by May 2015.</logic>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>both</methtype>
        <methdesc>Please see attached "Hydraulic_Conductivity_Methods_Barrow_2014.pdf"</methdesc>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Das, Braja M.</origin>
            <pubdate>1985</pubdate>
            <title>Principles of Geotechnical Engineering</title>
            <onlink>Print.</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Six individual ice cores were collected from Barrow Environmental Observatory in Barrow, Alaska, in May of 2013 as part of the Next Generation Ecosystem Experiment (NGEE). Each core was drilled from a different location at varying depths. A few days after drilling, the cores were stored in coolers packed with dry ice and flown to Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory (LBNL) in Berkeley, CA.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20130501</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>3-dimensional images of the cores were constructed using a medical X-ray computed tomography (CT) scanner at 120kV.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20130514</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Hydraulic conductivity samples were extracted from these cores at LBNL Richmond Field Station in Richmond, CA, in February 2014 by cutting 5 to 8 inch segments using a chop saw. Samples were packed individually and stored at freezing temperatures to minimize any changes in structure or loss of ice content prior to analysis.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20140225</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Hydraulic conductivity was determined through falling head tests using a permeameter [ELE International, Model #: K-770B] (Appendix A). Samples were placed in a latex membrane via a membrane stretcher while frozen. Use of a membrane stretcher made the membranes easier to secure and minimized contact with the sample. A clear polycarbonate sleeve, fabricated with a stainless steel ring at the bottom to keep the sleeve from floating, was placed around the sample inside the permeameter to minimize deformation during analysis. The permeameter was filled with water and 1.0 PSI of air was applied for confining pressure during sample defrost. Outflow valves were left open to allow for incremental thawing and samples were left to thaw for approximately 12 hours. &amp;#xD;
After approximately 12 hours of thaw, initial falling head tests were performed. When the flow was significantly too fast or too slow, the analysis was stopped and the burette size was adjusted accordingly (i.e. a larger diameter burette was used for flows that were faster than desired or a smaller diameter burette was used for flows that were slower than desired). Two to four measurements were collected on each sample and collection stopped when the applied head load exceeded 25% change from the original load. Analyses were performed between 2 to 3 times for each sample. The final hydraulic conductivity calculations were computed using methodology of Das et al., 1985.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20140703</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
    <cntinfo>
                                <cntperp>
                                        <cntper>Data Center Support</cntper>
                                        <cntorg>Next-Generation Ecosystem Experiments (NGEE) Arctic Project, Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
                                </cntperp>
                                <cntaddr>
                                        <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
                                        <address>1 Bethel Valley Road</address>
                                        <city>Oak Ridge</city>
                                        <state>TN</state>
                                        <postal>37831-6290</postal>
                                        <country>USA</country>
                                </cntaddr>
                                <cntvoice></cntvoice>
                                <cntfax></cntfax>
                                <cntemail>support@ngee.ornl.gov</cntemail>
                        </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150222</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Tim Kneafsey</cntper>
          <cntorg>LBNL</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Geological Staff Scientist, Hydrogeology Department Head</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, 1 Cyclotron</address>
          <city>Berkeley</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>94720</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>510.486.4414</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>tjkneafsey@lbl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FDGC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata and
			Biological Data Profile</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FDGC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
  <ome>
    <datause>The data can be applied to scale up hydrology models of specific soil types within patterned ground. The methodology used could also inform techniques on future hydraulic conductivity studies of active layer and permafrost samples.</datause>
    <ome_status>approved</ome_status>
    <taskname>HG</taskname>
  </ome>
</metadata>
