<onedcx:metadata xmlns:onedcx="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <onedcx:simpleDc>
    <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
    <dcterms:creator>Minnesota Population Center</dcterms:creator>
    <dcterms:title>IPUMS-International: Ecuador 1990 Census</dcterms:title>
    <dcterms:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_ec_1990_DC.xml</dcterms:identifier>
    <dcterms:subject>Census</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Other Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Fertility and Mortality Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Disability Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Industry Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
  </onedcx:simpleDc>
  <onedcx:dcTerms>
    <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
    <dcterms:available>2014-07-01</dcterms:available>
    <dcterms:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_ec_1990_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</dcterms:abstract>
    <dcterms:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Donated household; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Urban-rural status; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Ecuador [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Ecuador [Level 1; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Canton (20,000 and over), Ecuador 1974-2001 [Level 2; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Ownership of dwelling [general version]; Ownership of dwelling [detailed version]; Electricity; Water supply; Sewage; Telephone availability; Number of rooms; Kitchen or cooking facilities; Toilet; Bathing facilities; Floor material; Household language status, Ecuador; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Head's location in household; Dwelling number; Household number (within dwelling); Number of households in dwelling; Number of persons in dwelling; Number of persons in household; Dwelling created by splitting apart a large dwelling or household; Province; Urban administrative unit; Urban; Occupancy status; Electricity for dwelling; Waste water removal for dwelling; Garbage removal; Method of water supply for dwelling; Rooms in the dwelling; Exterior walls; Floor of dwelling; Water supply system for dwelling; Number of sleeping rooms in dwelling; Roof; Telephone; Type of dwelling; Number of households in dwelling; Household economic activity status; Kitchen; Fuel used for cooking; Sleeping rooms; Shower; Sequence of household within the dwelling; Language spoken in home; Any individual present at enumeration; Toilet; Household ownership of the dwelling; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Age; Age, grouped into intervals; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Consensual union; Children ever born; Children surviving; Mortality status of mother; Nativity status; Province of birth, Ecuador; School attendance; Literacy; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Years of schooling; Educational attainment, Ecuador; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Occupation, ISCO-1968, 3-digit; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Hours worked per week; Hours worked per week, categorized; Migration status, 5 years; Province of residence 5 years ago, Ecuador; Employment disability; Person number (within household); Literacy; School attendance; Educational level; Highest grade completed; Educational attainment; Some additional economic activity; Year of birth of last child born alive; Class of worker; Relationship; Sex; Age; Marital status; Children currently alive; Employment status; Household number within the dwelling; Number of hours worked; Month of birth of last child; Occupation, 1 digit; Occupation, 2 digits; Occupation, 3 digits; Province of habitual residence; Province of residence 5 years ago; Canton of residence 5 years ago; Province of birth; Canton of birth; Industry, 1 digits; Industry, 3 digits; Children ever born; Mother alive; Last child alive; </dcterms:tableOfContents>
    <dcterms:spatial>Ecuador</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=1.437782; eastlimit=-75.216845; southlimit=-5.000309; westlimit=-91.663891; name=Ecuador;</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:temporal>1990</dcterms:temporal>
    <dcterms:references>http://international.ipums.org</dcterms:references>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_ec_1990_ddic.xml</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_ec_1990_ddic_xml.html</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</dcterms:accessRights>
    <dcterms:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</dcterms:modified>
  </onedcx:dcTerms>  
</onedcx:metadata>