<onedcx:metadata xmlns:onedcx="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <onedcx:simpleDc>
    <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
    <dcterms:creator>Minnesota Population Center</dcterms:creator>
    <dcterms:title>IPUMS-International: Canada 1971 Census</dcterms:title>
    <dcterms:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_ca_1971_DC.xml</dcterms:identifier>
    <dcterms:subject>Census</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Appliances, Mechanicals, Other Amenities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Fertility and Mortality Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Ethnicity and Language Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Income Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Industry Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
  </onedcx:simpleDc>
  <onedcx:dcTerms>
    <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
    <dcterms:available>2014-07-01</dcterms:available>
    <dcterms:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_ca_1971_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</dcterms:abstract>
    <dcterms:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Group quarters status; Urban-rural status; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Canada [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Canada [Level 1; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Water supply; Sewage; Central heating; Food freezer; Refrigerator; Television set; Toilet; Bathing facilities; Dwelling number; Region; Province; Water supply; Bath facilities; Flush toilet facilities; Source of water supply; Method of sewage disposal; Heating equipment; Refrigerator; Home freezer; Electric dishwasher; Automatic clothes dryer; Black and white TV; Colour TV; Household classification; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Age; Age, grouped into intervals; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Age at first marriage or union; Relationship to head of subfamily; Children ever born; Nativity status; Country of birth; Province of birth, Canada; Citizenship; Country of citizenship; Year of immigration; Years since immigrated, categorized; Religion [general version]; Religion [detailed version]; Ethnicity, Canada; Speaks English; Speaks indigenous language; Language spoken at home, Canada; Mother tongue, Canada; School attendance; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Educational attainment, Canada; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Months worked last year; Full-time or part-time work; Total income; Earned income; Wage and salary income; Self-employment income; Migration status, 5 years; Same house 5 years ago; Household relationship; Family membership; Number of persons in family; Level of schooling of head of family; Level of schooling of spouse; Sex; Marital status; Mother tongue; Age; Place of birth; Period of immigration; Birthplace of parents; Country of citizenship; Ethnic or cultural group; Religion; Home language; Knowledge of official language; School attendance; Level of schooling; Place of highest grade of elementary or secondary school; Completed full-time vocational course; Kind of vocational course; Length of course of longest duration; Period when course of longest duration completed; Number of inter-municipal moves; Number of children ever born; Labour force status; When last worked; Weeks worked during 1970; 1970 work activity; Hours usually worked in a week; Industry; Occupation; Class of worker; Individual income; Age at first marriage; Family income; Residence on June 1, 1966; Place of residence on June 1, 1966; Place of residence on June 1, 1971; Major source of income; Income from wages and salaries; Income from self-employment; Sub-sample number; </dcterms:tableOfContents>
    <dcterms:spatial>Canada</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=83.113873; eastlimit=-52.617364; southlimit=41.675554; westlimit=-141.002991; name=Canada;</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:temporal>1971</dcterms:temporal>
    <dcterms:references>http://international.ipums.org</dcterms:references>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_ca_1971_ddic.xml</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_ca_1971_ddic_xml.html</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</dcterms:accessRights>
    <dcterms:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</dcterms:modified>
  </onedcx:dcTerms>  
</onedcx:metadata>