<onedcx:metadata xmlns:onedcx="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <onedcx:simpleDc>
    <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
    <dcterms:creator>Minnesota Population Center</dcterms:creator>
    <dcterms:title>IPUMS-International: Germany 1970 Census</dcterms:title>
    <dcterms:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_de_1970_DC.xml</dcterms:identifier>
    <dcterms:subject>Census</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Fertility and Mortality Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Ethnicity and Language Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Income Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Other Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
  </onedcx:simpleDc>
  <onedcx:dcTerms>
    <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
    <dcterms:available>2014-07-01</dcterms:available>
    <dcterms:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_de_1970_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</dcterms:abstract>
    <dcterms:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Group quarters status; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; NUTS1 Region, Europe; State, Germany [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; Telephone availability; Dwelling number; Municipality of residence / federal state; Serial number of household; Size of municipality of residence; Institution; Type of institution; Number of  persons in the household; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Relationship to head, Europe; Age; Age, grouped into intervals; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Marital status, Europe; Duration of current marriage or union; Year of birth; Children ever born; Citizenship; Country of citizenship; Religion [general version]; Religion [detailed version]; School attendance; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Educational attainment, Germany; Educational attainment, Europe; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Employment status, Europe; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Class of worker, Europe; Number of employees; Full-time or part-time work; Hours worked per week, categorized; Means of transportation to work or school; Wage and salary income; Source of livelihood; Person number (within household); Doubled case in Berlin; Sex; Year of birth; Marital status; Relationship to head of household; Religion; Other religious denominations, detailed; German; Citizenship; Has other dwelling; Goes to work from other dwelling; Lives in other dwelling; Officially registered in other dwelling; Other dwelling is abroad; Main source of livelihood; Presently attending a school; Completed primary school; Completed compulsory part-time vocational school; Completed 10th grade; Completed final high school exam; Completed full-time or advanced vocational school; Completed engineering school; Completed university; Economically active; Farmer; (Unpaid) assistant in family business; Unemployed / seeking work; No economic activity; Homemaker; In military / armed forces; Means of transport to school or work; Time to school or work; Industry; Position in occupation; Other economic activity; Usual hours worked per week; Residence on 1 Sept 1939 (outbreak of WWII); Arrived after WWII from the Soviet zone or East Berlin; Federalexpellee /Federal refugee identity card; Economically active in the past; Year of termination of former economic activity; Occupation, 2 digits; Occupation; Rank of public servants; Machinery operation; Monthly net income (in Deutsche Mark); Supervisory position; Number of persons employed; Some of employees are salary-earners; Agriculturally cultivated area (hectares); Completed practical vocational training; Years of practical vocational training completed; Completed technical school; Completed vocational school / professional school; Completed engineering school; Completed university; Years of training; Year of graduation (completed level); Year of marriage; Previously married; Ever gave birth; Year of birth of first child; Year of birth of 2nd child; Year of birth of 3rd child; Year of birth of 4th child; Year of birth of 5th child; Telephone; Age; Number of children born alive; Net-income extended (in Deutsche Mark); Expellee classifications; </dcterms:tableOfContents>
    <dcterms:spatial>Germany</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=55.055649; eastlimit=13.842180; southlimit= 47.275790; westlimit=5.865630; name=Germany;</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:temporal>1970</dcterms:temporal>
    <dcterms:references>http://international.ipums.org</dcterms:references>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_de_1970_ddic.xml</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_de_1970_ddic_xml.html</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</dcterms:accessRights>
    <dcterms:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</dcterms:modified>
  </onedcx:dcTerms>  
</onedcx:metadata>