<onedcx:metadata xmlns:onedcx="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <onedcx:simpleDc>
    <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
    <dcterms:creator>Minnesota Population Center</dcterms:creator>
    <dcterms:title>IPUMS-International: Malawi 2008 Census</dcterms:title>
    <dcterms:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_mw_2008_DC.xml</dcterms:identifier>
    <dcterms:subject>Census</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Appliances, Mechanicals, Other Amenities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Other Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Fertility and Mortality Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Ethnicity and Language Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Disability Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Other Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Industry Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Imputation Flags Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
  </onedcx:simpleDc>
  <onedcx:dcTerms>
    <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
    <dcterms:available>2014-07-01</dcterms:available>
    <dcterms:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_mw_2008_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</dcterms:abstract>
    <dcterms:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Urban-rural status; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; District, Malawi [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; District, Malawi [Level 1; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Traditional Authority, Malawi [Level 2; consistent boundaries over time]; Ownership of dwelling [general version]; Ownership of dwelling [detailed version]; Number of international migrants; Receives remittances; Electricity; Water supply; Cooking fuel; Telephone availability; Automobiles available; Refrigerator; Television set; Radio in household; Number of rooms; Number of bedrooms; Toilet; Floor material; Wall or building material; Roof material; Number of deaths in household last year; Any deaths in household last year; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Head's location in household; Dwelling number; Number of persons in household; Dwelling created by splitting apart a large dwelling or household; Region; District; Town (traditional authority); Type of household; Type of dwelling structure; Tenure of the dwelling; Main material of the roof; Main material of the walls; Main material of the floor; Number of rooms; Number of rooms for sleeping; Number of occupants; Main source of drinking water in dry season; Main source of drinking water in wet season; Type of toilet facility; Main source of energy for lighting; Main source of energy for cooking; Owned a radio; Owned a television; Owned a refrigerator/deep freezer; Owned a cooker/hot plate; Owned a bicycle; Owned a motorcycle; Owned a car or truck; Owned a telephone; Owned an ox-cart; Owned an ITN (insecticide-treated net); Household had emigrant member(s); Household received remittances; Regularity of remittances; Household had deaths in last 12 months; Present residents - male; Present residents - female; Present residents - total; Visitors - male; Visitors - female; Visitors - total; Total enumerated - male; Total enumerated - female; Total enumerated - total; Urban/rural status; Number of deaths in last year; Number of emigrants in last ten years; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Residence status: de facto, de jure; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Age; Age, grouped into intervals; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Age at first marriage or union; Year of birth; Month of birth; Children ever born; Children surviving; Number of female children ever born; Number of male children ever born; Number of female children surviving; Number of male children surviving; Number of births last year; Children surviving from births last year; Mortality status of mother; Mortality status of father; Nativity status; Country of birth; District of birth, Malawi; Citizenship; Country of citizenship; Religion [general version]; Religion [detailed version]; Ethnicity, Malawi; Speaks English; School attendance; Literacy; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Years of schooling; Educational attainment, Malawi; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Migration status, previous residence; Country of previous residence; Years residing in current locality; District of previous residence, Malawi; Disability status; Blind or vision-impaired; Deaf or hearing-impaired; Mute; Disability affecting lower extremities; Origin of disability; Person number (within household); Relationship to head of household; Sex; Month of birth; Year of birth; Age; District or country of birth; Malawian; Nationality; Residence status; Religion; Tribe; District or country of previous residence; Duration of residence (years); Type of disability, first; Cause of disability, first; Type of disability, second; Cause of disability, second; Type of disability, third; Cause of disability, third; Mother alive; Motherin house; Father alive; Father in house; Has birth certificate; Literate in English; Literate in Chichewa; Literate in other language; Literacy, detailed; School attendance; Highest school level and grade attended; Highest school level attended; Highest school years or grade attended; Highest education qualification attained; Economically active; Reason for not working; Subsistence work; Available to work; Looking for work; Occupation (2 digits); Occupation (1 digit); Class of worker; Main industry; Marital status; Age at first marriage or union; Male children ever born; Female children ever born; Male children surviving; Female children surviving; Males born last year; Females born last year; Males born last year surviving; Females born last year surviving; Relationship flag; Sex flag; Age flag; Malawian (Yes/No) flag; Nationality flag; Religion flag; Tribe flag; Mother alive flag; Father alive flag; Marital status flag; Male children ever born flag; Female children ever born flag; Male children surviving flag; Female children surviving flag; Males born last year flag; Females born last year flag; Males born last year surviving flag; Females born last year surviving flag; Children ever born; Children surviving; Children born last year; Children born last year surviving; </dcterms:tableOfContents>
    <dcterms:spatial>Malawi</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=-9.376673; eastlimit=35.920963; southlimit=-17.135282; westlimit=32.681873; name=Malawi;</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:temporal>2008</dcterms:temporal>
    <dcterms:references>http://international.ipums.org</dcterms:references>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_mw_2008_ddic.xml</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_mw_2008_ddic_xml.html</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</dcterms:accessRights>
    <dcterms:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</dcterms:modified>
  </onedcx:dcTerms>  
</onedcx:metadata>