<onedcx:metadata xmlns:onedcx="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <onedcx:simpleDc>
    <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
    <dcterms:creator>Minnesota Population Center</dcterms:creator>
    <dcterms:title>IPUMS-International: Thailand 1980 Census</dcterms:title>
    <dcterms:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_th_1980_DC.xml</dcterms:identifier>
    <dcterms:subject>Census</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Appliances, Mechanicals, Other Amenities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Fertility and Mortality Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Ethnicity and Language Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Disability Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Other Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Industry Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
  </onedcx:simpleDc>
  <onedcx:dcTerms>
    <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
    <dcterms:available>2014-07-01</dcterms:available>
    <dcterms:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_th_1980_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</dcterms:abstract>
    <dcterms:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Urban-rural status; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Thailand [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Thailand [Level 1; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Region, Thailand; Ownership of dwelling [general version]; Ownership of dwelling [detailed version]; Land ownership; Electricity; Water supply; Cooking fuel; Telephone availability; Automobiles available; Air conditioning; Refrigerator; Television set; Radio in household; Number of bedrooms; Kitchen or cooking facilities; Toilet; Bathing facilities; Wall or building material; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Head's location in household; Dwelling number; Number of persons in household; Dwelling created by splitting apart a large dwelling or household; Number of persons in large household before it was split; Sample Identification; Donated dwelling; Donation strata: Strata number; Region; Province (Changwat); Sanitary district; Type of household; Number of persons in household; Type of living quarter; Wall construction materials; Living quarter also for commercial use; Tenure of living quarter, excluding land; Payment of rent in advance; Rent per month; Dwelling owner; Land ownership; Owner of land; Number of bedrooms; Number of other rooms used for sleeping; Source of drinking water; Type of water supply; Type of bathroom; Type of lighting; Type of toilet; Type of kitchen; Type of cooking fuel; Radio; Television; Telephone; Refrigerator; Electric fan; Air conditioner; Bicycle; Motorcycle; Car; Engine operated boats; Water pumps; Tractor; Household weight; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Age; Age, grouped into intervals; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Age at first marriage or union; Year of birth; Month of birth; Children ever born; Children surviving; Number of children dead; Number of own children in household; Number of own children living elsewhere; Nativity status; Country of birth; Province of birth, Thailand; Religion [general version]; Religion [detailed version]; School attendance; Literacy; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Years of schooling; Educational attainment, Thailand; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Migration status, previous residence; Country of previous residence; Years residing in current locality; Reason for migration; Province of previous residence, Thailand; Employment disability; Person number (within household); Line number of person; Relationship to head of household; Month ofbirth; Year of birth; Age reported; Residence status; Sex; Highest grade completed; Marital status; Occupation last year; Principal industry last year; Work status; Language spoken in household; Line number of mother; Religion; Province or country of birth; School grade attended; Literacy; Length of residence; Previous province or country of residence; Place of previous residence: rural/urban; Reason for moving; Age at first marriage; Number of children ever born living at home; Number of children ever born living elsewhere; Number of children ever born that died; Family planning; Type of family planning; Principal occupation last week; Reason for not working; Age recoded; Children ever born; Children still living; Duration of marriage; Person weight; </dcterms:tableOfContents>
    <dcterms:spatial>Thailand</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=20.454584; eastlimit=105.639292; southlimit=5.633473; westlimit=97.347272; name=Thailand;</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:temporal>1980</dcterms:temporal>
    <dcterms:references>http://international.ipums.org</dcterms:references>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_th_1980_ddic.xml</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_th_1980_ddic_xml.html</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</dcterms:accessRights>
    <dcterms:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</dcterms:modified>
  </onedcx:dcTerms>  
</onedcx:metadata>