<onedcx:metadata xmlns:onedcx="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <onedcx:simpleDc>
    <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
    <dcterms:creator>Minnesota Population Center</dcterms:creator>
    <dcterms:title>IPUMS-International: South Africa 1996 Census</dcterms:title>
    <dcterms:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_za_1996_DC.xml</dcterms:identifier>
    <dcterms:subject>Census</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Other Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Fertility and Mortality Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Ethnicity and Language Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Income Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Disability Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Other Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Industry Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
  </onedcx:simpleDc>
  <onedcx:dcTerms>
    <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
    <dcterms:available>2014-07-01</dcterms:available>
    <dcterms:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_za_1996_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</dcterms:abstract>
    <dcterms:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Donated household; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Urban-rural status; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; Province, South Africa [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; Magisterial District, South Africa; Ownership of dwelling [general version]; Ownership of dwelling [detailed version]; Migrant worker absent from household; Migrant worker in household; Receives remittances; Electricity; Water supply; Cooking fuel; Fuel for heating; Telephone availability; Cellular phone availability; Number of rooms; Toilet; Number of households sharing one room; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Head's location in household; Dwelling number; Number of persons in household; Dwelling created by splitting apart a large dwelling or household; Dwelling created by splitting apart a corrupt or suspicious dwelling; Donated dwelling; Donation strata: strata number; Urban-rural; Province; Remarks on geographic coding; Household questionnaire type; Additional money generated by household; Remittances or payments received; Migrant workers absent from household; Migrant workers present in household; Type of dwelling; Number of rooms; Number of other households sharing the room; Dwelling ownership; Fuel used for cooking; Fuel used for heating; Fuel used for lighting; Main water supply; Toilet facilities; Refuse disposal; Access to telephone facilities; Derived household income (monthly); Household weight; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Age; Age, grouped into intervals; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Consensual union; Children ever born; Children surviving; Mortality status of mother; Mortality status of father; Nativity status; Country of birth; Citizenship; Country of citizenship; Religion [general version]; Religion [detailed version]; Language spoken at home, South Africa; Second language spoken, South Africa; School attendance; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Years of schooling; Educational attainment, South Africa; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Occupation, ISCO-1988, 3-digit; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Total income; Migration status, previous residence; Country of previous residence; Years residing in current dwelling; Province of previous residence, South Africa; Disability status; Employment disability; Blind or vision-impaired; Deaf or hearing-impaired; Mental disability; Person number (withinhousehold); Household questionnaire type; Type of institution; Sex; Age; Relationship to head; Marital status; Population group; First language; Second language; Religion; Country of birth; Citizenship; Citizen of South Africa; Migrant worker; Situation of usual residence; Year moved to usual residence; Magisterial district/country of previous residence; Disability status; Sight disability; Hearing disability; Physical disability; Mental disability; Mother still alive; Father still alive; Number of children ever born; Number of children still living; Age of mother at birth of first child; Number of births in last 12 months; Highest school grade completed; Highest post-school qualification field; Studying status; Highest post-school qualification level; Highest school class completed; Employment status; Full-time or part-time work; Class of worker; Occupation, 1 digit; Occupation, 2 digits; Occupation, 3 digits; Occupation when last employed; Industry, 1 digit; Industry, 2 digits; Individual income (monthly); Person weight; </dcterms:tableOfContents>
    <dcterms:spatial>South Africa</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=-22.136391; eastlimit=32.890427; southlimit=-34.822000; westlimit=16.483327; name=South Africa;</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:temporal>1996</dcterms:temporal>
    <dcterms:references>http://international.ipums.org</dcterms:references>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_za_1996_ddic.xml</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_za_1996_ddic_xml.html</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</dcterms:accessRights>
    <dcterms:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</dcterms:modified>
  </onedcx:dcTerms>  
</onedcx:metadata>