<onedcx:metadata xmlns:onedcx="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <onedcx:simpleDc>
    <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
    <dcterms:creator>Minnesota Population Center</dcterms:creator>
    <dcterms:title>IPUMS-International: Peru 1993 Census</dcterms:title>
    <dcterms:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_pe_1993_DC.xml</dcterms:identifier>
    <dcterms:subject>Census</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Appliances, Mechanicals, Other Amenities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Other Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Fertility and Mortality Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Ethnicity and Language Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Disability Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Industry Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
  </onedcx:simpleDc>
  <onedcx:dcTerms>
    <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
    <dcterms:available>2014-07-01</dcterms:available>
    <dcterms:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_pe_1993_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</dcterms:abstract>
    <dcterms:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Urban-rural status; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; Department, Peru [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Peru [Level 2; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Ownership of dwelling [general version]; Ownership of dwelling [detailed version]; Electricity; Water supply; Sewage; Telephone availability; Automobiles available; Computer; Clothes washing machine; Refrigerator; Television set; Videocassette recorder; Radio in household; Number of rooms; Number of bedrooms; Kitchen or cooking facilities; Toilet; Floor material; Wall or building material; Roof material; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Head's location in household; Dwelling number; Household number (within dwelling); Number of households in dwelling; Number of persons in dwelling; Number of persons in household; Dwelling created by splitting apart a large dwelling or household; Donated dwelling; Donation strata: strata number; Department; Province; Urban-rural; Water supply; Electric lighting; Occupancy; Number of rooms; Predominant material in the walls; Predominant material in the floor; Toilet facilities/sewerage connection; Predominant material in the roof; Ownership; Dwelling type; Vacuum cleaner in the household; Car or light truck for personal use in the household; Car for work use in the household; Use of sanitary facilities; Bicycle in the household; Light truck for work in the household; Use of room for cooking; Computer in the household; Number of sleeping rooms; Space in the dwelling used for economic activity; Washing machine in the household; Floor polisher in the household; Sewing machine in the household; Knitting machine in the household; Motorcycle/motor scooter in the household; Radio in the household; Refrigerator in the household; Stereo equipment in the household; Telephone in the household; Tricycle for work in the household; Black and white television in the household; Color television in the household; Video recorder in the household; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Age; Age, grouped into intervals; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Consensual union; Children ever born; Children surviving; Month of last birth; Year of last birth; Mortality status of last birth; Mortality status of mother; Nativity status; Country of birth; Province of birth, Peru; Religion [general version]; Religion [detailed version]; Mother tongue, Peru; School attendance; Literacy; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Years of schooling; Educational attainment, Peru; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Country of residence 5 years ago; Disability status; Blind or vision-impaired; Deaf or hearing-impaired; Mute; Disability affecting lower extremities; Disability affecting upper extremities; Mental disability; Psychological disability; Person number (within household); Economic activity (4 digits); Mental illness; Year of birth of last child; Currently attending an educational institution; Occupational category/employment status; Blindness; Age chronology; Age in years and months; Marital status; Economic activity (2 digits); Children currently alive; Maternal language or dialect; Physical disability; Other disability; Lower extremity loss or paralysis; Upper extremity loss or paralysis; Number of persons working in workplace; Literacy; Mother alive; Month of birth of last child; Muteness; Total children born alive; Nativity; Educational level; Last year/grade completed of basic education; Educational level completed; Occupation (3 digits); Country of birth; Country of residence in 1988; Relationship to head; Polio; Religion; Mental retardation; Sex; Employment situation; Total deafness; Province of birth; Last child alive; Age completed, years; Age completed, months; </dcterms:tableOfContents>
    <dcterms:spatial>Peru</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=-0.036873; eastlimit=-68.673909; southlimit=-18.348546; westlimit=-81.355146; name=Peru;</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:temporal>1993</dcterms:temporal>
    <dcterms:references>http://international.ipums.org</dcterms:references>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_pe_1993_ddic.xml</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_pe_1993_ddic_xml.html</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</dcterms:accessRights>
    <dcterms:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</dcterms:modified>
  </onedcx:dcTerms>  
</onedcx:metadata>