<onedcx:metadata xmlns:onedcx="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <onedcx:simpleDc>
    <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
    <dcterms:creator>Minnesota Population Center</dcterms:creator>
    <dcterms:title>IPUMS-International: Kyrgyz Republic 2009 Census</dcterms:title>
    <dcterms:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_kg_2009_DC.xml</dcterms:identifier>
    <dcterms:subject>Census</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Fertility and Mortality Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Ethnicity and Language Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Income Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Disability Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Industry Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
  </onedcx:simpleDc>
  <onedcx:dcTerms>
    <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
    <dcterms:available>2014-07-01</dcterms:available>
    <dcterms:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_kg_2009_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</dcterms:abstract>
    <dcterms:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Urban-rural status; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; Region, Kyrgyz Republic [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; District, Kyrgyz Republic [Level 2; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Number of rooms; Wall or building material; Year structure was built; Age of structure, coded from intervals; Stories in structure; Living area in square meters; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Dwelling number; Household number (within dwelling); Number of households in dwelling; Number of persons in dwelling; Number of persons in household; Number of structure; Residential premise type; Number of stories; Wall material of premises; Construction period; Seismic stability; Type of occupied residential premise; Occupancy; Total area of dwelling (square meters); Residential area of dwelling (square meters); Number of rooms occupied by household; Region; District; Urban or rural; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Age; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Consensual union; Year of birth; Month of birth; Children ever born; Children surviving; Number of female children ever born; Number of male children ever born; Number of female children surviving; Number of male children surviving; Number of own children living elsewhere; Number of own female children living elsewhere; Number of own male children living elsewhere; Nativity status; Country of birth; District of birth, Kyrgyz Republic; Citizenship; Speaks English; Mother tongue, Kyrgyz Republic; School attendance; Literacy; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Educational attainment, Kyrgyz Republic; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Source of livelihood; Years residing in current locality; Reason for migration; Employment disability; Person number (within household); Location of absent persons; How long have absent persons been away; Reason for absence; Relationship to person enumerated first; Number of the mother or father; Sex; Absent on census night; Month of birth; Year of birth; Age; Nationality; Mother tongue; Second fluently spoken language; Third fluently spoken language; District or city of birth; Country of birth; Citizenship; Residing from birth in current settlement; Year moved to current settlement; Reason for moving; Marital status; Person number of spouse; Education level; Read and write; Type of degree; Type of educational institution attending; Attending preschool; Sources of income; Type of industry, enterprise or organization; Employment status; Looking for work; Reason not looking for work; Total number of children born; Number of male children born; Number of female children born; Number of children surviving; Number of male children surviving; Number of female children surviving; Number of children born that are living elsewhere; Number of male children born that are living elsewhere; Number of female children born that are living elsewhere; </dcterms:tableOfContents>
    <dcterms:spatial>Kyrgyz Republic</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=43.216900; eastlimit=80.281582; southlimit=39.195473; westlimit=69.249500; name=Kyrgyz Republic;</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:temporal>2009</dcterms:temporal>
    <dcterms:references>http://international.ipums.org</dcterms:references>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_kg_2009_ddic.xml</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_kg_2009_ddic_xml.html</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</dcterms:accessRights>
    <dcterms:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</dcterms:modified>
  </onedcx:dcTerms>  
</onedcx:metadata>