<onedcx:metadata xmlns:onedcx="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <onedcx:simpleDc>
    <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
    <dcterms:creator>Minnesota Population Center</dcterms:creator>
    <dcterms:title>IPUMS-International: Cameroon 2005 Census</dcterms:title>
    <dcterms:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_cm_2005_DC.xml</dcterms:identifier>
    <dcterms:subject>Census</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Other Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Fertility and Mortality Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Ethnicity and Language Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Disability Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Other Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Industry Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
  </onedcx:simpleDc>
  <onedcx:dcTerms>
    <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
    <dcterms:available>2014-07-01</dcterms:available>
    <dcterms:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_cm_2005_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</dcterms:abstract>
    <dcterms:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Urban-rural status; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Cameroon [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Cameroon [Level 1; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Department, Cameroon [Level 2; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Arrondissement, Cameroon; Ownership of dwelling [general version]; Ownership of dwelling [detailed version]; Number of international migrants; Electricity; Sewage; Cooking fuel; Trash disposal; Number of bedrooms; Toilet; Floor material; Wall or building material; Roof material; Number of deaths in household last year; Any deaths in household last year; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Dwelling number; Province; Department or division; Urban; Household type; Present residents; Absent residents; Visitors; Incapacitating illness; Household type; Lodging type; Type of structure; Wall material; Roof material; Floor material; Toilet; Bedrooms; Mode of occupancy; Light source; Cooking energy source; Source of drinking water; Waste water disposal; Household waste; Site of dwelling; Accessibility means; Number of mortality records; Number of migration records; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Residence status: de facto, de jure; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Age; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Consensual union; Polygamous union; Year of birth; Month of birth; Children ever born; Children surviving; Number of female children ever born; Number of male children ever born; Number of female children surviving; Number of male children surviving; Number of births last year; Mortality status of mother; Mortality status of father; Arrondissement of birth, Cameroon; Citizenship; Country of citizenship; Religion [general version]; Religion [detailed version]; Speaks English; School attendance; Literacy; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Years of schooling; Educational attainment, Cameroon; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Migration status, 5 years; Migration status, previous residence; Country of previous residence; Country of residence 5 years ago; Years residing in current locality; Arrondissement of previous residence, Cameroon; Arrondissement of residence 5 years ago, Cameroon; Disability status; Employment disability; Blind or vision-impaired; Deaf or hearing-impaired; Mute; Disability affecting lower extremities; Disability affecting upper extremities; Psychological disability; Person number (within household); Last class attended (unedited); Sleeping place, homeless; Main reason for being in the street; Type of residence nomads; Primary activity nomad; Household type; Sex; Relationship to head of household; Age; Month of birth; Year of birth; Urban or rural place of birth; Arrondissement of birth; Country of birth; Marital Status; Residential status; Visitor's usual place of residence; Visitor's usual arrondissment or country of residence; Urban-rural status in 2000; Arrondissement of residence in 2000; Department of residence in 2000; Province of residence in 2000; Country of residence in 2000; Urban-rural status of previous residence; Arrondissement of previous residence; Department of previous residence; Province of previous residence; Country of previous residence; Number of years in current place of residence; Nationality; Religion; Disability; Chronic disease; Father still alive; Mother still alive; Literacy in national languages; Can read English; Write English; Speak English; Read French; Write French; Speak French; Ever attended school; Present school attendence; Educational sector; Profession; Employment status; Class of worker; Occupation; Type of employment; Sector of employment; Industry; Number of male live births; Number of female live births; Number of male children still living; Number of female children still living; Male live births in last 12 months; Female live births in last 12 months; Children born alive; Children still living; Children born in last 12 months; Heard of AIDS; Transmission of AIDS; </dcterms:tableOfContents>
    <dcterms:spatial>Cameroon</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=13.085000; eastlimit=16.207000; southlimit=1.654164; westlimit=8.502363; name=Cameroon;</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:temporal>2005</dcterms:temporal>
    <dcterms:references>http://international.ipums.org</dcterms:references>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_cm_2005_ddic.xml</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_cm_2005_ddic_xml.html</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</dcterms:accessRights>
    <dcterms:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</dcterms:modified>
  </onedcx:dcTerms>  
</onedcx:metadata>