<onedcx:metadata xmlns:onedcx="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <onedcx:simpleDc>
    <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
    <dcterms:creator>Minnesota Population Center</dcterms:creator>
    <dcterms:title>IPUMS-International: Costa Rica 1973 Census</dcterms:title>
    <dcterms:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_cr_1973_DC.xml</dcterms:identifier>
    <dcterms:subject>Census</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Appliances, Mechanicals, Other Amenities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Fertility and Mortality Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Income Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Industry Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
  </onedcx:simpleDc>
  <onedcx:dcTerms>
    <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
    <dcterms:available>2014-07-01</dcterms:available>
    <dcterms:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_cr_1973_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</dcterms:abstract>
    <dcterms:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Urban-rural status; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Costa Rica [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; Canton (20,000 and over), Costa Rica [Level 2; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Ownership of dwelling [general version]; Ownership of dwelling [detailed version]; Electricity; Water supply; Sewage; Telephone availability; Hot water heater; Refrigerator; Television set; Radio in household; Number of rooms; Toilet; Bathing facilities; Floor material; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Head's location in household; Dwelling number; Number of persons in household; Household created by splitting apart a large dwelling; Number of persons in large dwelling before it was split; Province; Region; Urban; Dwelling type; Occupancy and ownership status; Monthly rent; Wall material; Floor material; Roof material; Condition of the dwelling; Total number of rooms; Rooms used only as bedrooms; Water supply; Bathroom facility; Type and use of toilet; Type of lighting; Cooking fuel; Radio and television; Stove and refrigerator; Washing machine and water heater; Electric iron and vacuum cleaner; Telephone; Ownership of appliances (one or more); Crowding (occupants vs. sleeping rooms); Dwelling classification; Condition of the dwelling; Household type (composition); Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Age; Age, grouped into intervals; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Consensual union; Children ever born; Children surviving; Nativity status; Country of birth; Province of birth, Costa Rica; Citizenship; Country of citizenship; School attendance; Literacy; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Years of schooling; Educational attainment, Costa Rica; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Migration status, 5 years; Country of residence 5 years ago; Canton of residence 5 years ago, Costa Rica; Person number (within household); Relationship to head of the household; Sex; Age; Children ever born; Children surviving at the census time; Marital status; Different canton 5 years ago; Residence 5 years ago, canton or country; Place of birth this canton; Citizenship; Nationality code; Social Security affiliation; Social Security type; Currently attending regular schooling; Currently attending any other type of education institution; Educational attainement, regular schooling; Educational level; Literacy; Employment status; Occupation, 3 digits; Occupation, 2 digits; Occupation, 1 digit; Industry, 4 digits; Industry, 2 digits; Industry, 1 digit; Class of worker; Household type, person record; Years of schooling; </dcterms:tableOfContents>
    <dcterms:spatial>Costa Rica</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=11.212845; eastlimit=-82.561400; southlimit=8.025673; westlimit=-85.911391; name=Costa Rica;</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:temporal>1973</dcterms:temporal>
    <dcterms:references>http://international.ipums.org</dcterms:references>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_cr_1973_ddic.xml</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_cr_1973_ddic_xml.html</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</dcterms:accessRights>
    <dcterms:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</dcterms:modified>
  </onedcx:dcTerms>  
</onedcx:metadata>