<onedcx:metadata xmlns:onedcx="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <onedcx:simpleDc>
    <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
    <dcterms:creator>Minnesota Population Center</dcterms:creator>
    <dcterms:title>IPUMS-International: Argentina 2010 Census</dcterms:title>
    <dcterms:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_ar_2010_DC.xml</dcterms:identifier>
    <dcterms:subject>Census</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Appliances, Mechanicals, Other Amenities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Other Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
  </onedcx:simpleDc>
  <onedcx:dcTerms>
    <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
    <dcterms:available>2014-07-01</dcterms:available>
    <dcterms:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_ar_2010_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</dcterms:abstract>
    <dcterms:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Argentina [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; Department, Argentina [Level 2; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Ownership of dwelling [general version]; Ownership of dwelling [detailed version]; Land ownership; Water supply; Sewage; Cooking fuel; Telephone availability; Cellular phone availability; Computer; Refrigerator; Number of rooms; Number of bedrooms; Toilet; Bathing facilities; Floor material; Roof material; Dwelling number; Number of persons in household; Province; Dwelling type; Floors material; Roof material; Interior ceiling; Water location; Water source; Household have bathroom; Household have toilet; Sewage disposal; Private bath; Cooking fuel; Number of bedrooms; Number of rooms; Ownership of dwelling; Land ownership; Refrigerator; Computer; Cellular telephone; Landline telephone; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Age; Sex; Year of birth; Month of birth; Nativity status; Country of birth; School attendance; Literacy; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Years of schooling; Educational attainment, Argentina; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Person number (within household); Relationship to household head; Sex; Age; Birth month; Birth year; Country of birth (Argentina or other); Country of birth outside Argentina; Literacy; Attend school; Educational level; Highest grade completed; Educational attainment; Type of primary school; Completed educational level; Uses computer; Worked at least 1 hour last week; Informal work last week; Did not work but had work; Looked for work last 4 weeks; </dcterms:tableOfContents>
    <dcterms:spatial>Argentina</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=-21.780098; eastlimit=-53.649555; southlimit=-55.051293; westlimit=-73.581548; name=Argentina;</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:temporal>2010</dcterms:temporal>
    <dcterms:references>http://international.ipums.org</dcterms:references>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_ar_2010_ddic.xml</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_ar_2010_ddic_xml.html</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</dcterms:accessRights>
    <dcterms:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</dcterms:modified>
  </onedcx:dcTerms>  
</onedcx:metadata>