<onedcx:metadata xmlns:onedcx="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <onedcx:simpleDc>
    <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
    <dcterms:creator>Minnesota Population Center</dcterms:creator>
    <dcterms:title>IPUMS-International: Hungary 1970 Census</dcterms:title>
    <dcterms:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_hu_1970_DC.xml</dcterms:identifier>
    <dcterms:subject>Census</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Fertility and Mortality Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Ethnicity and Language Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
    <dcterms:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</dcterms:subject>
  </onedcx:simpleDc>
  <onedcx:dcTerms>
    <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
    <dcterms:available>2014-07-01</dcterms:available>
    <dcterms:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_hu_1970_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</dcterms:abstract>
    <dcterms:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Donated household; Group quarters status; Urban-rural status; Continent and region of country; Type of locality, Hungary; Ownership of dwelling [general version]; Ownership of dwelling [detailed version]; Water supply; Sewage; Number of rooms; Kitchen or cooking facilities; Toilet; Number of bathrooms; Bathing facilities; Year structure was built; Age of structure, coded from intervals; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Head's location in household; Dwelling number; Number of persons in household; Number of families in the household; Donated dwelling; Donation strata: strata number; Type of locality; Occupancy of the dwelling; Type of ownership; Ownership; Construction year; Water supply; Water closet (flush toilet); Sewage system; Gas supply; Number of kitchens; Number of bathrooms; Number of rooms (of 13 sqm or more); Dwelling conveniences; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Relationship to head, Europe; Age; Age, grouped into intervals; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Marital status, Europe; Relationship to head of subfamily; Subfamily membership number; Children ever born; Mother tongue, Hungary; School attendance; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Educational attainment, Hungary; Educational attainment, Europe; Labor force status, Hungary; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Class of worker, Europe; Sector of employment; Person number (within household); Age; Sex; Marital status; Household number; Relationship to family head; Number of live-born children; Mother-tongue; Highest educational attainment; Certificate of apprentice school (after 1960); Educational attainment; Economic activity; Occupation; Status in employment; Sector; Commuting to work; Type of locality of work location; Relationship to household head; Family number within household; </dcterms:tableOfContents>
    <dcterms:spatial>Hungary</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=48.574173; eastlimit=22.8948; southlimit=45.748327; westlimit=16.1118; name=Hungary;</dcterms:spatial>
    <dcterms:temporal>1970</dcterms:temporal>
    <dcterms:references>http://international.ipums.org</dcterms:references>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_hu_1970_ddic.xml</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_hu_1970_ddic_xml.html</dcterms:hasPart>
    <dcterms:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</dcterms:accessRights>
    <dcterms:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</dcterms:modified>
  </onedcx:dcTerms>  
</onedcx:metadata>