<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-pie.266.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=PIE,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <title>Individual Towns that are Fully or Partially in the Ipswich Watershed - Idrisi Vector File</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Stephen</givenName>
        <surName>Aldrich</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Ipswich Project, Clark University</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>950 Main Street</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Worcester</city>
        <administrativeArea>Massachusetts</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>01610-1477</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
      <organizationName>Plum Island Ecosystems LTER Program</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Woods Hole</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7485</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>pie_im@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://pie-lter.ecosystems.mbl.edu</onlineUrl>
    </metadataProvider>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <surName>Gil Pontius</surName>
      </individualName>
      <role>additional investigator</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>20010113</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>This datalayer is part of a group of layers used for research in the Ipswich River Watershed. This layer includes the area within each town in the 
      	Ipswich River Watershed in vector form. This map contains complete information and was derived from the ip30_noinfo_towns layer. To show area within the towns 
      	the make up the Ipswich River Watershed study area.</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Town Boundary</keyword>
    	<keyword keywordType="theme">Town</keyword>
    	<keyword keywordType="theme">GIS</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="place">United States</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="place">New England</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="place">Massachusetts</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="place">Ipswich River Watershed</keyword>
    	<keyword keywordType="place">PIE LTER</keyword>
    	<keyword keywordType="place">Plum Island Ecosystems</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <section>
        <title>Use Constraints</title>
        <para>General Data Use Agreement</para>
        <para>Definitions:
          &#8220;Data Set&#8221; &#8211; Digital data and its metadata derived from any research activity such as field observations, 
          collections, laboratory analysis, experiments, or the post-processing of existing data and identified by a unique identifier issued by a recognized 
          cataloging authority such as a site, university, agency, or other organization.</para>
        <para>&#8220;Data User&#8221; - individual to whom access has been granted to this Data Set, 
          including his or her immediate collaboration sphere, defined here as the institutions, partners, students and staff with whom the Data User collaborates, 
          and with whom access must be granted, in order to fulfill the Data User's intended use of the Data Set.</para>
        <para>&#8220;Data Set Creator&#8221; - individual or institution that produced the Data Set.</para>
        <para>&#8220;Data Set Owner&#8221; &#8211; individual or institution that holds intellectual property rights to the dataset. Note that this may or may not 
          be defined as a legal copyright. If no other party is designated in the metadata as Data Set Owner, it may be presumed that these rights are held by the 
          Data Set Creator.</para>
        <para>&#8220;Data Set Distributor&#8221; - individual or institution providing access to the Data Sets.</para>
        <para>&#8220;Data Set Contact&#8221; - party designated in the accompanying metadata of the Data Set as the primary contact for the Data Set.</para>
        <para>Conditions of Use: The re-use of scientific data has the potential to 
          greatly increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines, and thus is fostered, supported and encouraged. 
          Permission to use this dataset is granted to the Data User free of charge subject to the following terms:</para>
        <para>1) Acceptable use. Use of the dataset will be restricted to academic, research, educational, government, recreational, or other not-for-profit 
          professional purposes. The Data User is permitted to produce and distribute derived works from this dataset provided that they are released under the same license terms as those accompanying 
          this Data Set. Any other uses for the Data Set or its derived products will require explicit permission from the dataset owner.</para>
        <para>2 ) Redistribution. 
          The data are provided for use by the Data User. The metadata and this license must accompany all copies made and be available to all users of this 
          Data Set. The Data User will not redistribute the original Data Set beyond this collaboration sphere.</para>
        <para>3 ) Citation. It is considered a matter of 
          professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Data Set in any publications or in the 
          metadata of any derived data products that were produced using the Data Set. Citation should take the following general form: 
          Creator, Year of Data Publication, Title of Dataset, Publisher, Dataset identifier.</para> 
        <para>For example:</para>
        <para>Giblin, A. 1993. Rates of benthic metabolism and nutrient cycling in the Parker and Rowley Rivers of the Plum Island Sound estuary. 
          Plum Island Ecosystems LTER, The Ecosystems Center, Marine Biological Laboratory, Woods Hole, MA 02543.
          http://ecosystems.mbl.edu/pie/data/ben/BEN-PR-Flux.html</para>
        <para>4 ) Acknowledgement. The Data User should 
          acknowledge any institutional support or specific funding awards referenced in the metadata accompanying this dataset in any publications where the 
          Data Set contributed significantly to its content. Acknowledgements should identify the supporting party, the party that received the support, and any 
          identifying information such as grant numbers. For example:Data sets were provided by the Plum Island Ecosystems LTER. This material is based upon work 
          supported by the National Science Foundation under Grants #OCE-9726921, OCE-0423565, OCE-1058747, OCE-1238212.</para>
        <para>5 ) Notification. The Data User will notify 
          the Data Set Contact when any derivative work or publication based on or derived from the Data Set is distributed. The Data User will provide the data 
          contact with two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the Data Set and will provide copies, or on-line access to, any derived digital 
          products. Notification will include an explanation of how the Data Set was used to produce the derived work.</para>
        <para>6 ) Collaboration. The Data Set has been 
          released in the spirit of open scientific collaboration. Data Users are thus strongly encouraged to consider consultation, collaboration and/or 
          co-authorship with the Data Set Creator.</para>
        <para>By accepting this Data Set, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. The Data Owner shall 
          have the right to terminate this agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. 
          The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement.</para>
        <para>Disclaimer: While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation contained in this Data Set, complete accuracy of data 
          and metadata cannot be guaranteed. All data and metadata are made available "as is". The Data User holds all parties involved in the production or 
          distribution of the Data Set harmless for damages resulting from its use or interpretation.</para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url function="information">http://pie-lter.ecosystems.mbl.edu/content/GIS_ip30_info_townsvector</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Ipswich River Watershed, Plum Island Ecosystem, Massachusetts</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-71.3343127</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-70.7134174</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>42.4465968</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>42.7602526</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
    	<temporalCoverage><singleDateTime><calendarDate>2001</calendarDate></singleDateTime></temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>Progress: Complete. Maintenance and Update Frequency: None Planned. Edition: First</para>
        <para>Metadata converted from MSWord documentation on 1.15.2013 by M. Hayn using "PIE_WordMetaConvert" package developed for conversion of data to EML 2.1.0 in R environment.</para>
      </description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <individualName><givenName>Gil</givenName><surName>Pontius</surName></individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Ipswich Project, Clark University</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>950 Main Street</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Worcester</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>01610-1477</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(508)793-7761</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>rpontius@clark.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <publisher>
      <organizationName>Plum Island Ecosystems LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Woods Hole</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7485</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>pie_im@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://pie-lter.ecosystems.mbl.edu</onlineUrl>
    </publisher>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
             Edit town boundary vector polygon to include only polygons within our Ipswich Study Area. Import edited vector polygon 
             into Idrisi 32 Release 2. Rasterize with POLYRAS module. Remove &#8220;no information&#8221; category using a reclass. Vectorize using POLYVEC module.
          </para>
          <para>Process_Date: January 2002</para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
  	<project>
  		<title>Plum Island Ecosystems Long-Term Ecological Research (PIE LTER) Program</title>
  		<personnel>
  			<individualName>
  				<givenName>Anne</givenName>
  				<surName>Giblin</surName>
  			</individualName>
  			<address>
          <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Woods Hole</city>
          <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
  			<phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7488</phone>
  			<electronicMailAddress>agiblin@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  			<role>Lead PI</role>
  		</personnel>
  		<personnel>
  			<individualName>
  				<givenName>Hap</givenName>
  				<surName>Garritt</surName>
  			</individualName>
  			<address>
          <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Woods Hole</city>
          <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
  			<phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7485</phone>
  			<electronicMailAddress>pie_im@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  			<role>Information Manager</role>
  		</personnel>
  		<abstract>
  			<para>
  				The Plum Island Ecosystems (PIE) LTER is an integrated research, education and outreach program whose goal is to develop a predictive 
  				understanding of the long-term response of watershed and estuarine ecosystems at the land-sea interface to changes in climate, land use 
  				and sea level. The principal study site is the Plum Island Sound estuary, its coupled Parker, Rowley and Ipswich River watersheds and the 
  				adjacent coastal ocean, the Gulf of Maine. The PIE LTER focuses on how several aspects of global change influence organic matter and inorganic 
  				nutrient biogeochemistry and estuarine foodwebs. The inputs of organic matter and nutrients from land, ocean and marshes interact with the external 
  				drivers (climate, land use, river discharge, sea level) to dictate the extent and degree of nutrient and organic matter processing and determine the 
  				spatial patterns of estuarine productivity and trophic structure.
  			</para>
  		</abstract>
  		<funding>
  			<para>This material is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation under Grants OCE-9726921, OCE-0423565. Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed in the material are those of the author\(s\) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation.</para>
  		</funding>
  		<studyAreaDescription>
  			<coverage>
  				<geographicCoverage>
  					<geographicDescription>The Plum Island Ecosystems (PIE) LTER site, is located in northeastern Massachusetts, 42.72 N, 70.85 W. The PIE LTER lies at the interface of a thinly soiled, 
  						formerly glaciated New England land mass and the highly productive Gulf of Maine. Three watersheds comprise the estuarine drainage basin: Parker (155 km2), Rowley (26 km2) and Ipswich 
  						(404 km2). The Ipswich River watershed is highly urbanized with Boston "bedroom" communities encroaching in the headwater region while the Parker is less urbanized and retains a 
  						higher proportion of forest.
  					</geographicDescription>
  					<boundingCoordinates>
  						<westBoundingCoordinate>-71.2198</westBoundingCoordinate>
  						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-70.7568</eastBoundingCoordinate>
  						<northBoundingCoordinate>42.8276</northBoundingCoordinate>
  						<southBoundingCoordinate>42.4965</southBoundingCoordinate>
  						<boundingAltitudes>
  							<altitudeMinimum>0</altitudeMinimum>
  							<altitudeMaximum>100</altitudeMaximum>
  							<altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
  						</boundingAltitudes>
  					</boundingCoordinates>
  				</geographicCoverage>
  			</coverage>
  		</studyAreaDescription>
  	</project>
    <spatialVector>
      <entityName>GIS_ip30_info_townsvector</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Vector file of town boundaries in Ipswich Watershed</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>GIS_ip30_info_townsvector.zip</objectName>
        <dataFormat>
          <externallyDefinedFormat>
            <formatName>zip</formatName>
          </externallyDefinedFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>http://pie-lter.ecosystems.mbl.edu/files/gis/GIS_ip30_info_townsvector.zip</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Value</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Town Name</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain>
            <definition>Town Name</definition>
          </textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>    
      <geometry>Polygon</geometry>
      <geometricObjectCount>22</geometricObjectCount>
      <spatialReference>
        <horizCoordSysDef name="NAD 1983 StatePlane Massachusetts Mainland FIPS 2001">
          <projCoordSys>
            <geogCoordSys>
              <datum name="D North American 1983" />
              <spheroid denomFlatRatio="298.257222101" name="GRS 1980" semiAxisMajor="6378137.0" />
              <primeMeridian longitude="0.0" name=" Greenwich" />
              <unit name="degree" />
            </geogCoordSys>
            <projection name="Lambert Conformal Conic">
              <parameter description="Line of constant latitude at which the Earth and the plane intersect" name="Standard Parallel" value="41.716667" />
              <parameter description="The line of logitude at the center of the map projection" name="Longitude at central meridian" value="-71.5" />
              <parameter description="The latitude chosen as center of the projection" name="Latitude of projection origin" value="41.0" />
              <parameter description="A value added in a rectangular coordinate system, usually used to avoid negative values" name="False Easting" value="200000.0" />
              <parameter description="A value added in a rectangular coordinate system, usually used to avoid negative values" name="False Northing" value="750000.0" />
              <unit name="meter" />
            </projection>
          </projCoordSys>
        </horizCoordSysDef>
      </spatialReference>
    </spatialVector>
  </dataset>
</eml:eml>