<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-jrn.20020600.9903" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=JRN, o=lter, dc=ecoinformatics, dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <shortName>JornadaStudy_121_biodiversity_bird_survey_data</shortName>
  <title>The Effects of Changing Vegetative Composition on the Abundance,  Species Diversity and Activity of Birds in the Chihuahuan Desert</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>John</givenName>
      <surName>Anderson</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>
	Jornada LTER

	New Mexico State University

	P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>janderso@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <metadataProvider>
    <organizationName>The Jornada</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>2995 Knox Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-4842</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <onlineUrl>http://jornada.nmsu.edu</onlineUrl>
  </metadataProvider>
  <pubDate>1997</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para> A variety of mechanisms, both anthropogenic and natural, can lead
 to changes in the vegetation composition of a community. In semi-
 desert grasslands, for example, Schlesinger et al. (1990) suggested
 that overgrazing can result in desertification through a shift
 from primarily grasses to desert shrubs. Changes in plant
 communities can also occur as a result of introduced species,
 artificial watering, plant removal for human use, disease,
 competition, and prolonged drought. In the future, global
 problems, such as the greenhouse effect, could possibly lead to
 climate changes (and therefore changes in vegetation) that we can
 only attempt to predict.

 Changes in plant composition have the potential to cause
 disturbances in both structure and function throughout the
 ecosystem. One element of the ecosystem that could possibly be
 affected is bird diversity and behavior. Several studies such as
 Dixon (1959), Raitt and Pimm (1976), Naranjo and Raitt (1993),
 MacAurthur et al. (1962), Vander Wall and MacMahon (1984) and
 Raitt and Maze (1968), all suggest that certain species of birds
 depend more, or entirely, on habitats containing specific
 functional groups or species of vegetation. According to Naranjo
 and Raitt (1993), habitat preferences in birds develop because of
 factors such as availability of food, nesting and perching
 locations, and cover.

 Birds may utilize some plant species more than other plant
 species. Vander Wall and MacMahon (1984) suggest that some
 particular plant species are ideally suited to particular bird
 species. For example, the northern mockingbird relies on tall
 plants for perching and singing sites. Other plant species
 provide cover for birds like the Gambel's Quail. Certain species
 of birds may also use a wider variety of different plants because
 of broad habitat requirements. In this study we examine how
 different types of plant types and growth affect bird abundance,
 bird species diversity, and bird activity in the Chihuahuan
 desert.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>animal</keyword>
    <keyword>behavior</keyword>
    <keyword>birds</keyword>
    <keyword>breeding birds</keyword>
    <keyword>completed</keyword>
    <keyword>desert birds</keyword>
    <keyword>habitat preference</keyword>
    <keyword>perching</keyword>
    <keyword>populations</keyword>
    <keyword>signature</keyword>
    <keyword>singing</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Jornada Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout> From the stone pillars at the south entrance of the Jornada
 Experimental Range (USDA), follow the road west approximately
 4 miles to the first (wretched) gate on the right (north). Go
 through this gate approximately one quarter mile, parking spot
 is on west side of road under power lines. The biodiversity site
 is on the right (east) side of the road across from the parking
 spot.</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>Objectives:
The Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System (JIMS) provides protocol and services for data collection, verification, organization, archives, and distribution in accordance with recommendations and guidelines developed by the LTER Information Managers Committee (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html).

Disclaimer:
While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is". The Jornada Basin LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of data sets.

Quality Assurance Policy:
Data managers interact with researchers during the entire scientific process--from the initial planning of sampling designs and field data collection to archiving and distribution of data. The goal of data management is to build and maintain an archive of Jornada Basin LTER data files that are fully documented, error free, and organized in useful ways. Our protocol for data collection and processing seeks maximum interaction between researchers and data management personnel to avoid confusion and potential loss of data or problems with integrity of data; e.g., identification of historical site treatments that may impact a proposed study or incomplete data set variable descriptions. Site and Data Manager involvement begins during the Project Design phase with the completion of the Jornada Notification of Research form by the researcher prior to the start of work; this alerts both Site and Data Manager to the new study and potential LTER data sets. Upon initiation of a new study, the researcher completes Project Documentation that provides the second level of "metadata" documentation.
In the Data Collection phase, the data manager helps researchers design field and laboratory data sheets that facilitate data entry and analysis. Prior to JIMS data entry the investigator completes Data Set Documentation to provide the metadata that fully describe the data set. Both Project and Data set documentation are provided with the data set when it is requested or obtained from our Web site. JIMS data entry programs error-check and verify data as they are entered. Computer files are subjected to further verification by graphing and/or error-checking programs, and/or examination by field investigators. Final quality assurance of the data rests with the investigator who submits data for inclusion in the Data Management System. Direct communication with the Site Manager, or through a collaborating JRN P.I., is used to encourage the timely submission of documentation and of data by researchers.

Error-checked data files are stored with associated documentation files on the file server. Archived data files are maintained in ASCII format on 30-yr magneto-optical (MO) disks, portable hard drives, CD-R media, and DVD media to guard against loss of data access that can result from changing technology. This may also include proprietary binary format files to facilitate recovery of working versions. Image data are archived on 8mm tape. Routine tape data backups of the file server are done daily, weekly, and monthly. One set of off-site copies are maintained elsewhere on the NMSU campus of routine backup tapes, MO disks, CD disks, and DVD disks with a second set of MO, CD and DVD disks maintained off-campus in case of a catastrophe on campus. The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data manag ement staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data management staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

Policy on Submission of data:
Data submission into JIMS is expected from LTER researchers, LTER collaborators, and their graduate students where data and information is derived from publicly funded research in the U.S. LTER Network, totally or partially from LTER funds from NSF, Institutional Cost-Share, or Partner Agency or Institution where a formal memorandum of understanding with LTER has been established. Other Jornada Basin researchers are encouraged to submit their documented data for inclusion within JIMS to provide them with an archived backup, ensure its longevity, and provide online access to encourage synthesis efforts. Minimally, for non-LTER associated researchers, we request that publications be provided of research conducted on the Jornada Basin.
Initial documentation for a data set must be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager within 90 days of initiation of data collection. Documentation forms are available at http://jornada-www.nmsu.edu/site/dm/readme.php . These consist of Project Abstract and Data Set and Attribute documentation forms, which include objectives of the study, methods, as well as format and content of the data. All data collected during a calendar year should be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager prior to July first of the following year. First time data submissions must be submitted with updated standard Jornada Basin LTER forms previously submitted.

Data Access Policy:
Data will be made publicly available no later than 2 years after submission of the data unless an earlier date is specified by the principal investigator. In the event that an extension of the 2 year period is necessary, the principal investigator may petition the Jornada Basin LTER Executive Committee for a longer protected period. Graduate student research data will be available online after degree completion and they have the opportunity to publish their research.

Policies for re-use, distribution, or the production of derivatives:
Data re-use, distribution and production of derivative products are governed by the LTER Network data policies (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html) in the spirit of having the potential to increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines. Appropriate citation, acknowledgement, notification and collaboration are outlined and recommended. No commercial redistribution of data and derived products are allowed.

Data Acknowledgment Policy:
Please send notification to the Information Manager and Responsible Investigator(s) of the data sets you are downloading and your intended use.
Individuals and institutions utilizing data from the Jornada Basin LTER database are requested to place the following acknowledgment in any publication in which these data are mentioned:
Data sets were provided by the Jornada Basin Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) project. Funding for these data was provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210).

Please send 1 copy of any publication that cites Jornada Basin LTER data to:
     John P. Anderson
     Jornada Experimental Range
     P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
     New Mexico State University
     Las Cruces, NM 88003-0003</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="download">http://jornada-data.nmsu.edu/files/dataset_packages/JornadaStudy_121_biodiversity_bird_survey_data.zip</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>1997-07-01</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>1997-09-21</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <maintenance>
    <description>
      <para>
        <literalLayout> mm/dd/yyyy - Date of Comment
 Int - Initials of person making Comment
 JPA = John P. Anderson
 JL = Jim Lenz
 LFH = Laura F. Huenneke
 PG = Peg Gronemeyer
 Changes/Updates - List any changes made to document

 mm/dd/yyyy Int Changes/Updates
 ---------- --- -----------------------------------------------
 01/10/1997 PG Form completed by investigator
 01/12/1997 JPA Entered into Data Management system
 06/13/2002 JL Added Dataset ID and Project ID sections.
 08/20/2003 JPA Changed to Unrestricted as per LFH e-mail.
 11/15/2011 JPA Changed responsible investigator for contact person
 from Laura Huenneke to John P Anderson per Deb Peters</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </description>
  </maintenance>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Data</givenName>
      <surName>Manager</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>PO Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>The Jornada</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout> Observations (using binoculars) of birds and their behavior were
 recorded on field data sheets.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout> The experiment took place on the Biodiversity plots at the New
 Mexico State University Chihuahuan Desert Rangeland Research
 Center from June through August 1997. The site contained 6
 blocks, each containing 8 treatments. The treatments consisted
 of plots of land (25m x25m) which had been altered by removing
 plant types in a systematic fashion. Species were removed based
 on plant functional group and species dominance within the
 community.

 Birds were observed in each plot for periods of 35 minutes with a
 10 minute acclimation period prior to the start of the
 observation period. The acclimation period was meant to allow
 time for birds to settle and to orient the observer.
 Observations started at sunrise and ended between and 8:30 and
 9:00 am. In all cases, observer movement was coordinated so as
 not to disturb other observers.

 Four observers participated each day, each observing a total of
 four plots. They watched (using binoculars) their assigned plot
 from a step ladder at the corner of the plot in order to get a
 better view of the entire plot. Also, in order to help the
 observers distinguish between adjacent plots, markers were placed
 around the perimeter of the plots. These markers were put in
 place the day before and then promptly taken down so that
 ecosystem function was not disrupted. An attempt was made to
 choose and place the markers so as not to frighten or attract the
 birds in any way. The following data were recorded in each plot:
 species type, time spent in plot, type of vegetation utilized,
 presence of a pair or family group, and behavior. Behaviors
 recorded included perching, singing, calling, foraging on the
 ground, foraging in the vegetation, nesting , and preening.
 Birds that simply flew over the plot or that landed on the plot
 boundaries were not counted.

 There were four replications over the course of ten weeks. The
 replications were done according to a predetermined schedule
 which was developed in such a manner so as to reduce sampling
 error as much as possible. In order to do this, the following
 were avoided: replications of the same plot at the same time of
 day, replicating all of the 6 similar treatments on the same day,
 and having the same observer do more than one of the
 replications of a single plot.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
    <qualityControl>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout> Responsible investigator(s):
 ----------------------------
 Laura Huenneke
 ****************************
 Data access originally restricted until Heidi Bogner had a chance
 to publish. No publication resulted. Data is unrestricted.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </qualityControl>
  </methods>
  <project>
    <title>Jornada LTER</title>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
        <givenName>Debra</givenName>
        <surName>Peters</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-2777</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">575-646-5889</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>debpeter@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Lead Principal Investigator</role>
    </personnel>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Data</givenName>
        <surName>Manager</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Information Manager</role>
    </personnel>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>The Jornada Basin Long Term Ecological Research program, in collaboration with 
                         the USDA ARS Jornada Experimental Range, studies the causes and consequences of 
                         desertification: the broad scale expansion of woody plants into grasslands that 
                         results in more "desert like" conditions. We are interested in spatial and 
                         temporal variation in desertification dynamics, and how historic legacies, the 
                         geomorphic template, transport vectors (wind, water, animals), and environmental 
                         drivers (climate, land use, disturbance) interact with the patch structure of the 
                         vegetation to determine past, present, and future ecosystem dynamics across 
                         scales.
                        
                         Our study site is located in the northern Chihuahuan Desert, approximately 25 km 
                         northeast of Las Cruces, New Mexico, USA (+32.5 N, -106.8 W, elevation 1188 m). 
                         Annual precipitation is 24 cm and maximum temperatures average 13 C in January 
                         and 36 C in June. Our study site includes the 78,000 ha Jornada Experimental 
                         Range operated by the USDA Agricultural Research Service, and the 22,000 ha 
                         Chihuahuan Desert Rangeland Research Center (CDRRC) operated by New Mexico State 
                         University. The Jornada Basin LTER project was established in 1982, and is 
                         administered by New Mexico State University. This site is a member of the LTER 
                         Network, one of  more than 25 long term sites funded by the U.S. National Science 
                         Foundation.</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <funding>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210)</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </funding>
  </project>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>JornadaStudy_121_biodiversity_bird_survey_data.csv</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data file information for the following Jornada data set: The Effects of Changing Vegetative Composition on the Abundance,
 Species Diversity and Activity of Birds in the Chihuahuan Desert
</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>JornadaStudy_121_biodiversity_bird_survey_data.csv</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <numHeaderLines>34</numHeaderLines>
          <numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
          <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url function="download">http://jornada-data.nmsu.edu/sites/jornada-data.nmsu.edu/files/data_files/JornadaStudy_121_biodiversity_bird_survey_data.csv</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1997-07-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>1997-09-21</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Block</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_bird_survey_block</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>block number at BD</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>block number at BD</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Plot</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_bird_survey_plot</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Plot number</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Plot number</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Treatment</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_bird_survey_treatment</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>plot treatment</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1</code>
                  <definition>Control</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>2</code>
                  <definition>PG; perennial grass removed; all perennial grasses removed, (Muhlenbergia, Dasychloa, Setaria, etc.)</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3</code>
                  <definition>RedL; reduced minus Larrea; dominant of each growth form removed, only subordinates remain; Larrea removed as dominant shrub</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>4</code>
                  <definition>RedP; reduced minus Prosopis; dominant of each growth form removed, only subordinates remain; Prosopis removed as dominant shrub</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>5</code>
                  <definition>S; shrub removal; all shrubs removed (Larrea, Prosopis, Ephedra, etc.)</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>6</code>
                  <definition>Simp; simplified; only a single species (the dominant) of each growth form remaining, all subordinate species removed;  plot contains only LATR, ZIAC, MUPO, and YUBA, ( Larrea, Zinnia, Muhlenbergia, and Yucca)</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>7</code>
                  <definition>Ss; subshrub removed; (Zinnia, Xanthocephalum, etc)</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>8</code>
                  <definition>Succ; succulent removed; all leave and stem succulents removed (Yucca, Opuntia, etc)</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>INDV count</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_bird_survey_indv_count</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>total number of individual birds seen in plot</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Time1</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_bird_survey_time1</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>total time (seconds) in plot by family group 
(Time1 is the total time in seconds that any bird spent in a particular plot. Time1 is different from Time2 in that if a family group was present, the young were not counted as individuals, (since they were probably just following their parent and not choosing that plot for any.  For Time2, these young were counted as separate individuals.  This is also true of pairs of birds. For Time1, they were counted as 1 total, and for Time2, they were counted as separate individuals.)</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>sss</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Time2</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_bird_survey_time2</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>total time in plot by family member
(Time1 is the total time in seconds that any bird spent in a particular plot. Time1 is different from Time2 in that if a family group was present, the young were not counted as individuals, (since they were probably just following their parent and not choosing that plot for any.  For Time2, these young were counted as separate individuals.  This is also true of pairs of birds. For Time1, they were counted as 1 total, and for Time2, they were counted as separate individuals.)</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>sss</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>SPP count</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_bird_survey_spp_count</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>number of bird species seen in plot</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>FG count</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_bird_survey_fg_count</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>number of birds foraging on ground in plot</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>FV count</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_bird_survey_fv_count</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>number of birds foraging in vegetation in plot</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>P count</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_bird_survey_p_count</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>number of birds perching in plot</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>SSP list</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_bird_survey_spp_list</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>species codes of birds in plot</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>BTSP</code>
                  <definition>black-throated sparrow</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>SCOR</code>
                  <definition>Scott's oriole</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>LOSH</code>
                  <definition>loggerhead shrike</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>CACW</code>
                  <definition>cactus wren</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>WEKI</code>
                  <definition>western kingbird</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>SCQU</code>
                  <definition>scaled quail</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>GAQU</code>
                  <definition>Gambel's quail</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>CRTH</code>
                  <definition>crissal thrasher</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>HUMMER</code>
                  <definition>unknown species of hummingbird</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>BCHU</code>
                  <definition>black-chinned hummingbird</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>UNKN</code>
                  <definition>unknown bird species</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>UNSP</code>
                  <definition>unknown sparrow</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>HOFI</code>
                  <definition>house finch</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>PYRR</code>
                  <definition>pyrrhuloxia</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>NOMO</code>
                  <definition>northern mockingbird</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>.</code>
          <codeExplanation>missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
</eml:eml>