<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.239.43944" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Gunnison's Prairie Dog Restoration Experiment (GPDREx): Small Mammal Mark-Recapture Population Assessment within Grasslands at the Sevilleta National Widlife Refuge, New Mexico</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Stephanie</givenName>
      <surName>Baker</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-8119</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>srbaker@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Jon</givenName>
      <surName>Erz</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>Jon_Erz@fws.gov </electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Stephanie</givenName>
      <surName>Baker</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-8119</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>srbaker@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <role>data manager</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>Prairie dogs (Cynomys&#160;spp.) are burrowing rodents considered to be ecosystem engineers and keystone species of the central grasslands of North America. Yet, prairie dog populations have declined by an estimated 98% throughout their historic range. This dramatic decline has resulted in the widespread loss of their important ecological role throughout this grassland system. The 92,060 ha Sevilleta NWR in central New Mexico includes more than 54,000 ha of native grassland. Gunnison&#8217;s prairie dogs (C.&#160;gunnisoni) were reported to occupy ~15,000 ha of what is now the SNWR during the 1960&#8217;s, prior to their systematic eradication. In 2010, we collaborated with local agencies and conservation organizations to restore the functional role of prairie dogs to the grassland system. Gunnison&#8217;s prairie dogs were reintroduced to a site that was occupied by prairie dogs 40 years ago. &#160;This work is part of a larger, long-term study where we are studying the ecological effects of prairie dogs as they re-colonize the grassland ecosystem. With this project, we would like to further investigate the impact that Gunnison&#8217;s prairie dogs have on the landscape.&#160; Gunnison&#8217;s prairie dog monitoring data has been collected from the beginning of the reintroduction project, but little information has been collected on how grassland species respond to the sudden presence of prairie dogs on the refuge.This project will help determine if the prairie dog reintroduction has had positive impacts on the grassland ecosystem.&#160; Prairie dogs benefit grasslands in many ways, but their role as ecosystem engineers directly impacts other species by creating new habitat that would not be present without prairie dogs.&#160; We have documented physical landscape changes, but we have not specifically documented benefits to other grassland species.&#160; This work will help determine if the reintroduced prairie dog populations on Sevilleta NWR are now acting as a keystone species in a grassland ecosystem by monitoring small mammal populations to see if species richness, diversity, and density are different on prairie dog colonized areas versus non-colonized areas.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>populations</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>This data is collected each summer, starting in 2013, by an student in the Sevilleta LTER Research Experience for Undergraduates Summer Program.&#160;Data Collector HistoryTy Werdel 2013</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/7269</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <singleDateTime>
        <calendarDate>2013-12-12</calendarDate>
      </singleDateTime>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
      <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint> 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Trapping Location and Design:&#160;Trapping will be done on the Gunnison's Prairie Dog Restoration Experiment (GPDREx)Plots.&#160;&#160;There are 4 of them that rodent trapping is conducted on- A, B, C, and D.&#160;&#160;Each plot will have 169 traps placed in a grid covering 9 hectares. Using the vegetation quad map, there will be a trap placed at 1 meter to the north at each of the following vegetation plots 11-17, 20-26, 29-35, 38-44, 47-53, 56-62, 65-71.&#160;&#160;This accounts for 49 of the traps.&#160;&#160;There will also be a trap placed in between each veg plot, with rows running North/South, which accounts for 42 more of the traps.&#160;&#160;Then making a complete row in between the North/South vegetation quad rows, will account for the remaining 78 traps&#160;&#160;To locate the veg plots, each are marked with a rebar and short white PVC.&#160;&#160;There is a numbered tag on each PVC corresponding to the map.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Trapping Periods:Trapping period will be one plot a week for 4 nights.&#160;Trapping Procedure:Each on the traps should be numbered and flagged as they are first set up on the plots.&#160; This would ideally be Monday morning.The traps are set each evening for four nights.&#160;&#160;This entails setting and baiting the traps at a given locality on Monday afternoon, then checking the traps at dawn on Tuesday (night 1), Wednesday (night 2), Thursday (night 3), and Friday (night 4). Each trap is baited with a handful of steamed, crimped oats tossed into the trap after it is placed on the ground; a few oats are left outside the trap entrance to entice passers-by.&#160;&#160;The ground needs to be smoothed out with a foot to make sure that the trap is level and not unbalanced.&#160;&#160;Each morning, traps are checked as follows:&#160;&#160;the worker walks up and down the transects and closes open traps as you go along.&#160;&#160;Traps are not reopened until the late afternoon/early evening, at which time additional bait is also put in.&#160;When a closed trap is encountered, it is first checked to see if an animal is present by carefully and just slightly opening the door of the trap and looking inside.&#160;&#160;Be aware that kangaroo rats can jump out while doing this, so use caution. Sometimes, although a trap may appear empty, a tiny rodent may be hiding under the treadle (especially in the large traps).&#160;&#160;To check for this, one must reach into the trap and lightly push down the treadle.&#160;If the treadle will not go down, there is likely a mouse underneath.&#160;&#160;If no animal is in the trap, the trap is left closed until the afternoon. If a trap has an animal, the worker processes the animal at the stake and takes the relevant data.&#160;&#160;While checking for animals on Friday morning (night four), traps are picked up, emptied, and returned to storage boxes, ready for placement at another locality the following week.&#160;Importantly, traps MUST BE counted as they are placed into storage boxes in order to insure that no traps (or animals) are left on the plot.&#160;&#160;If rain falls on the baited traps, they may require cleaning and drying back at the field station before storage or use the following week.Animal Processing:For each capture, the trap number is recorded first.&#160;&#160;Next, a given animal is shaken from the trap into a plastic zip-lock bag.&#160;&#160;This is accomplished by securing the opening of the plastic bag over the door end of the trap.&#160;&#160;The door is then opened, and if the animal hasn&#8217;t jumped out on its own, a single, arcing, downward thrust with the open end of the trap facing down into the bag will readily transfer the animal.&#160;&#160;From the bag, the processor grasps the animal with the thumb and forefingers by the loose skin around the back of the neck and shoulders, and then removes it for inspection.&#160;&#160;Each animal is identified to species, then sexed and aged.&#160;&#160;Specific measurements are taken only for those genera which required them for species identification:&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Peromyscus: Total length, tail, foot, ear;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Onychomys:&#160;&#160;Total length, tail, foot.Perognathus, and&#160;Reithrodontomys: Total length, tail.&#160;All measurements are taken to the nearest millimeter using a plastic ruler. Reproductive status is then determined by examination of the genitalia (lactating/vaginal/pregnant/scrotal). In order to recognize recaptures during the week, all new captures are clearly marked on their bellies with a permanent marker (red for females, blue for males). This is not necessary on the fourth morning.&#160;&#160;Before releasing the individual, it is weighed to the nearest gram, using a Pesola scale clipped to the base of the animal&#8217;s tail.&#160;&#160;Recaptures only need to be identified by species and the sex of the animal needs to be recorded.&#160;</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
  </methods>
</dataset>
</eml:eml>