<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-jrn.20020530.9925" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=JRN, o=lter, dc=ecoinformatics, dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Arson burn on LTER-I transect plant line intercepts - LT series (percent cover)</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>John</givenName>
      <surName>Anderson</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>
	Jornada LTER

	New Mexico State University

	P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>janderso@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <metadataProvider>
    <organizationName>The Jornada</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>2995 Knox Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-4842</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <onlineUrl>http://jornada.nmsu.edu</onlineUrl>
  </metadataProvider>
  <pubDate>2000</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para> On March 19, 2000, an arson burn occurred of 2.5 acres of the upper
 grassland area on the Summerford bajada just below the powerline
 road. The area affected included portions of the LTER-I Transect
 Plant Line Intercept study that was begun in 1982. To evaluate the
 impact of the burn on those lines, the line intercepts were read
 for the upper grassland area extending from immediately above the
 creosotebush fringe to the base of Summerford Mountain. The
 stations measured were C73-C89, T75-T90, and X76-X91 (Control,
 Treatment, and Alternate Control, respectively). Measurements were
 made immediately after the burn, after the spring growing season,
 and after the fall growing season in 2000 only. In the initial
 sampling period, the burn area intercepted by the line was noted in
 the data set using a "species" code of BURN.

 Average percent coverage of each plant species per 5-meter segment
 along a 30-meter line intercept perpendicular to each of 91 stations
 on each of the three LTER-I permanent transects. Data consists of
 week number, transect, station number, species, carbon reduction
 pathway, habit, form, and average percent cover. It is sorted by
 transect, station number, then plant species.

 Measurements are made on 30-meter line intercept transects located
 perpendicular to each of 91 stations on each of the 2.7 km long
 Control, Treatment, and Alternate Control Transects established at
 the beginning of LTER-I. Following January 1, 1987, spring line-
 intercepts will only record cover of annual species. All perennial
 cover data will be limited to fall samples. Both annuals and perennials
 are measured during the fall. Measurements were made biannually from
 1982 - 1988. After this they are measured every 5 years. Annuals are
 measured through 1998; however, after this only perennials are measured
 and only in the fall. Each plant line transect is divided into 6
 5-meter segments. Annuals are measured only in the first meter of
 segments 1, 2, and 3 and in the last meter of segments 4, 5, and 6.
 Perennials are measured for the full length of all segments.

 BACKGROUND.
 In the spring of 1982, as part of the establishment of
 the Jornada Long-Term Ecological Research site in southern
 New Mexico, a 135 ha portion of a 1500 ha, internally
 drained, watershed was exclosed from grazing by domestic
 livestock. Prior to exclosure the watershed, as well as the
 rest of the Jornada basin, had been moderately to heavily
 grazed for the past 100 years. Concurrent with grazing, the
 vegetation had undergone a dramatic change from desert
 grassland, with an almost continuous cover of C4 perennial
 grasses, to isolated patches of the original grassland in a
 mosaic with desert shrub dominated plant communities
 (Buffington and Herbel, 1965).
 The exclosure lies along a northeast facing piedmont
 slope at the base of a steep isolated mountain peak, and
 covers a variety of component landforms from the foot of the
 mountain to the basin floor. This provided the opportunity
 to investigate the response of vegetation with respect to
 landscape characteristics as well as release from grazing.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>completed</keyword>
    <keyword>line intercept</keyword>
    <keyword>plant</keyword>
    <keyword>plant community</keyword>
    <keyword>plant cover</keyword>
    <keyword>populations</keyword>
    <keyword>vegetative cover</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Jornada Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout> In the spring of 1982, as part of the establishment of
 the Jornada Long-Term Ecological Research site in southern
 New Mexico, a 135 ha portion of a 1500 ha, internally
 drained, watershed was exclosed from grazing by domestic
 livestock. Prior to exclosure the watershed, as well as the
 rest of the Jornada basin, had been moderately to heavily
 grazed for the past 100 years. Concurrent with grazing, the
 vegetation had undergone a dramatic change from desert
 grassland, with an almost continuous cover of C4 perennial
 grasses, to isolated patches of the original grassland in a
 mosaic with desert shrub dominated plant communities
 (Buffington and Herbel, 1965).
 The exclosure lies along a northeast facing piedmont
 slope at the base of a steep isolated mountain peak, and
 covers a variety of component landforms from the foot of the
 mountain to the basin floor. The northeast side of the
 exclosure is immediately upslope of the College Playa
 located near the NMSU College Ranch.
 Three parallel transects (2.7 km in length) run from the middle
 of the College Playa up into the foot of Mt. Summerford. The Control
 transect is to the west, the Treatment transect on the east side of
 the Control transect, and the Alternate Control to the east of the
 Treatment transect. Each transect is 30 meters wide with a 45 meter
 buffer zone between each transect. The Treatment transect was treated
 annually until 1987 with NHNO3 in a concentration equal to 10g N/m2.
 There are station markers at 30 meter intervals along each transect.
 Perpendicular to each transect and crossing at each station marker is
 the 30 meter plant line intercept transect. This extends 15 meters on
 either side of the station marker. The ends of the plant line intercept
 transect are marker by short rebar sticking up about 6 inches aboveground.
 The plant line intercept transects are thus perpendicular to the
 direction of major drainage flow.
 There are 91 stations on each of the three 2.7 km transects
 with a plant line intercept transect perpendicular to each station.
 This study only uses stations C73-C89, T75-T90, and X76-X91.</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>Objectives:
The Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System (JIMS) provides protocol and services for data collection, verification, organization, archives, and distribution in accordance with recommendations and guidelines developed by the LTER Information Managers Committee (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html).

Disclaimer:
While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is". The Jornada Basin LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of data sets.

Quality Assurance Policy:
Data managers interact with researchers during the entire scientific process--from the initial planning of sampling designs and field data collection to archiving and distribution of data. The goal of data management is to build and maintain an archive of Jornada Basin LTER data files that are fully documented, error free, and organized in useful ways. Our protocol for data collection and processing seeks maximum interaction between researchers and data management personnel to avoid confusion and potential loss of data or problems with integrity of data; e.g., identification of historical site treatments that may impact a proposed study or incomplete data set variable descriptions. Site and Data Manager involvement begins during the Project Design phase with the completion of the Jornada Notification of Research form by the researcher prior to the start of work; this alerts both Site and Data Manager to the new study and potential LTER data sets. Upon initiation of a new study, the researcher completes Project Documentation that provides the second level of "metadata" documentation.
In the Data Collection phase, the data manager helps researchers design field and laboratory data sheets that facilitate data entry and analysis. Prior to JIMS data entry the investigator completes Data Set Documentation to provide the metadata that fully describe the data set. Both Project and Data set documentation are provided with the data set when it is requested or obtained from our Web site. JIMS data entry programs error-check and verify data as they are entered. Computer files are subjected to further verification by graphing and/or error-checking programs, and/or examination by field investigators. Final quality assurance of the data rests with the investigator who submits data for inclusion in the Data Management System. Direct communication with the Site Manager, or through a collaborating JRN P.I., is used to encourage the timely submission of documentation and of data by researchers.

Error-checked data files are stored with associated documentation files on the file server. Archived data files are maintained in ASCII format on 30-yr magneto-optical (MO) disks, portable hard drives, CD-R media, and DVD media to guard against loss of data access that can result from changing technology. This may also include proprietary binary format files to facilitate recovery of working versions. Image data are archived on 8mm tape. Routine tape data backups of the file server are done daily, weekly, and monthly. One set of off-site copies are maintained elsewhere on the NMSU campus of routine backup tapes, MO disks, CD disks, and DVD disks with a second set of MO, CD and DVD disks maintained off-campus in case of a catastrophe on campus. The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data manag ement staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data management staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

Policy on Submission of data:
Data submission into JIMS is expected from LTER researchers, LTER collaborators, and their graduate students where data and information is derived from publicly funded research in the U.S. LTER Network, totally or partially from LTER funds from NSF, Institutional Cost-Share, or Partner Agency or Institution where a formal memorandum of understanding with LTER has been established. Other Jornada Basin researchers are encouraged to submit their documented data for inclusion within JIMS to provide them with an archived backup, ensure its longevity, and provide online access to encourage synthesis efforts. Minimally, for non-LTER associated researchers, we request that publications be provided of research conducted on the Jornada Basin.
Initial documentation for a data set must be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager within 90 days of initiation of data collection. Documentation forms are available at http://jornada-www.nmsu.edu/site/dm/readme.php . These consist of Project Abstract and Data Set and Attribute documentation forms, which include objectives of the study, methods, as well as format and content of the data. All data collected during a calendar year should be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager prior to July first of the following year. First time data submissions must be submitted with updated standard Jornada Basin LTER forms previously submitted.

Data Access Policy:
Data will be made publicly available no later than 2 years after submission of the data unless an earlier date is specified by the principal investigator. In the event that an extension of the 2 year period is necessary, the principal investigator may petition the Jornada Basin LTER Executive Committee for a longer protected period. Graduate student research data will be available online after degree completion and they have the opportunity to publish their research.

Policies for re-use, distribution, or the production of derivatives:
Data re-use, distribution and production of derivative products are governed by the LTER Network data policies (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html) in the spirit of having the potential to increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines. Appropriate citation, acknowledgement, notification and collaboration are outlined and recommended. No commercial redistribution of data and derived products are allowed.

Data Acknowledgment Policy:
Please send notification to the Information Manager and Responsible Investigator(s) of the data sets you are downloading and your intended use.
Individuals and institutions utilizing data from the Jornada Basin LTER database are requested to place the following acknowledgment in any publication in which these data are mentioned:
Data sets were provided by the Jornada Basin Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) project. Funding for these data was provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210).

Please send 1 copy of any publication that cites Jornada Basin LTER data to:
     John P. Anderson
     Jornada Experimental Range
     P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
     New Mexico State University
     Las Cruces, NM 88003-0003</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <coverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>1982-01-01</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>1998-08-14</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <maintenance>
    <description>
      <para>
        <literalLayout> mm/dd/yyyy - Date of Comment
 Int - Initials of person making Comment
 JPA = John P. Anderson
 Changes/Updates - List any changes made to document

 mm/dd/yyyy Int Changes/Updates
 ---------- --- -----------------------------------------------
 08/17/2000 JPA Form completed.
 09/01/2003 JPA References to Week 945 changed to Week 948.
 Added week translation and measurement dates to
 Comments section.
 11/17/2011 JPA Changed responsible investigator for contact person
 to John Anderson per Deb Peters</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </description>
  </maintenance>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Data</givenName>
      <surName>Manager</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>PO Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>The Jornada</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Data recorded on audio cassette tape</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout> Canopy cover of plant species intercepted by a line stretched the
 length of the 30-meter plant line transect are measured and recorded for
 each of 6 5-meter segments. The ends of the line are anchored on
 permanently placed 3/8" rebar extending about 6 inches out of the ground.
 When measurements are to be made, a length of clothesline is stretched
 between the two rebar so it is taut. Before making readings, ensure
 the line is freed from obstructions so it is perfectly straight
 between the two rebar. This may require threading the line through
 large plants or lifting free where the line is snagged.
 The clothesline is pre-stretched overnight when new to
 minimize changes in length when stretched tight in the field.
 The first meter of segments 1, 2, and 3, and the last meter of
 segments 4, 5, and 6, are marked with enamel paint to indicate a new
 segment as well as to identify the portion of the segment where
 annuals are read. The length of the line should be checked before
 beginning a new season of measurements to ensure that stretching
 has not distorted line.
 Data is recorded by identifying Station number (metal
 tag is located on fence post) and Segment number. The 5-meter
 segments are numbered 1 through 6 beginning at the west end of
 the line (right end if facing upslope). Length of each plant species
 that is intercepted by line is recorded. Multiple readings (intercept
 observation) can occur for a single plant if vegetation is broken up
 with open areas along the line intercept. Each new 5-meter line
 segment is identified as it is encountered. Plant species are
 recorded as a 4 letter acronym consisting of first 2 letters of genus
 and first 2 letters of species epithet. If a duplicate acronym
 results for 2 different species, generally the 3rd letter of the
 species epithet is then used. Acronyms used are found in the Plant
 Checklist for the NSF/LTER Jornada Sites.
 Data sheets were used to record the data until Week 300. At this
 time tape recorders were used to record the field data. This data
 was entered and processed using several programs. INPUT.EXE (Fortran)
 is used to input tape recorded data. This data is then sorted by
 transect, station number, plant species, then segment. CONVERT.EXE
 (Fortran) is used to convert the sorted data to a format that matches
 that entered from data sheets. SRELCHEK.EXE (QuickBasic) error checks
 data. (Data must be sorted in the order described above before running
 SRELCHEK.) Once any corrections are made, LTERCOVR.EXE (Fortran)
 summarizes and calculates mean percent cover for each species on
 each 30-meter line transect at each station.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
    <qualityControl>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout> History of Responsible investigator(s):
 Laura F. Huenneke
 ****************************
 On 17 July 1986 the Control Transect was aerially fertilized
 by mistake with granular NHNO3 (equivalent of 10 g N/m2) instead of
 the Treatment Transect. After this the Treatment Transect was
 fertilized by hand by a team of 12 persons using mechanical spreaders.
 As a result of the mistake made in fertilizing the Control Transect,
 the Alternate Control Transect was established parallel and east of
 the Treatment Transect prior to the fall measurements. 91 station
 markers and corresponding plant line intercepts were established so
 they are in-line across the slope with the corresponding station and
 plant line intercept on the Control and Treatment Transects.

 The Treatment Transect was fertilized for the last time on 19 Sep 1987.

 Both Perennials and Annuals are measured for this Arson Burn Plant
 Line Intercept study.

 Week 948 begins 19 Mar 2000. Measurements made 24 Mar 2000.
 Week 954 begins 30 Apr 2000. Measurements made 03 May 2000.
 Week 971 begins 27 Aug 2000. Measurements made 29 Aug 2000.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </qualityControl>
  </methods>
  <project>
    <title>Jornada LTER</title>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
        <givenName>Debra</givenName>
        <surName>Peters</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-2777</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">575-646-5889</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>debpeter@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Lead Principal Investigator</role>
    </personnel>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Data</givenName>
        <surName>Manager</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Information Manager</role>
    </personnel>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>The Jornada Basin Long Term Ecological Research program, in collaboration with 
                         the USDA ARS Jornada Experimental Range, studies the causes and consequences of 
                         desertification: the broad scale expansion of woody plants into grasslands that 
                         results in more "desert like" conditions. We are interested in spatial and 
                         temporal variation in desertification dynamics, and how historic legacies, the 
                         geomorphic template, transport vectors (wind, water, animals), and environmental 
                         drivers (climate, land use, disturbance) interact with the patch structure of the 
                         vegetation to determine past, present, and future ecosystem dynamics across 
                         scales.
                        
                         Our study site is located in the northern Chihuahuan Desert, approximately 25 km 
                         northeast of Las Cruces, New Mexico, USA (+32.5 N, -106.8 W, elevation 1188 m). 
                         Annual precipitation is 24 cm and maximum temperatures average 13 C in January 
                         and 36 C in June. Our study site includes the 78,000 ha Jornada Experimental 
                         Range operated by the USDA Agricultural Research Service, and the 22,000 ha 
                         Chihuahuan Desert Rangeland Research Center (CDRRC) operated by New Mexico State 
                         University. The Jornada Basin LTER project was established in 1982, and is 
                         administered by New Mexico State University. This site is a member of the LTER 
                         Network, one of  more than 25 long term sites funded by the U.S. National Science 
                         Foundation.</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <funding>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210)</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </funding>
  </project>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>ablilt.dat</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data file information for the following Jornada data set: Arson burn on LTER-I transect plant line intercepts - LT series (percent cover)</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>ablilt.dat</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <numHeaderLines>34</numHeaderLines>
          <numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
          <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>Tab-delimited</fieldDelimiter>
            <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url function="download">http://jornada-data.nmsu.edu/sites/jornada-data.nmsu.edu/files/data_files/ablilt.dat</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1982-01-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>1998-08-14</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>File Id</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_arson_burn_percent_cover_file_id</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>file identification code
</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>file identification code
</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Wk</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_arson_burn_percent_cover_wk</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>week number
(Week 1 begins 01 Jan 1982)
(Week 11 begins 12 Mar 1982)
</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>N/A</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>T</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_arson_burn_percent_cover_t</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Transect</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>C </code>
                  <definition> Control</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>T </code>
                  <definition> Treatment</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>X </code>
                  <definition> Alternate Control (begins with Week 247)</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>S</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_arson_burn_percent_cover_s</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>station number
</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>N/A</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">91</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Spp</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_arson_burn_percent_cover_spp</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>plant species i.d.
</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>*</code>
                  <definition>See Jornada LTER Plant Species List @ https://jornada.nmsu.edu/jornada/species/lter-plants</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>C </attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_arson_burn_percent_cover_c</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>carbon reduction pathway
PAR = parasite
</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>carbon reduction pathway
PAR = parasite
</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>H</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_arson_burn_percent_cover_h</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>habit</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>A </code>
                  <definition> annual</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>B </code>
                  <definition> biennial</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>P </code>
                  <definition> perennial</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Form</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_arson_burn_percent_cover_form</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Form</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>FERN</code>
                  <definition>fern</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>FORB</code>
                  <definition>broad-leaved herb</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>GRASS</code>
                  <definition>grass or graminoid</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>S-SHR</code>
                  <definition>sub-shrub</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>ST-SU</code>
                  <definition>tem succulent</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>LF-SU</code>
                  <definition>leaf succulent</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>% Cvr</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_arson_burn_percent_cover_cvr</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>average percent coverage per 5 meter segment of a 30-meter line.
</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>%</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
    <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
<ns2:unit id="N/A" />
<ns2:unit id="%" />
    </ns2:unitList>
  </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>