<dryad:DryadDataPackage xmlns:dryad="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dwc="http://rs.tdwg.org/dwc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1 http://datadryad.org/profile/v3.1/dryad.xsd">
  <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
  <dcterms:creator>Peloso, Pedro L. V.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Frost, Darrel R.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Richards, Stephen J.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Rodrigues, Miguel T.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Donnellan, Stephen</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Matsui, Masafumi</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Raxworthy, Cristopher J.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Biju, S. D.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Lemmon, Emily M.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Wheeler, Ward C.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2015-03-19T16:58:59Z</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
  <dcterms:available>2015-03-19T16:58:59Z</dcterms:available>
  <dcterms:title>Data from: The impact of anchored phylogenomics and taxon sampling on phylogenetic inference in narrow-mouthed frogs (Anura, Microhylidae)</dcterms:title>
  <dcterms:identifier>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.8112f</dcterms:identifier>
  <dcterms:description>Despite considerable progress in unravelling the phylogenetic relationships of microhylid frogs, relationships among subfamilies remain largely unstable and many genera are not demonstrably monophyletic. Here, we used five alternative combinations of DNA sequence data (ranging from seven loci for 48 taxa to up to 73 loci for as many as 142 taxa) generated using the anchored phylogenomics sequencing method (66 loci, derived from conserved genome regions, for 48 taxa) and Sanger sequencing (seven loci for up to 142 taxa) to tackle this problem. We assess the effects of character sampling, taxon sampling, analytical methods and assumptions in phylogenetic inference of microhylid frogs. The phylogeny of microhylids shows high susceptibility to different analytical methods and datasets used for the analyses. Clades inferred from maximum-likelihood are generally more stable across datasets than those inferred from parsimony. Parsimony trees inferred within a tree-alignment framework are generally better resolved and better supported than those inferred within a similarity-alignment framework, even under the same cost matrix (equally weighted) and same treatment of gaps (as a fifth nucleotide state). We discuss potential causes for these differences in resolution and clade stability among discovery operations. We also highlight the problem that commonly used algorithms for model-based analyses do not explicitly model insertion and deletion events (i.e. gaps are treated as missing data). Our results corroborate the monophyly of Microhylidae and most currently recognized subfamilies but fail to provide support for relationships among subfamilies. Several taxonomic updates are provided, including naming of two new subfamilies, both monotypic.</dcterms:description>
  <dcterms:subject>Anchored Phylogenomics</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Narrow-mouthed frogs</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Systematics</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Phylogeny</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Maximum Likelihood</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Parsimony</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Data Exploration</dcterms:subject>
  <dwc:scientificName>Microhylidae</dwc:scientificName>
  <dwc:scientificName>Amphibia</dwc:scientificName>
  <dwc:scientificName>Anura</dwc:scientificName>
  <dcterms:references>http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/cla.12118</dcterms:references>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.8112f/1</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.8112f/2</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.8112f/3</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.8112f/4</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.8112f/5</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.8112f/6</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.8112f/7</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.8112f/8</dcterms:hasPart>
</dryad:DryadDataPackage>