<dryad:DryadDataPackage xmlns:dryad="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1 http://datadryad.org/profile/v3.1/dryad.xsd">
  <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
  <dcterms:creator>Bodenmann, Patrick</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Favrat, Bernard</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Wolff, Hans</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Guessous, Idris</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Panese, Francesco</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Herzig, Lilli</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Bischoff, Thomas</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Casillas, Alejandra</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Golano, Thomas</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Vaucher, Paul</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-04-04T20:06:30Z</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
  <dcterms:available>2014-04-04T20:06:30Z</dcterms:available>
  <dcterms:title>Data from: Screening primary-care patients forgoing health care for economic reasons</dcterms:title>
  <dcterms:identifier>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.2mg29</dcterms:identifier>
  <dcterms:description>Background: Growing social inequities have made it important for general practitioners to verify if patients can afford treatment and procedures. Incorporating social conditions into clinical decision-making allows general practitioners to address mismatches between patients&#8217; health-care needs and financial resources. Objectives: Identify a screening question to, indirectly, rule out patients&#8217; social risk of forgoing health care for economic reasons, and estimate prevalence of forgoing health care and the influence of physicians&#8217; attitudes toward deprivation. Design: Multicenter cross-sectional survey. Participants: Forty-seven general practitioners working in the French&#8211;speaking part of Switzerland enrolled a random sample of patients attending their private practices. Main Measures: Patients who had forgone health care were defined as those reporting a household member (including themselves) having forgone treatment for economic reasons during the previous 12 months, through a self-administered questionnaire. Patients were also asked about education and income levels, self-perceived social position, and deprivation levels. Key Results: Overall, 2,026 patients were included in the analysis; 10.7% (CI95% 9.4-12.1) reported a member of their household to have forgone health care during the 12 previous months. The question &#8220;Did you have difficulties paying your household bills during the last 12 months&#8221; performed better in identifying patients at risk of forgoing health care than a combination of four objective measures of socio-economic status (gender, age, education level, and income) (R2=0.184 vs. 0.083). This question effectively ruled out that patients had forgone health care, with a negative predictive value of 96%. Furthermore, for physicians who felt powerless in the face of deprivation, we observed an increase in the odds of patients forgoing health care of 1.5 times. Conclusion: General practitioners should systematically evaluate the socio-economic status of their patients. Asking patients whether they experience any difficulties in paying their bills is an effective means of identifying patients who might forgo health care.</dcterms:description>
  <dcterms:subject>Primary Health Care</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Cost Sharing</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Health Services Accessibility</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Poverty</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Social Isolation</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:spatial>Switzerland</dcterms:spatial>
  <dcterms:references>http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0094006</dcterms:references>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.2mg29/2</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.2mg29/5</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.2mg29/6</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.2mg29/7</dcterms:hasPart>
</dryad:DryadDataPackage>