<dryad:DryadDataPackage xmlns:dryad="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dwc="http://rs.tdwg.org/dwc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1 http://datadryad.org/profile/v3.1/dryad.xsd">
  <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
  <dcterms:creator>Reichert, Michael S.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>H&#246;bel, Gerlinde</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2015-08-03T13:41:24Z</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
  <dcterms:available>2015-08-03T13:41:24Z</dcterms:available>
  <dcterms:title>Data from: Modality interactions alter the shape of acoustic mate preference functions in gray treefrogs</dcterms:title>
  <dcterms:identifier>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.pm37b</dcterms:identifier>
  <dcterms:description>Sexual selection takes place in complex environments where females evaluating male mating signals are confronted with stimuli from multiple sources and modalities. The pattern of expression of female preferences may be influenced by interactions between modalities, changing the shape of female preference functions, and thus ultimately altering the selective landscape acting on male signal evolution. We tested the hypothesis that the responses of female gray treefrogs, Hyla versicolor, to acoustic male advertisement calls are affected by interactions with visual stimuli. We measured preference functions for several call traits under two experimental conditions: unimodal (only acoustic signals presented), and multimodal (acoustic signals presented along with a video-animated calling male). We found that females were more responsive to multimodal stimulus presentations and, compared to unimodal playbacks, had weaker preferences for temporal call characteristics. We compared the preference functions obtained in these two treatments to the distribution of male call characteristics to make inferences on the strength and direction of selection expected to act on male calls. Modality interactions have the potential to influence the course of signal evolution and thus are an important consideration in sexual selection studies.</dcterms:description>
  <dcterms:subject>sexual selection</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>animal communication</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>preference functions</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>multimodal integration</dcterms:subject>
  <dwc:scientificName>Hyla versicolor</dwc:scientificName>
  <dcterms:spatial>Wisconsin</dcterms:spatial>
  <dcterms:references>http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/evo.12750</dcterms:references>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.pm37b/1</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.pm37b/2</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.pm37b/3</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.pm37b/4</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.pm37b/5</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.pm37b/6</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.pm37b/7</dcterms:hasPart>
</dryad:DryadDataPackage>