<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.281.58927" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Fungal Thermophile Survey at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Don</givenName>
      <surName>Natvig</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>dnatvig@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">13800</userId>
  </creator>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Miriam</givenName>
      <surName>Hutchinson</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>yesterdaymail@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <metadataProvider>
    <positionName>, </positionName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuqeurque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
  </metadataProvider>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Sevilleta</givenName>
      <surName>Information Manager</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <role>data manager</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <pubDate>2012</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para> Biological soil crusts (BSCs) are complex assemblages of fungi, lichens, bacteria, mosses and green algae that stabilize surface soils and manage and traffic photosynthate, nutrients and water to diverse microbial and producer communities in arid environments worldwide.&#160; In Sevilleta grasslands, BSCs occupy much of the open space between clumps of vegetation and vary substantially in terms of structure.&#160;  BSCs have important biological and physical roles.&#160; They have been termed &#8216;mantles of fertility&#8217; because of their general importance in biogeochemical cycling and net primary production in arid ecosystems.&#160; It has been proposed that BSCs play a role in the rapid movement of N, C and water from open areas to plants (see below).&#160; BSCs stabilize soils, and physical and chemical disturbances of BSCs lead to topsoil loss and dust storms.&#160; BSCs are therefore critical components in efforts to understand implications of both climate change and physical disturbance.&#160; Related to this, it has been suggested that BSC diversity can be used to inform conservation policies.  BSCs have been the subject of several previous Sevilleta LTER studies.&#160; Green et al. showed that stable-isotope carbon and nitrogen could be transferred bi-directionally between BSCs and adjacent plants.&#160; This led Collins et al. to propose that fungal hyphae provide connections between plant roots and BSCs that allow for transport between the two, a proposal known as the &#8220;fungal loop hypothesis.&#8221;&#160; Porras-Alfaro et al. have surveyed the diversity of fungi in BSCs from Sevilleta grasslands using molecular methods.&#160; We have also shown that thermophilic fungi are common in BSCs (unpublished results), a result that is not unexpected given the high summer temperatures attained in Sevilleta surface soils.&#160; Yet, many questions remain regarding the organisms present in BSCs, their biological roles and how long it takes for BSCs to re-establish after disturbance.&#160; Long-term, we are interested in the types of fungi present in BSCs and in how fungi function in transporting nutrients between BSCs and adjacent plants.&#160; We are also interested in the extent to which specific fungi provide structure to BSCs and in how they help protect from stress agents such as desiccation.&#160; We are interested in the extent to which fungi might help BSCs tolerate high summer soil temperatures, which often reach &#8805; 60C.&#160; We therefore have a special interest in thermophilic fungi present in the BSCs.&#160; To date, little has been done to actually culture fungi from Sevilleta BSCs, hence the need for the current study.&#160;&#160;  In summary, BSCs are one of the most important features of aridland ecosystems and form a critical interface between physical and biological domains.&#160; Understanding the roles of BSCs in protecting soil structure, and in the cycling of carbon, water and nitrogen, is fundamental to aridland ecology.&#160; The work proposed here continues efforts to characterize the specific fungi associated with Sevilleta BSCs.&#160; It is a modest but important step toward addressing the long-term goals mentioned above.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>populations</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>organizational units</keyword>
    <keyword>habitats</keyword>
    <keyword>populations</keyword>
    <keyword>species</keyword>
    <keyword>population and community properties</keyword>
    <keyword>soil properties</keyword>
    <keyword>organisms</keyword>
    <keyword>fungi</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>Data was collected at: LTER PJ site (N 34 23&#8217; 08.7&#8221; W 106 31&#8217; 27.0&#8221;), a sand dune above the railroad tracks near the Sevilleta wetlands (N34 18' 06.5" &#160;W106 51' 14.1"), gypsum outcroppings (N34 12' 40.5" &#160;W106 45' 35.5"), grasslands near the Sev LTER warming and monsoon sites (N34 21' 34.3" W106 41' 29.4" and N34 20' 38.1" &#160;W106 43' 34.5"), and the Rio Grande Bosque (N34 19'45" W106 51'40").&#160;</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/6906</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Cerro Montosa Pinyon-Juniper site has been the location of major Sevilleta LTER research since 1989. Meteorological trends, net primary productivity, rodent and ground-dwelling arthropod populations, mycorrhizal responses to fertilizer, pinyon-juniper fruit and nut production, and pinyon mortality are all being investigated at this site. Previous studies have included analyses of pinyon tree rings for regional climate reconstruction.Vegetation: The vegetation is New Mexico Pinyon-Juniper Woodland, dominated by Colorado pinyon (Pinus edulis) and one-seed juniper (Juniperus monosperma), and accompanied by gray oak (Quercus grisea).  There is a diverse shrub component, including scrub live oak (Q. turbinella), mountain mahogany (Cercocarpus montanus), broom snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae), sacahuista (Nolina microcarpa), red barberry (Mahonia haematocarpa), Apache plume (Fallugia paradoxa), tree cholla (Opuntia imbricata), skunkbush (Rhus trilobata), and banana yucca (Yucca baccata).  Grass diversity is also high, and open spaces between trees are dominated by blue grama (Bouteloua gracilis), with hairy and sideoats grama (B. hirsuta and B. curtipendula) and black grama (B. eriopoda) also being significant. Other common grasses include purple threeawn (Aristida purpurea), wolftail (Lycurus phleoides), mountain and ring muhly (M. montanus and M. torreyi), and New Mexican porcupinegrass (Heterostipa neomexicana). Common forbs include small-flowered milkvetch (Astragalus nuttallianus), white sagebrush (Artemesia ludoviciana), Fendler&#8217;s arabis (Arabis fendleri), Fendler&#8217;s sandmat (Chamaesyce fendleri), New Mexico thistle (Cirsium neomexicanum), false pennyroyal (Hedeoma oblongifolia), bastard sage (Eriogonum wrightii), ping&#252;e rubberweed (Hymenoxys richardsonii), large four o&#8217;clock (Mirabilis multiflora), Fendler's penstemon (Penstemon fendleri), and globemallows (Sphaeralcea hastulata and S. wrightii). , </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.368</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.368</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1976</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1976</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Rio Grande bisects New Mexico and the Sevilleta NWR, and contains the second largest drainage basin in the southwestern US. The Middle Rio Grande riparian zone extends from Otowi Bridge near Santa Fe south through Albuquerque and the Sevilleta to elephant Butte Reservoir about 150 kilometers south of Albuquerque.&#160; Currently there is an Evapotranspiration (ET) Flux tower installed in Salt Cedar (Tamarix chinensis ) at the San Acacia Diversion as part of Dr. Cliff Dahm's Bosque ET Monitoring project.&#160;Vegetation: Vegetation is characterized as Floodplain Riparian, typically dominated by Fremont cottonwood (Populus fremontii), but in this immediate study site by saltcedar (Tamarix spp.), </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.5222</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.5222</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.15555</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.15555</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1428</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1428</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Warming site is located just to the northeast of the Deep Well meteorological station. The site can best be accessed by parking on the main road next to signs for Deep Well and the mini-rhizotron study. Note that vehicles are not permitted on the road to the Deep Well meteorological station.&#160; Travel on foot towards Deep Well and look for a well-trod path to the northwest shortly before the meteorological station.&#160; For plot maps, see power point slides in the on-line Sevilleta LTER WIKI page. On August 4, 2009, a  lightning-initiated fire began on the Sevilleta   National Wildlife  Refuge. By August 5, 2009, the fire had reached the   Warming site,  which was burned extensively though not entirely. Approximately 50% of  plots burned on August 5 and those plots   which did not burn were burned within  three weeks by US Fish   and Wildlife.&#160; Thus, the condition of all plots  at the Warming site   was comparable by early September 2009.Vegetation: The vegetation is Chihuahuan Desert Grassland, dominated by black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda) and blue grama (B. gracilis)., siteid: 28</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.6908662</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.6908662</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.35946709</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.35946709</southBoundingCoordinate>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Monsoon site is located within Five Points Black Grama, just to the north of the grassland drought plots.&#160;On August 4, 2009, a lightning-initiated fire began on the Sevilleta  National Wildlife Refuge. The Monsoon site was entirely burned on this date, with all plots subjected to fire of comparable intensity.Vegetation: The Monsoon site is dominated by black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda).  Other prevalent grasses include Sporobolus contractus, S. cryptandrus, S. flexuosus, Muhlenbergia arenicola, and Bouteloua gracilis., siteid: 35</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.41489</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.41489</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.20143</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.20143</southBoundingCoordinate>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>2012-06-01</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2012-06-15</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <contact>
    <positionName>, </positionName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuqeurque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
  </contact>
  <publisher>
    <positionName>, </positionName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque, NM  </city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
  </publisher>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout> For each sampling site and sampling period a small amount of surface crust (approx. one teaspoon per sample) was taken from each of 10 locations at approximately 1 meter intervals across a transect.&#160; Samples were transported back to the laboratory in plastic bags. On rare occasions, a larger sample of 0.5 liter volume or less may have been removed at one or two sampling stations.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
  </methods>
</dataset>
</eml:eml>