<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.284.93509" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV, o=lter, dc=ecoinformatics, dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Stress Response from Male-Male Competition in Varying Thermal Environments at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Travis</givenName>
      <surName>Rusch</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>trusch@asu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Michael </givenName>
      <surName>Angilletta</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>angilletta@asu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Michael</givenName>
      <surName>Sears</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress> msears@brynmawr.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <metadataProvider>
    <positionName>, </positionName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuqeurque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
  </metadataProvider>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Travis</givenName>
      <surName>Rusch</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>trusch@asu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <role>data manager</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Travis</givenName>
      <surName>Rusch</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>trusch@asu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>Environmental temperature influences virtually all aspects of organismal performance, including fitness. And since temperature varies throughout space and time, organisms must regularly compete for optimal thermal habitats, much as they do for other resources (e.g. territory, food, or females). However, competition for thermal resources imposes costs, often in the form of a stress response (i.e. increased corticosterone production). Elevated corticosterone promotes physiological and behavioral responses that can increase an organism&#8217;s chance of survival, but if left in an organism&#8217;s system for too long, it will reduce immunity, degenerate neurons, and lower fitness. Previous theoretical and empirical work indicates that, all else being equal, patchy thermal landscapes reduce the energetic cost of thermoregulation. Therefore, I hypothesize that lizards exposed to patchy distributions of preferred temperatures will have less stress (and thus lower levels of corticosterone) than those exposed to clumped distributions. Furthermore, patchily distributed resources are more difficult for territorial males to monopolize, and thus, subordinate males in patchy thermal landscapes should experience less stress than subordinate males in clumped thermal landscapes.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>populations</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>populations</keyword>
    <keyword>biology</keyword>
    <keyword>ecology</keyword>
    <keyword>measurements</keyword>
    <keyword>methods</keyword>
    <keyword>field methods</keyword>
    <keyword>physiological processes</keyword>
    <keyword>species interactions</keyword>
    <keyword>competition</keyword>
    <keyword>organisms</keyword>
    <keyword>animals</keyword>
    <keyword>vertebrates</keyword>
    <keyword>reptiles</keyword>
    <keyword>lizards</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/6922</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The UNM Field Station and USFandWS Headquarters are the primary support facilities for all research conducted on the Sevilleta NWR. As such the area has also been important as a research site - especially as regards meteorology and monitoring of rodent populations for Hantavirus. While the breaks above and behind are characterized as black grama dominated desert grassland, the immediate area around the Field Station is best described as an ecotonal mixture of Plains-Mesa Sand Scrub and Great Basin Scrub vegetaion greatly influenced by honey mesquite (Prosopis glandulosa) and the drainages which bisect the area at regular intervals and support many one-seed Junipers (Juniperus monosperma). Dominant grasses include 4 species of dropseed (Sporobolis contractus, S. cryptandrus, S. flexuosus and S. airoides) and indian rice grass (Oryzopsis hymenoides)</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.885</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.885</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.356</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.356</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1466</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1466</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>2012-07-16</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2012-12-31</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Travis</givenName>
      <surName>Rusch</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>trusch@asu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Sevilleta</givenName>
      <surName>Information Manager</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <publisher>
    <positionName>, </positionName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque, NM  </city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
  </publisher>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Experimental design: Starting in the July of 2012, I will initiate this project as part of a continuing large-scale field study at Sevilleta LTER site in collaboration with PI Michael Angilletta&#8217;s Spatially Explicit Theory of Thermoregulation project. As in past research conducted in 2008, 2009 and 2011, I will use male Yarrow&#8217;s spiny lizard. This lizard thermoregulates accurately in the absence of predators14,15 and aggressively defends resources from conspecific males14,16.Nine outdoor arenas (20 x 20 m), consisting of sheet metal walls and a canopy of shade cloth, will be used to manipulate the thermal environments. Among the arenas, three patterns of shade patches will be replicated three times each to generate distinct thermal landscapes (see Figure 1). &#160;Lizards will be paired by size: large dominant (22-30 g) with a small subordinate (15-21 g). Each pair (n = 12) will be randomly assigned one of the thermal environments. Prior to each trial, males will be habituated to their arenas for 10 days. During this period, each male will be exposed to the thermal arena every other day (for a 24-h period) in the absence of a competitor (total of 5 days per animal). After the habituation period, males will be placed in arenas for a 4-day testing period. Males will spend two of these days in isolation and the other two in competition. Half the pairs will start the trial in isolation (solitary treatment), and the other half of the pairs will start the trial in competition (social treatment). A matched pair of lizards will be placed together in one arena, and the other two arenas will each have one individual (either small or large) placed into it. &#160;After two days, all lizards will be captured and blood samples will be collected within three minutes (speed of collection is necessary to prevent handling stress from affecting plasma corticosterone levels17). Blood will be taken from the orbital sinus with a glass capillary tube and then taken back to the lab where the plasma will be obtained through centrifugation. Plasma will be stored at -80&#730;C for hormone assays18. After bleeding, solitary lizards will be placed together in one arena, and the previously paired individuals will be separated and split between the two remaining arenas. Thus, a completed habituation and observation set for six pairs (two pairs per type of thermal environment) will take 14 days. And 3 sets will be conducted per season giving a total of 18 pairs per season in each thermal environment (54 pairs in isolation and competition per season). Mixed modeling procedures in the statistical software R will be used to quantify the effects of competition and thermal patchiness on the corticosterone levels of lizards19.&#160;Fig. 1. Patterns of shade patches for arenas (each replicated 3x).</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
  </methods>
</dataset>
</eml:eml>