<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.261.26306" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Capital Breeding and Allocation to Life History Demands are Highly Plastic in Lizards at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico: Field Study</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Robin</givenName>
      <surName>Warne</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>rwarne@siu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>The use of stored resources to fuel reproduction, growth and maintenance to balance variation in nutrient availability is common to many organisms. The degree to which organisms rely upon stored resources in response to varied nutrients, however, is not well quantified. Through stable isotope methods we quantified the use of stored versus incoming nutrients to fuel growth, egg and fat body development in lizards under differing nutrient regimes. We found that the degree of capital breeding is a function of an individual&#8217;s body condition. Furthermore, given sufficient income lizards in poor condition can allocate simultaneously to storage, growth, and reproduction, which allowed them to catch up to better conditioned animals. In a parallel, inter-specific survey of wild lizards we found that the degree of capital breeding varied widely across a diverse community. These findings demonstrate that capital breeding in lizards is not simply a one-way flow of endogenous stores to eggs, but is a function of the condition state of individuals and the availability of nutrients during both breeding and non-breeding seasons. Here we explore the implications of these findings for our understanding of capital breeding in lizards and the utility and value of the capital-income concept in general.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>populations</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>consumers</keyword>
    <keyword>species</keyword>
    <keyword>biology</keyword>
    <keyword>physiology</keyword>
    <keyword>measurements</keyword>
    <keyword>methods</keyword>
    <keyword>field methods</keyword>
    <keyword>physiological processes</keyword>
    <keyword>biological processes</keyword>
    <keyword>life history</keyword>
    <keyword>animals</keyword>
    <keyword>vertebrates</keyword>
    <keyword>reptiles</keyword>
    <keyword>lizards</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>&#160;Study Area 1: &#160;*Study Area Name: &#160;Socorro NM*Study Area Location: &#160;BLM land 11 miles south of Socorro, NM*Study Area Description: &#160;Mixed creosote and gramma grass shrubland*GPS Coordinates: &#160;North Coordinate: &#160;33&#176;56'54.88"NWest Coordinate: 106&#176;57'6.26"W&#160;Study Area 2: &#160;*Study Area Name: &#160;Tres pistoles&#160;*Study Area Location: &#160;BLM land 13 miles east of Albuquerque, NM*Study Area Description: &#160;Mixed shrub and gramma grassland*GPS Coordinates: &#160;North Coordinate: &#160;35&#176; 4'44.38"NWest Coordinate: 106&#176;26'48.29"W</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/6689</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>2008-04-10</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2008-07-15</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Sevilleta</givenName>
      <surName>Information Manager</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Lizard Capture:&#160;For measures of capital breeding in wild lizards, females of seven species were caught April through July of 2008 under the approval of the University of New Mexico institutional animal care and use committee (UNM-IACUC #05MCC004). &#160;The species captured were: Cophosaurus texanus, Crotaphytus collaris, Eumeces multivirgatus, Phrynosoma modestum, Sceloporus undulates consubrinus, Urosaurus ornatus, and Uta stansburiana. &#160; Lizards deemed by palpation to be egg-bearing were returned to the lab, euthanized and reproductive tissues prepared for stable isotope analysis (see below). &#160;Stable isotope treatments:After the lizards were euthanized liver, fat body, and thigh muscle samples were harvested, freeze dried and a 0.5 mg sample was placed into a pre-cleaned tin capsule (Costech, #041074, Valencia, CA) for stable isotope analysis. &#160;Eggs and follicles were also harvested, their length and width measured and freeze dried. &#160;All lipids were extracted from freeze dried and ground muscle and eggs/follicles by a 2:1 chloroform and methanol bath; lizard muscle had undetectable amounts of lipids. &#160;The suspended lipids from eggs were pipetted into separate storage vials and air dried. &#160;Lipids and lipid-free egg tissues were then loaded into tin capsules. &#160;We measured the &#948;13C of each egg and follicle greater than 6mm in length (&#189; the length of shelled eggs and assumed to reflect reproductive allocation). &#160;Our stable isotope methodology follows standard methods and our protocol is described in detail in Warne et al. (2010a, 2010b). &#160;We report all isotope values in the standard delta notation (&#948;X = (Rsample /Rstandard &#8211; 1) x 1000) in parts per thousand (&#8240;) relative to the international carbon standard VPDB (Vienna Pee Dee Belemnite). &#160;Measurements were conducted on a continuous flow isotope ratio mass spectrometer in the UNM Earth and Planetary Sciences Mass Spectrometry lab. &#160;The precision of these analyses was &#177; 0.1&#8240; SD for &#948;13C based on long-term variation of the working laboratory standard (valine &#948;13C = -26.3&#8240; VPDB), samples of which were included on each run in order to make corrections to raw values obtained from the mass spectrometer.&#160;Essential to this study is the observation that differences in photosynthetic biochemistry inherent to C3- and C4-plants produces distinct differences in the d13C of their tissues, which can be used to trace the movement of nutrients through consumers (Hobson et al. 1997, O'Brien et al. 2000). &#160;Because winter and summer monsoonal rains drive seasonally separated C3 and C4 plant production and resource flux in Chihuahuan Desert food webs (Warne et al. 2010b), we hypothesized that we could use natural variation in the &#948;13C of C3 and C4 resources to examine capital breeding in wild lizards. We predicted that during the late summer and early fall lizards would develop endogenous lipid stores (capital) from C4 derived sources because C4 plants (primarily grasses) comprise the bulk of primary production during this period. &#160;We also hypothesized that reproduction in the spring (the income source) would be fueled by C3 plants associated with winter rains. We subsequently sampled female lizards of a variety of species during April through June 2008 to gauge the relative use of capital (C4) versus income (C3) resources for their first clutch of the season. &#160;The lizards were collected from a mixed Creosote and gramma grassland.&#160;We used tissue d13C values and a standard two-end-point mixing model to estimate the proportion of endogenous fat or muscle (capital) and incoming insect-dietary sources used to provision eggs. &#160;The mean &#948;13C value of insects feeding on C3 plants (-27.3&#8240;) served as an income source (see Warne et al. 2010b). &#160;The discrimination (&#916;13C) values used in this model for muscle (-1.9&#8240;) and fat bodies (0&#8240;) were experimentally determined for S. undulatus (Warne et al. 2010a). &#160;</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
  </methods>
</dataset>
</eml:eml>