<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-cdr." scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd"><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=CDR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataset scope="document"><alternateIdentifier>knb-lter-cdr.aaae211.1</alternateIdentifier><shortName>aaae211</shortName><title>Decomposition Model Parameters : Nitrogen limitation in decomposition</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Sarah</givenName><surName>Hobbie</surName></individualName></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><organizationName>Cedar Creek LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Cedar Creek Ecosystem Science Reserve</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>100 Ecology Building</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>1987 Upper Buford Circle</deliveryPoint><city>Saint Paul</city><administrativeArea>MN</administrativeArea><postalCode>55108</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">612-625-5740</phone><phone phonetype="fax">612-624-6777</phone><electronicMailAddress>webmaster@cedarcreek.umn.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.cedarcreek.umn.edu/</onlineUrl></metadataProvider><pubDate>2012-06-14</pubDate><abstract><para>Modern agriculture and fossil fuel combustion contribute to the transfer of N from largely inert pools (atmospheric N2, fossil fuel reserves) to biologically reactive forms that can be transported downwind from agricultural or industrial areas to ecosystems that historically may have experienced low levels of N inputs. Understanding how increased N inputs alter the cycling of another biologically important element, C, has been impeded by uncertainties about N effects on the process of decomposition. To date, ecologists remain unable to predict when, where, and in what forms N addition stimulates rates of decomposition. For example, recent work showed that in eight low-N sites in Central Minnesota, litter N was positively correlated with decomposition, suggesting N limitation of decomposition, yet addition of inorganic N fertilizer increased decomposition in only two of eight sites. These paradoxical results call into question the assumption that the often-observed correlation between substrate N concentration and decomposition arises because N limits decomposition. Research is addressing three interrelated questions:* (1) Why do litter N and externally supplied N have contrasting effects on decomposition in low-N ecosystems? (2) Do different forms of N (organic vs. inorganic; substrate vs. externally supplied) affect the activity, function and composition of the decomposer community differently, and, if so, what are the consequences for decomposition? (3) What are temporal dynamics of the activity, function, and composition of the decomposer community and do these dynamics depend upon the amount and forms of N supplied to the decomposer community?* These questions will be addressed using a 4-y decomposition experiment manipulating the quantity and form of N available to decomposers via use of substrates ranging in N concentrations and of inorganic (ammonium nitrate) and organic (amino acids) N fertilizers. The response of microbial biomass, stoichiometry, efficiency, function (decomposition rate, enzyme activity) and community structure (assessed using phospholipids fatty acid analysis) are being compared among treatments. The proposed research will increase understanding of how atmospheric N deposition alters C cycling in ecosystems. 
 
This research is additionally supported by an NSF CAREER award to Sarah E. Hobbie (DEB-0347103). Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed in the material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">Decomposition</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Ecology</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Modeling</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Organisms</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Substrates</keyword></keywordSet><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage id="geoReferenceID" scope="document"><geographicDescription>The Cedar Creek Ecosystem Science Reserve is located in Anoka and Isanti counties, approximately 30 miles north of Saint Paul, MN. CCNHA lies at the boundary between prairie and forest. It is a mosaic of uplands dominated by oak savanna, prairie, hardwood forest, pine forests,and abandoned agricultural fields and of lowlands comprised of ash and cedar swamps, acid bogs, marshes, and sedge meadows. Large tracts of the pre-agricultural ecosystems of the region are preserved within its boundaries, as is a successional chronosequence of more than 80 old fields of known history.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-93.22445</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-93.16289</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>45.44138</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>45.384865</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2005</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2005</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Dan</givenName><surName>Bahauddin</surName></individualName><organizationName>Cedar Creek Ecosystem Science Reserve</organizationName><positionName>Information Manager</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Ecology Evolution and Behaviour Dept. University Of Minnesota</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>100 Ecology Building</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>1987 Upper Buford Circle</deliveryPoint><city>Saint Paul</city><administrativeArea>MN</administrativeArea><postalCode>55108</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">612-625-5740</phone><phone phonetype="fax">612-624-6777</phone><electronicMailAddress>webmaster@cedarcreek.umn.edu</electronicMailAddress></contact><methods><methodStep><description><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Plot Treatments</para></listitem><listitem><para>In fall 2004, at each site we initiated a nutrient enrichment experiment. Plots (3 m2, 1.5 x 2 m) received one of the following treatments (5 replicate plots/treatment): control (X, no nutrient addition), inorganic N addition (IN, 10 g N m-2 y-1 as NH4NO3), organic N addition (ON, 10 g N m-2 y-1 as 3.33 g N m-2 y-1 each of alanine, glycine, and glutamate), carbon addition (C, 28.5 g C m-2 y-1 as D-glucose, the same rates of C addition as in the ON treatment), inorganic N + carbon addition (INC, 10 g N m-2 y-1 as NH4NO3 + 28.5 g C m-2 y-1 as D-glucose), long-term N addition (LTN, 10 g N m-2 y-1 as NH4NO3, initiated in 1999 as part of another experiment, Hobbie 2008), and non-N nutrient addition (NON, 10 g P m-2 y-1 and, 12.6 g K m-2 y-1 as KH2PO4, 10 g Ca m-2 y-1 as CaCl2, 5 g Mg m-2 y-1 and 6.6 g S m-2 y-1 as MgSO4, 0.5 g Fe m-2 y-1 as FeNaEDTA). All nutrients were added in aqueous solution divided into three applications over the season (May, July, October, 1 L solution plot-1 application-1; control plots received water only). Except in the LTN treatment, treatments were initiated in August, 2004 with one-third of the annual application rate.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Substrates</para></listitem><listitem><para>Four substrates used in the experiments were: 
9G: green leaves (collected by hand picking fully expanded leaves from branches) one unburned stand (Burn Unit 209, never burned) 
9B: leaf litter (collected by hand picking freshly fallen litter from the ground) from one unburned stand (Burn Unit 209, never burned) 
3G: green leaves from a frequently burned stand (Burn Unit 103, burned 0.7 fire/year) 
3B: leaf litter from a frequently burned stand (Burn Unit 103, burned 0.7 fire/year)</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Sites</para></listitem><listitem><para>The study was conducted in three forested sites at the Cedar Creek Ecosystem Science Reserve, a Long Term Ecological Research (LTER) site in central Minnesota (latitude 45.40 N, longitude 93.20 W, elevation 270 m) located on sandy, poorly developed soils. Sites included two forest stands dominated by Quercus ellipsoidalis (Oak N, Oak S) and one stand dominated by Pinus strobus (Pine).</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></description></methodStep></methods><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>e211_Decomposition Model Parameters</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>e211_Decomposition Model Parameters.txt</objectName><size unit="rows">420</size><characterEncoding>ASCCII</characterEncoding><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines><recordDelimiter>\r</recordDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>\t</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution id="dist_knb-lter-cdr." scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-cdr.&amp;urlTail=lno_data_request.php?input=aaae211</url></online><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=CDR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Site</attributeName><attributeDefinition>site within Cedar Creek where experiment was conducted</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>site within Cedar Creek where experiment was conducted</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Treatment</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Treatment code</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>X</code><definition>Control. no nutrient addition</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>IN</code><definition>inorganic N addition. 10 g N m-2 y-1 as NH4NO3</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>ON</code><definition>organic N addition. 10 g N m-2 y-1 as 3.33 g N m-2 y-1 each of alanine glycine and glutamate</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>C</code><definition>carbon addition. 28.5 g C m-2 y-1 as D-glucose the same rates of C addition as in the ON treatment</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>INC</code><definition>inorganic N   carbon addition . 10 g N m-2 y-1 as NH4NO3   28.5 g C m-2 y-1 as D-glucose</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>LTN</code><definition>long-term N addition. 10 g N m-2 y-1 as NH4NO3</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>NON</code><definition>non-N nutrient addition. 10 g P m-2 y-1 and 12.6 g K m-2 y-1 as KH2PO4 10 g Ca m-2 y-1 as CaCl2 5 g Mg m-2 y-1 and 6.6 g S m-2 y-1 as MgSO4 0.5 g Fe m-2 y-1 as FeNaEDTA</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Replicate</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Replicate</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Replicate</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Substrate</attributeName><attributeDefinition>substrate (litter type) decomposed</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>substrate (litter type) decomposed</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>ID</attributeName><attributeDefinition>sample identification number</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>sample identification number</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>k (single)</attributeName><attributeDefinition>decay constant obtained by fitting the proportion mass remaining over time with a single exponential decay model</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>decayConstant</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>k (asymptote)</attributeName><attributeDefinition>initial exponential decay constant obtained by fitting the proportion mass remaining over time with an asymptotic decomposition model</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>decayConstant</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><metadata><ns2:unitList convention="CML"><ns2:unit constantToSI="0.0" id="decayConstant" multiplierToSI="1.0" name="decayConstant"><ns2:description>decayConstant</ns2:description></ns2:unit></ns2:unitList></metadata></additionalMetadata></eml:eml>