<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-cdr." scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd"><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=CDR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataset scope="document"><alternateIdentifier>knb-lter-cdr.nohe053.1</alternateIdentifier><shortName>nohe053</shortName><title>Soil nitrate and ammonium: Components of Plant Competition Along an Experimental Gradient of Nitrogen Availability</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Scott</givenName><surName>Wilson</surName></individualName></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><organizationName>Cedar Creek LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Cedar Creek Ecosystem Science Reserve</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>100 Ecology Building</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>1987 Upper Buford Circle</deliveryPoint><city>Saint Paul</city><administrativeArea>MN</administrativeArea><postalCode>55108</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">612-625-5740</phone><phone phonetype="fax">612-624-6777</phone><electronicMailAddress>webmaster@cedarcreek.umn.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.cedarcreek.umn.edu/</onlineUrl></metadataProvider><pubDate>2012-06-14</pubDate><abstract><para>This experiment was set up in Field C, on top of the already existing experiment C011. For a description of the plot layout, see E011. For a list of fertilizer treatments for each plot, see file trmte11 and fertilization details. The object of this research was to measure the intensity of above and below-ground competition along a gradient of soil resource availability. Neighbor effects were quantified by measuring the biomass, growth, morphology and survivorship of three species transplanted into vegetation along a gradient of soil nitrogen availability. Transplants were used to test for an inverse relationship between above and below-ground competition, variation in the intensity of competition at different levels of nutrient availability, and reversal of competitive hierarchies. Eight plots of each nitrogen treatment were randomly selected and used for competition experiments. Three competition treatments were used to measure the above and below-ground effects of neighbors on transplanted seedlings at each rate of nitrogen supply. Transplants were grown in subplots with no neighbors, or in subplots with the roots but not shoots of neighbors, or in subplots with all above- and below-ground parts of neighbors present. No neighbor treatments were imposed by driving a ring of galvanized sheet steel (50cm in diameter, 15cm tall) into the ground until the top of it was at the soil surface and then killing all the plants in the enclosed circle with a systemic, rapidly decomposing herbicide (Roundup). Transplants were grown with only the roots of neighbors using white plastic garden net (50x50cm; mesh:1x2cm) to tie back the shoots and leaves of neighbors so that a transplant in the center of the net was not shaded by neighbors but was surrounded by neighbor roots. The all neighbors treatment consisted of a transplant grown in the center of a 50cm x 50cm subplot of undisturbed vegetation. Treatments were replicated five times for each of three transplanted species in each of the 8 replicate plots for each of the three levels of the experimental nitrogen gradient. Thus, the 24 plots of the nitrogen gradient (3 nitrogen levels x 8 replicates used in the competition experiment) each contained 45 subplots(3 competition treatments x 3 transplanted species x 5 replicates), each subplot comprising one transplant of a single species in one competition treatment. A total of 1080 seedlings were transplanted. Competition treatments and species were assigned randomly to subplots within each plot. Transplants were of three grass species, Schizachyrium scoparium, Poa pratensis and Agropyron repens, selected for their different distributions along the experimental nitrogen gradient. One transplant was planted in the center of each subplot.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">Biodiversity</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Climatic Variation</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Disturbance Patterns</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Ecology</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Ecosystem functioning</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Fire Frequency</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Long Term</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Nitrogen limitation</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Nutrient Budgets</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Nutrient Cycles</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Plant Competition</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Primary Productivity</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Successional dynamics</keyword></keywordSet><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage id="geoReferenceID" scope="document"><geographicDescription>The Cedar Creek Ecosystem Science Reserve is located in Anoka and Isanti counties, approximately 30 miles north of Saint Paul, MN. CCNHA lies at the boundary between prairie and forest. It is a mosaic of uplands dominated by oak savanna, prairie, hardwood forest, pine forests,and abandoned agricultural fields and of lowlands comprised of ash and cedar swamps, acid bogs, marshes, and sedge meadows. Large tracts of the pre-agricultural ecosystems of the region are preserved within its boundaries, as is a successional chronosequence of more than 80 old fields of known history.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-93.22445</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-93.16289</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>45.44138</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>45.384865</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1988</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>1988</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Dan</givenName><surName>Bahauddin</surName></individualName><organizationName>Cedar Creek Ecosystem Science Reserve</organizationName><positionName>Information Manager</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Ecology Evolution and Behaviour Dept. University Of Minnesota</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>100 Ecology Building</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>1987 Upper Buford Circle</deliveryPoint><city>Saint Paul</city><administrativeArea>MN</administrativeArea><postalCode>55108</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">612-625-5740</phone><phone phonetype="fax">612-624-6777</phone><electronicMailAddress>webmaster@cedarcreek.umn.edu</electronicMailAddress></contact><methods><methodStep><description><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Field Operations: Fertilization</para></listitem><listitem><para>Fertilizer is mixed and spread by hand twice a year, once in early May and once in late June. Each plot gets the fertilizer mixture specified by its fertilizer treatment code.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Field Operations: Fencing</para></listitem><listitem><para>The entire experiment was surrounded by electric fence to discourage entry by white-tailed deer.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Field Operations: Competition Treatments</para></listitem><listitem><para>No neighbor treatment was imposed by driving a ring of galvanized sheet steel (50cm diameter, 15cm tall) into the ground until its top was at the soil surface, and killing all plants in the enclosed area with Roundup. Any resprouting neighbor biomass was removed by hand. Steel was installed during May 11-13, 1988 and Roundup applied on 13 May 1988. Transplants that were grown with only roots of neighbors had a net that tied back the shoots and leaves of neighbors so that a transplant in the center of the net was not shaded by neighbors but was surrounded by neighbor roots. White plastic garden net (50cm x 50cm; mesh:1cm x 2cm) was fastened at its center to the soil surface using four steel pins, each 8cm long. The center portion (5cm x 5cm) of the net was cut out to allow transplanting. The outer corners of the net were held 10cm above the soil using pins 20cm long. Nets were installed on May 16, 1988.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Field Operations: Insecticide</para></listitem><listitem><para>Transplants were dusted with an insecticide (Sevin) weekly during June to prevent insect grazing.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Field Operations: Small Mammal Trapping</para></listitem><listitem><para>1400-trap nights in May and June failed to capture any small mammals.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Sampling for C053</para></listitem><listitem><para>During May 18-19, the length of each tiller of Agropyron and Poa was measured from its base to the tip of the longest leaf. This information was used to calculate total tiller length, tiller number, and mean tiller length for each individual. Because of difficulty in distinguishing individual tillers of Schizachyrium seedlings, leaf number was recorded for this species. The above and below-ground biomass of 50 seedlings of each species was measured and tested for correlation with size measurements. 
 
Tiller number, total tiller length, and flowering stem number of transplants were recorded during September 5-9, 1988. The above-ground parts of transplants were harvested during September 12-16, dried to constant mass, and weighed. 
 
Survivorship was determined as the proportion of each species in each competition treatment in each plot that survived from planting to harvest. The proportion of flowering individuals of Schizachyrium was recorded. All above-ground plant material within 15cm of each transplant ("neighbor biomass") was harvested after the transplant had been harvested. Neighbor biomass was harvested during September 12-23, 1988, dried to constant mass and weighed. One sample from each competition treatment in each plot was separated into live standing crop and litter before weighing. The mean proportion of live neighbor biomass in each competition treatment at each nitrogen level was used to estimate live neighbor biomass in each subplot. Root biomass was measured in soil cores taken 10cm from each transplant during September 12-23. Cores were sieved through a 2mm mesh to remove sand and then washed, dried and weighed.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Vegetation Sampling Methods</para></listitem><listitem><para>E053 is in field C. Species composition was measured on August 28, 1988 in those plots not involved in the competition experiments. This was done by centering a 0.5m x 1m quadrat in each plot and recording the cover of each species using Daubenmire's scale (Mueller-Dombois and Ellenberg 1974). Cover values were converted to equivalent percent and the mean cover of each species in each treatment was determined. 
 
Documentation on where the strips are located for each year can be found in the clipping maps.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>"Microplot" Fertilization Treatments</para></listitem><listitem><para>The "microplot" fertilization treatments are used in experiments 1, 2, 4, 8, 9, 11, 23, 25, and 52. Experiments 5, 6, 28, 36,53,97, 98 and 100 are conducted within plots that are fertilized and should be treated as part of the fertilized plot.  There are nine treatment levels, assigned a letter A through I. This is also equivalent to the numeric labels 1 to 9. Treatment levels A through H differ in the amount of NH4NO3 added. Treatment I is a true control and receives no nutrients. The nutrients are applied twice a year, once in early May and once in late June. An exception is experiment 25 where time of application is experimentally manipulated. Not all experiments  use all possible treatments. Nutrients are given in g/m2 for each fertilization; plot area and treatments used follow the nutrient lists. 
 
Treatment A to H receive the following base nutrients: 
	 	 	 
Rate  	Volume  	Element 
10 g/m2  	150 ml  	P2O5 (0-46-0) 
10 g/m2  	150 ml  	K2O (0-0-61) 
20 g/m2  	200 ml  	CaCO3 (lime) 
15m2  	200 ml  	MgSO4 (Epsom Salts) 
0.0625 ml/m2  	trace mineral solution in 1 ml to 10 ml sand	 	 	 
 
The description for making trace mineral sand is at the end of this section. 
 
The amount of NH4NO3 fertilizer added at the different treatment levels is: 
	 	 	 
Treatment  	Rate  	Volume 
A  	0.0 g/m2  	0 ml 
B  	1.5 g/m2  	25 ml 
C  	3.0 g/m2  	50 ml 
D  	5.0 g/m2  	90 ml 
E  	8.0 g/m2  	140 ml 
F  	14.0 g/m2  	250 ml 
G  	25.0 g/m2  	445 ml 
H  	40.0 g/m2  	710 ml 
I  	0.0 g/m2  	0 ml	 	 	 
 
These rates are added twice a year. Actual annual N addition is calculated as: 
 
0.34%N * rate (g/m2) * 2 times/year 
 
The trace mineral stock solutions are made by adding the following grams of reagent to 1000 ml of water: 
 
CuSO4*5H2O 9.8 g 
ZnSO4*7H2O 22.0 g 
or 
ZnCl2 10.5 g 
CoCl2*6H2O 10.0 g 
MnCl2*4H2O 180.0 g 
Na2MoO4*2H2O 6.3 g 
H3BO3 6.0 g 
 
The trace metal solution is made by combining 120ml of each stock solution, adding 67.2g of citric acid dissolved in deionized water and adding deionized water to bring the volume to a total of 2 liters. The working solution is then autoclaved to chelate the trace metals. 
 
The size of the plots and treatments used for each experiment are: 
	 	 	 
Experiment  	Treatments  	Plot size (m2) 
Experiment 1 except Field D  	A thru I  	16 
Experiment 1 Field D  	A thru I  	6 
Experiment 2  	A thru I  	16 
Experiment 4  	E, G, I  	1000 
Experiment 8  	C, F, H, I  	16 
Experiment 9  	C, F, H, I  	16 
Experiment 11  	E, G, I  	16 
Experiment 24  	E, G, I  	16 
Experiment 25  	E, G, I  	5.25 
Experiment 52  	A, C, F, G  	25</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></description></methodStep></methods><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>e053_Soil nitrate and ammonium</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>e053_Soil nitrate and ammonium.txt</objectName><size unit="rows">216</size><characterEncoding>ASCCII</characterEncoding><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines><recordDelimiter>\r</recordDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>\t</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution id="dist_knb-lter-cdr." scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-cdr.&amp;urlTail=lno_data_request.php?input=nohe053</url></online><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=CDR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Field number/letter</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Field number/letter</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Field number/letter</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Experiment number</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Experiment number</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Experiment number</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Plot number</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Plot number</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Plot number</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Cell number</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Cell number</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Cell number</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Nitrogen Treatment</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Nitrogen Treatment</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>1</code><definition>0.0 g/m2 0 ml</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>2</code><definition>1.5 g/m2 25 ml</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>3</code><definition>3.0 g/m2 50 ml</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>4</code><definition>5.0 g/m2 90 ml</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>5</code><definition>8.0 g/m2 140 ml</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>6</code><definition>14.0 g/m2 250 ml</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>7</code><definition>25.0 g/m2 445 ml</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>8</code><definition>40.0 g/m2 710 ml</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>9</code><definition>0.0 g/m2 0 ml</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Competition Treatment</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Competition Treatment</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>1</code><definition>0.0 g/m2 0 ml</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>2</code><definition>1.5 g/m2 25 ml</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>3</code><definition>3.0 g/m2 50 ml</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>4</code><definition>5.0 g/m2 90 ml</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>5</code><definition>8.0 g/m2 140 ml</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>6</code><definition>14.0 g/m2 250 ml</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>7</code><definition>25.0 g/m2 445 ml</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>8</code><definition>40.0 g/m2 710 ml</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>9</code><definition>0.0 g/m2 0 ml</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Sampling date</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Sampling date</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>YYMMDD</formatString></dateTime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Species Taxon code</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Code specific to unique species or category samples have been seperated into</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Code specific to unique species or category samples have been seperated into</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>NH4 in soil (mg/kg)</attributeName><attributeDefinition>NH4 in soil (mg/kg)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>milligramsPerKilogram</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>NO3 in soil (mg/kg)</attributeName><attributeDefinition>NO3 in soil (mg/kg)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>milligramsPerKilogram</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>NH4 + NO3 in soil (mg/kg)</attributeName><attributeDefinition>NH4 + NO3 in soil (mg/kg)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>milligramsPerKilogram</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><metadata><ns2:unitList convention="CML"><ns2:unit constantToSI="0.0" id="milligramsPerKilogram" multiplierToSI="1.0" name="milligramsPerKilogram"><ns2:description>milligramsPerKilogram</ns2:description></ns2:unit></ns2:unitList></metadata></additionalMetadata></eml:eml>