<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-ntl.73.5" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0  http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
	<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
		<allow>
			<principal>uid=NTL,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
			<permission>all</permission>
		</allow>
		<allow>
			<principal>public</principal>
			<permission>read</permission>
		</allow>
	</access>
	<dataset>
		<alternateIdentifier system="NTL-DEIMS">5621</alternateIdentifier>
		<shortName>CPROC1</shortName>
		<title>Cascade Project at North Temperate Lakes LTER: Process Data 1984 - 2007</title>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Stephen</givenName>
				<surName>Carpenter</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">(608) 262-3014</phone>
			<phone phonetype="fax">(608) 265-2340</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>srcarpen@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Jim</givenName>
				<surName>Kitchell</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
    </address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">(608) 262-3014</phone>
			<phone phonetype="fax">(608) 265-3014</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>kitchell@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Jon</givenName>
				<surName>Cole</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>colej@caryinstitute.org</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Mike</givenName>
				<surName>Pace</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>pacem@virginia.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<metadataProvider>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</metadataProvider>
		<pubDate>2009</pubDate>
		<language>english</language>
		<abstract>
			<para>Data on chlorophyll, primary productivity, and alkaline phosphatase activity from
				1984-95. Samples were collected with a Van Dorn bottle at 6 depths determined from the
				percent of surface irradiance (100%, 50%, 25%, 10%, 5% and 1%) and in the hypolimnion (12 m
				in Peter, East Long, West Long, and Tuesday lakes; 9 m in Paul Lake; and 4.5 m in Central
				Long Lake). Sampling Frequency: varies Number of sites: 8 </para>
		</abstract>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>primary production</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>LTER Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>DIC</keyword>
			<keyword>NTL LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>North Temperate Lakes - LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>P</keyword>
			<keyword>phaeophyton</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>NTL Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<intellectualRights>
			<section>
				<title>Data Policies</title>
				<para>Copyright Board of Regents, University of Wisconsin, Madison. This information is
					released to the public and may be used for academic, educational, or commercial purposes
					subject to the following restrictions: The Data User must realize that these data sets are
					being actively used by others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary
					to prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the NTL lead Principal
					Investigator, leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu, to check on other uses of the data. Where
					appropriate, the Data User may be encouraged to consider collaboration and/or
					co-authorship with original investigators.</para>
				<para>The Data User must realize that the data may be misinterpreted if taken out of
					context. We request that you provide the NTL lead Principal Investigator, ATTN: Data
					Access, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison, 680 North Park St.,
					Madison, WI 53706 with a copy of any manuscript using the data so that it may be reviewed
					and comments provided on the presentation of our data.</para>
				<para>The Data User must acknowledge use of the data by an appropriate citation (see
					Citation) of the NTL-LTER database. A generic citation for our databases is: name of data
					set, North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research program, NSF, contact person for
					data set, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison. The data set name and
					contact person for each data set can be found in the metadata header of the online data
					sets.</para>
				<para>The Data User must send two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the
					data to the address above. We would like to include such manuscripts in our LTER
					publications list.</para>
				<para>The Data User must not redistribute original data and documentation without permission
					from Emily Stanley, lead Principal Investigator, (ehstanley@wisc.edu).</para>
				<para>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation,
					complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is".
					The North Temperate Lakes LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or
					misinterpretation of data sets. Data users should be aware that we periodically update
					data sets.</para>
				<para>Our goal is to release all long term data associated with core research areas within 2
					years of collection. These data and accompanying metadata will be available for download
					from the NTL-LTER web site.</para>
				<para>By using these data, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement.
					Thank you for your cooperation. </para>
			</section>
		</intellectualRights>
		<distribution>
			<online>
				<url function="information">http://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/node/5621</url>
			</online>
		</distribution>
		<coverage>
			<geographicCoverage>
				<geographicDescription>Cascade lakes: Peter, Paul, Tuesday, East Long, West Long, Central Long, Hummingbird, Crampton, UNDERC (University of Notre Dame Environmental Research Center) Vilas County, WI and Gogebic County, MI, USA
</geographicDescription>
				<boundingCoordinates>
					<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.506</westBoundingCoordinate>
					<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.468</eastBoundingCoordinate>
					<northBoundingCoordinate>46.254</northBoundingCoordinate>
					<southBoundingCoordinate>46.206</southBoundingCoordinate>
				</boundingCoordinates>
			</geographicCoverage>
			<temporalCoverage>
				<rangeOfDates>
					<beginDate>
						<calendarDate>1984-06-03</calendarDate>
					</beginDate>
					<endDate>
						<calendarDate>2007-08-28</calendarDate>
					</endDate>
				</rangeOfDates>
			</temporalCoverage>
		</coverage>
		<maintenance>
			<description>
				<para>completed </para>
			</description>
		</maintenance>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Information Manager</positionName>
			<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
			<organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<publisher>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</publisher>
		<pubPlace>North Temperate Lakes</pubPlace>
		<methods>
			<methodStep>
				<description>
					<section>
						<para>CHLOROPHYLL a ANALYSIS EQUIPMENT: Film canisters Turner 450 Fluorometer fitted
							with: 1. Quartz-halogen lamp 2. Emission filter -SC665 3. Excitation filter -NB440
							47mm Whatman GForF filters 12 x 75 mm disposable glass culture cuvettes (Do not reuse
							cuvettes!) 1-5 mL Oxford pipettor Finnpipette Stepper Pipetter with 5 mL tip
							timestimesNOTEtimestimes -Change filters with fluorometer off! (Remember that
							chlorophyll analysis filters are different from APA analysis filters.) -Make sure
							Fluorometer has been calibrated for chlorophyll a (see Fluorometer Calibration for
							Chlorophyll a Analysis). REAGENTS: 100percent Methanol, spectrophotometric grade
							CAUTION - wear gloves whenever you use methanol. 0.1 N HCL Ethidium Bromide Stock 3
							standard (40microM solution) PROCEDURE: A. Filter water samples from each of the 6
							light-depths onto a 47 mm GForF filter. 1. Filters have a grid side and a smooth side.
							Place filter smooth side up. 2. Shake sample bottle well before filtering (do this
							after the DIC sample has been taken from the same bottle.) 3. For each depth, filter
							enough water so there is a faint color on the filter. For our lakes this ranges
							between 100-300ml. Record the volume filtered. Make sure you filer at less than 200 mm
							Hg pressure. 4. Rinse filter towers and filters with DI water, place filters in
							labeled film canisters and place in freezer. Labels should include lake, date, and
							depth ID. 5. If measuring edible chlorophyll as well, repeat steps 1-4 above, but
							first filter the sample through 35 microm mesh. (This has not been done since 2001,
							inclusive.) B. Extraction - DO IN DIM LIGHT and WEAR GLOVES!! 1. Remove one tray of
							film canisters from the freezer. Extract chlorophyll by adding 25 mL 100percent MeOH
							to each film canister. If using re-pipettor, verify dispensed volume. (Record
							extraction volume if different from 25 mL.) Note the extraction time for each group of
							samples. 2. Re-cap and place canisters in refrigerator to extract for exactly 24 hours
							(in the dark). 3 Repeat steps 1 and 2 for all trays that have been in the freezer more
							than 24 hours. C. Fluorometry Calibration of the fluorometer using a chlorophyll
							standard is typically performed at the beginning of the field season, or when a bulb
							is changed. Calibration using Ethidium Bromide is done at the beginning of each sample
							set. 1. Insert correct filters in fluorometer while fluorometer is off. (Emission
							filter -SC665, Excitation filter -NB440), and warm it up for 1 hour . 2. TURN LIGHTS
							OUT. Chlorophylls must be read in low light and samples must be kept cool. Do not
							remove film canisters from the refrigerator until you are ready to process the
							samples. 3. Place clean cuvettes into a labeled rack (12 cuvettes per rack). Remove
							one lake-day of film canisters from the refrigerator. 4. Place Ethidium Bromide Stock
							3 standard into fluorometer and record reading on datasheet. Then, turn the span knob
							until the reading is 908. Record this on the datasheet. 5. Shake film canister, remove
							the lid, and rinse the pipette tip with 2.5 mL of the sample. Then remove 2.5 mL of
							sample and place in cuvette.times Repeat for all film canisters. 6. Pipette 2.5 mL of
							100percent methanol into a cuvette for the blank and use it to zero the fluorometer.
							Choose a gain and turn the zero knob until the fluorometer reads 000. You must zero
							the machine every time you change gains. 7. Remove the first sample cuvette from the
							rack, wipe with a Kimwipe, and place in fluorometer. Record the gain and the
							fluorescence before acidification, Fb. Repeat for all 12 cuvettes in the rack.
							Readings should be between about 200 and 1000. If not, adjust the gain and re-zero. 8.
							Acidify each cuvette with 100 microL 0.0773 N HCl using the repeating pipetter and mix
							(hold the top of the cuvette securely, then "thump" the bottom several times). Check
							for condensation on the outside of the cuvettes, and wipe with a Kimwipe if necessary.
							Wait about 1 min from the acidification of the first cuvette. 9. Record the
							fluorescence after acidification for all 12 cuvettes. VERY IMPORTANT: Make sure you
							read the Fb and Fa values for each sample on the same gain. 10. Remove a new lake-day
							batch of film canisters from the refrigerator and repeat steps 3-9. times if
							particulate matter is present, centrifuge sample for 10 min. and use supernatant. D.
							Clean Up: DO THIS UNDER THE HOOD! 1. Dump methanol solution from cuvettes and film
							canisters into a metal tray. Place the film canisters and lids in a separate tray.
							Position them in one layer on the tray with their openings facing up. Leave the trays
							under the hood overnight to evaporate the methanol. REFERENCES: Marker, A.F.H., C.A.
							Crowther, and R.J.M. Gunn. 1980. Methanol and acetone as solvents for estimating
							chlorophyll a and phaeopigments by spectrophotometry. Arch. Hydrobiol. Beih. Ergebn.
							Limnol 14: 52-69. Strickland, J.H. and T.R. Parsons. 1968. A practical handbook of
							seawater analysis. Fish. Res. Brd. Can. Bulletin 167.pp. 201-206. Holm-Hansen, O.
							1978. Chlorophyll a determination: improvements in methodology. Oikos 30:438-447. &#194;&#160;
						</para>
					</section>
					<section>
						<para>14C-PRIMARY PRODUCTIVITY EQUIPMENT: Field: PPR float with line and clips for
							hanging bottles at selected depths PPR field boxes containing: 18, 60 mL reagent
							bottles wor glass stoppers, plus extra bottles and tops. 2, 100-1000 microL automatic
							pipettor and several tips lab gloves and plastic apron plastic bag for used gloves and
							pipette tips extra clips for hanging bottles water pump Lab: 6-tower vacuum filter
							apparatus 4.7 cm Whatman GForF filters Scintillation vials with labeled caps (label
							includes lake, day, "D" or "L" for dark or light bottle, and depth, respectively.
							(e.g.: "L145 L1"; "W224 D6") REAGENTS: 10 microCi 14C-bicarbonate (2 microCi mL-1)
							Dichlorophenol-dimethyl urea (DCMU) saturated solution 0.1 N HCL Scintillation fluor
							(Biosafe) PROCEDURE: (Observe safe radioisotope handling techniques at all times
							during this analysis!) A. In lab (morning, before going to the field) 1. Transfer 14C
							from ampule to labeled scintillation vial with a disposable pipettor (under the fume
							hood). Put scintillation vial in the field box. 2. Replenish supply of lab gloves,
							pipette tips, and DCMU in the field box. 3. Remember to include the PPR float and the
							field boxes (check contents with list) in the items loaded into the field vehicle(s).
							106 B. In field 1. Rinse and fill 3, 60 mL BOD bottles with water from each depth,
							corresponding to 100, 50, 25, 10, 5 and 1percent of surface irradiance. Avoid getting
							air bubbles in bottles. TRY TO KEEP BOTTLES IN THE DARK AS MUCH AS POSSIBLE. 2.
							Pipette 250 microL of water from each bottle (using the "14C pipettor"). 3. Pipette an
							additional 500 microL of water from the 6 dark bottles using the "DCMU pipettor" (the
							dark bottles are used as a t = 0 control). 4. Using the "DCMU pipettor," add 500
							microL DCMU to the dark bottles to kill the phytoplankton. (always done before 14C
							addition.) It is important not to contaminate "light" bottles with DCMU! Dark bottles
							are labeled, and are used only as dark bottles. 5. Using the "14C pipettor," Pipette
							250 microL of 14C into each of the 18 bottles, starting with the dark bottles to
							ensure there is enough isotope for controls. Summary of subtractions and additions:
							light bottles dark bottles remove 250 microL 750 microL (250 plus 500) add DCMU - 500
							microL add 14C 250 microL 250 microL 6. Replace stoppers and invert bottles 2 or 3
							times to mix. Ensure that stoppers are well-seated, so they don t come out. It often
							helps to twist the stopper as you push it into the bottle. 7. Suspend bottles at
							appropriate depths for incubation. Record incubation start time. 8. AFTER 6 HRS:
							Remove bottles from water and place in carrying case until ready to filter (filtering
							should be done promptly after removal of bottles from water). Record incubation finish
							time. (Incubations usually go from ~9:30am-3:30pm) C. In lab (afternoon) 1. Have ready
							a. Flask used only for collecting 14C waste 107 b. Filter towers equipped with 4.7 cm
							GForF filters. Separate towers should be used for light and dark (DCMU) bottles. c.
							Scintillation vials, with caps labeled for all samples. d. A full squirt bottle of 0.1
							N HCl and a full squirt bottle of Milli-Q TURN OFF THE LIGHTS - THE REST OF THE
							PROCEDURE SHOULD BE DONE IN DIM LIGHT! 2. Prepare 3 totals: a. Add 10 mL scintillation
							solution (Biosafe) and 100 microL 1 N NaOH to 6 vials (label on cap should include
							lake, day, "TOT" ,and depth id). b. Remove 250 microL from one of the light bottles
							from each depth and add it to the proper vial. These vials are for calculating the
							total amount of 14C added to the bottles. c. Tightly cap the total vials and put aside
							for later analysis with the scintillation counter 3. Samples (process samples in the
							designated 14C fume hood): a. Empty the entire BOD bottle into the appropriate "light"
							or "dark" filter tower. Record volume if entire bottle is not filtered. b. Once the
							sample has filtered completely, rinse the bottle with a squirt of 0.1 N HCl, and
							filter this rinse. Then rinse the bottle with water and filter this rinse. Rinse tower
							with 0.1N HCl, and then finally with Milli-Q. c. Remove filter by folding it in
							quarters and place it at the bottom of the appropriate scintillation vial. Filter
							should be compact enough in the bottom of the vial to be completely covered by the
							scintillation fluor (which fills half of the vial). d. Dry at 60-70degreeC for 24
							hours. e. After drying filters, add 10 mL liquid scintillation solution to vials and
							count in scintillation counter (see Scintillation Counting Procedure). D. Clean up:
							108 1. When all samples have been filtered, squirt some acid down the last tower in
							the line to rinse. When the acid has been pumped out of the line, vent the tower to
							expel all liquid. Lift towers to drain completely. 2. Rinse BOD bottles and caps three
							times with hot tap water. 3. Radioactive waste goes into a carboy marked and reserved
							for radioactive waste. timestimesNOTEtimestimes The total radioactivity in each carboy
							must be known; Record the date when 14C is initially put in the carboy and the date
							when the final amount of 14C is put in the carboy. 4. Empty the remaining amount of
							14C from the scintillation vial taken into the field into the radioactive waste
							carboy. Discard the vial in the dry radioactive waste bag. 5. Record the amount of
							radioactivity used in the isotope log book. CALCULATIONS: Use the SYSTAT command file
							CALCPPR.CMD to calculate primary productivity according to the following equation: mg
							Ctimesm-3timesh-1 = (CPMs - CPMb) times (VincorVfil) times (A) times (1.05) (DPMt)
							times (Eff) times (T) where: CPMs = counts per minute for sample CPMb = counts per
							minute for DCMU control Vine = volume (mL) incubated Veil = volume (mL) filtered A =
							total C in sample (in mg Corm3), calculated from sample alkalinity 1.05 = isotope
							discrimination factor DPMt = disintegrations per minute of total amount of 14C added
							to each bottle Eff = efficiency of scintillation fluor calculated from internal
							standards for each sample T = length of incubation (h) 2. Use the method in Appendix
							III, along with measurements of solar radiationtimes and light extinction from the
							weekly light profiles, to calculate daily production of the photic zone and the mixed
							layer (see Carpenter et al., 1986). times see Pyranograph Method 109 REFERENCES:
							Carpenter, S.R., M.M Elser and J.J. Elser. 1986. Chlorophyll production, degradation,
							and sedimentation: Implications for paleolimnology. Limnol. Oceanogr. 31:112- 124.
							Strickland, J.D.H., and T.R. Parsons. 1968. A practical handbook of seawater analysis.
							Bull. Fish. Res. Board Can. 167:267-279. Legendre, L., S. Demers, C.M. Yentsch, and
							C.S. Yentsch. 1983. The 14C method: Patterns of dark CO2 fixation and DCMU correction
							to replace the dark bottle. Limnol. Oceanogr. 28: 996-1003. </para>
					</section>
				</description>
			</methodStep>
		</methods>
		<project>
			<title>Cascade Project at North Temperate Lakes LTER</title>
			<personnel>
				<individualName>
					<givenName>Stephen</givenName>
					<surName>Carpenter</surName>
				</individualName>
				<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
				<address>
        <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Street</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
				<phone phonetype="voice">(608) 262-3014</phone>
				<phone phonetype="fax">(608) 265-2340</phone>
				<electronicMailAddress>srcarpen@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
				<role>project personnel</role>
			</personnel>
			<personnel>
				<individualName>
					<givenName>Jim</givenName>
					<surName>Kitchell</surName>
				</individualName>
				<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
				<address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      </address>
				<phone phonetype="voice">(608) 262-3014</phone>
				<phone phonetype="fax">(608) 265-3014</phone>
				<electronicMailAddress>kitchell@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
				<role>project personnel</role>
			</personnel>
			<personnel>
				<individualName>
					<givenName>Jon</givenName>
					<surName>Cole</surName>
				</individualName>
				<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
				<address>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
				<electronicMailAddress>colej@caryinstitute.org</electronicMailAddress>
				<role>project personnel</role>
			</personnel>
			<personnel>
				<individualName>
					<givenName>Mike</givenName>
					<surName>Pace</surName>
				</individualName>
				<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
				<address>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
				<electronicMailAddress>pacem@virginia.edu</electronicMailAddress>
				<role>project personnel</role>
			</personnel>
			<abstract>
				<para>The Cascade project is a whole-ecosystem experimental test of the theory that: 1)
					increased variance 2) red-shift of variance 3) critical slowing down of recovery rate
					across components of a food web are leading indicators of a common type of regime shift in
					lake ecosystems caused by changes in the structure of the fish community. Variability will
					be assessed at all trophic levels for three years in both a manipulated lake and a
					non-manipulated reference lake using high-frequency data acquisition methods including
					automated in situ instrumentation for analysis of alagal biomass and primary production,
					zooplankton abundance and size structure, acoustical measure of fish migration, and daily
					measures of fish growth from otoliths. Modern signal processing methods of time series,
					spectral and wavelet analysis will evaluate changes in variance, variance sprectra and
					return rate. </para>
			</abstract>
		</project>
		<dataTable>
			<entityName>cascade_process</entityName>
			<entityDescription>Cascade Project: Process Data</entityDescription>
			<physical>
				<objectName>cascadeprocess</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
						<recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
							<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-ntl.73&amp;urlTail=ntl/data/5621_v2.csv</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<attributeList>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>lakeid</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>lake identifier</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>lake identifier</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<enumeratedDomain>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>C</code>
										<definition>Central Long Lake</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>E</code>
										<definition>East Long Lake</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>H</code>
										<definition>Hummingbird Lake</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>L</code>
										<definition>Paul Lake</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>M</code>
										<definition>Crampton Lake</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>R</code>
										<definition>Peter Lake</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>T</code>
										<definition>Tuesday Lake</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>W</code>
										<definition>West Long Lake</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
								</enumeratedDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>lakename</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>lake name</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>lake name</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>lake name</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>year4</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>year</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>year</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>nominalYear</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<precision>1</precision>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>daynum</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>day of year</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>day of year</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>nominalDay</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<precision>1</precision>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
								<bounds>
									<minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum>
									<maximum exclusive="false">366</maximum>
								</bounds>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>sampledate</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>sample date</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>sample date</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>date</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<dateTime>
							<formatString>yyyy-MM-dd</formatString>
						</dateTime>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>depth</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>sample depth meter</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>depth at which the sample or measurement was taken</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>depth_id</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>depth identifier</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>depth identifier</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>depth identifier</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>dic</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>dissolved inorganic carbon</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>dissolved inorganic carbon</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>primary_prod_rep1</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>primary production rep 1</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>primary production rep 1</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerMeterCubedPerHour</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>primary_prod_rep2</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>primary production rep 2</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>primary production rep 2</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerMeterCubedPerHour</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>chla</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>chlorophyll a </attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>total fluorometric chlorophyll a concentration</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microgramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>phaeo</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>phaeopigment </attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>total fluorometric phaeopigment concentration</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microgramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>chla_lt_35um</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>edible chlorophyll a</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>edible (less than 35 micrometers) chlorophyll a concentration</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microgramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>phaeo_lt_35um</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>edible phaeopigment </attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>edible (less than 35 micrometers) phaeopigment concentration</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microgramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>alk_phosphatase</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>alkaline phosphatase activity</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>alkaline phosphatase activity</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>nanomolePerMinute</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
			</attributeList>
		</dataTable>
	</dataset>
	<additionalMetadata>
		<metadata>
			<ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1     http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
				<ns2:unit abbreviation="mg/l" constantToSI="0" id="milligramPerLiter" multiplierToSI="0.001" name="milligramPerLiter" parentSI="kilogramPerCubicMeter" unitType="massDensity">
					<ns2:description>milligrams / liter</ns2:description>
				</ns2:unit>
				<ns2:unit abbreviation="mg/m&#179;/h" id="milligramPerMeterCubedPerHour" name="milligramPerMeterCubedPerHour" unitType="volumetricMassDensityRate">
					<ns2:description />
				</ns2:unit>
				<ns2:unit abbreviation="&#181;g/l" constantToSI="0" id="microgramPerLiter" multiplierToSI="0.000001" name="microgramPerLiter" parentSI="kilogramPerCubicMeter" unitType="massDensity">
					<ns2:description>micrograms / liter</ns2:description>
				</ns2:unit>
				<ns2:unit id="nanomolePerMinute" />
			</ns2:unitList>
		</metadata>
	</additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>