<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-bes.449.56 " system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 ./eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"> 
<dataset>
<title>Climate and Meteorology, Precipitation Data, Station Locations, Photographs, Equipment (USGS): Station: Rain Gauge at Cromwell Valley Park near Glen Arm, MD (CVPG) BES ID 449-</title>
<creator>
<individualName>
<surName>Peter Groffman ,     Email: groffmanp@caryinstitute.org, Gordon M. Heisler, gheisler@fs.fed.us</surName>
</individualName>
</creator>
<pubDate>2010-01-07</pubDate>
<abstract><para>
Location
Lat. 39&#65533; 24' 49", long. 76&#65533; 33' 11"
Directions

   1. 695 to Exit 29 Cromwell Bridge Rd towards Loch Raven High School
   2. Past Loch Raven high school
   3. Take the first entrance to the park - Sherwood House
   4. Follow entrance towards house
   5. Gauge is located just inside electric fence surrounding garden on left of road 

USGS Quadrangle - Towson
Potential Hazards - Electric Fence
Establishment - October 2001
Datum of Station - To be determined soon!
Equipment - J&amp; S Tipping Bucket rain gauge with HOBO Data recorder 
History

    * 31 October 2001 Gauge is installed in public gardens just inside of electric fence
    * Window screening is installed around gauge to prevent organisms from occupying it. The screening is taped around outside of gauge and stapled to platform it sets on. Refer to pictures for further illustration. This has been done sometime after installation. 

Panorama - This gauge is in a relatively open field bounded by forest
Calibration Measurements -Calibration Measurements - Calibration of this gauge should be preformed as described in the users manual. Each bucket should hold 8.24 mL of water before tipping. This should occur five consecutive times. Adjust calibration screws as needed.
Extreme Events No extreme events have been observed at this station to date.
Winter Records - Rain gauge is not heated and is subject to freezing.
Accuracy - Data should be ran through a quality control algorithm before use.
Cooperation - Baltimore Ecosystem Study and University of Maryland, Baltimore County; Cromwell Valley Park, Baltimore County
Photographs - Print collections may be available. Contact the MD-DE-DC District Office about any collections in the official station records.    See Baltimore Ecosystem Study Meteorology Overview here: http://beslter.org/frame7-page_1p.html .
</para></abstract>
<keywordSet>
<keyword keywordType="theme">atmospheric science,  ecology,  air pollution,  rainfall,  gauge,  rain</keyword>
</keywordSet>
<keywordSet>
<keyword keywordType="place">Baltimore, MD, Washington, D.C, Chesapeake Bay, Baltimore-Washington, Maryland</keyword>
</keywordSet>
<distribution>
<online>
<url>http://md.water.usgs.gov/BES/wxcvpg/index.html</url>
</online>
</distribution>
<coverage>
<geographicCoverage>
<geographicDescription>The Baltimore Ecosystem Study ultimately will conduct research and educational activities throughout the Baltimore metropolitan area. This large area includes Baltimore City, Baltimore County, and the counties of Ann Arundel, Carrol, Harford, Howard, and Montgomery. Gwynns Falls includes agricultural lands, recently suburbanized areas, established suburbs, and dense urban areas having residential, commercial and open spaces. In addition, a reference area has been established in a forested catchment of the Gunpowder drainage in Oregon Ridge County Park. </geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates>
<westBoundingCoordinate>-77.314183</westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>-76.012008</eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>39.724847</northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>38.708367</southBoundingCoordinate>
<boundingAltitudes>
<altitudeMinimum>50</altitudeMinimum>
<altitudeMaximum>700</altitudeMaximum>
<altitudeUnits>feet</altitudeUnits>
</boundingAltitudes>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
</coverage>
<contact>
<individualName>
<givenName>Jonathan</givenName>
<surName>Walsh</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies</organizationName>
<positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>IES</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>Box AB, 65 Sharon Tpke</deliveryPoint>
<city>Millbrook</city>
<administrativeArea>NY</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>12545</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">845-677-7600</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">  </phone>
<electronicMailAddress>walshj@ecostudies.org</electronicMailAddress>
</contact>
<publisher>
<organizationName> The scientists, the BES-LTER Program, and the Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies must receive adequate acknowledgement for the use of data by other scientists, and the BES LTER program must receive two copies of any publication using that data.   Baltimore Ecosystem Study</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>Room 134 TRC Building</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint> University of Maryland, Baltimore County</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint> 5200 Westland Blvd</deliveryPoint>
<city>Baltimore</city>
<administrativeArea>MD</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>21227</postalCode>
</address>
</publisher>
<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
<allow>
<principal>uid="BES",o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
<principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
</dataset>
</eml:eml>