<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-bes.412.56 " system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 ./eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"> 
<dataset>
<title>Permanent Plot Vegetation Sampling, 2003 Sapling Data BES ID 412-</title>
<creator>
<individualName>
<surName>M.L. Cadenasso, University of California, Davis; Email: mlcadenasso@ucdavis.edu; S.T.A. Pickett, Institute of Ecosystem Studies; Email: picketts@ecostudies.org</surName>
</individualName>
</creator>
<pubDate>2007-01-30</pubDate>
<abstract><para>
Permanent plots are a powerful tool for understanding systems over the long term because of the rigorous quantification of patterns in a spatially refined way and because of the comparability of numerous variables measured in the same place. In 1998, 7 plots were surveyed into 3 forests in the study region of the Baltimore Ecosystem Study (BES): Oregon Ridge Park (4 plots), Hillsdale Park (1 plot), and Leakin Park (2 plots).  In 2003, the same seven plots were re-surveyed and one in Hillsdale Park was added, for a total of eight plots.  Plots were surveyed in order to correct for slope and to achieve an accuracy of plot side length to within 0.5 cm. Plots are 1600 m2 with the exception of the Hillsdale plots which are 900 m2. The Hillsdale plots are smaller to fit within the confines of the forest patch. Sites were selected 1) to represent urban and non-urban forests, 2) away from obvious habitat boundaries or edges, 3) with consistent drainage lines within the plot, and 4) with at least 80 % continuous tree canopy. All vegetation layers were sampled in order to characterize the structure and composition of the plant community. A variety of sampling methods were used for the different layers but all layers were quantified with a high level of detail to minimize variation and to best characterize the plot. 
</para></abstract>
<keywordSet>
<keyword keywordType="theme">biodiversity, permanent plots, vegetation</keyword>
</keywordSet>
<keywordSet>
<keyword keywordType="place">Baltimore, MD, Washington, D.C, Chesapeake Bay, Baltimore-Washington, Maryland</keyword>
</keywordSet>
<distribution>
<online>
<url>http://beslter.org/data_http/biodiversity/vegetation/2003_raw_sapling.txt</url>
</online>
</distribution>
<coverage>
<geographicCoverage>
<geographicDescription>The Baltimore Ecosystem Study ultimately will conduct research and educational activities throughout the Baltimore metropolitan area. This large area includes Baltimore City, Baltimore County, and the counties of Ann Arundel, Carrol, Harford, Howard, and Montgomery. Gwynns Falls includes agricultural lands, recently suburbanized areas, established suburbs, and dense urban areas having residential, commercial and open spaces. In addition, a reference area has been established in a forested catchment of the Gunpowder drainage in Oregon Ridge County Park. </geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates>
<westBoundingCoordinate>-77.314183</westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>-76.012008</eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>39.724847</northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>38.708367</southBoundingCoordinate>
<boundingAltitudes>
<altitudeMinimum>50</altitudeMinimum>
<altitudeMaximum>700</altitudeMaximum>
<altitudeUnits>feet</altitudeUnits>
</boundingAltitudes>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
</coverage>
<contact>
<individualName>
<givenName>Jonathan</givenName>
<surName>Walsh</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies</organizationName>
<positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>IES</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>Box AB, 65 Sharon Tpke</deliveryPoint>
<city>Millbrook</city>
<administrativeArea>NY</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>12545</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">845-677-7600</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">  </phone>
<electronicMailAddress>walshj@ecostudies.org</electronicMailAddress>
</contact>
<publisher>
<organizationName> The scientists, the BES-LTER Program, and the Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies must receive adequate acknowledgement for the use of data by other scientists, and the BES LTER program must receive two copies of any publication using that data.   Baltimore Ecosystem Study</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>Room 134 TRC Building</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint> University of Maryland, Baltimore County</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint> 5200 Westland Blvd</deliveryPoint>
<city>Baltimore</city>
<administrativeArea>MD</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>21227</postalCode>
</address>
</publisher>
<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
<allow>
<principal>uid="BES",o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
<principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
</dataset>
</eml:eml>