<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-ntl.259.3" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0  http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
	<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
		<allow>
			<principal>uid=NTL,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
			<permission>all</permission>
		</allow>
		<allow>
			<principal>public</principal>
			<permission>read</permission>
		</allow>
	</access>
	<dataset>
		<alternateIdentifier system="NTL-DEIMS">5730</alternateIdentifier>
		<shortName>NTLPH08</shortName>
		<title>North Temperate Lakes LTER: Light Extinction - Trout Lake Area 1981 - current</title>
		<creator>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
			<organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<metadataProvider>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</metadataProvider>
		<pubDate>2010</pubDate>
		<language>english</language>
		<abstract>
			<para>A light (PAR) extinction coefficient is calculated for the water column for the seven
				northern study lakes (Allequash, Big Muskellunge, Crystal, Sparkling, and Trout lakes,
				unnamed lakes 27-02 [Crystal Bog] and 12-15 [Trout Bog]). The fraction of surface light is
				computed at 0.25-m to 1-m depth intervals depending on the lake. The light (PAR) extinction
				coefficient is calculated by regressing ln(fraction of light(z)) on depth z. Sampling
				Frequency: fortnightly during ice-free season - every 6 weeks during ice-covered season
				Number of sites: 7 </para>
		</abstract>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>light</keyword>
			<keyword>primary production</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>LTER Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>NTL LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>North Temperate Lakes - LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>light extinction</keyword>
			<keyword>light penetration</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>NTL Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<intellectualRights>
			<section>
				<title>Data Policies</title>
				<para>Copyright Board of Regents, University of Wisconsin, Madison. This information is
					released to the public and may be used for academic, educational, or commercial purposes
					subject to the following restrictions: The Data User must realize that these data sets are
					being actively used by others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary
					to prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the NTL lead Principal
					Investigator, leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu, to check on other uses of the data. Where
					appropriate, the Data User may be encouraged to consider collaboration and/or
					co-authorship with original investigators.</para>
				<para>The Data User must realize that the data may be misinterpreted if taken out of
					context. We request that you provide the NTL lead Principal Investigator, ATTN: Data
					Access, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison, 680 North Park St.,
					Madison, WI 53706 with a copy of any manuscript using the data so that it may be reviewed
					and comments provided on the presentation of our data.</para>
				<para>The Data User must acknowledge use of the data by an appropriate citation (see
					Citation) of the NTL-LTER database. A generic citation for our databases is: name of data
					set, North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research program, NSF, contact person for
					data set, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison. The data set name and
					contact person for each data set can be found in the metadata header of the online data
					sets.</para>
				<para>The Data User must send two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the
					data to the address above. We would like to include such manuscripts in our LTER
					publications list.</para>
				<para>The Data User must not redistribute original data and documentation without permission
					from Emily Stanley, lead Principal Investigator, (ehstanley@wisc.edu).</para>
				<para>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation,
					complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is".
					The North Temperate Lakes LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or
					misinterpretation of data sets. Data users should be aware that we periodically update
					data sets.</para>
				<para>Our goal is to release all long term data associated with core research areas within 2
					years of collection. These data and accompanying metadata will be available for download
					from the NTL-LTER web site.</para>
				<para>By using these data, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement.
					Thank you for your cooperation. </para>
			</section>
		</intellectualRights>
		<distribution>
			<online>
				<url function="information">http://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/node/5730</url>
			</online>
		</distribution>
		<coverage>
			<geographicCoverage>
				<geographicDescription>Allequash Lake, Big Muskellunge Lake, Crystal Lake, Sparkling Lake,
					Trout Lake, and unnamed lakes 27-02 (Crystal Bog) and 12-15 (Trout Bog), Vilas County, WI,
					USA </geographicDescription>
				<boundingCoordinates>
					<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.704</westBoundingCoordinate>
					<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.596</eastBoundingCoordinate>
					<northBoundingCoordinate>46.079</northBoundingCoordinate>
					<southBoundingCoordinate>45.999</southBoundingCoordinate>
				</boundingCoordinates>
			</geographicCoverage>
			<temporalCoverage>
				<rangeOfDates>
					<beginDate>
						<calendarDate>1981-06-06</calendarDate>
					</beginDate>
					<endDate>
						<calendarDate>2013-11-14</calendarDate>
					</endDate>
				</rangeOfDates>
			</temporalCoverage>
		</coverage>
		<maintenance>
			<description>
				<para>ongoing </para>
			</description>
		</maintenance>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Information Manager</positionName>
			<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
			<organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<publisher>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</publisher>
		<pubPlace>North Temperate Lakes</pubPlace>
		<methods>
			<methodStep>
				<description>
					<section>
						<para>Light (PAR) extinction coefficient is calculated by linearly regressing ln
							(FRLIGHT (z)) on depth z where the intercept is not constrained. FRLIGHT(z) = LIGHT(z)
							or DECK(z) where LIGHT(z) is light measured at depth z and DECK(z) is light measured
							on deck (above water) at the same time. For open water light profiles, the surface
							light measurement (depth z = 0) is excluded from the regression. For winter light
							profiles taken beneath the ice, the first light data are taken at the bottom of the
							ice cover and are included in the regression. The depth of uppermost light value is
							equal to the depth of the ice adjusted by the water level in the sample hole, i.e.,
							the depth below the surface of the water. The water level can be at, above or below
							the surface of the ice. If the water level was not recorded, it is assumed to be 0.0
							and the calculated light extinction coefficient is flagged. If ice thickness was not
							recorded, a light extinction coefficient is not calculated. For light data collected
							prior to March, 2007, light values less than 3.0 (micromolesPerMeterSquaredPerSec) are
							excluded. For light data collected starting in March 2007, light values less than 1.0
							(micromolesPerMeterSquaredPerSec) are excluded. Except for bog lakes before August
							1989, a light extinction coefficient is not calculated if there are less than three
							FRLIGHT values to be regressed. For bog lakes before August 1989, a light extinction
							coefficient is calculated if there are least two FRLIGHT values to be regressed. In
							these cases, the light extinction coefficient is flagged as non-standard. FRLIGHT
							values should be monotonically decreasing with depth. For light profiles where this is
							not true, a light extinction coefficient is not calculated. For samples for which
							light data at depth are present, but the corresponding deck light are missing, a light
							extinction coefficient is calculated by regressing ln (LIGHT (z)) on depth z. Note
							that if actual deck light had remained constant during the recording of the light
							profile, the resulting light extinction coefficient is the same as from regressing
							ln(FRLIGHT(z)). In these cases, the light extinction coefficient is flagged as
							non-standard. </para>
					</section>
				</description>
			</methodStep>
		</methods>
		<project>
			<title>North Temperate Lakes LTER</title>
			<personnel>
				<positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
				<organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
				<address>
        <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
				<electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
				<role>project personnel</role>
			</personnel>
			<abstract>
				<para>North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research studies the ecology of lakes as
					one of a network of sites established by the National Science Foundation. We are
					interested in how biophysical setting, climate, and changing land use and cover interact
					to shape lake characteristics and dynamics over time (past, present, future). Our primary
					study sites include a set of seven northern Wisconsin and four southern Wisconsin lakes
					and their surrounding landscapes. The project, which started in 1981, is administered by
					the Center for Limnology at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. Perception of Long-Term
					Change: How and why have the lake districts changed, and how will they change in the
					future? Climatic Forcing of Change: What are the major ecological and social responses of
					lake districts to climate change? Interacting Drivers, Scales of Space and Time, and
					Regional Change: How do multiple interacting drivers affect regional change in lake
					districts at multiple scales? Ecosystem Services: Past, Present and Future: What are the
					magnitudes, interactions and potential future flows of ecosystem services in lake
					districts? </para>
			</abstract>
		</project>
		<dataTable>
			<entityName>light_ext_v1</entityName>
			<entityDescription>North Temperate Lakes LTER: Light Extinction - Trout Lake
				Area</entityDescription>
			<physical>
				<objectName>lightextv1</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
						<recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
							<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-ntl.259&amp;urlTail=ntl/data/5730_v2.csv</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<coverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Crystal Bog is located within the Northern
						Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County. It is a small and shallow bog lake.
						It has a surface area of 0.5 hectare, mostly undeveloped shoreline and a maximum depth
						of 2.5 meters. Bog lakes are isolated to a large extent from surrounding groundwater
						flow systems. However, they exhibit a similar pattern, across landscapes, to that
						exhibited by other lakes in general. The proportional input of groundwater to the bogs'
						hydrologic inputs increases with decreasing elevation in the landscape. More detailed
						studies of Crystal Bog reveal a complex interplay between conditions in the lake and in
						the surrounding wetland due to the groundwater flow regime and resulting chemical
						transfers.</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.606183</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.606183</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>46.007583</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>46.007583</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Trout Bog is located within the Northern
						Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County. It is a small bog lake. It has a
						surface area of 1.1 hectare, a mostly undeveloped shoreline and a maximum depth of 7.9
						meters.</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.686283</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.686283</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>46.04125</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>46.04125</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Crystal Lake is located within the Northern
						Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County. It is a seepage lake with
						predominantly sand substrate. It has a surface area of 36.7 hectare, 2.3 kilometers of
						mostly undeveloped (campground) developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 20.4 meters.
						Crystal Lake represents one extreme in the groundwater input gradient, with a marked
						predominance of precipitation inputs. Groundwater accounts for only 5% of input water,
						yet, because groundwater is more concentrated chemically than precipitation, groundwater
						accounts for substantial amounts of incoming solutes. For example, about 50% of the
						silica budget comes into the lake via groundwater, exerting a major influence on primary
						production. The lake is an oligotrophic, dimictic lake high in the landscape with
						minimal groundwater input, a light attenuation coefficient of 0.24 per meter (average
						ice-free Secchi depth of 8 m), a mean depth of 11.4 m, and a maximum depth of 20.4 m.
						Crystal Lake is circular with a shoreline development factor very close to 1.0. The
						littoral zone is fairly homogenous and is dominated by sandy substrate with low
						macrophyte and coarse woody habitat densities. The fish community has been historically
						dominated by pelagic yellow perch. However, yellow perch drastically declined after the
						detection of rainbow smelt in 1985.</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.612</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.612</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>46.003</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>46.003</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Big Muskellunge Lake is located within the Northern
						Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County. It is a seepage lake with
						predominantly sand and gravel substrate. It has a surface area of 396.3 hectare, 16.1
						kilometers of moderately developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 21.3 meters. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;
						</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.611783</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.611783</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>46.021067</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>46.021067</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Sparkling Lake is located within the Northern
						Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County. It is a seepage lake with
						predominantly sand and gravel substrate. It has a surface area of 64 hectare, 4.3
						kilometers of moderately developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 20 meters. &#160; &#160; &#160;
						</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.701183</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.701183</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>46.007733</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>46.007733</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Allequash Lake is located within the Northern
						Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County. T41N-R7E, Sections 16, 17, 20, 21.
						398 acres. (detailed lake description by the WDNR) It is a drainage lake with
						predominantly sand and gravel substrate. It has a surface area of 168.4 hectare, 9.5
						kilometers of mostly undeveloped shoreline and a maximum depth of 8 meters.</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.620617</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.620617</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>46.038317</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>46.038317</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Trout Lake is located within the Northern
						Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County. It is a drainage lake with
						predominantly gravel and sand substrate. It has a surface area of 1607.9 hectare, 25.9
						kilometers of mostly undeveloped shoreline and a maximum depth of 35.7 meters.</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.665017</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.665017</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>46.029267</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>46.029267</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
			</coverage>
			<attributeList>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>lakeid</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>lake name abbreviation</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>lake name abbreviation</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<enumeratedDomain>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>AL</code>
										<definition>Allequash Lake</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>BM</code>
										<definition>Big Muskellunge Lake</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>CB</code>
										<definition>Bog 27-2 (Crystal Bog)</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>CR</code>
										<definition>Crystal Lake</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>SP</code>
										<definition>Sparkling Lake</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>TB</code>
										<definition>Bog 12-15 (Trout Bog)</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>TR</code>
										<definition>Trout Lake</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
								</enumeratedDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>year4</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>year</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>year</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>nominalYear</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<precision>1</precision>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>daynum</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>day of year</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>day of year</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>nominalDay</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<precision>1</precision>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
								<bounds>
									<minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum>
									<maximum exclusive="false">366</maximum>
								</bounds>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>sampledate</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>sample date</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>sample date</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>date</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<dateTime>
							<formatString>yyyy-MM-dd</formatString>
						</dateTime>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>extcoef</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>light extinction coefficient</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>light extinction coefficient</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>lightext_flag</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>flag for light extinction coef</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>flag for light extinction coefficient</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<enumeratedDomain>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>J</code>
										<definition>Non standard routine followed</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>V</code>
										<definition>Could not be computed; set to missing</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
								</enumeratedDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>comments</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>comments for light ext coeff</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>comments for light extinction coefficient</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>comments for light extinction coefficient</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
			</attributeList>
		</dataTable>
	</dataset>
</eml:eml>