<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-bes.331.56 " system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 ./eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"> 
<dataset>
<title>Soil Survey Geographic (SSURGO) database for City of Baltimore, Maryland BES ID 331-</title>
<creator>
<individualName>
<surName>U.S. Department of Agriculture, Natural Resources Conservation Service</surName>
</individualName>
</creator>
<pubDate>2009-12-31</pubDate>
<abstract><para>
This data set is a digital soil survey and generally is the most detailed level of soil geographic data developed by the National Cooperative Soil Survey. The information was prepared by digitizing maps, by compiling information onto a planimetric correct base and digitizing, or by revising digitized maps using remotely sensed and other information. This data set consists of georeferenced digital map data and computerized attribute data. The map data are in a 3.75 minute quadrangle format and include a detailed, field verified inventory of soils and nonsoil areas that normally occur in a repeatable pattern on the landscape and that can be cartographically shown at the scale mapped. A special soil features layer (point and line features) is optional. This layer displays the location of features too small to delineate at the mapping scale, but they are large enough and contrasting enough to significantly influence use and management. The soil map units are linked to attributes in the National Soil Information System relational database, which gives the proportionate extent of the component soils and their properties.
</para></abstract>
<keywordSet>
<keyword keywordType="theme">soil survey,  soils,  Soil Survey Geographic,  SSURGO, </keyword>
</keywordSet>
<keywordSet>
<keyword keywordType="place">Maryland, City of Baltimore, Baltimore West NW Quadrangle       (s3907643), Baltimore West NE Quadrangle       (s3907643), Baltimore East NW Quadrangle       (s3907644), Baltimore East NE Quadrangle       (s3907644), Baltimore West SW Quadrangle       (s3</keyword>
</keywordSet>
<distribution>
<online>
<url>http://SoilDataMart.nrcs.usda.gov/</url>
</online>
</distribution>
<coverage>
<geographicCoverage>
<geographicDescription>The Baltimore Ecosystem Study ultimately will conduct research and educational activities throughout the Baltimore metropolitan area. This large area includes Baltimore City, Baltimore County, and the counties of Ann Arundel, Carrol, Harford, Howard, and Montgomery. Gwynns Falls includes agricultural lands, recently suburbanized areas, established suburbs, and dense urban areas having residential, commercial and open spaces. In addition, a reference area has been established in a forested catchment of the Gunpowder drainage in Oregon Ridge County Park. </geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates>
<westBoundingCoordinate>-77.314183</westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>-76.012008</eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>39.724847</northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>38.708367</southBoundingCoordinate>
<boundingAltitudes>
<altitudeMinimum>50</altitudeMinimum>
<altitudeMaximum>700</altitudeMaximum>
<altitudeUnits>feet</altitudeUnits>
</boundingAltitudes>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
</coverage>
<contact>
<individualName>
<givenName>Jonathan</givenName>
<surName>Walsh</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies</organizationName>
<positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>IES</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>Box AB, 65 Sharon Tpke</deliveryPoint>
<city>Millbrook</city>
<administrativeArea>NY</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>12545</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">845-677-7600</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">  </phone>
<electronicMailAddress>walshj@ecostudies.org</electronicMailAddress>
</contact>
<publisher>
<organizationName> The scientists, the BES-LTER Program, and the Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies must receive adequate acknowledgement for the use of data by other scientists, and the BES LTER program must receive two copies of any publication using that data.  james.brown@md.usda.gov Baltimore Ecosystem Study</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>Room 134 TRC Building</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint> University of Maryland, Baltimore County</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint> 5200 Westland Blvd</deliveryPoint>
<city>Baltimore</city>
<administrativeArea>MD</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>21227</postalCode>
</address>
</publisher>
<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
<allow>
<principal>uid="BES",o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
<principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
</dataset>
</eml:eml>