<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="evilanova.5.1" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataset scope="document"><title>Understanding the Link between the Ocean Surface and the Sinking Flux of Particulate Carbon in the Cariaco Basin, Venezuela</title><creator id="1279915752296" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Ram&#243;n</givenName><surName>Varela</surName></individualName><organizationName>Estaci&#243;n de Investigaciones Marinas (EDIMAR) - Fundaci&#243;n La Salle de Ciencias Naturales</organizationName><positionName>Assistant professor and researcher</positionName></creator><abstract><para>Over the past twelve years, the Ocean Time Series project called CARIACO (CArbon Retention In A Colored Ocean) has studied the relationship between surface primary production, physical forcing variables like the wind, and the settling flux of particulate carbon in the Cariaco Basin. This depression, located on the continental shelf of Venezuela (Map), shows marked seasonal and interannual variation in hydrographic properties and primary production (carbon fixation rates by photosynthesis of planktonic algae). An ocean time series in the Cariaco Basin is particularly important as it has long been the center of attention of scientists trying to explain paleoclimate. Due to its high rates of sedimentation (30 to &gt;100 cm/ky) and excellent preservation, the varved sediments of the Cariaco Basin offer the opportunity to study high resolution paleoclimate and better understand the role of the tropics in global climate change. Now, this ocean time series called the CARIACO program, provides a link between the sediment record and processes near the surface of the ocean. Sediment traps maintained by the CARIACO program show that over 5% of autochtonous material reaches 275 m depth, and that nearly 2% reaches 1,400 m. The significance of this flux is that it represents a sink for carbon and that it helps explain the record of ancient climate stored at the bottom of the Cariaco Basin.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>Carbon</keyword><keyword>Cariaco Basin</keyword><keyword>Productivity</keyword><keyword>Venezuela</keyword></keywordSet><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Cariaco</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-65.625</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-63.5</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>11.625</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>9.625</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage></coverage><contact id="1279915797218" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Ram&#243;n</givenName><surName>Varela</surName></individualName><organizationName>Estaci&#243;n de Investigaciones Marinas (EDIMAR) - Fundaci&#243;n La Salle de Ciencias Naturales</organizationName><positionName>Assistant Professor and researcher</positionName></contact></dataset></eml:eml>