<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>James E. Hines, and John R. Sauer</origin>
            <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
            <title>CONTRAST- general procedure for the comparison of several rate estimates that incorporates associated variance and covariance estimates</title>
            <geoform>tools software</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Laurel, Maryland</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division, Patuxent Wildlife Research Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>Several statistical procedures have recently become available for the estimation of rates of survival and recovery from banding and band recovery data for animal populations (e.g., White 1983, Conroy and Williams 1984, Brownie et al. 1985). In spite of the sophistication of these models, there has been comparatively little discussion regarding tests for multiple comparisons of these rates, and the standard method remains the z-test discussed by Brownie et al. (1985). Sauer and Williams (1989) recently described a general procedure for the comparison of several rate estimates that incorporates associated variance and covariance estimates. The method requires matrix multiplication and inversion, which may limit its use among biologists.</abstract>
         <purpose>Contrast is a computer program which aids in estimating rates of survival and recovery from banding and band recovery data.</purpose>
         <supplinf>The information for this metadata was taken from http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software/doc/contrast.html.  (previous geoform was 'software')</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>Unknown</update>
      </status>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>survival rate estimates</themekey>
            <themekey>recovery rate estimates</themekey>
            <themekey>general procedure</themekey>
            <themekey>statistics</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <taxonomy>
         <keywtax>
            <taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
            <taxonkey>birds</taxonkey>
         </keywtax>
         <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
            <taxoncl>
               <taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
               <taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
               <taxoncl>
                  <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
                  <taxonrv>Aves</taxonrv>
               </taxoncl>
            </taxoncl>
         </taxoncl>
      </taxonomy>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>James E. Hines</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>11510 American Holly Dr. #201</address>
               <city>Laurel</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20708-4017</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5661</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>Jim_Hines@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>We thank J. B. Hestbeck, W. Link, J. D. Nichols, G. W. Pendleton, and B. K. Williams for commenting on the manuscript.</datacred>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Sauer J.R. And B.K. Williams</origin>
            <pubdate>1989</pubdate>
            <title>Generalized procedures for testing hypotheses about survival or recovery rates</title>
            <geoform>Book chapter</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>J. Wildl. Manage.</sername>
               <issue>53:137-142</issue>
            </serinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Hines, J.E., and J.R. Sauer.</origin>
            <pubdate>1989</pubdate>
            <title>Program CONTRAST - A General Program for the Analysis of Several Survival or Recovery Rate Estimates.</title>
            <geoform>Journal article</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Technical Report</sername>
               <issue>24</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Washington, D.C.</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</publish>
            </pubinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>not applicable</logic>
      <complete>not applicable</complete>
      <lineage>
         <method>
            <methtype>lab</methtype>
            <methdesc>In the user's manual, a computer program is described to implement the methods of Sauer and Williams, 1989</methdesc>
            <methcite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Sauer J.R. And B.K. Williams</origin>
                  <pubdate>1989</pubdate>
                  <title>Generalized procedures for testing hypotheses about survival or recovery rates</title>
                  <geoform>Book chapter</geoform>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>J. Wildl. Manage.</sername>
                     <issue>53:137-142</issue>
                  </serinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </methcite>
         </method>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The program allows for multiple comparisons of rate estimates, computation of the contrast Matrix C, A-priori Tests and A-posteriori Tests.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>James E. Hines</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>11510 American Holly Dr. #201</address>
               <city>Laurel</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20708-4017</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5661</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>Jim_Hines@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a U.S.. Geological Survey server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data.  The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ZIP</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software.html</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None if available online.</fees>
      </stdorder>
      <techpreq>
CONTRAST was written on an IBM PS/2 using the Ryan McFarland FORTRAN compiler (and the 8087 emulator library), so the math coprocessor is not required. The program should run on all IBM-PC compatible computers. The program currently is set up to compare up to 50 survival rates, and takes up less than 256K of memory. However, the
size of the program depends upon the maximum number of survival rates. For those who have a FORTRAN77 compiler, the maximum number of survival rates can be decreased or increased by changing all occurrences of 'IDIM=50' to 'IDIM=XX' in the source code, where XX is the desired number of survival rates.
</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20020329</metd>
      <metfrd>20030329</metfrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
               <cntorg>Science Systems and Applications, Inc.</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Metadata specialist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>10210 Greenbelt Road, Suite 500</address>
               <city>Lanham</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20706</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 867-2080</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301-867-2149.</cntfax>
            <cntemail>solomon@gcmd.nasa.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
      <metac>none</metac>
      <metuc>none</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
