<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Kenneth R. Wilson, Cooperative Fish and Wildlife Research Unit, Colorado State University, Fort Collins, Colorado; James D. Nichols and James E. Hines, Patuxent Wildlife Research Center</origin>
            <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
            <title>Band 2: A Computer Program for Sample Size Computations for Banding Studies</title>
            <geoform>tools software</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Laurel, Maryland</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division, Patuxent Wildlife Research Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>Information to create the metadata was obtained from http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software/doc/band2.html</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software.html</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>Band 2 computes the number of animals that must be banded in order to achieve a specified level of precision for survival rates estimated using band recovery models. Sample sizes necessary for estimating survival rates of banded birds are derived based on specified levels of precision. The equations are derived for studies involving adults only, or adults and young, and the banding study can be new or ongoing. Precision is based on the desired coefficient of variation (CV) of the survival estimates. The CV for annual survival estimates, the CV for mean annual survival estimates, and the length of the study must be specified to compute samples sizes. A computer program, BAND2, has been written to compute the necessary sample sizes given the desired precision level and length of the study. A description of the input and output for this program is described.</abstract>
         <purpose>Data from migratory bird banding programs can be used to draw inferences about migration pathways and geographic distribution patterns. This data can also aid in estimating survival rate and, in conjunction with data from other sources, harvest rate, recruitment rate and population size.</purpose>
         <supplinf>Information was taken from http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software/doc/band2.html  (previous geoform was 'computer program')</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>Unknown</update>
      </status>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>sample size</themekey>
            <themekey>survival rates</themekey>
            <themekey>banding</themekey>
            <themekey>tagging</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <taxonomy>
         <keywtax>
            <taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
            <taxonkey>birds</taxonkey>
         </keywtax>
         <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Animal</taxonrv>
            <taxoncl>
               <taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
               <taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
               <taxoncl>
                  <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
                  <taxonrv>Aves</taxonrv>
               </taxoncl>
            </taxoncl>
         </taxoncl>
      </taxonomy>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>James S. Clark</cntper>
               <cntorg>Duke University, Department of Biology &amp; Nicholas School of the Environment</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>H. L. Blomquist Professor</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
               <city>Durham</city>
               <state>North Carolina</state>
               <postal>27708</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>919-613-8036</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>919-660-7425</cntfax>
            <cntemail>jimclark@duke.edu</cntemail>
            <cntinst>http://www.biology.duke.edu/research_by_area/eeob/clark.html</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>We would like to thank John Sauer, Bob Trost, David Anderson, Eric Rexstad, and two anonymous referees for reviewing the manuscript.</datacred>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Wilson, K.R., J.D. Nichols, and J.E. Hines.</origin>
            <pubdate>1989</pubdate>
            <title>A Computer Program for Sample Size Computations for Banding Studies</title>
            <geoform>Book chapter</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Fish and Wildlife Technical Report</sername>
               <issue>No. 23</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Washington, D.C.</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</publish>
            </pubinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>not applicable</logic>
      <complete>An important error condition that will cause program BAND2 to stop is if f &gt; 1-S for a new study, or if f _ &gt; 1-S _ for a new or an ongoing study. In a new study, this results from choosing yearly or average survival and recovery values that are illogical, but for an ongoing study this can also result from poor estimates of the yearly survival and recovery rates, S and f , such that S _ +f _ &gt; 1.0. For an ongoing study, the investigator must manually choose the "best" guess for the previous yearly survival and recovery rates such that the sum of the average rates, S _ and f _ , is not greater than 1. In some instances, the data from an ongoing study (and thus, also, the survival and recovery estimates) may be so "poor" that sample size must be computed as if a new study is beginning.</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Sample sizes necessary for estimating survival rates of banded birds, adults and young, are derived based on specified levels of precision. The banding study can be new or ongoing. The desired coefficient of variation (CV) for annual survival estimates, the CV for mean annual survival estimates, and the length of the study must be specified to compute samples sizes. A computer program is available for computation of the sample sizes, and a description of the input and output is described.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>James E. Hines</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>11510 American Holly Dr. #201</address>
               <city>Laurel</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20708-4017</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5661</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>Jim_Hines@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a U.S.. Geological Survey server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data.  The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ZIP (see below)</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>ftp://pwrcftpr.er.usgs.gov/research</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None, if available online.</fees>
         <ordering>The FTP server is located at ftp://pwrcftpr.er.usgs.gov/research. This should have no effect on downloading files. If you have trouble, please let the distributor know. The programs are stored as "zip" archives. Most of the zip files contain both the source code (usually FORTRAN) and IBM-PC compatible executable files. If you need an unzipping program, you can download a free Windows unzipper [PowerArc] or a free MSDOS unzipper [unzip.exe].</ordering>
      </stdorder>
      <techpreq>The program will run on an IBM PC, AT, 80386, or compatible and most runs only take a few seconds. The program was written in FORTRAN 77, and compiled with the Ryan-McFarland compiler, RMFORT. Program BAND2 consists of a main routine and 2 subroutines. Currently, 30 years of previous banding can be input, and up to 50 years of proposed banding computed. This can easily be changed by increasing the dimensions of the program. The program should compile using most MSDOS FORTRAN compilers, including mainframe compilers, with few changes, if any.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20020331</metd>
      <metfrd>20030331</metfrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
               <cntorg>Science Systems and Applications, Inc.</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Metadata specialist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>10210 Greenbelt Road, Suite 500</address>
               <city>Lanham</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20706</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 867-2080</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301-867-2149.</cntfax>
            <cntemail>solomon@gcmd.nasa.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
      <metac>none</metac>
      <metuc>none</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
