<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>James E. Hines</origin>
            <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
            <title>TMSURVIV- computes parameter estimates of survival and capture probability and proportions of ''residents'' under the Jolly-Seber models described in ''Capture-Recapture Survival Models Taking Account of Transients'' </title>
            <geoform>tools software</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Laurel, Maryland</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division, Patuxent Wildlife Research Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>Program TMSURVIV (Transient-Model-SURVIVal analysis) computes parameter estimates of survival and capture probability and proportions of ''residents'' under the Jolly-Seber models described in ''Capture-Recapture Survival Models Taking Account of Transients'' (Pradel et. al., 1997). Actually, TMSURVIV is a specially modified version of Dr. G. White's program SURVIV (White, 1983) which incorporates the transient models. With this program and it's companion program, CNVTMSRV, users are able to get parameter estimates for these complex models from capture-history data without having to specify the cell probabilities.</abstract>
         <purpose>TMSURVIV is intended to be used in a situation where the sampling area includes animals which pass through the area and are not part of the "resident" population.</purpose>
         <supplinf>The information for this metadata was taken from http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software/doc/tmsurviv.html.  (previous geoform was 'software')</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>parameter estimates</themekey>
            <themekey>survival and capture probability and proportions</themekey>
            <themekey>residents</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <taxonomy>
         <keywtax>
            <taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
            <taxonkey>animal</taxonkey>
         </keywtax>
         <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Animal</taxonrv>
         </taxoncl>
      </taxonomy>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>James E. Hines</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>11510 American Holly Dr. #201</address>
               <city>Laurel</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20708-4017</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5661</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>Jim_Hines@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Pradel, R., J.E. Hines, J-D Lebreton, and J.D. Nichols</origin>
            <pubdate>1996</pubdate>
            <title>Capture-Recapture Survival Models Taking Account of Transients</title>
            <geoform>Publication</geoform>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>not applicable</logic>
      <complete>unknown</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Output from TMSURVIV includes survival probability estimates, capture probability estimates, estimates of the proportion of residents, goodness-of-fit tests, and likelihood-ratio tests. By default, models are generated for standard Jolly-Seber models (where all animals are assumed to be residents), and transient models (a portion of the population is transient and only available for capture in one sample). The model names signify the structure of the model. Each model name is in the form "S.P.G." where "S" stands for survival, "P" stands for capture probability, and "G" stands for "gamma (proportion of residents)". If S,P, or G are followed by a "t", then the corresponding parameter is "time-dependent". If there is no "G" in the name, then all animals are assumed to be residents (proportion of residents = 1.0), which is equivalent to the Jolly-Seber models.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>James E. Hines</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>11510 American Holly Dr. #201</address>
               <city>Laurel</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20708-4017</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5661</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>Jim_Hines@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a U.S.. Geological Survey server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data.  The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ZIP</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software.html</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None if available online.</fees>
         <ordering>The FTP server is located at ftp://pwrcftpr.er.usgs.gov/research. This should have no effect on downloading files. If you have trouble, please let the distributor know. The programs are stored as "zip" archives. Most of the zip files contain both the source code (usually FORTRAN) and IBM-PC compatible executable files. If you need an unzipping program, you can download a free Windows unzipper [PowerArc] or a free MSDOS unzipper [unzip.exe].</ordering>
      </stdorder>
      <techpreq>The program has been compiled for DOS and Windows 95.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20020329</metd>
      <metfrd>20030329</metfrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
               <cntorg>Science Systems and Applications, Inc.</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Metadata specialist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>10210 Greenbelt Road, Suite 500</address>
               <city>Lanham</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20706</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 867-2080</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301-867-2149.</cntfax>
            <cntemail>solomon@gcmd.nasa.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
      <metac>none</metac>
      <metuc>none</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
