<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>National Audubon Society</origin>
            <pubdate>1996</pubdate>
            <title>Audubon Christmas Bird Counts (CBCs)</title>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>New York, NY</pubplace>
               <publish>National Audubon Society</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>
This metadata file can be found at:
ftp://cameron.cr.usgs.gov/pub/nbii_metadata/brdpwrc0006.txt
(text format)
and
ftp://cameron.cr.usgs.gov/pub/nbii_metadata/brdpwrc0006.html
(HTML format)
and
ftp://cameron.cr.usgs.gov/pub/nbii_metadata/brdpwrc0006.sgml
(SGML format).
</othercit>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>
The first Christmas Bird Counts (CBCs) were conducted in 1900 in
response to a suggestion made in the National Audubon Society's
magazine Bird-Lore. Twenty-seven individuals responded by spending
several hours on Christmas Day in their neighborhood, counting all of
the birds they observed or heard. This survey has been coordinated by
the National Audubon Society ever since, and has become the oldest
continuous wildlife survey in North America.
CBCs quickly expanded into entire day censuses, when single observers
covered as much territory as possible counting all of the individuals
that could be positively identified. While the number of hours in the
field and miles covered varied from individual to individual, the
intention was that repetition of these surveys would allow for the
monitoring of trends in bird populations of each area.
These single observer counts quickly evolved into a more organized
effort, where groups of people would count birds in a larger area
during a single day. By the 1920s, most of the CBCs consisted of group
counts rather than censuses by individuals. Unfortunately, as CBCs
evolved into group efforts, there was little consistency in some of
the aspects of the methodologies followed by these counts. The area
covered varied from CBC to CBC, as did the count date and level of
coverage. While these differences prevented meaningful comparisons of
the results between CBCs, the data from single CBCs could still
provide useful information on the status and trends of populations
within each area.
In order to provide more useful results from CBCs, the National
Audubon Society implemented uniform standards beginning in the late
1950s. This methodology is still in use today.
</abstract>
         <purpose>
USES OF CBC DATA CBC data has received considerable use during recent
decades, primarily directed towards two topics: winter distribution
patterns and population trends. Many other potential uses exist for
these data, such as showing patterns of winter species diversity over
large geographic scales, but these studies would require a better
understanding of the biases associated with the data before they could
be conducted.
These data provide a wealth of information on the early
winter distributions of birds in North America, and geographic
patterns in their relative abundances. Root (1988) used CBC data in
preparation of an atlas of winter bird distribution.
Other distribution maps have been developed by others.
These data have also been widely used to establish the population
trends of birds. Given the lack of consistency of coverage, temporal
changes in effort, and other problems, the estimation of trends using
CBC data has remained controversial. Some preliminary analyses have
been conducted, but additional studies are needed in order to better
understand the potential biases associated with CBC data and how to
estimate population trends with these data.
</purpose>
         <supplinf>
AVAILABILITY OF CBC DATA At this time, only the CBC data between the
winters of 1900-1901 through 1908-1909, 1959-1960 through 1988-1989,
and 1994-1995 have been computerized. An effort is underway to
computerize the remainder of the database, hopefully, the entire CBC
database will be computerized and readily accessible within the next
1-2 years.
CBC census data organized by state is available on our ftp server.
ftp://ftp.mp1-pwrc.usgs.gov/pub/data/cbc/
With nearly 100 years of data, the CBC is a valuable source of
information on historic and recent changes in the status
and distribution of birds during the early winter period in the United
States and Canada.  Unfortunately, the absence of standardization of
many aspects of the CBC complicates any analyses of these data. A
number of factors need to be considered whenever CBC data are
used. Some of these factors are briefly discussed below, and are
described in greater detail in some of the cited references.
Representativeness of CBC Locations While CBCs represent approximately
4.3% of the land mass north of the Mexican border, they are hardly
representative of the landscape as a whole. Two factors influence the
location of CBC circles: the distribution of participants and the
concentrations of birds. Hence, CBCs tend to be concentrated near
cities.  The circles tend to avoid urban areas, since these areas are
frequently devoid of birds, but suburban areas tend to be
over-represented on CBCs. The count circles also reflect
the distribution of the human population, with a preponderance of counts
in heavily populated areas such as the Atlantic coast of New England
and the Mid-Atlantic states, but relatively few counts where the human
population is sparse. For example, most of the Canadian counts are in
located in the southern quarter of the country, while very few counts
are made in central and northern Canada.
Additionally, CBCs tend to be located near areas where large numbers
of birds are concentrated during that season of the year. These
locations tend to be coastal, along the Great Lakes or other large
bodies of water, or at wildlife refuges and other similar areas that
attract birds.
These biases do not reflect on the counts of individuals reported on
CBCs. However, drawing inferences on changes in status
and distribution from CBC data to overall populations may be risky,
since the habitats surveyed on CBCs may not be representative of a
region or continent as a whole.
Even within CBCs, coverage of residential areas or other developed
sites is generally poor or non-existent, so most of the data tend to
come from the "natural" habitats. As count circles become more
developed over time, coverage tends to become more concentrated in the
less- developed areas. These subtle changes in coverage could
influence the apparent population trends of some species within a
count, but could never be detected by the effort data collected for
each CBC.
Changes in Coverage
While the locations of the count circles has remained fairly constant
during recent years, some of the circles have been shifted somewhat
yet retained the same name. Some of these shifts are relatively minor
changes in the boundaries to avoid overlap with neighboring counts,
while other changes are more significant.  Depending upon the extent
of these changes, comparison of the results before and after the
modifications may not be valid. Unfortunately, these changes are not
necessarily well documented in the count results, and recent compilers
may not be aware of changes that occurred decades ago.
Documenting observer effort undertaken each year also poses some
problems. Each count provides a summary of the effort, but these
summaries are frequently incorrect. Estimates of total party-hours or
total party-miles on foot may be very unlikely given the number of
observers participating on a CBC, and these estimates should be
carefully examined prior to conducting any analyses of the
data. Additionally, the summaries of effort have changed over
time. For example, the amount of time spent counting birds at feeders
was only recently separated from the other effort categories of hours
spent in the field. There are other potential problems as well, such
as people participating in the count but not paying the count fee and
appearing in the published list of participants. Hence, the number of
"official" participants and their effort may under-represent the true
effort expended on the CBC.
EXPERTISE OF CBC PARTICIPANTS
No qualification criteria exist for CBC participants, and it is up to
the individual count compilers to decide which people can participate
in a CBC. For most CBCs, anybody who wants to participate will be
allowed to do so, whether they are expert birders or beginners. Hence,
a whole range of bird identification expertise is usually represented
in the participants of each count.
The results from each CBC will reflect both the identification skills
of the participants and the knowledge of the compiler. Counts from
adjacent areas may produce very different results, reflecting the
expertise of the participants rather than actual changes in
the distributions of birds. In some cases, the addition of a few expert
birders can significantly improve the results from a CBC. All of these
factors are very difficult to assess without considerable familiarity
with the count participants, but can influence the conclusions drawn
from the results.
As better field guides and optical equipment have been developed, bird
identification skills have generally improved in the United States and
Canada. This improvement in bird identification skills has been most
apparent within the past 20 years, and poses some significant
challenges in the analyses of CBC data. As these skills improve,
birders generally count greater numbers of individuals and species
within the area they cover each year. Even if overall effort within a
count remains constant, this improvement in skill levels will probably
result in slightly higher totals over time, and analyses based on
counts adjusted by party-hour may be positively biased as a
consequence. These factors need to be considered when analyzing CBC
data, but trying to quantify the extent of these potential biases may
prove to be impossible.
</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>1900</begdate>
               <enddate>1996</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>From conversation with Geoffrey LeBaron</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>in work</progress>
         <update>annually</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <descgeog>|Continental U.S., Canada, &amp; Alaska, with spotty coverage in Alaska|and northern half of Canada.  A few routes have been recently|established in northern Mexico, Central American and Caribbean.|The growth in CBC effort was summarized by Butcher (1990). Wh</descgeog>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-165</westbc>
            <eastbc>-50</eastbc>
            <northbc>75</northbc>
            <southbc>20</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>Christmas Bird Counts</themekey>
            <themekey>National Audubon Society</themekey>
            <themekey>early winter bird census</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>GCMD location keyword thesaurus</placekt>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>Canada</placekey>
            <placekey>Mexico</placekey>
            <placekey>Central America</placekey>
            <placekey>Caribbean Islands</placekey>
            <placekey>Hawaii</placekey>
            <placekey>South America</placekey>
            <placekey>Western Hemisphere</placekey>
            <placekey>Pacific Islands</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <taxonomy>
         <taxonkey>Aves</taxonkey>
         <taxoncov>
            <taxoninf>
               <kingdom>Animal</kingdom>
               <phylum>Chordata</phylum>
               <class>Aves</class>
            </taxoninf>
            <taxongen>birds</taxongen>
         </taxoncov>
      </taxonomy>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>National Audubon Society</cntorg>
               <cntper>Geoffrey S. LeBaron</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>700 Broadway</address>
               <city>New York</city>
               <state>NY</state>
               <postal>10003</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>212 979-3083</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>212 353-0321</cntfax>
            <cntemail>glebaron@audubon.org</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>National Audubon Society</datacred>
      <native>In development</native>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>National Audubon Society</origin>
            <pubdate>1996</pubdate>
            <title>Christmas Bird count issue</title>
            <edition>96th Christmas Bird Count</edition>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>National Audubon Society Field Notes</sername>
               <issue>Vol. 50 No. 4</issue>
            </serinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>
Volunteer generated, but thoroughly reviewed in field.  Reviewed by
33 regional editors, many of whom are part of the rare birds
committee.
</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>not applicable</logic>
      <complete>Completeness varies depending on geographic area in question.</complete>
      <lineage>
         <method>
            <methtype>field CBC</methtype>
            <methdesc>
All CBCs occur within a 15-mile diameter circle. These circles are
not randomly located, but are chosen by the compiler. The only
restriction is that they should not overlap any other CBC circle in
the area. Each count is conducted during a single calendar day within
two weeks of Christmas; the census periods are currently determined by
the National Audubon Society but the actual census day is chosen by
the count coordinator.  There are no limits to the number of people
who can participate in a CBC, or qualifications for their abilities to
identify birds. The proportion of the circle that is actually covered
varies from CBC to CBC, but none of the counts has even covered an
entire 15-mile diameter circle.
Any variety of methods may be used to collect data. Most data are
collected on foot, in cars, or by people watching birds coming to
feeders. However, some counts have employed bicycles, boats, canoes,
snowmobiles, and even airplanes to count birds. Effort used to census
nocturnal birds is kept separate from diurnal effort. Hopefully, the
same methods will be utilized each year in order to provide comparable
results.  Such consistency is seldom possible, and yearly differences
in methodology can significantly influence the results of the counts.
The results from the CBCs are submitted to the National Audubon
Society, which has compiled the data since the inception of the
survey. The results are currently published in an issue of the
National Audubon Society Field Notes (formerly American Birds).
</methdesc>
            <methcite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>National Audubon Society</origin>
                  <pubdate>1996</pubdate>
                  <title>Christmas Bird Count Issue</title>
                  <edition>96th Christmas Bird Count</edition>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>National Audubon Society Field Notes</sername>
                     <issue>Vol. 50, No. 4</issue>
                  </serinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </methcite>
         </method>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Analysis of Christmas Bird Count data and trends</procdesc>
            <procdate>unknown</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Sam Droege</cntper>
                     <cntorg>
Patuxent Wildlife Research Center,
Biological Resources Division,
U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)
</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>12100 Beech Forest Road</address>
                     <city>Laurel</city>
                     <state>MD</state>
                     <postal>20708-4038</postal>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>301 497-5840</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>301 497-5784</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>frog@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <indspref>Based on local reference names</indspref>
   </spdoinfo>
   <eainfo>
      <overview>
         <eaover>
Entity - birds
Associated Attributes - christmas bird counts, early winter bird
census, distribution, population trends
</eaover>
         <eadetcit>unknown</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>
Patuxent Wildlife Research Center,
Biological Resources Division,
U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)
</cntorg>
               <cntper>Brett Hoover</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>12100 Beech Forest Road</address>
               <city>Laurel</city>
               <state>MD</state>
               <postal>20708-4038</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5819</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301 497-5784</cntfax>
            <cntemail>brett_hoover@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>unknown</resdesc>
      <distliab>
No warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or
utility of the data on any system or for general or scientific
purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such
warranty.  This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data
and aggregate use with other data.  It is strongly recommended that
these data are directly acquired from the Biological Resources Division (BRD)
U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and not indirectly though other sources which may have
changed the data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended that
careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file
associated with these data.  Neither the BRD nor the NASA
Global Change Master Directory shall be held liable for improper or
incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.
</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>unknown</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.mp1-pwrc.usgs.gov/birds/cbc.html#participant</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
               <offoptn>
                  <offmedia>unknown</offmedia>
                  <recfmt>unknown</recfmt>
               </offoptn>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>unknown</fees>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>Please contact Brett Hoover listed in section 6.1</custom>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>1996</metd>
      <metrd>19970415</metrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Hughes STX</cntorg>
               <cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>7701 Greenbelt Rd</address>
               <city>Greenbelt</city>
               <state>MD</state>
               <postal>20770</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 441-4249</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301 441-9486</cntfax>
            <cntemail>solomon@gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>
DRAFT Content Standard for National Biological Information
Infrastructure Metadata.
</metstdn>
      <metstdv>December 1995</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
