<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>James Hines</origin>
            <pubdate>1988</pubdate>
            <title>Jolly- compute survival rate, population size, and immigration rate estimates from capture-recapture data</title>
            <geoform>tools software</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Laurel, Maryland</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S.Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division, Patuxent Wildlife Research Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This program is used to compute survival rate, population size, and immigration rate estimates from capture-recapture data. The program computes these statistics using the model suggested by Jolly (1965; Biometrika 52:225- 246) which allows both death and immigration . A goodness-of-fit test is also provided to determine if this model is appropriate. A second model (Model A' ) is available which allows for death but no immigration. The same statistics (except for the estimate of immigration), including a goodness-of-fit test, are computed in this model. Another model (Model 2) included in this program assumes survival rates are different for animals which are captured for the first time than unmarked or previously marked animals. The program also computes estimates under two reduced parameter models (Model B: constant survival rate, time-specific capture probability and Model D: constant survival rate and constant capture probability).   A more modern Windows95 program, MARK (written by G. White) is recommended instead of JOLLY.  Mark is available at http://www.cnr.colostate.edu/~gwhite/mark/mark.htm.</abstract>
         <purpose>The program JOLLY computes estimates of survival and capture probability for 1-age class open population capture-recapture models.</purpose>
         <supplinf>The information was taken from http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software/doc/jolly.html.  (previous geoform was 'software')</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>1988</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>capture recapture data</themekey>
            <themekey>capture</themekey>
            <themekey>recapture</themekey>
            <themekey>survival rate</themekey>
            <themekey>population size</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <taxonomy>
         <keywtax>
            <taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
            <taxonkey>animal</taxonkey>
         </keywtax>
         <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Animal</taxonrv>
         </taxoncl>
      </taxonomy>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>James E. Hines</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>11510 American Holly Dr. #201</address>
               <city>Laurel</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20708-4017</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5661</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>Jim_Hines@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Pollock, K.H., J.D. Nichols, C. Brownie, and J.E. Hines</origin>
            <pubdate>1990</pubdate>
            <title>Statistical Inference for Capture-Recapture Experiments</title>
            <geoform>Journal article</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Wildlife Monographs</sername>
               <issue>107</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <othercit>97pp.</othercit>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>Error number 3023 indicates that a carriage return and/or linefeed character is missing at the end of the input file. Use your word-processor to check the input file.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>not applicable</logic>
      <complete>unknown</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>If specified, the program will perform a goodness-of-fit test assuming death but no immigration, similar to the goodness-of-fit test for the death and immigration model.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>James E. Hines</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>11510 American Holly Dr. #201</address>
               <city>Laurel</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20708-4017</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5661</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>Jim_Hines@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a U.S. Geological Survey server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data.  The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ZIP</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software.html</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None if available online.</fees>
         <ordering>The FTP server is located at ftp://pwrcftpr.er.usgs.gov/research. This should have no effect on downloading files. If you have trouble, please let the distributor know. The programs are stored as "zip" archives. Most of the zip files contain both the source code (usually FORTRAN) and IBM-PC compatible executable files. If you need an unzipping program, you can download a free Windows unzipper [PowerArc] or a free MSDOS unzipper [unzip.exe].</ordering>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20020329</metd>
      <metfrd>20030329</metfrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
               <cntorg>Science Systems and Applications, Inc.</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Metadata specialist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>10210 Greenbelt Road, Suite 500</address>
               <city>Lanham</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20706</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 867-2080</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301-867-2149.</cntfax>
            <cntemail>solomon@gcmd.nasa.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
