<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Patuxent Wildlife Research Center,
Biological Resources Division,
U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)
</origin>
            <pubdate>1994</pubdate>
            <title>Maryland Winter Bird Survey- 1988 to 1993 </title>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Laurel, MD</pubplace>
               <publish>
Patuxent Wildlife Research Center,
Inventory and Monitoring,
Biological Resources Division,
U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)
</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>
This metadata file can be found at:
ftp://cameron.cr.usgs.gov/pub/nbii_metadata/brdpwrc0009.txt
(text format)
and
ftp://cameron.cr.usgs.gov/pub/nbii_metadata/brdpwrc0009.html
(HTML format)
and
ftp://cameron.cr.usgs.gov/pub/nbii_metadata/brdpwrc0009.sgml
(SGML format).
</othercit>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>
A winter bird survey was conducted throughout Maryland, primarily by
volunteers, during the 6 winters of 1988 to 1993 between the dates 10
Jan and 10 Feb. The state of Maryland is covered by 1231 blocks (9.5
sq.  miles each), each comprising one-sixth of the standard
U.S.G.S. 7.5 minute topographic quadrangle, and 548 of these blocks
(44.5%) were surveyed for winter birds. Blocks were chosen in a
systematic pattern with eventually almost every other block in the
state having been surveyed as of Feb, 1993. Volunteers conducted each
4-hour survey by walking a 4-6 mile route chosen by the volunteer to
sample habitats in proportion to their availability in the
block. Surveys began around sunrise (7:30 a.m.) and all birds seen or
heard during the 4 hours were recorded on data sheets. The data were
then used to create maps representing the distribution and relative
abundance of each species of wintering bird found in at least 10
blocks in the state.
</abstract>
         <purpose>
GOAL: To survey in a uniform manner the wintering bird life of
Maryland. After an initial 6-year survey period, we will develop
winter range and relative abundance maps for diurnal wintering
birds. In subsequent decades this technique will be used to monitor
fluctuations, trends, and cycles in populations. It may also serve to
monitor emigrations of unpredictable northern species.
The Maryland winter bird survey is to provide an accurate picture of
the winter distribution of birds in a region and will work well in
areas with high volunteer labor pools.
</purpose>
         <supplinf>http://www.mp1-pwrc.usgs.gov/winter/instruct.html</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>1988</begdate>
               <enddate>1993</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>
From Maryland Winter Bird Survey Metadata and from Maryland Birdlife
cited in 1.15
</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>none planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <descgeog>|Maryland|For the purpose of interpreting the maps, a brief discussion of the|geography of the state and its physiographic regions (see Fig. 1a)|follows. Maryland contains parts of 3 physiographic provinces (Frese|1994): Coastal Plain, Piedmont, and Appal</descgeog>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-78</westbc>
            <eastbc>-75.5</eastbc>
            <northbc>40</northbc>
            <southbc>38</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>Maryland Winter Bird Survey</themekey>
            <themekey>bird survey</themekey>
            <themekey>bird census</themekey>
            <themekey>winter bird survey</themekey>
            <themekey>winter bird census</themekey>
            <themekey>bird atlas</themekey>
            <themekey>winter bird atlas</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Maryland</placekey>
            <placekey>District of Columbia</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <taxonomy>
         <taxonkey>birds</taxonkey>
         <taxoncov>
            <taxoninf>
               <kingdom>Animal</kingdom>
               <phylum>Vertebrata</phylum>
               <class>Aves</class>
            </taxoninf>
            <taxongen>birds, Aves</taxongen>
         </taxoncov>
      </taxonomy>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>
Patuxent Wildlife Research Center,
Biological Resources Division,
U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)
</cntorg>
               <cntper>Jeffrey S. Hatfield</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>11510 American Holly Drive</address>
               <city>Laurel</city>
               <state>MD</state>
               <postal>20708-4017</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5633</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301 497-5666</cntfax>
            <cntemail>jeff_hatfield@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>
We gratefully acknowledge all the volunteers below who conducted the
counts. Volunteers with an asterisk following the name surveyed 10 or
more blocks. Volunteers: Ted Banvard, Polly Batchelder, Chris Beaton*,
Judy Blake, Rick Blom, Larry Bonham, Bob Boxwell, Jim Boxwell, Michael
Braun, Dave Brinker, Carol Broderick, Danny Bystrak*, Paul Bystrak,
John Canoles, Jim Cheevers, Marty Chestem, John Chrisafis, Roger
Clapp, Les Coble, Patty Craig, Jean Crump, Jon G. Cupp, Lynn Davidson,
Deanna Dawson*, Alan Dixon, Bob Dixon, Kevin Dodge, Sam Droege*, Chuck
Dupree, Tad Eareckson, Les Eastman, Jeff Effinger, Gerald Elgert, Fred
Fallon*, Jane Fallon, Rick Farrar, Jane Farrell, Rob Fleischer, Harold
Fogleman, Robert Folker, Mark Garland, Carol Ghebelian, Rob Gibbs,
Caleb Gordon, Greg Gough*, Russ Greenberg, Alex Hammer, Helene Hammer,
Peter Hanan, Allan Haury, Jeffrey Hatfield, Mark Hoffman, David
Holmes, Marshall Howe, Bill Howe, Clark Jeschke, Emily Joyce, Paul
Jung, Hank Kaestner*, Robert Keedy, Dennis Kirkwood, Wayne Klockner,
Bryan Knedler, Henry Leskinen, Lloyd Lewis, Doug Lister, Gail
Mackiernan, Carol McCollough, Lee McCollough, Joan McKearnan, Don
Merritt, Stauffer Miller, Gene Morton, Dave Mozurkewich, Harvey Mudd*,
Marion Mudd*, Floyd Murdoch, Jay Nelson, Michael O'Brien*, Paul
O'Brien, Rob Peeples, Bruce Peterjohn, Lisa Petit, Kyle Rambo, Jan
Reese, Sue Ricciardi*, Robert Ringler*, Chan Robbins, Brian Rollfinke,
Gene Sattler, Cynthia Sibrel, Teresa Simons, Connie Skipper, Ann
Smith, David Smith, Joanne Solem, David Spector, Jim Stasz, Chris
Swarth, Byron Swift, Charles Swift, Bill Thompson, Spike Updegrove,
Brad Vaughn, Charles Vaughn, June Vaughn, David Wallace, Peter Webb*,
Steve Westre, Claudia Wilds, Jim Wilkinson, Levin Willey, George
Wilmot*, and Erika Wilson.
In addition, Leslie Gerstenfeld-Press helped with data entry. Michael
O'Brien provided the drawing of the Dark-eyed Junco used on the front
cover. Eirik A.T. Blom, Robert F. Ringler, and John R. Sauer provided
helpful reviews to earlier versions of this manuscript.
</datacred>
      <native>
Map Viewer Software Version 1.1 (Golden Software, Golden, Colorado)
was used to create dot maps.  Files were not saved.  Dots maps
viewable in Maryland Birdlife magazine cited in 1.15 Cross Reference.
Surfer Software Version 5.01 (Golden Software, Golden, Colorado) was
used to create the contour maps. The second map (designated "b") of
each pair of species' maps is the contour map. The contour maps are
viewable in Maryland Birdlife magazine cited in 1.15 Cross Reference.
</native>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Jeffrey S. Hatfield, Sue A. Ricciardi, Greg A. Gough,
Danny Bystrak, Sam Droege, and Chandler S.  Robbins
</origin>
            <pubdate>1993</pubdate>
            <title>Distribution and Abundance of Birds Wintering in Maryland 1988-1993</title>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Maryland Birdlife</sername>
               <issue>V. 50, nos. 1-4</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <othercit>pp. 3-83</othercit>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>
Data has been completely verified to the best of the investigators' abilities.
Care should be taken not to over-interpret the edges of the contour
divisions on the kriged maps. The edges of boundaries often look
"busy" with lots of "squiggles" which should be ignored for the most
part. This is due to a choice made in applying the software (e.g.,
200-unit grid) to make the resulting surface follow the outline of
blocks, representing the true area surveyed. Thus, the dot maps should
be compared to the contour maps for questionable abundance contours on
the contour maps. The dot and contour maps each describe the data from
a different perspective and, generally, either the dot map or the
contour map is better for any given species, but it will be left to
the reader to decide which map is preferred for each species. However,
any contour map with an asterisk (*) following the figure number
indicates that this map was particularly uninformative, usually
because the species was difficult to detect and was missed in parts of
its range. For these species, the dot map should be used, not the
contour map.
</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>not applicable</logic>
      <complete>
Any contour map with an asterisk (*) following the figure number
indicates that this map was particularly uninformative, usually
because the species was difficult to detect and was missed in parts of
its range. For these species, the dot map should be used, not the
contour map.
</complete>
      <lineage>
         <method>
            <methtype>field surveys</methtype>
            <methdesc>
METHODS: Maryland has been divided into a grid of approximately 1200
blocks, each about 10 sq. mi. in size. This is the same grid system
used in the Maryland Breeding Bird Atlas project. Each surveyed block
will receive 4-hours of on-foot coverage by experienced birders. Due
to the difficulties of attempting to survey all 1200 + blocks, only
the blocks will be covered, namely a checkerboard pattern of "target"
blocks.  In the first year, alternate southern blocks in each 7 minute
quadrangle will be surveyed, in the second year, middle blocks and in
the third year, northern blocks. The cycle will then repeat in the
4th, 5th, and 6th years, to complete the targeted blocks.
CHOOSING A ROUTE: It is important to cover a block in proportion to
the habitats present in the block.  For example, if the block contains
40% suburbs, 10% marsh, 10% fields, and 40% woods you should spend
about 1 hours in the suburbs and in the woods and about hour in the
marsh and in the fields. Most blocks can meet this criterion with one
continuous 4-hour route. However, if the habitats present are too
scattered, some driving is permitted. Do not exceed hour of driving
time and do not count birds during that time or consider it part of
the total 4 hours. It might also be necessary to retrace part of your
route to sample an important habitat. Again, the time spent retracing
should not be considered part of the 4 hours, nor should birds be
counted. A walking speed of 1-1.5 miles per hour is suggested. Hence,
4 hours of coverage should be about 4-6 miles. This speed allows time
to "work" mixed flocks of birds, but not to dawdle or sit.  Complete
roadside coverage is not recommended, but in some blocks it might be
necessary. If a block dictates largely or entirely walking on roads,
it will probably be easy to cover up to 6 miles. If you complete 4
hours of coverage before you complete your proposed route, stop
counting and return to your car. If you reach your proposed end point
before the 4 hours is up, extend coverage, but not along the
already-covered route. If possible, examine the map and scout the area
ahead of time, asking permission if necessary. Plan your route before
the actual day of coverage.
TIMING OF ROUTES: In order to keep the surveys comparable, a time
period of 7:30-11:30 has been chosen. This avoids the brief period of
intense bird activity at dawn, and everyone gets to sleep later. The
survey can be extended up till noon to compensate for driving time, as
described above.
COUNTING: Each block will be visited once by one observer. A companion
may act as recorder but should not help lure or spot birds. Pishing
may be used to attract mixed flocks but no tapes or owl imitations are
permitted. The object is not to maximize the number of birds recorded,
but to survey winter birds in a uniform manner. Use the field sheet
provided, counting all individual birds seen or heard in each of 8
half-hour segments. If you would rather not carry a clip board, a
small note pad, with a page for each hour will be satisfactory. In
blocks with water, time should not be spent scoping or waiting for
birds. Open water or other special habitats like landfills should be
surveyed following the 4 hours of foot coverage. The results from
these special areas should be written in at the bottom of the
form. Waterbirds flying over or in fields found during the walking
portion of the survey should be treated like any other species. Upon
completion of your survey be sure to record all weather information
and mark the location of the route you took on the map. Also be sure
to mark the location of the end point of each hour segment.
GENERIC SPECIES: Winter birds are often difficult to identify to
species. For completeness sake, please record all birds such as crows
and gulls that you are not able to separate by species.
REPORTING: After completing the count, transfer the data to the
summary sheet provided, and fill in the weather data. Total the 8
columns and double-check the species total for each column to make
sure it agrees with the species total for each half-hour on the field
sheet. Please return your field sheets and maps.  These maps are from
a personal collection and their replacement is expensive.
WEATHER CODES: Please record the percentage of ground that is covered
with snow and the percentage of ice on the water bodies in your
block. Please record wind speed using the following codes: 0 - smoke
rises vertically, 1 - smoke drifts, 2 - wind felt on face, 3 - light
flags extended, 4 - wind raises dust and loose paper, 5 - crested
wavelets on inland waters. Please record sky conditions using the
following Weather Bureau codes: 0 - clear or a few clouds, 1 - partly
cloudy (scattered), 2 - cloudy, 4 - fog or smoke, 5 - drizzle, 7 -
snow, 8 - showers.
A FEW PRACTICAL HINTS:
If there is snow on the ground wear waterproof boots.
Dress in layers and bring 2 more layers than you think you could possibly need.
Bring Chapstick.
A pocketful of "trail mix" can keep your energy and spirits high while
walking those boring fields.
Two observers can easily survey different blocks using one car by
establishing pickup locations along a road at the end of the count.
http://www.mp1-pwrc.usgs.gov/winter/instruct.html
</methdesc>
            <methcite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>
Jeffrey S. Hatfield, Sue A. Ricciardi, Greg
A. Gough, Danny Bystrak, Sam Droege, and Chandler S.  Robbins
</origin>
                  <pubdate>1993</pubdate>
                  <title>
The Distribution and Abundance of Birds Wintering in
Maryland 1988-1993
</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>Maryland Birdlife</sername>
                     <issue>V. 50, nos. 1-4</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <othercit>pp. 3-83</othercit>
               </citeinfo>
            </methcite>
         </method>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Summary statistics were tabulated for each species. These included the
percent of blocks in which each species was detected, the mean
abundance in blocks where each species was detected (i.e., occupied
blocks), and the mean abundance over all 548 blocks, including blocks
where the species was not detected (counted as 0 in the overall
means). Species found in 10 or more blocks were ranked using each of
these 3 statistics for comparison of the relative abundance among
species. Rarer species were not ranked because of imprecision in
rankings of such species.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Two maps were produced for each species found in at least 10 blocks
during the 6 years of the survey. The first map (designated "a") for
each species, the dot map, has a black dot in each surveyed block
where it was found, with the area of the dot proportional to the size
of the count obtained during the 4-hour survey.  The areas of the dots
on each map were scaled between the smallest and largest count and a
small "o" was placed in each surveyed block where a count of 0 was
obtained (i.e., block was sampled but no birds of that species were
found on that survey). Therefore, the dot maps present the actual data
with no statistical smoothing between blocks. Map Viewer Software
Version 1.1 (Golden Software, Golden, Colorado) was used to create
these dot maps.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
The second map (designated "b") of each pair of species' maps is the
contour map. These maps were produced using Surfer Software Version
5.01 (Golden Software, Golden, Colorado) with a statistical procedure
called kriging (Isaaks and Srivastava 1989) and thus represent a
statistically smoothed version of the data. In kriging, a grid is
superimposed on the state and a linear model is calculated that
estimates the count at any grid point as a weighted average of nearby
points where data were collected. The counts from (at most) the 9
closest blocks within about 2 block-widths around each grid point were
used in the calculations. This was necessary due to the irregular
shape of Maryland, especially the narrow part of the panhandle between
Allegany and Washington counties, but sometimes resulted in a blotchy
effect for the contour maps of less abundant species. For contour maps
that appear particularly blotchy, the dot map should be used rather
than the contour map for those species.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
For the reader interested in more technical detail, kriging was used
because it is a smoothing procedure that incorporates the
autocorrelation structure among the blocks. The kriging was performed
over a 200-unit grid assuming a Gaussian variogram estimated
separately for each species. The weights were a function of distance,
estimated using the variogram, which measures the spatial association
among blocks as a function of the distance between them (Isaaks and
Srivastava 1989).
Contour intervals for each species were chosen such that the largest
contour was the maximum count over all the 4-hour surveys. The next
three contours for most species were the 75th, 50th (median), and 25th
percentiles of the nonzero counts of these species. To illustrate, see
the contour scale for Turkey Vulture (Fig. 19b). Seventy-five percent
of the surveys of blocks where Turkey Vultures were detected resulted
in counts ranging from 1 to 12 birds and 25% found from 12 to 157
birds. The median count was 6 birds and the count of 3 was the 25th
percentile. For some species, however, some of the percentiles were
the same and therefore these species have fewer than 4 contour
intervals. The 0.1 contour interval subdivision present on some maps
was chosen arbitrarily to represent a very low density of birds (i.e.,
1 bird detected in 10 4-hour surveys).
</procdesc>
            <procdate>unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <indspref>Based on local reference names</indspref>
   </spdoinfo>
   <eainfo>
      <overview>
         <eaover>
Entity - birds
Associated Attributes - point counts, relative abundance
</eaover>
         <eadetcit>unknown</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>
Patuxent Wildlife Research Center,
Biological Resources Division,
U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)
</cntorg>
               <cntper>Jeffrey S. Hatfield</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>11510 American Holly Drive</address>
               <city>Laurel</city>
               <state>MD</state>
               <postal>20708-4017</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5633</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301 497-5666</cntfax>
            <cntemail>jeff_hatfield@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>
No warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or
utility of the data on any system or for general or scientific
purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such
warranty.  This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data
and aggregate use with other data.  It is strongly recommended that
these data are directly acquired from the Biological Resources Division (BRD)
U.S. Geological Survey and not indirectly though other sources which may have
changed the data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended that
careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file
associated with these data.  Neither the BRD nor the NASA
Global Change Master Directory shall be held liable for improper or
incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.
</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>unknown</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.mp1-pwrc.usgs.gov/birds/othbird.html#winter</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
               <offoptn>
                  <offmedia>unknown</offmedia>
                  <recfmt>unknown</recfmt>
               </offoptn>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>unknown</fees>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>Please contact Jeffrey Hatfield (section 6.1)</custom>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>19970414</metd>
      <metrd>19970414</metrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Hughes STX</cntorg>
               <cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>7701 Greenbelt Rd</address>
               <city>Greenbelt</city>
               <state>MD</state>
               <postal>20770</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 441-4249</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301 441-9486</cntfax>
            <cntemail>solomon@gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>
DRAFT Content Standard for National Biological Information
Infrastructure Metadata.
</metstdn>
      <metstdv>December 1995</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
