<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Ben McPherson (retired)

Arturo Torres
</origin>
            <pubdate>2005</pubdate>
            <title>Compilation, Integration, and Synthesis of Water Quality and Flow Data for Assessing Nutrient Flux to South Florida Coastal Ecosystems</title>
            <geoform>project</geoform>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/projects/index.php?project_url=nutrient_flux</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The scope and objectives of this phase of the study are to: (1) Compile and summarize data that have been collected by different agencies and universities on water flow and water quality in tidal creeks and rivers that flow into coastal waters of ENP. (2) Evaluate and use flow and nutrient data from two river index systems (Trout Creek and Shark River) to estimate annual and monthly nutrient flux for a 9-year period (1995-2003). (3) Develop a plan based on results from the two index stations to expand nutrient load estimates for other major stream and river systems of ENP and nearby coastal waters.</abstract>
         <purpose>
Documentation of coastal nutrient loads prior to CERP implementation is important to evaluate the impact of increasing freshwater flows to Florida Bay and the southwest coast. Although nutrient data is currently being collected by the USGS and by the Florida International University (FIU) Long-Term Ecosystem (LTER) program from several tidal creeks along the costal region of the Everglades National Park, this network has yet to produce nutrient loads into Florida Bay and the southwest coast. At present the USGS operates 30 flow stations of which only three stations currently collect continuous nutrient data (auto-samplers). The water-quality network operated by FIU in this same coastal region of the Everglades (along Taylor Creek and Shark River) consists of about 16 nutrient auto-samplers. However, none of the FIU stations collect flow data from which coastal nutrient loads could be computed. The USGS is currently contemplating expanding and improving the existing coastal nutrient network (1) by combining the water-quality data being collected by FIU with flow data being collected in nearby flow stations operated by the USGS and (2) by adding water-quality sampling sites at existing coastal discharge monitoring stations which will allow computation of nutrient loading from freshwater wetlands to the mangrove coastline.

The study provides a review and analysis of historical water-quality data in BCNP, ENP, and LNWR (Phase 1) and nearby coastal waters of south Florida (Phase 2). This information will help establish water-quality standards and baseline conditions in the parks, and will help evaluate the potential effects of CERP on water quality.
</purpose>
         <supplinf>This project is Phase 2 of Analysis of Historic Water Quality Data.  The data used in this synthesis project can be found at http://sofia.usgs.gov/exchange/rmiller/</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>1959</begdate>
               <enddate>2000</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-81.5</westbc>
            <eastbc>-80.5</eastbc>
            <northbc>26.375</northbc>
            <southbc>25.25</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>water quality</themekey>
            <themekey>flow</themekey>
            <themekey>nutrients</themekey>
            <themekey>hydrology</themekey>
            <themekey>chemistry</themekey>
            <themekey>synthesis</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>environment</themekey>
            <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
            <themekey>007</themekey>
            <themekey>012</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1995, Countries, Dependencies, Areas of Special Sovereignty, and Their Principal Administrative Divisions,  Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS) 10-4, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>US</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>U.S. Department of Commerce, 1987, Codes for the identification of the States, the District of Columbia and the outlying areas of the United States, and associated areas (Federal Information Processing Standard 5-2): Washington, DC, NIST</placekt>
            <placekey>Florida</placekey>
            <placekey>FL</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1990, Counties and Equivalent Entities of the United States, Its Possessions, and Associated Areas, FIPS 6-3, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>Broward County</placekey>
            <placekey>Collier County</placekey>
            <placekey>Miami-Dade County</placekey>
            <placekey>Monroe County</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>USGS Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
            <placekey>Everglades National Park</placekey>
            <placekey>Big Cypress National Preserve</placekey>
            <placekey>Shark River Slough</placekey>
            <placekey>Taylor Slough</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Central Everglades</placekey>
            <placekey>SW Big Cypress</placekey>
            <placekey>Water Conservation Area 3A</placekey>
            <placekey>WCA3A</placekey>
            <placekey>ENP</placekey>
            <placekey>BCNP</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Arturo Torres</cntper>
               <cntorg>U. S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>
USGS Florida Integrated Science Center; FISC-Tampa

10500 University Center Drive, Suite 215
</address>
               <city>Tampa</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33612</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>
813 975-8620 ext 128 office

813 215-4500 cell
</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>aetorres@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://sofia.usgs.gov/publications/wri/03-4249/images/figure1.gif</browsen>
         <browsed>map showing Big Cypress National Preserve and Everglades National Park and major features and sampling sites</browsed>
         <browset>GIF</browset>
      </browse>
      <datacred>Project personnel included Ronald Miller, Mark Zucker, and Paul Conrads</datacred>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Miller, Ronald L.

McPherson, Benjamin F.;
Sobczak, Robert;
Clark, Christine
</origin>
            <pubdate>2004</pubdate>
            <title>Water Quality in Big Cypress National Preserve and Everglades National Park - Trends and Spatial Characteristics of Selected Constituents</title>
            <geoform>publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Water Resources Investigations Report</sername>
               <issue>03-4249</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Tallahassee, FL</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>accessed as of 6/22/2011</othercit>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/publications/wri/03-4249/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Duever, M. J.

Carlson, J. E.;
Meeder, J. F.;
Duever, L. C.;
Gunderson, L. H.;
Riopelle, L. A.;
Alexander, T. R.;
Myers, R. F.;
Spangler, D. P.
</origin>
            <pubdate>1979</pubdate>
            <title>Resource inventory and analysis of the Big Cypress National Preserve</title>
            <geoform>publication</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Naples, FL</pubplace>
               <publish>Center for Wetlands, UF-Gainesville and National Audabon Society</publish>
            </pubinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>McPherson, B. F.</origin>
            <pubdate>1970</pubdate>
            <title>Hydrobiological Characteristics of Shark River Estuary, Everglades National Park, Florida</title>
            <geoform>publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>USGS Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>71-199 (formerly 71002)</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Tallahassee, FL</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>accessed as of 4/20/2011</othercit>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/publications/ofr/71-199/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
McPherson, B. F.

Torres, A. E.
</origin>
            <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
            <title>Freshwater and nutrient fluxes to coastal waters of Everglades National Park - a synthesis</title>
            <geoform>publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>USGS Fact Sheet</sername>
               <issue>2006-3076</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Florida</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>accessed as of 6/22/2011</othercit>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/fs/2006/3076/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
McPherson, B. F.

Miller, R. L.;
Sobczak, R.;
Clark, C.
</origin>
            <pubdate>1997</pubdate>
            <title>Water Quality In Big Cypress National Preserve And Everglades National Park, 1960-2000</title>
            <geoform>publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>USGS Fact Sheet</sername>
               <issue>097-03</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Tallahassee, FL</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>accessed as of 6/22/2011</othercit>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/publications/fs/097-03/index.html</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Klein, H.

Schneider, W. J.;
McPherson, B. F.;
Buchanan, T. J.
</origin>
            <pubdate>1970</pubdate>
            <title>Some hydrologic and biologic aspects of the Big Cypress Swamp draininge area, southern Florida</title>
            <geoform>publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>USGS Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>OFR-70003</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Tallahassee, FL</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>accessed as of 6/27/2011</othercit>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/publications/ofr/70003/index.html</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Klein, H.

Armbruster, J. T.;
McPherson, B. F.;
Freiberger, H. J.
</origin>
            <pubdate>1975</pubdate>
            <title>Water and the south Florida environment</title>
            <geoform>publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>USGS Water-Resources Investigations Report</sername>
               <issue>75-24</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Tallahassee, FL</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Kolipinski, M. C.

Higer, A. L.
</origin>
            <pubdate>1969</pubdate>
            <title>Some aspects of the effects of the quantity and quality of water on biological communities in Everglades National Park</title>
            <geoform>publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>USGS Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>OFR-FL-69007</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Tallahassee, FL</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>accessed as of 6/27/2011</othercit>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/publications/ofr/69-007/index.html</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Kolipinski, M.

Higer, A.;
Morris, M.
</origin>
            <pubdate>1971</pubdate>
            <title>Appraisal of water quality needs and criteria for Everglades National Park</title>
            <geoform>publication</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Washington, D.C.</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>U.S. Geological Survey report prepared for the National Park Service</othercit>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Schertz, T. L.

Alexander, R. B.;
Ohe, D. J.
</origin>
            <pubdate>1991</pubdate>
            <title>The computer program estimate trend (estrend),a system for the detection of trends in water-quality data</title>
            <geoform>publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>USGS Water-Resources Investigations Report</sername>
               <issue>91-4040</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>accessed as of 6/27/2011</othercit>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/wri/wri91-4040/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Slack, J. R.

Lorenz, D. L. and others
</origin>
            <pubdate>2003</pubdate>
            <title>USGS library for S-PLUS for Windows - Release 2.1</title>
            <geoform>publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>USGS Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>2003-357</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>unknown</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>
accessed as of 6/27/2011

web page only
</othercit>
            <onlink>http://water.usgs.gov/software/S-PLUS/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Waller, B. G.</origin>
            <pubdate>1982</pubdate>
            <title>Water-quality characteristics of Everglades National Park 1959-77, with reference to the effects of water management</title>
            <geoform>publication</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>USGS Water-Resources Investigations Report</sername>
               <issue>82-34</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Tallahassee, FL</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>In addition to the water-quality data currently being collected in the park and preserve, other agencies and individuals have collected water-quality data and information over the years. Some of these sources extend coverage of water-quality conditions back into the 1960's and 70's (Duever and others, 1979; Kolipinski and Higer, 1969; Kolipinski and others, 1971; Klein and others, 1970; McPherson, 1970; Klein and others, 1975; Waller, 1982). Some of this earlier information is included in this report to provide the longest record possible for water-quality conditions in BICY and EVER.</logic>
      <complete>unavailable</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
1. Provide baseline water quality and trends in Loxahatchee National Wildlife Refuge

Baseline historic water-quality data in LNWR was assembled, evaluated and made available on SOFIA. An interpretative report that summarizes the historic water-quality data and trends in LNWR is being prepared and will be published in 2005.

2. Assemble and make available metadata and data for flow and water quality that have been collected in tidal rivers of ENP. Include methods of collection and QA for water-quality data, including comparisons of grab samples and auto-samples with cross section and depth data.

The major task is to compile and summarize data on flows and water-quality that have been collected in tidal rivers of ENP by different agencies and universities. Metadata and selected data collected by different agencies and universities over the last 50 years will be summarized and posted into the USGS South Florida Information Access (SOFIA) web site.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>2005</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Data analysis

We used loess (locally weighted scatter-plot smoothing) plots (Slack and others, 2003) to evaluate long-term data and to show the generalized direction of change in concentration with time.Loess smoothing was used for adjusting concentrations for flow or stage changes in order to reduce the normal seasonal changes in concentration due to variations in flow or stage. Without these adjustments, cyclical variations in concentrations due to seasonal or drought-related changes in flow or stage make it difficult to determine if there are real long-term trends in concentration due to other changes within the drainage basin.  Loess smoothing is accomplished by fitting a linear regression for many small parts of the x-axis (horizontal axis) and piecing together a line. The loess regression weights the close (local) data points more than more distant data points, and is similar to a moving average. When viewing plots of data and loess smooth lines, the reader may perceive a trend in concentration that is not statistically significant especially when the statistical programs adjust for severe wet and dry periods.

The uncensored seasonal Kendall test and Tobit regression procedures, provided with the S-ESTREND program, were used to analyze water-quality data for trends. A 95-percent confidence level (p = 0.05) was used for all of the statistical tests. The uncensored seasonal Kendall test requires that a minimum of 5 years of data be available, that censored (less than) data be no more than about 5 percent of the data set, and that there is only one censoring level. In addition, there are requirements for a minimum abundance of data in the first and last fifth of the time span being tested. This test allows water-quality data to be flow or stage adjusted. The uncensored seasonal Kendall test was used to test for trends in specific conductance, chloride, and TN. The uncensored seasonal Kendall test is considered robust; that is, it is not sensitive to outliers in the data (Schertz and others, 1991). The uncensored seasonal Kendall test permits the user to compare only data from the same seasons over the period of record, which reduces the effect of seasonal water-quality changes and improves one's ability to determine long-term trends. Three seasons were used in most cases. Comparisons were made between concentrations in the same seasons in the first year and each following year to count the number of increases and decreases. Then, comparisons were made between concentrations in the same seasons in the second year and each following year, and so on. For each season, a single value was selected for use in the seasonal Kendall test. For seasons with multiple values, the most central value with respect to time, that is also paired with discharge or stage, was selected to represent the season (Schertz and others, 1991). Because of this selection process, some of the data that are visible on a graph and that influence the shape of the loess smooth plots, may not be used by the seasonal Kendall test procedure. Consequently, graphs showing all of the data points over time may appear to show a trend that is not found to be statistically significant using this procedure.

The Tobit regression analysis was used to test for trends in sulfate and TP concentrations. This was necessary because the percentage of censored data was often more than the 5-percent limit suggested for the uncensored seasonal Kendall test, and because the sulfate and TP data sets usually contained more than one censoring level, making the data set unsuitable for the uncensored seasonal Kendall test.

Data requirements for using the S-ESTREND program sometimes prevented the use of the full period of record for statistical analysis. In addition, the S-ESTREND program assumes a monotonic trend (tends to increase, decrease, or have no trend, but not change from an increase to a decrease or vice versa) in concentration, which is not the case for sites where an increase in concentration was followed by a decrease. Consequently, we used loess smooth plots to decide where to break the data sets into shorter periods for trend analysis. Common linear regressions were used to look for trends in stage over time.

Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not constitute endorsement by the U.S. Government
</procdesc>
            <procdate>2002</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Freshwater and nutrient fluxes to Coastal Waters of Everglades National Park

1. Assemble historical water-quality and nutrient data (1995-2003) at two index sites, Shark River and Trout Creek, and evaluate how well these data represent total channel flows (by measuring water quality across the section and at different depths compared with grab samples and auto samples and assigning error bars). Post on SOFIA

2. Prepare and publish a 4-page USGS Fact Sheet that summarizes work that has been done and work that is underway on nutrient loading to coastal waters of ENP.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>2006</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Arturo Torres</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U. S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>
USGS Florida Integrated Science Center; FISC-Tampa

10500 University Center Drive, Suite 215
</address>
                     <city>Tampa</city>
                     <state>FL</state>
                     <postal>33612</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>
813 975-8620 ext 128 office

813 215-4500 cell
</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>aetorres@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20110622</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Heather Henkel</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth Street South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727 803-8747 ext 3028</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727 803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>sofia-metadata@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <metac>none</metac>
      <metuc>This metadata record may have been copied from the SOFIA website and may not be the most recent version.  Please check http://sofia.usgs.gov/metadata to be sure you have the most recent version.</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
