<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Roy Sonenshein</origin>
            <pubdate>Unpublished Material</pubdate>
            <title>SOFIA Environmental Database Development and Maintenance</title>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/projects/sofia/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>
The long-term goal of the SOFIA program is to provide a central archive of data and products for all Department of Interior products related to the south Florida Ecosystem restoration program.

The primary objectives of this project were to 1) provide a central location for the archive of all products and data collected as part of the USGS PES program and related work for the restoration of the South Florida Ecosystem; and 2) provide a means for customers to obtain the archived information. The database was been developed using PostgreSQL, an open source relational database management system. PostgreSQL was selected because it is freely available, widely used, actively maintained and supported, and runs on all modern UNIX-like and Windows based computer systems. As projects were completed or data sets were made available to the public, the data was to be loaded into the database.
</abstract>
         <purpose>
The South Florida restoration effort requires multidisciplinary information relating to present and historical conditions for use in responsible decision-making.  The South Florida Information Access (SOFIA) database is the cornerstone of information management for the South Florida place-based science program.

Responsible resource management requires a firm scientific basis for decision making. The SOFIA database will provide hydrologic, cartographic, geologic, and biologic data and metadata to aid in the decision process. Ecosystem restoration and sound resource management will benefit south Florida by allowing a balance of uses and interests.  The data are available to Federal, State, and local agencies through a web interface and can be retrieved from the SOFIA database. The database has been redesigned to provide storage and access to a greater variety of data types. A new web-based interface will be developed to provide access to the database. The interaction between the database, the other SOFIA products, and other available web-based databases is being evaluated. The database will be updated to provide greater interoperability between the database, other SOFIA products and other web-based databases.
</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>20011001</begdate>
               <enddate>2005</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-82.375</westbc>
            <eastbc>-80</eastbc>
            <northbc>28.5</northbc>
            <southbc>24.5</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>information management</themekey>
            <themekey>database</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>environment</themekey>
            <themekey>007</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1995, Countries, Dependencies, Areas of Special Sovereignty, and Their Principal Administrative Divisions,  Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS) 10-4, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>US</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>U.S. Department of Commerce, 1987, Codes for the identification of the States, the District of Columbia and the outlying areas of the United States, and associated areas (Federal Information Processing Standard 5-2): Washington, DC, NIST</placekt>
            <placekey>Florida</placekey>
            <placekey>FL</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1990, Counties and Equivalent Entities of the United States, Its Possessions, and Associated Areas, FIPS 6-3, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>Broward County</placekey>
            <placekey>Charlotte County</placekey>
            <placekey>Collier County</placekey>
            <placekey>Hendry county</placekey>
            <placekey>Highlands County</placekey>
            <placekey>Lee County</placekey>
            <placekey>Martin County</placekey>
            <placekey>Monroe County</placekey>
            <placekey>Miami-Dade County</placekey>
            <placekey>Okeechobee County</placekey>
            <placekey>Osceola County</placekey>
            <placekey>Palm Beach County</placekey>
            <placekey>Polk County</placekey>
            <placekey>St. Lucie County</placekey>
            <placekey>Indian River  County</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Central Everglades</placekey>
            <placekey>Kissimmee Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Greater Lake Okeechobee</placekey>
            <placekey>Florida Keys</placekey>
            <placekey>South East Coast</placekey>
            <placekey>SW Big Cypress</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>The database is no longer available and further development has been halted</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Roy Sonenshein</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>3110 SW 9th Avenue</address>
               <city>Ft. Lauderdale</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33315</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>954 377-5924</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>sunshine@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://sofia.usgs.gov/aboutsofia.html</browsen>
         <browsed>map showing the location of the study area</browsed>
         <browset>GIF</browset>
      </browse>
      <datacred>Project personnel included Bruce Irvin, Cortney Mills, Tarla Toomer, Tim Boozer, Joann Dixon, and Sandy Womble.</datacred>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>not applicable</logic>
      <complete>not available</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Design, maintenance, and population of the database

1. Update the database structure as needed to handle new types of data that currently do not fit into the database structure.
2. Load new data sets into the database as they become available.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>Not complete</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Collect data and prepare metadata records:

1. Obtain published data sets and other released data sets.
2. Rework data sets if necessary to prepare in the form required to enter into the database.
3. Reformat data as needed to prepare for dissemination on the Data Exchange web site.
4. Prepare metadata records for all data sets to be placed on the Data Exchange.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>Not complete</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Prepare atlas of USGS data collection sites

1. Prepare GIS base maps and standard template to be used for Atlas maps.
2. Design report, deciding on which data sets to include on the maps, and how to organize the maps.
3. Prepare the text to include with each map.
4. Get the report reviewed and published.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>Not complete</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Roy Sonenshein</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>3110 SW 9th Avenue</address>
                     <city>Ft. Lauderdale</city>
                     <state>FL</state>
                     <postal>33315</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>954 377-5924</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>sunshine@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20070309</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Heather Henkel</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth Street South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727 803-8747 ext 3028</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727 803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>sofia-metadata@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
