<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Ann M. Foster, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <origin>Thomas J. Smith III, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <origin>John W. Jones, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <origin>Ursula Garfield, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <origin>Ginger Tiling-Range, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <origin>Paul R. Nelson, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
            <title>Fire, Hydrology and Soils along the Mangrove Ecotone within the Greater Everglades Ecosystem</title>
            <geoform>Maps and Data</geoform>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/projects/index.php?project_url=firehydrosoils_mang</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>
Fire in the south Florida landscape has historically been influential in shaping the ecosystem. The link between hydrology, soil formation, and fire is a critical complex component in the persistence of the biotic components of the Everglades (Smith et al 2003, Beckage 2005). As a result, Everglades National Park has been at the forefront of NPS fire policy development since the inception of the park. It was the first to allow prescribed burns and one of the first to develop a fire management plan (Taylor 1981).

The occurrence of invasive exotic plants has confounded the fire regime in Everglades National Park by changing the dynamics of how the vegetation burns. This phenomenon has been observed in mangrove forests especially along ecotones with upland vegetation communities. By examining the association between fire, soil, water and vegetation we can begin to understand the ecology and dynamics of these areas.
</abstract>
         <purpose>
Project objectives: 
Update Everglades National Park (ENP)/Big Cypress National Preserve (BCNP) fire history geodatabase to 2011 to both expand data available for project analysis and provide increased time-line of data for development and testing of remote sensing methods.
Enhance on-going development and evaluation of remote sensing methods for mapping vegetation characteristics and monitoring vegetation changes with emphasis through this collaborative work on the targeted mangrove - upland ecotone.
Conduct a thorough analysis of the history of fire in ENP and develop relationships between natural fires and aspects of water management.
By using the fire history database we will determine which ecotones have burned more frequently than others.
Relate fire frequency to occurrence of exotic plants along the mangrove-non-mangrove ecotones in ENP.
</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>2010</begdate>
               <enddate>2013</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>In work</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <descgeog>Everglades National Park, Florida, USA</descgeog>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-81.6</westbc>
            <eastbc>-80.1</eastbc>
            <northbc>27.6</northbc>
            <southbc>25.00000</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>Everglades</themekey>
            <themekey>vegetation mapping</themekey>
            <themekey>fire</themekey>
            <themekey>hydrology</themekey>
            <themekey>soil formation</themekey>
            <themekey>invasive species</themekey>
            <themekey>invasive plants</themekey>
            <themekey>mangrove forests</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
            <themekey>Environment</themekey>
            <themekey>Inland waters</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1990, Counties and Equivalent Entities of the United States, Its Possessions, and Associated Areas, FIPS 6-3, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>Lee</placekey>
            <placekey>Collier</placekey>
            <placekey>Hendry</placekey>
            <placekey>Charlotte</placekey>
            <placekey>Glades</placekey>
            <placekey>Monroe</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>U.S. Department of Commerce, 1987, Codes for the identification of the States, the District of Columbia and the outlying areas of the United States, and associated areas (Federal Information Processing Standard 5-2): Washington, DC, NIST</placekt>
            <placekey>Florida</placekey>
            <placekey>FL</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>Cite primary authors and database when using or publishing these data.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Ann M. Foster</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>U.S. Geological Survey, Southeast Ecological Science Center,</address>
               <address>7920 NW 71st Street</address>
               <city>Gainesville</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>32653</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>352.264.3565</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>352.378.4965</cntfax>
            <cntemail>amfoster@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Thomas J. Smith III, Ann M. Foster, Ginger Tiling-Range, and John W. Jones</origin>
            <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
            <title>Dynamics of Mangrove-Marsh Ecotones in Subtropical Coastal Wetlands: Fire, Sea-Level Rise, and Water Levels</title>
            <geoform>journal article</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Fire Ecology</sername>
               <issue>9(1): 66-77</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://fireecology.org/journal/abstract/?abstract=184</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>Unavailable</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Unavailable</logic>
      <complete>All parameters are not available for all sites. See Entity and Attribute Overview description for more detail.</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>No process steps have been described for this data set</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Heather S. Henkel</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth Street South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727-803-8747 x3028</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727-803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>hhenkel@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>The data have no explicit or implied guarantees.</distliab>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20130924</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Heather S. Henkel</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth St. South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727-803-8747 x3028</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727-803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>sofia-metadata@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
