<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Charles W. Holmes (retired)

Debra Willard
</origin>
            <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
            <title>Florida Bay core logs disposition and analysis parameters</title>
            <geoform>spreadsheet</geoform>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/exchange/holmes/holmescores.html</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The data set contains the core number, location, latitude/longitude, date collected, storage location, core surface description, and analyses for cores taken from Rabbitt Key, Cluett Key, Whipray Basin, Bob Allen Key, Rankin Bight, Lake Ingraham, Russell Bank, Johnson Key, Porjoe Key, Trout Creek, Little Madeira Bay, Crocodile Point, Pass Key, and Park Key</abstract>
         <purpose>The use of radioactive isotopes is founded on the known physical property of radioactive material, the half-life. A half-life of an isotope is the amount of time it takes for half of a given number of atoms to "decay" to another element. The age of objects that contain radioactive isotopes with known half-lives can be calculated by determining the percent of the  remaining radioactive material. To use this method successfully certain other prerequisites must be met. These are: 1. the chemistry of the nuclide (element) is known; 2. once the nuclide is incorporated into the substrate the only change is radioactive decay, and 3. in order to be useful, it is relatively easy to measure.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>19940207</begdate>
               <enddate>19970613</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>complete</progress>
         <update>none planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-81.096</westbc>
            <eastbc>-80.4082</eastbc>
            <northbc>25.2091</northbc>
            <southbc>24.9843</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>core location</themekey>
            <themekey>radionuclides</themekey>
            <themekey>radioactive isotopes</themekey>
            <themekey>sediments</themekey>
            <themekey>nutrients</themekey>
            <themekey>surface disturbed zones</themekey>
            <themekey>piston core</themekey>
            <themekey>geology</themekey>
            <themekey>geochemistry</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>environment</themekey>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
            <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
            <themekey>007</themekey>
            <themekey>008</themekey>
            <themekey>012</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1995, Countries, Dependencies, Areas of Special Sovereignty, and Their Principal Administrative Divisions,  Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS) 10-4, Washington, D.C., National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>US</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>U.S. Department of Commerce, 1987, Codes for the identification of the States, the District of Columbia and the outlying areas of the United States, and associated areas (Federal Information Processing Standard 5-2): Washington, D. C., NIST</placekt>
            <placekey>Florida</placekey>
            <placekey>FL</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1990, Counties and Equivalent Entities of the United States, Its Possessions, and Associated Areas, FIPS 6-3, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>Monroe County</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>USGS Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
            <placekey>Bob Allen Key</placekey>
            <placekey>Cluett Key</placekey>
            <placekey>Crocodile Point</placekey>
            <placekey>Florida Bay</placekey>
            <placekey>Johnson Key</placekey>
            <placekey>Lake Ingraham</placekey>
            <placekey>Little Madeira Bay</placekey>
            <placekey>Pass Key</placekey>
            <placekey>Porjoe Key</placekey>
            <placekey>Rabbit Key</placekey>
            <placekey>Rankin Bight</placekey>
            <placekey>Taylor Slough</placekey>
            <placekey>Trout Creek</placekey>
            <placekey>Whipray Basin</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Central Everglades</placekey>
            <placekey>Russell Bank</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>None.  Acknowledgement of the U.S. Geological Survey would be appreciated for products derived from these data.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Debra A Willard</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>926A National Center</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>703 648 5320</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>703 648 6953</cntfax>
            <cntemail>dwillard@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>Marci Margot and Bowdewjn Remick assisted in analysis of the cores.</datacred>
      <native>MS Excel</native>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Holmes, Charles W.

Robbins, John,
Halley, Robert,
Bothner, Michael,
ten Brink, Marilyn,
Marot, Marci
</origin>
            <pubdate>2001</pubdate>
            <title>Sediment dynamics of Florida Bay mud banks on a decadal time scale</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Bulletins of American Paleontology</sername>
               <issue>361</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Ithica, NY</pubplace>
               <publish>Paleontoligical Research Institution</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>
in Paleoecological studies of South Florida

Bruce Wardlaw, editor
</othercit>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>not applicable</logic>
      <complete>Information is provided for all the cores used in the study.  The list was revised 10/29/1997</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>The location of sample sites was established by GPS.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Long cores (&gt;1 m in length), were taken in &gt;30 cm of water through the "moon pool" of a motorized 25 ft pontoon barge either grounded on the bank or anchored with 4 anchors. The location was established by GPS.  A portable 12 ft high tripod was placed over the moon pool to hold the coring piston and for extraction of the core. Cores were taken with 10.8 cm-diameter, clear, FDA food grade polycarbonate tubing. A PVC piston with two O-ring seals was used. The piston was pushed into the bottom of the core tube to a position several cm above the bottom of the tube. A 10 m length of .25 cm diameter braided polypropylene line, attached to a ring threaded into the top of the piston, was pulled through the core tube. The core tube was then carefully lowered through the moon pool and any air trapped in the space between piston and the bottom of the core tube was removed and filled with water.  When the tube was several cm above the bottom, the free end of line attached to the piston was affixed to the head of the tripod. Thus  when the core tube penetrates the sediment, the piston remains in  a fixed position a few cm above the sediment surface producing a vacuum that retards compaction. When the apparatus was set in position, the core tube was quickly thrust about 30 cm into the sediment by hand.  Next, an aluminum clamp with handles was fixed to the core tube and two people then forced the core barrel in until it reached the underlying Pleistocene limestone. Next the clamp with handles was removed and a clamp with lifting rings was attached near the air/water interface. A cable through a pulley at the top of the tripod and attached to a hand winch mounted on one leg of the tripod was attached to the lifting ring on the clamp.  The cable winch was necessary for extraction due to the weight of the core and strong suction created by the mud. Before extraction, the polypropylene line was removed from the tripod and fixed to the extraction clamp. This was to ensure that the piston remained in a fixed position during extraction and to retard loss of sediment from the bottom of the barrel. A benefit of the clear core tubing was that any leakage around the piston's O-ring seal could be readily observed during the extraction process. A person in the water wearing a face mask observed the core tube to be certain no sediment was lost at the sediment/water interface, to record any elevation difference between the sediment surface inside and outside the core at full penetration, and to quickly place a plastic pipe cap on the bottom of the core as it emerged from the sediment. The core was winched above the surface of the moon pool and lowered to rest vertically on deck. The pipe cap was taped tightly to the tube to prevent leakage. Excess tubing was cut off just below the piston using a large pipe cutter so the piston could be carefully removed without disturbing the sediment surface. In some cases the water above the sediment was carefully siphoned off with a tube to prevent sloshing of water during transport to the laboratory which would disturb the sediment surface. In other cases the piston was left in the core tube during transport. All cores were transported vertically. Each evening cores were transported vertically to a local hospital where X-ray photographs were prepared.

The cores were selected for analysis based on the x-rays. Those cores selected for further analysis were selected on the basis of laminations or other features which indicated the lack of disturbance.  The core was placed in an extruding device vertically.  The core was then extruded up into a template and sliced. This slice (hockey puck) was place on a preweighed titanium plate and the wet weight determined. The ring was then removed and the slice was trimmed to remove the outer portion of the core.  This was done to prevent any contamination that may have occurred at the side of the core barrel during the coring operation.  This sample was then bagged and weighed. This weight was found to be important in the determination of water content and thus the dry weight as water was lost during the period of initial sampling and the laboratory analysis. These sample were then stored in a refrigerator and then transhipped to the home based laboratory. For those core selected for trace metal analysis, the slices were sampled from the center of the "hockey puck" with titanium tools and place in an acid washed plastic bottle and frozen.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Debra A Willard</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
                     <address>926A National Center</address>
                     <city>Reston</city>
                     <state>VA</state>
                     <postal>20192</postal>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>703 648 5320</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>703 648 6953</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>dwillard@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <indspref>Florida Bay</indspref>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <latres>0.01</latres>
            <longres>0.01</longres>
            <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
         </geograph>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
            <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.257</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <overview>
         <eaover>The spreadsheet contains the following information: Core No., Location, Latitude, Longitude, Date Collected, Storage Location, Core Surface Description, and Analyses.</eaover>
         <eadetcit>USGS personnel</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Heather S.Henkel</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth St. South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727 803-8747 ext 3028</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727 803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>hhenkel@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>Florida Bay Core Logs Disposition and Analysis Parameters</resdesc>
      <distliab>The data have no implied or explicit guarantees</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>MS Excel</formname>
               <formverd>1997</formverd>
               <transize>0.02</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://sofia.usgs.gov/exchange/holmes/holmescores.html</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>Data may be downloaded from the SOFIA website</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20071031</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Heather Henkel</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth Street South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727 803-8747 ext 3028</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727 803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>sofia-metadata@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
