<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Mark Hansen</origin>
            <pubdate>2005</pubdate>
            <title>Hydrological Data</title>
            <geoform>maps and data</geoform>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/exchange/10000_islands/index.html</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>Hydrological data was collected at 11 sites for the Caloosahatchee Estuary and Estero Bay regions.using two methods, one developed by the USGS and the other developed by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.  Data collected include date and time of collection, stage, discharge, salinity, and water temperature.</abstract>
         <purpose>This project addresses the collection and interpretation of data necessary to develop the present day bathymetry of the lower portions of South Florida including: Estero Bay, Charlotte Harbor, Pine Island Sound, offshore regions of Sanibel and Captiva Islands and the Caloosahatchee, Loxahatchee, and St. Lucie Rivers. In addition, a need for an Estero Bay and Charlotte Harbor estuarine mixing model has been identified by the Southwest Florida Regional Restoration Coordination Team and the Southwest Florida Feasibility Study. In order to create an accurate numerical model, current bathymetric data must be obtained. Bathymetry data is also needed for the creation of a seagrass vision maps (an NEP effort) and to populate the species response models being created as assessment tools for several restoration programs.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>20041021</begdate>
               <enddate>20050606</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-81.59</westbc>
            <eastbc>-81.38</eastbc>
            <northbc>25.96</northbc>
            <southbc>25.89</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>salinity</themekey>
            <themekey>stage</themekey>
            <themekey>discharge</themekey>
            <themekey>chemistry</themekey>
            <themekey>hydrology</themekey>
            <themekey>geography</themekey>
            <themekey>water temperature</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>environment</themekey>
            <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
            <themekey>oceans</themekey>
            <themekey>007</themekey>
            <themekey>012</themekey>
            <themekey>014</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1995, Countries, Dependencies, Areas of Special Sovereignty, and Their Principal Administrative Divisions,  Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS) 10-4, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>US</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>U.S. Department of Commerce, 1987, Codes for the identification of the States, the District of Columbia and the outlying areas of the United States, and associated areas (Federal Information Processing Standard 5-2): Washington, DC, NIST</placekt>
            <placekey>Florida</placekey>
            <placekey>FL</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1990, Counties and Equivalent Entities of the United States, Its Possessions, and Associated Areas, FIPS 6-3, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>Monroe County</placekey>
            <placekey>Collier County</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>USGS Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
            <placekey>Barron River</placekey>
            <placekey>Blackwater River</placekey>
            <placekey>East River</placekey>
            <placekey>Faka Union River</placekey>
            <placekey>Fakahatchee River</placekey>
            <placekey>Ferguson River</placekey>
            <placekey>Little Wood River</placekey>
            <placekey>Palm River</placekey>
            <placekey>Pumpkin River</placekey>
            <placekey>Wood River</placekey>
            <placekey>Whitney River</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Central Everglades</placekey>
            <placekey>SW Big Cypress</placekey>
            <placekey>Southwest coast</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Mark Hansen</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth Street South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727 803-8747 x 3036</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727 803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>mhansen@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <native>text files</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>
Palm River's Index velocity meter came out of the water during low tide. The record for this period was deleted. There was a large volume of data deleted due to the sensor coming out of the water often. We decided to try and estimate the discharge record by using the index velocity meter at Blackwater River. Therefore, the entire period of record of discharge for Palm River is estimated.

All other values are direct measurements
</logic>
      <complete>The data were collected at 15 minute intervals at each site over 3 to 6 month periods</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>GPS was used to establish the location of the sampling sites.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
The plan to acquire bathymetric data for the area is to employ two methods which have been developed by the U. S. Geological Survey (USGS) and National Aeronautical and Space Administration (NASA). The USGS method is an acoustic based system named System for Accurate Nearshore Depth Surveys (SANDS), and the NASA method is an airborne LIDAR system named Experimental Advanced Airborne Research Lidar (EAARL).

The USGS has developed a hydrographic survey system specifically designed to map in very shallow water. The system can acquire data in water depths of ~25cm, but in practice boat/motor draft limitations prevent surveying in water depths less than 45cm. Precise differential GPS receivers are used to measure boat position and dynamic elevation, a survey quality 200 kHz depth sounder acquires water depth measurements, and a motion sensor measures heave, pitch, and roll of the boat. A measurement is collected about every 3m along a survey line. The vertical accuracy of the system is +/- 8cm and +/- 4cm inches horizontally.

EAARL is a new airborne lidar that provides unprecedented capabilities to bays, the nearshore shoreface, benthic habitats, coastal vegetation, and sandy beaches. The EAARL sensor suite includes a rasterscanning- water penetrating full-waveform adaptive lidar, a down-looking color digital camera, a hyperspectral scanner, and an array of precision kinematic GPS receivers which provide for sub-meter georeferencing of each laser and hyper-spectral sample. EAARL has the unique real-time capability to detect, capture, and automatically adapt to each laser return backscatter over a large signal dynamic range and keyed to considerable variations in vertical complexity of the surface target. EAARL limited to water depths greater than 50 cm and can penetrate the water column to approximately 1.5 secchi disk depth. The lidar has a ground footprint of 30cm with vertical and horizontal accuracies equal to the SANDS system. The swath width is 250m which converts to a spatial coverage of approximately 1 laser shot per square meter.

The EAARL system wasa used to map shallow (less than 1.5 secchi depth) and nonturbid areas in Estero Bay and nearshore areas. The SANDS system was used in deeper areas and those which are turbid which include the Caloosahatchee River.

Bathymetric mapping has been done for the following areas: Estero Bay, Charlotte Harbor, Pine Island Sound, offshore regions of Sanibel and Captiva Islands and on the Florida West Coast the Caloosahatchee, Shark, Little Shark, Broad, Harney, Lopez, Chatham, and Turner Rivers. The offshore region between Ft. Myers and Naples, FL will be mapped during FY05.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>2006</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Hydrologic information was collected at the main tributary rivers flowing into the Ten Thousand Islands Aquatic Preserve, including (1) Barron River, (2) Ferguson River/Tide Creek, (3) East River, (4) Fakahatchee River, (5) Faka Union River, (6) Wood River, (7) Little Wood River, (8) Pumpkin River, (9) Whitney River, (10) Blackwater River, and (11) Palm Bay River. The information collected includes time-series data for water level, velocity, salinity, and temperature, for a period not to exceed 3-months. Acoustic Doppler Velocity Meters (ADVM) equipped with an up-looking transducer were installed to facilitate the collection of water stage and velocity with one single instrument. ADCP discharge measurements were made for the development of Index-Velocity calibration ratings at all instrumented sites. ADCP measurement sessions thru tide were made to capture the tidal characteristics of these rivers, and used for rating development. Discharge was computed for the 3-month period for all stations, and analyzed to describe tidal magnitudes that include possible variations due to meteorological events, such as rain and wind. Priorities for bathymetric and hydrologic information needs were set by the comparison of these tidal magnitudes at all measured rivers. In turn, hydrodynamic modelers can use these data to calibrate and verify models describing flow patterns throughout the study area. The study area encompasses the estuarine regions from Everglades City to Goodland.</procdesc>
            <procdate>2006</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Mark Hansen</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>600 Fourth Street South</address>
                     <city>St. Petersburg</city>
                     <state>FL</state>
                     <postal>33701</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>727 803-8747 x 3036</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>727 803-2030</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>mhansen@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <indspref>southwest coast of Florida</indspref>
      <direct>Point</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>11</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <latres>1</latres>
            <longres>1</longres>
            <geogunit>Degrees, minutes, and decimal seconds</geogunit>
         </geograph>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
            <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.257</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <overview>
         <eaover>Hydrological data collected for each site includes stage, discharge, salinity, and temperature</eaover>
         <eadetcit>USGS personnel</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Heather S. Henkel</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth St. South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727 803-8747 ext 3028</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727 803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>hhenkel@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>Hydrological Data</resdesc>
      <distliab>The data have no explicit or implied guarantees.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ASCII</formname>
               <formcont>each file contains data for a site</formcont>
               <transize>0.9</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://sofia.usgs.gov/exchange/10000_islands/index.html</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>The data may be downloaded from the SOFIA website</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20110606</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Heather Henkel</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth Street South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727 803-8747 ext 3028</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727 803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>sofia-metadata@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <metac>none</metac>
      <metuc>This metadata record may have been copied from the SOFIA website and may not be the most recent version.  Please check http://sofia.usgs.gov/metadata to be sure you have the most recent version.</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
