<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Arturo Torres

G. Ronnie Best
</origin>
            <pubdate>Unpublished Material</pubdate>
            <title>CERP/RECOVER restoration technology transfer: USGS-CERP liaison with SFWMD</title>
            <geoform>unknown</geoform>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/projects/index.php?project_url=rtt_sfwmd</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This management and coordination effort supports several of the initiatives listed in the DOI science plan.  The USGS representative will participate in CERP and RECOVER meetings and share information with USGS Priority Ecosystem Science (PES) staff, represent USGS in the SFWMD Biscayne Bay work group meetings, and assist DOI partners with obtaining and using USGS technical data and information on the Greater Everglades area.</abstract>
         <purpose>This project includes support of Comprehensive Everglades Restoration Plan/REstoration COordination and VERification (CERP/RECOVER), assistance with Greater Everglades Priority Ecosystem Science coordination, and USGS liaison with the South Florida Water Management District.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>20051001</begdate>
               <enddate>Unknown</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>In Work</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-82.5</westbc>
            <eastbc>-80</eastbc>
            <northbc>28.6</northbc>
            <southbc>24.5</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>technology transfer</themekey>
            <themekey>information management</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>environment</themekey>
            <themekey>007</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1995, Countries, Dependencies, Areas of Special Sovereignty, and Their Principal Administrative Divisions,  Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS) 10-4, Washington, D.C., National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>US</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>U.S. Department of Commerce, 1987, Codes for the identification of the States, the District of Columbia and the outlying areas of the United States, and associated areas (Federal Information Processing Standard 5-2): Washington, D. C., NIST</placekt>
            <placekey>Florida</placekey>
            <placekey>FL</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1990, Counties and Equivalent Entities of the United States, Its Possessions, and Associated Areas, FIPS 6-3, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>Broward County</placekey>
            <placekey>Collier County</placekey>
            <placekey>Miami-Dade County</placekey>
            <placekey>Monroe County</placekey>
            <placekey>Palm Beach County</placekey>
            <placekey>Martin County</placekey>
            <placekey>Okeechobee County</placekey>
            <placekey>Highlands County</placekey>
            <placekey>Osceola County</placekey>
            <placekey>Glades County</placekey>
            <placekey>Charlotte County</placekey>
            <placekey>St. Lucie County</placekey>
            <placekey>Hendry County</placekey>
            <placekey>Polk County</placekey>
            <placekey>Orange County</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Kissimmee Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Greater Lake Okeechobee</placekey>
            <placekey>Central Everglades</placekey>
            <placekey>South East Coast</placekey>
            <placekey>SW Big Cypress</placekey>
            <placekey>Florida Keys</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Arturo Torres</cntper>
               <cntorg>U. S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>
USGS Florida Integrated Science Center; FISC-Tampa

10500 University Center Drive, Suite 215
</address>
               <city>Tampa</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33612</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>
813 975-8620 ext 128 office

813 215-4500 cell
</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>aetorres@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>not applicable</logic>
      <complete>not applicable</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Work planned for FY 2006

A. USGS Participation in CERP PDT and RECOVER Meetings

The Principal Investigator (PI) participates in Everglades restoration work groups and committees in support of the Comprehensive Everglades Restoration Plan (CERP):
1. CERP Regional Central and Southern project delivery teams (RPDTs)
2. CERP Interagency Modeling Center (IMC)
a. Oversees the role of the USGS/JEM Lab at the IMC
b. Represents the USGS and participates in meetings at the IMC
3. CERP RECOVER Teams and sub teams including
a.  Assessment Team
1.  Monitoring and Assessment Plan (MAP) Financial Sustainability sub team
2.  Implementation team - coordinates USGS PIs initial input on the yearly requests for project ideas (topics forms)
3.  MAP Greater Everglades wetlands module group
b.  Evaluation Team
RECOVER/Projects liaisons sub team
4. Participates in workshops to integrate science towards specific DOI, CERP &amp;/or RECOVER science needs.

Work includes:
1. Sharing information on all CERP meetings attended with GE PES and other USGS staff as appropriate.
2. Coordinating USGS PIs initial input on the yearly requests for project ideas (topics forms).
3. Representing the USGS in the CERP Interagency Modeling Center housed in the South Florida Water Management District. Helps coordinate work of the USGS/Joint Ecological Modeling Laboratory (JEM Lab). Ensures technology transfer and science synthesis of USGS studies/products at the IMC. Provides progress activity reports to IMC managers on work/tasks being completed by the USGS/JEM Lab. Participates in IMC meetings including the weekly modeling service requests meetings and IMC board meetings when requested.

B. Work with DOI, SFWMD and other Restoration Partners to Ensure Technology Transfer and Science Synthesis.

The PI represents the USGS in the SFWMD Biscayne Bay science coordination work group meetings. Provides technical information to DOI partners managing and conducting work on Biscayne Bay. Ensures technology transfer and science synthesis of USGS studies/products at this Biscayne Bay work group and assists technology transfer and science synthesis of USGS studies/products within the Greater Everglades area.

Work includes:
1. Preparing and updating summary listing of USGS completed and current studies in Biscayne Bay. By September 2006, will compile and help post into SOFIA other work being conducted by federal and state partners on Biscayne Bay (request made by Richard Curry - Biscayne Bay National Park).
2. Assisting GE PES coordinator in providing GE PES sponsored products on the Greater Everglades (summary reports, fact sheets, publications, etc.) to DOI partners as these become available.

C. Provide DOI-specific immediate response for critical information needs.

1. Participates on DOI science meetings related to the restoration of the south Florida environment. Assist GE PES coordinator and DOI partners in providing technical information and products within the context of Everglades restoration.
2. As requested, participates on weekly DOI restoration science meetings. Provides assistance in the preparation of tables (science needs and funding) in support of the DOI restoration science needs coordination effort.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>Not complete</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Assists with GE PES coordination

1.  Coordinates, review, edits, and compiles yearly progress reports (Summary Reports) from principal investigators (PIs).
2. Coordinates, review, edits, and compiles yearly work plans and project budget tables from principal investigators (PIs).
3. Provides administrative support to GE PES coordinator (Ronnie Best) including support during the budgeting process, production of Green Book report, meetings with DOI partners.
4. Participates in DOI Everglades restoration science coordination meetings
5. Responds and provides follow ups to requests from GE PES PIs and SOFIA staff on all type of project needs (information, coordination, revisions to project budget tables, data, agency contacts, proposal development, etc.)
6. Reviews reports from DOI agencies, CERP documents
7. Represents USGS and GE PES at CERP IMC

Work includes:
1. Requests summary reports for activities conducted in FY06 from PIs in August 2006 and will be posted into SOFIA by September 30, 2006
2. Requests work plans and budget tables from PIs in September 2006 and reviewed by October 2006.
3. Completes entries into the Green Book by September 2006.
4. Participates and provides assistance on DOI Everglades restoration science coordination meetings as requested.
5. Provides follow ups and immediate assistance to GE PES PIs during the preparation of the summary reports and work plans. Provides immediate assistance to SOFIA staff on all type of project needs and requests on (a) summary reports and work plans, (b) coordination with PIs, (c) revisions to projects budget tables, data, metadata, and (d) agency contacts.
6. Coordinates USGS review comments on the SFWMD annual environmental report.
7. Represents USGS and GE PES at CERP IMC meetings. Provides assistance to the USGS/JEM Lab consortium by coordinating the interaction of USGS staff (including modelers) with IMC technical staff. Oversees progress and activities of the USGS JEM Lab at IMC.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>Not complete</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
USGS liaison with SFWMD

1.  Participates in program development meetings. Develops USGS proposals and statements of work
2. Coordinates USGS/SFWMD annual meetings, quarterly meetings and other meetings related to the Federal-Cooperative program or any other USGS programs
3. Provides follow ups to requests made by SFWMD staff and USGS staff, including follow up to invoices and billings, status of USGS reports, data requests.
4. Address and responds to technical and administrative issues between the SFWMD and USGS. Represents coop projects during SFWMD meetings
5. Participates in project reviews and staff meetings conducted separately or jointly by the USGS and SFWMD
6. Represents USGS at meetings with SFWMD
7. Distributes USGS publications (hard copies and electronic links) among SFWMD staff, and CERP staff housed in the SFWMD
8. Keeps track of progress made, technical issues, deliverable schedules or any problems on all agreements/contracts/projects between the USGS and SFWMD, including projects awarded to USGS contractors.
9. Reviews draft reports (Fact Sheets, Open-File reports, and Scientific Investigation reports) submitted to SFWMD by USGS.
10. Coordinates proposals, statement of works, and projects requested by SFWMD staff to USGS.
11. Coordinates and provides follow ups to USGS projects funded by SFWMD (e.g., USGS DOQ contract, Wading Bird SFR USGS contract with University of Georgia, WQ module to RSM, Biscayne Bay integrated surface/ground water model)
12. Coordinates annual field trip to Everglades and south Florida by students and professors from the University of South Florida

Work includes:
1. During FY06, coordinates a series of USGS/SFWMD technical exchange meetings. Topics planned during 2006 include, but are not limited to:
1. Saltwater Intrusion issues
2. Ecosystem restoration issues
3. ASR and deep injection issues
4. Seepage issues
5. Hydrostratigraphy studies
6. Lake Okechobee issues
7. Water supply issues
2. Continues coordination of meetings between SFWMD Kissimmee Division staff and USGS in the development of a project on 'Geomorphic Monitoring of the Kissimmee River Restoration, South-Central Florida'.
3. Represents the USGS on the Biscayne Bay science coordination work group meetings and coordinates all USGS Biscayne Bay related investigations.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>Not complete</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Arturo Torres</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U. S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>
USGS Florida Integrated Science Center; FISC-Tampa

10500 University Center Drive, Suite 215
</address>
                     <city>Tampa</city>
                     <state>FL</state>
                     <postal>33612</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>
813 975-8620 ext 128 office

813 215-4500 cell
</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>aetorres@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20090630</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Heather Henkel</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth Street South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727 803-8747 ext 3028</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727 803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>sofia-metadata@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <metac>none</metac>
      <metuc>This metadata record may have been copied from the SOFIA website and may not be the most recent version.  Please check http://sofia.usgs.gov/metadata to be sure you have the most recent version.</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
