<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata xmlns="http://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/csdgm"
          xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/metadata/usgswrd/fgdc-std-001-1998.xsd">
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Joel Galloway, Ghaith Hamade, Gregory Jarrell</origin>
            <pubdate>2000</pubdate>
            <title>Potentiometric surface contours for the Inyan Kara aquifer, Black Hills area, South Dakota </title>
            <edition>Version 1.0, April 18, 2000</edition>
            <geoform>map</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>USGS Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>USGS OFR00-471</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://water.usgs.gov/lookup/getspatial?ofr00471_inkrpcon</onlink>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Michael Strobel, Joel Galloway, Ghaith Hamade,
Greg Jarrell
						</origin>
                  <pubdate>2000</pubdate>
                  <title>Potentiometric surface of the Inyan Kara
aquifer, Black Hills area, South Dakota.
						</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>Hydrologic Investigations Atlas</sername>
                     <issue>HA-745-A</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Rapid City, SD</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This data set represents potentiometric surface contours for
the Inyan Kara aquifer, Black Hills, South Dakota.
			</abstract>
         <purpose>This data set was created as part of the Black Hills Hydrology
Study (BHHS). The BHHS is a long-term investigation that was
initiated in 1990 as a cooperative effort between the
U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), the South Dakota Department of
Environment and Natural Resources (DENR), and the West Dakota
Water Development District. West Dakota represents various
local and county cooperators. The purpose of the study is to
assess the quantity, quality, and distribution of surface and
ground water in the Black Hills area of western South Dakota
(Driscoll, 1992). The study area includes parts of Butte,
Custer, Fall River, Lawrence, Meade, and Pennington counties
in South Dakota.
			</purpose>
         <supplinf>Reviews_Applied_to_Data:
This electronic report was subjected to the same review
standard that applies to all U.S. Geological Survey
reports. Reviewers were asked to check the topological
consistency, tolerances, attribute frequencies and statistics,
projection, and geographic extent. The reviewers checked the
metadata and a_readme.1st files for completeness and accuracy.
Related_Spatial_and_Tabular_Data_Sets:
Potentiometric contours for the Deadwood, Madison,
Minnelusa, and Minnekahta aquifers (ddwdpcon, mdsnpcon,
mnlspcon, mnktpcon) and data set of wells with water-level
information (inkrpwpt) for the Minnekahta aquifer. Digital
data set of spring locations in the Black Hills area
(spngppt). Also, surficial hydrogeology in the Black Hills
study area (hydrogeo).

Other_References_Cited:

&gt;Driscoll, D.G., 1992, Plan of study for the Black Hills Hydrology
&gt;  Study, South Dakota: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 92-84,
&gt;  10 p.

Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes
only and does not imply endorsement by the
U.S. Government.

Although this Federal Geographic Data Committee-compliant metadata
file is intended to document the data set in nonproprietary form,
as well as in ARC/INFO format, this metadata file may include some
ARC/INFO-specific terminology.
			</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>19980730</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>The contours were drawn with information on elevation,
geologic outcrops, geologic structure, and water levels from
wells drilled as of 1998.
			</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-104.07846864</westbc>
            <eastbc>-103.00801418</eastbc>
            <northbc>44.78117334</northbc>
            <southbc>43.19160721</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>potentiometric</themekey>
            <themekey>water level</themekey>
            <themekey>contour</themekey>
            <themekey>hydrology</themekey>
            <themekey>ground water</themekey>
            <themekey>Inyan Kara aquifer</themekey>
            <themekey>Inyan Kara Group</themekey>
            <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>None</placekt>
            <placekey>Black Hills</placekey>
            <placekey>South Dakota</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>These data should not be used at scales larger than 1:100,000 scale.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Joel Galloway</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Hydrologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>1608 Mt. View Rd.</address>
               <city>Rapid City</city>
               <state>South Dakota</state>
               <postal>57702</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(605) 355-4523</cntfax>
            <cntemail>(jgallowa@usgs.gov)</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>Compilation of this data set and the associated
metadata was funded in cooperation with the South Dakota
Department of Environment and Natural Resources and the West
Dakota Water Development District.
		</datacred>
      <native>SunOS, 5.6, sun4u UNIX
ARC/INFO version 8.0.1
		</native>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Joel Galloway, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>2000</pubdate>
            <title>Selected data for wells used in potentiometric-contour maps
of the Inyan Kara aquifer in the Black Hills area, South
Dakota.
				</title>
            <geoform>map</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>USGS open-file report</sername>
               <issue>OFR00-471</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Rapid City, South Dakota</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://water.usgs.gov/lookup/getspatial?ofr00471_inkrpwpt</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Joel Galloway, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>2000</pubdate>
            <title>Selected data for springs used in potentiometric-contour
maps for the Black Hills Hydrology Study in the Black Hills
Area, South Dakota.
				</title>
            <geoform>map</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>USGS open-file report</sername>
               <issue>OFR00-471</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Rapid City, South Dakota</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://water.usgs.gov/lookup/getspatial?ofr00471_spngppt</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Joel Galloway, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>1999</pubdate>
            <title>Selected Hydrogeologic Data for the Inyan Kara, Minnekahta,
Minnelusa, Madison, and Deadwood Aquifers in the Black Hills
Area, South Dakota.
				</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>USGS open-file report</sername>
               <issue>OFR-99-602</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Rapid City, South Dakota</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>none</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>Multiple visual checks were done to verify that the attribute
data was coincident with the original source map.
			</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Chain-node topology present.</logic>
      <complete>This data set consists of potentiometric surface contours for
the Inyan Kara aquifer in the vicinity of the Black Hills, South
Dakota.
		</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>Paper plots at 1:100,000 scale were overlaid on the
original mylar sheet and contour lines were compared.
				</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Joel Galloway, U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
                  <pubdate>unpublished material</pubdate>
                  <title>Potentiometric surface contours for the Inyan Kara
aquifer, Black Hills, South Dakota
						</title>
                  <geoform>map</geoform>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>none</sername>
                     <issue>none</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Rapid City, South Dakota</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>100000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>mylar map</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1998</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition based on well-data as of July 1998.</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>none</srccitea>
            <srccontr>The potentiometric contours were digitized from the
hand-drawn contours on this mylar base map.
				</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>A point coverage representing wells open to the Inyan Kara
aquifer (inkrpwpt) and a point coverage of springs (spngppt)
reselected for those discharging from the Inyan Kara aquifer
were used in plotting water-level information on a mylar
sheet at 1:100,000 scale with a boundary drawn for the Black
Hills study area. This sheet was overlain on a mylar sheet
of equivalent scale with elevation contours, and paper plots
of geologic outcrops and geologic structure for the Inyan
Kara Group. These features and information were used in hand
drawing contours representing water-level elevation.

Water-level information from each well was considered when
drawing the water-level elevation contours. Information from
some wells was considered better than that from others
because of variable accuracy describing location, altitude,
and lithology of the wells. A numeric index was calculated
for each well based on its respective accuracy (see
attribute section in metadata file for data set
"inkrpwpt"). Where wells were clustered, water-level
information from a well with a higher index value was given
more weight in drawing the contour than that from a well
with a lower index value.

The mylar-based contours were then digitized. The coverage
was then built as a line coverage using the Arc/Info BUILD
command. Pseudo nodes were removed using the UNSPLIT NONE
command in Arcedit. Some arcs became jagged after the
UNSPLIT. These arcs were smoothed interactively in
Arcedit. The coverage was then rebuilt. Attribute items were
added to the coverage arc attribute table.

The attribute item INTERP was used to indicate where lines
were to be dashed on the map of potentiometric surface
contours. Dashed lines, represented by an INTERP value of
'Y', indicate that water level was "interpreted" in the
area, and was not known because of lack of measured water
levels. Other line segments, where there was confidence in
water level, were assigned a value of 'N' for the
INTERP attribute item, indicating that water levels for these
contours was not interpreted. These non-interpreted lines
were drawn as solid lines on the map.

An automated method was used to assign values to the
attribute item INTERP based on proximity to a well with a
known water level. Wells with water-level information for
the Inyan Kara aquifer (inkrpwpt) were buffered at
2000 meters, creating polygons of singular and in some cases
overlapping, well buffers. Countour lines within the well
buffers were assigned a value of 'N' to INTERP.

Arc: BUFFER INKR_WELLS INKR_BUF2K # # 2000 # POINT
Arc: IDENTITY INKR_CON INKR_BUF2K INKR_CON2K LINE # JOIN

In Tables:

Enter command: SEL INKR_CON2K.AAT
Enter command: RES INKR_BUF2K# NE 1
Enter command: MOVE 'N' TO INTERP
Enter command: ASEL
Enter command: MOVE 'Y' TO INTERP
Enter command: Q STOP

In some instances where contour lines were close around a
well, the above method assigned values of 'N' to INTERP
where they should be 'Y'. Arcedit was used to change values
of INTERP for these lines back to 'Y', so that they would
appear dashed on the map (water level interpreted).

Attribute items that were joined to the arc attribute table
and were associated with the IDENTITY well buffer coverage
were dropped.

In some instances, very short segments of contour lines
fell within the buffer regions.  Any segment that was less
than 100 meters in length were assigned the INTERP value of the
ajoining segments for consistancy.  UNSPLIT INTERP was then run
on the segments to remove pseudo nodes.
				</procdesc>
            <procdate>19980730</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>First draft of metadata created by gjarrell using
FGDCMETA.AML ver. 1.33 07/15/99 on ARC/INFO data set
/home/student/gja/meta/inkrpcon
				</procdesc>
            <procdate>20000418</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Vector</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>String</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>234</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <gridsys>
               <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
               <utm>
                  <utmzone>13</utmzone>
                  <transmer>
                     <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
                     <longcm>-105.0</longcm>
                     <latprjo>0.0000</latprjo>
                     <feast>500,000</feast>
                     <fnorth>0.0000</fnorth>
                  </transmer>
               </utm>
            </gridsys>
            <planci>
               <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>15.0016002655</absres>
                  <ordres>15.0016002655</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>Meters</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1927</horizdn>
            <ellips>Clarke 1866</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378206.4</semiaxis>
            <denflat>294.98</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <overview>
         <eaover>&gt;
&gt;INKRPCON.AAT:
&gt;
&gt;COLUMN   ITEM NAME        WIDTH OUTPUT  TYPE N.DEC  ALTERNATE NAME
&gt;    1  FNODE#                 4     5     B      -
&gt;    5  TNODE#                 4     5     B      -
&gt;    9  LPOLY#                 4     5     B      -
&gt;   13  RPOLY#                 4     5     B      -
&gt;   17  LENGTH                 4    12     F      3
&gt;   21  INKRPCON#              4     5     B      -
&gt;   25  INKRPCON-ID            4     5     B      -
&gt;   29  INTERP                 1     1     C      -
&gt;   30  ALTITUDE               8     8     I      -
&gt;
&gt;

FNODE# -     Internal number of from-node

TNODE# -     Internal number of to-node

LPOLY# -     Internal number of the left polygon; set to 0 for this
data set because there are no polygons

RPOLY# -     Internal number of the right polygon; set to 0 for this
data set because there are no polygons

LENGTH -     Length of arc in meters

INKRPCON# -  Internal sequence number (i.e. the record number) of the
arc in the ARC file

INKRPCON-ID- User-assigned feature ID

INTERP-      Item used for drawing solid and dashed contour lines.
A value if 'Y' indicates that some interpretation
was involved in drawing the contour line. A value of
'N' indicates that the contour line was drawn using
water level information from a nearby well(s).

ALTITUDE-    Altitude of water level, in feet
			</eaover>
         <eadetcit>none</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Ask USGS - Water Webserver Team</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing</addrtype>
               <address>445 National Center</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747 (1-888-ASK-USGS)</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>http://answers.usgs.gov/cgi-bin/gsanswers?pemail=h2oteam&amp;subject=GIS+Dataset+ofr00471_inkrpcon</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although this data set has been used by the U.S. Geological
Survey, U.S. Department of the Interior, no warranty expressed or
implied is made by the U.S. Geological Survey as to the accuracy
of the data and related materials. The act of distribution shall not 
constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumed by 
the U.S. Geological Survey in the use of this data, software, or 
related materials.

Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive
purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S.
Government.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Export</formname>
               <formcont>Full coverage</formcont>
               <transize>1</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/dsdl/ofr00471_inkrpcon.e00</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Export</formname>
               <formcont>Full coverage</formcont>
               <transize>1</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/dsdl/ofr00471_inkrpcon.e00.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>SDTS</formname>
               <formcont>Full coverage</formcont>
               <filedec>zipped</filedec>
               <transize>1</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/dsdl/ofr00471_inkrpcon.tgz</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Other</formname>
               <formcont>Full coverage</formcont>
               <filedec>zipped</filedec>
               <transize>1</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/dsdl/ofr00-471_inkrpcon_shp.tgz</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None. This dataset is provided by USGS as a public service.</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20041108</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Ask USGS -- Water Webserver Team</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing</addrtype>
               <address>445 National Center</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747 (1-888-ASK-USGS)</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>http://answers.usgs.gov/cgi-bin/gsanswers?pemail=h2oteam&amp;subject=GIS+Dataset+ofr00471_inkrpcon</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
