<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Biewick, Laura R.H.</origin>
            <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
            <title>Oil and Gas Exploration and Production in the State of Illinois Shown as Quarter-Mile Cells</title>
            <geoform>Downloadable GIS Data</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <publish>U. S. Geological Survey</publish>
               <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
            </pubinfo>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Biewick, Laura R.H.</origin>
                  <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                  <title>Areas of Historical Oil and Gas Exploration and Production in the United States</title>
                  <geoform>Digital Maps</geoform>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Digital Data Series</sername>
                     <issue>DDS-069-Q</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/dds/dds-069/dds-069-q/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
            <onlink>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/data/noga00/natl/spatial/geodatabase/uscells06gg.zip</onlink>
            <onlink>http://energy.cr.usgs.gov/oilgas/noga/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>A cells polygon feature class was created by the U. S. Geological Survey (USGS) to illustrate the degree of exploration, type of production, and distribution of production in the State of Illinois.  Each cell represents a quarter-mile square of the land surface, and the cells are coded to represent whether the wells included within the cell are predominantly oil-producing, gas-producing, both oil and gas-producing, or the type of production of the wells located within the cell is unknown or dry.  Data were retrieved from the Illinois State Geological Survey (ISGS) oil and gas wells database.  Cells were developed as a graphic solution to overcome the problem of displaying proprietary well data.  No proprietary data are displayed or included in the cell maps.  The data are current as of 2006.</abstract>
         <purpose>This Geographic Information System (GIS) dataset was created to display present and past oil and gas production in the United States, as well as the location and intensity of exploratory drilling outside producing areas.  This map compilation is an updated version of the USGS map that was published by Mast and others (1998). This product differs from other oil and gas maps of the United States in the following ways:  (1) the oil and gas data sources are current as of 2004 through 2006,  (2) base cartographic reference data are included, using the USGS National Map and a World Shaded Relief map service from the ESRI geography network,  (3) an internet map service is available online,  (4) Alaska oil and gas data are included.
			
To construct this map, digital data were used from more than 3 million wells in IHS Inc.'s PI/Dwights PLUS Well Data on CD-ROM, current through 10/1/2005.  In some areas, the PI/Dwights data tend not to be complete, particularly for pre-1920 production. IHS data was supplemented with state wells databases for Indiana, Pennsylvania, Kentucky, Illinois, and Ohio, (current as of 2004 to 2006).</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>2006</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>data retrieval date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>
-91.446530</westbc>
            <eastbc>
-87.494399</eastbc>
            <northbc>
42.510489</northbc>
            <southbc>
37.040746</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>Gateway to the Earth draft 9 28-Jun-2002</themekt>
            <themekey>Natural gas resources</themekey>
            <themekey>Oil shale resources</themekey>
            <themekey>Oil sand resources</themekey>
            <themekey>Coalbed methane resources</themekey>
            <themekey>Economic geology</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ArcIMS Metadata Server Theme Codes</themekt>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
            <themekey>economy</themekey>
            <themekey>environment</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>USGS Energy Program Themes Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>Impacts of Energy Production</themekey>
            <themekey>Coalbed Methane</themekey>
            <themekey>Sedimentary Basin</themekey>
            <themekey>Oil and Natural Gas</themekey>
            <themekey>Energy Resources</themekey>
            <themekey>Earth Science</themekey>
            <themekey>Natural Resources</themekey>
            <themekey>U.S. Geological Survey</themekey>
            <themekey>USGS</themekey>
            <themekey>Geology</themekey>
            <themekey>Natural Gas</themekey>
            <themekey>Petroleum</themekey>
            <themekey>Oil</themekey>
            <themekey>Gas</themekey>
            <themekey>Oil and Gas Exploration</themekey>
            <themekey>Oil and Gas Production</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>None</placekt>
            <placekey>U.S.</placekey>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>North America</placekey>
            <placekey>Illinois</placekey>
            <placekey>IL</placekey>
         </place>
         <theme>
            <themekt>EnergyResourceActivities</themekt>
            <themekey>OilGas</themekey>
            <themekey>HistoricalProduction</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>This database should not be distributed in whole or in part without acknowledgement of the Illinois State Geological Survey and the U.S. Geological Survey.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Central Energy Resources Team</cntorg>
               <cntper>Laura R.H. Biewick</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Geologist / GIS Coordinator</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>U.S. Geological Survey, Box 25046, MS 939, Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>303-236-7773</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>datamgt@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/data/noga00/natl/graphic/ilcells06g.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Thumbnail view of Illinois State oil and gas cells</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.1.0.722</native>
      <datacred>To aggregate well data into quarter-mile cells, oil and gas well data were run through an Arc Macro Language (AML) program written by L.R.H. Biewick, S. Weiler, and C.C. Skinner.</datacred>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>The cell locations and cell attributes were visually compared to the hard-copy map:  Mast, R.F., Root, D.H., Williams, L.P., Beeman, W.R., and Barnett, D.L., 1998, Areas of historical oil and gas exploration and production in the conterminous United States: U.S. Geological Survey Oil and Gas Investigations Map I-2582, 1 sheet; http://energy.cr.usgs.gov/oilgas/noga/oilgasmap.htm and http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/1995/ofr-95-0075-c/</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>The accuracy of the cells, as created by the Arc Macro Language (AML) program of L.R.H. Biewick, S. Weiler and C.C. Skinner, depends upon the accuracy of the locatable oil and gas wells GIS data layer from the Illinois State Geological Survey. For the USGS map compilation showing Areas of Historical Oil and Gas Exploration and Production in the United States, the assumption was made that the data from the Illinois State Geological Survey were of sufficient accuracy for such a national-scale analysis.</logic>
      <complete>The cells were defined using the 2006 well data in the Illinois State Geological Survey (ISGS) oil and gas wells GIS data set.  The information is based on well data supplied to the Illinois State Geological Survey (ISGS) and is not field verified.  The ISGS does not guarantee the validity, accuracy, and completeness of this data.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>A visual comparison was made using a sampling of cell locations and cell attributes with well locations and attributes. The horizontal positional accuracy of the Illinois oil and gas well locations is based on well data supplied to the Illinois State Geological Survey (ISGS) and is not field verified.  The ISGS does not guarantee the validity, accuracy, and completeness of this data.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
         <vertacc>
            <vertaccr>Not applicable.</vertaccr>
         </vertacc>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Illinois State Geological Survey (ISGS)</origin>
                  <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
                  <title>Illinois State Oil and Gas Wells Database</title>
                  <geoform>tabular data</geoform>
                  <onlink>http://www.isgs.uiuc.edu/sections/oil-gas/launchims.shtml</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>comma-delimited file</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>20060316</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>date file downloaded and made available via ftp</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>ISGS</srccitea>
            <srccontr>There are 192,310 records of all types of Oil &amp; Gas wells in this file (isgshead.txt).  

This file has the following items:

API number
LAM_X
LAM_Y
Latitude
Longitude
Status
</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The Illinois State Geological Survey (ISGS) created a comma-delimited file that they made available for download at their ftp site (03/16/06).  There are 192,310 records of oil and gas wells in this file (isgshead.txt).  3/20/06  the file was exported from Microsoft Excel to a .csv file that was imported into ArcMap and saved as a shapefile.  The shapefile was converted to a coverage and run through an Arc Macro Language (AML) program written by L.R.H. Biewick, S. Weiler, and C.C. Skinner. This program aggregated and converted the 2006 Illinois oil and gas well data into quarter-mile cells and latitude-longitude points that represent the center-points of the quarter-mile cells. The Illinois cells were then assigned an attribute based on the type of production of the wells located within the cell.</procdesc>
            <procdate>200603</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Vector</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>G-polygon</sdtstype>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <latres>0.000001</latres>
            <longres>0.000001</longres>
            <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
         </geograph>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
            <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.257222</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>
ilcells06g</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Polygon attribute table</enttypd>
            <enttypds>U.S. Geological Survey</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>CC83XCOORD</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Center-cell X-coordinate</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>-91.446530</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>-87.494399</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>decimal degrees</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>CC83YCOORD</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Center-cell Y-coordinate</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>37.040746</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>42.510489</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>decimal degrees</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>CELLSYMB</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Production Status</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Cell contains at least one productive oil well, but no productive gas wells (green).</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
               </edom>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Cell contains at least one productive gas well, but no productive oil wells (red).</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
               </edom>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Cell contains at least one productive oil well and at least one productive gas well or one well producing both oil and gas (gold).</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
               </edom>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>4</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The type of production of the wells located within the cell is unknown, or the wells within the cell had no production (charcoal).</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Information Services</address>
               <address>Box 25286 Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-888-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>303-202-4693</cntfax>
            <cntemail>ask@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <cntinst>The dataset is available at the Energy Program website - http://energy.usgs.gov/</cntinst>
            <cntvoice>303-202-4700</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>datamgt@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  The U.S. Geological survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.  Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items for other than personal use must be secured from the copyright owner.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Shapefile</formname>
               <formcont>Oil and gas quarter-mile cell geographic features and attribute data</formcont>
               <filedec>unzip</filedec>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/data/noga00/natl/spatial/shape/ilcells06g.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>The URL above links to a zipped file containing oil and gas cells for the State of Illinois.</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ArcInfo Export File</formname>
               <formcont>Oil and gas quarter-mile cell geographic features and attribute data</formcont>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/data/noga00/natl/spatial/export/ilcells06ge.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>The URL above links to a zipped file containing oil and gas cells for the State of Illinois.</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Image Map Service (US_Production)</formname>
               <formvern>9x</formvern>
               <formspec>ArcIMS Image Map Service</formspec>
               <formcont>A web-based interactive mapping system that accesses an ArcIMS Map Service running on certmapper.cr.usgs.gov.</formcont>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/pubs/servlet/MapViewerBroker?project=national&amp;Service=US_Production&amp;OVMap=US_overview</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>This URL links to a web-based interactive mapping system that accesses an ArcIMS Image Map Service.  The mapservice can also be accessed using any custom client that adheres to the protocol specified through ArcXML.</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ArcGIS Geodatabase</formname>
               <formvern>9x</formvern>
               <formcont>Contains polygon features depicting oil and gas cells in the State of Illinois</formcont>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/data/noga00/natl/spatial/geodatabase/uscells06gg.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>The URL above links to a zipped file containing oil and gas cells for the U.S. as well as the States of Ohio, Indiana, Illinois, Kentucky and Pennsylvania.</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None</fees>
         <ordering>These products can be downloaded individually using any one of the Network_Resource_Name URLs above. Each of these URLs provide access to various formats of these data.</ordering>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>Send email to datamgt@usgs.gov or call the USGS Central Energy Team main office at 303-236-1644.</custom>
      <techpreq>Requires software that reads GIS data.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20071219</metd>
      <metrd>20071217</metrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Central Energy Resources Team</cntorg>
               <cntper>Laura R.H. Biewick</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Geologist \ GIS Coordinator</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>U.S. Geological Survey, Box 25046, MS 939, Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntemail>datamgt@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <cntinst>For inquiries regarding this document, please include the metadata contact person's name, dataset name, and publication series and number.</cntinst>
            <cntvoice>303-236-7773</cntvoice>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
      <metextns>
         <onlink>http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink>
         <metprof>ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof>
      </metextns>
   </metainfo>
   <Esri>
      <MetaID>{9734F9FA-F438-4BAC-9BDC-A9E692CC803F}</MetaID>
      <CreaDate>20080303</CreaDate>
      <CreaTime>14325100</CreaTime>
      <SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce>
      <PublishedDocID>{CA648F53-9006-4D44-9F57-F48EE39E3C8F}</PublishedDocID>
      <PublishStatus>Published</PublishStatus>
      <ModDate>20100526</ModDate>
      <ModTime>14215500</ModTime>
   </Esri>
   <mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20090428</mdDateSt>
   <USGSErp>
      <SyncDataGov>y</SyncDataGov>
      <FileSystemMetadataPath>\\netapp1\public_data\noga00\natl\spatial\shape\ilcells06g.shp.xml</FileSystemMetadataPath>
      <ReferencingURLs>http://pubs.usgs.gov/dds/dds-069/dds-069-q/text/layer.htm, AU data model</ReferencingURLs>
      <MetadataProblems/>
      <MetadataNotes/>
   </USGSErp>
</metadata>
