<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>USGS, Energy Resources Program</origin>
            <pubdate>2007</pubdate>
            <title>National Coal Resources Data System (NCRDS)</title>
            <geoform>Applications</geoform>
            <serinfo/>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Reston Virginia</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Energy Resources Program</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink/>
            <onlink>http://energy.er.usgs.gov/coal_quality/coal_databases.html</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The U.S. Geological Survey Energy Resources Program has developed coal databases to monitor the location, quantity, and physical and chemical characteristics of U.S. coal and coal-related deposits.  The National Coal Resources Data System (NCRDS) database is an integrated system utilizing commercial software to produce maps, resource calculations, and coal quality location maps.  NCRDS correlates and standardizes coal data from Federal and State agencies, universities, the private sector, and foreign countries. NCRDS is comprised of three major components, of which two are available online:</abstract>
         <purpose>NCRDS Cooperative Agreements provide geologic information that can be used to support energy resource assessments. The following activities meet the requirements for Cooperative Agreements:

    Collection, entry, or validation of stratigraphic coal data, related chemical and priority GIS data such as outcrop, areas of mining, and other relevant societal or environmental energy-related GIS layers
    Compilation of coalbed gas occurrences, gas storage potential, produced gas and water chemical attributes, well completion and production data, and geotechnical data related to coal conversion processes
    Characterization of organic-rich shales (i.e. hydrocarbon-, gas-, kerogen-rich shales), through geophysical or seismic data, and sample collection for generation of thermal maturity data

Progress Reports will be available in Adobe® (.PDF) format. If you do not have Adobe® Acrobat® you can download a free copy of Adobe® Acrobat® Reader® here.
STATE / DESCRIPTIVE PROJECT TITLE

Alabama

Deep Coal Resources of the Pottsville Formation in the Warrior Coal Basin, Alabama

Alaska

Studies of Coal Resource Data for Alaska: North Slope, Cook Inlet, Healy and Matanuska Area Coal Fields

Arkansas

South Arkanses Lignite Assessment – Gulf Coastal Plain Region

Colorado

Collection and Verification of Colorado Coal Quality and Coalbed Methane Data 

Illinois

Management of Illinois Coal Resources Data 

Indiana

Data Collection, Verification, and Encoding for the National Resources Data System

Kentucky

Compiling Kentucky Coal Information for the National Coal Resources Data System (Kentucky Geological Survey) 

Kentucky

Support Services in Petrographic Analysis of Coal and Flyash Studies (University of Kentucky Center for Applied Energy Research) 

Louisiana

Coal Bed Atlas of Louisiana (Louisiana Geological Survey) 

Louisiana

National Coal Resource Data System North Louisiana Carbonaceous Sediments Natural Gas Data Collection and Geological Assessment Program (University of Louisiana at Lafayette)

Mississippi

Inventory of Tertiary Lignites of the Claiborne, Wilcox, and Midway Groups in Mississippi, and Data Collection Related to Shale Gas and Coal-Bed Methane in Mississippi

Missouri

Entry of Drill Hole Logs from the Thomas Hill Mine in Macon, Randolph, and Chariton Counties into the National Coal Resources Data System and Compilation of Geologica Maps for Portions of Browns and Worland 7.5 Minute USGS Quadrangles

Montana

Compilation and Analysis of Montana Coal Data for Fort Union Region, Bull Mountain Basin and Red Lodge-Big Horn Basin, and Powder River Basin.

New Mexico

Computerization of Point-Source Data and Geographic Information for New Mexico's Coal-Bearing Formations 

North Dakota

Stratigraphic Evaluation and Entry of North Dakota Lignite Data into the National Coal Resources Data System—Southeastern Williston Basin (University of North Dakota)

Ohio

Capture and Entry into the National Coal Resources Data System of Geological Information on Abandoned Underground Mine Maps, Bridge Core Descriptions including Coal Elevation and Thickness, and Ohio Coal Geochemistry

Oklahoma

Oklahoma Coal Resource Appraisal and Computerization through the National Coal Resources Data System

Pennsylvania

National Coal Resources Data System Data Collection, Database Management, and Resource Analysis in Pennsylvania

Tennessee

Compiling and Digitizing Point-Source Coal Stratigraphic Data and Revising Quadrangle-Scale Coal Reserve Estimates for Tennessee Coal

Texas

Texas Gas-Shale Samples for Thermal Maturity Determination

Utah

Preparation of Publicly Available Coal Stratigraphic Database for Utah and New Drill-Hole Data from Deep Utah Coal Deposits 

Virginia

Virginia Energy Resources Studies National Coal Resources Data System Cooperative—Virginia Coal and Gas Resources

West Virginia

Mapping of West Virginia Coal by Quadrangle and Completion of Data Collection for a State-Wide Coal Resource Assessment

Wyoming

Greater Green River Basin Coal and Uranium Occurrence Study </purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>2004</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-126.1</westbc>
            <eastbc>-73.77</eastbc>
            <northbc>53.59</northbc>
            <southbc>25.3</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>Gateway to the Earth draft 9 28-Jun-2002</themekt>
            <themekey>Natural gas resources</themekey>
            <themekey>Economic geology</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ArcIMS Metadata Server Theme Codes</themekt>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
            <themekey>economy</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>Central Energy Resources Team Keyword Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>Energy Resources</themekey>
            <themekey>Earth Science</themekey>
            <themekey>Natural Resources</themekey>
            <themekey>U.S. Geological Survey</themekey>
            <themekey>USGS</themekey>
            <themekey>Geology</themekey>
            <themekey>Coal Quality</themekey>
            <themekey>Coal</themekey>
            <themekey>National Coal Resources Data System</themekey>
            <themekey>NCRDS</themekey>
            <themekey>Stratigraphy</themekey>
            <themekey>Coal Data</themekey>
            <themekey>Downloadable Data</themekey>
            <themekey>Data Access</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>EnergyResourceActivities</themekt>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>None</placekt>
            <placekey>United States of America</placekey>
            <placekey>America</placekey>
            <placekey>National</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>USGS Energy Resource Regions (NOGA-95)</placekt>
            <placekey>Gulf Coast</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Central Energy Resources Team</cntorg>
               <cntper>Robert Matthias</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Supervisory IT Specialist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>U.S. Geological Survey, Box 25046, MS 939, Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntemail>rmatthias@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <cntvoice>703.648.6477</cntvoice>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
      </status>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/data/nca/graphic/ncrds.jpg</browsen>
      </browse>
   </idinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <resdesc>Applications</resdesc>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>2007</metd>
      <metrd>2007</metrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Central Energy Resources Team, Data Management Project</cntorg>
               <cntper>Gregory L. Gunther</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Spatial Data Manager, Web Developer</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>U.S. Geological Survey, Box 25046, MS 939, Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntemail>datamgt@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <cntinst>For inquiries regarding this document, please include the metadata contact person's name, dataset name, and publication series and number.</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
   <Esri>
      <ModDate>20100526</ModDate>
      <ModTime>14213100</ModTime>
      <MetaID>{786AA4C3-3F48-46AC-973A-3ED689B4A1C8}</MetaID>
      <CreaDate>20071221</CreaDate>
      <CreaTime>10393900</CreaTime>
      <SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce>
      <PublishedDocID>{5B34C7B6-FA5B-434F-98A9-E64209357B8F}</PublishedDocID>
      <PublishStatus>Published</PublishStatus>
   </Esri>
   <mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20071221</mdDateSt>
   <USGSErp>
      <SyncDataGov>y</SyncDataGov>
      <FileSystemMetadataPath/>
      <ReferencingURLs/>
      <MetadataProblems/>
      <MetadataNotes/>
   </USGSErp>
</metadata>
