<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Frank Mazzotti

Ken Rice;
Laura Brandt
</origin>
            <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
            <title>Ecological Models for Evaluating Effects of Restoration Alternatives on Coastal Ecosystems of Southwest Florida</title>
            <geoform>reports</geoform>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/projects/index.php?project_url=eco_model</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>
The objectives of this project are to develop and apply forecasting models to evaluate the impacts of CERP projects on ecological attributes selected from the conceptual models developed for coastal ecosystems as part of the Southwest Florida Feasibility Study (SWFFS).

The study supports Lower West Coast projects in the Department Of Interior (DOI) science plan (specifically: Southwest Florida Feasibility Study and C-43 Basin Storage Reservoir) by (a) developing stress-response models of habitat for coastal species selected during Caloosahatchee conceptual modeling and (b) developing integrated assessment tools to support landscape level decision-making.
</abstract>
         <purpose>The SWFFS is a component of the Comprehensive Everglades Restoration Plan (CERP). The SWFFS will result in an independent but integrated implementation plan for CERP projects. The SWFFS will provide a framework to address the health and sustainability of aquatic systems. This includes water quantity and quality, flood protection, and ecological integrity. The SWFFS was initiated in recognition of the fact that there were additional water resource issues (needs, problems, and opportunities) within southwest Florida that were not being addressed directly by CERP. A purpose of the SWFFS is to identify alternatives that address those issues in the study area. The purpose of this project is to evaluate the effects of those alternatives on coastal systems of southwest Florida.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>2004</begdate>
               <enddate>2008</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>Unknown</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-82.25</westbc>
            <eastbc>-80.75</eastbc>
            <northbc>27.25</northbc>
            <southbc>25</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>modeling</themekey>
            <themekey>hydrology</themekey>
            <themekey>ecology</themekey>
            <themekey>Southwest Florida Feasibility Study</themekey>
            <themekey>SWFFS</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>environment</themekey>
            <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
            <themekey>oceans</themekey>
            <themekey>007</themekey>
            <themekey>012</themekey>
            <themekey>014</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1995, Countries, Dependencies, Areas of Special Sovereignty, and Their Principal Administrative Divisions,  Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS) 10-4, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>US</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>U.S. Department of Commerce, 1987, Codes for the identification of the States, the District of Columbia and the outlying areas of the United States, and associated areas (Federal Information Processing Standard 5-2): Washington, DC, NIST</placekt>
            <placekey>Florida</placekey>
            <placekey>FL</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1990, Counties and Equivalent Entities of the United States, Its Possessions, and Associated Areas, FIPS 6-3, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>Lee County</placekey>
            <placekey>Collier County</placekey>
            <placekey>Charlotte County</placekey>
            <placekey>Hendry County</placekey>
            <placekey>Glades County</placekey>
            <placekey>Monroe County</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>SW Big Cypress</placekey>
            <placekey>Central Everglades</placekey>
            <placekey>Greater Lake Okeechobee</placekey>
            <placekey>Southwest coast</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Frank J. Mazzotti</cntper>
               <cntorg>University of Florida</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>
University of Florida, Fort Lauderdale Research and Education Center

3205 College Ave.
</address>
               <city>Davie</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33314</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>954 577-6304</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>fjma@ufl.edu</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://www.evergladesplan.org/pm/studies/study_docs/swfl/031209_swffs_scoping_letter_map.pdf</browsen>
         <browsed>figure shows the SWFFS area</browsed>
         <browset>PDF</browset>
      </browse>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://pubs.usgs.gov/fs/2004/3113/</browsen>
         <browsed>figure 1 shows the SWFFS area in green</browsed>
         <browset>GIF</browset>
      </browse>
      <datacred>Project personnel include: Kevin Chartier and Adam Dougherty</datacred>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Pearlstine, L. G.

Mazzotti, F J.
</origin>
            <pubdate>2004</pubdate>
            <title>Spatial Decision Support Systems for Landscape Ecological Evaluations in the Southwest Florida Feasibility Study</title>
            <geoform>fact sheet</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>USGS Fact Sheet</sername>
               <issue>2004-3113</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Ft. Lauderdale, FL</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>accessed as of 11/18/2009</othercit>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/fs/2004/3113/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Pearlstine, Leonard

DeAngelis, Donald;
Mazzotti, Frank;
Barnes, Tomma;
Duever, Michael;
Starnes, Janet
</origin>
            <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
            <title>Spatial Decision Support Systems for Landscape Ecological Evaluations in the Southwest Florida Feasibility Study (CIRC 1479)</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Wildlife Ecology and Conservation Department Circular</sername>
               <issue>1479</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Ft. Lauderdale, FL</pubplace>
               <publish>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Services</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>accessed as of 11/18/2009</othercit>
            <onlink>http://edis.ifas.ufl.edu/pdffiles/UW/UW23500.pdf</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>Criteria for assessing ecological effects to southwestern Florida are being developed at three principal scales. The criteria address changes in: (1) potential habitat distributions and quality for individual species, (2) community composition and hydrologic characteristics, and (3) landscape connectivity.</logic>
      <complete>Models for the Eastern Oyster, Blue Crab, Sea Trout, Sea Grasses (Halodule and Thalassia), and a Freshwater Submerged Grass (Vallisneria) have been completed and are being used for alternative selection. The Eastern Oyster, Blue Crab, and Sea Trout models have been submitted to the Interagency Modeling Center.</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Develop and apply forecasting models to evaluate alternatives as they are being developed.

Coastal: Five ecological suitability models, Blue Crab, Eastern Oyster, Spotted Sea Trout, Seagrasses (Halodule and Thalassia) and freshwater submerged grass Valisneria have been completed and incorporated as modules into a decision interface that allows the user to perform pair-wise comparisons of spatially-explicit species habitat suitability model runs against alternative Caloosahatchee River water release scenarios, examine the contribution of each input variables (e.g., salinity, temperature, flow) to the resulting suitability values, and obtain habitat units for decision models.

Inland: Meetings with the SWFFS Natural Systems Group are resulting in a series inland systems performance measures and modeling efforts that will be incorporated as modules in a decision interface. Dale Gawlik and Philip Heidemann have been collecting in-depth information in one-on-one interviews with wading bird experts in Southwestern Florida and completed a conceptual model with associated parameter values to be coded. An amphibian work group composed of Mike Duever, Ken Rice, Harden Waddle, and David Ceilly has completed a conceptual model with associated parameter values to be coded. Work on potential performance measures for landscape connectivity of large mammals, and models of aquatic fauna communities begins in September.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>2005</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Coastal modeling and decision management interface development is completed for Eastern Oyster, Spotted Sea Trout, Blue Crab, Seagrass and Valisneria models. A submerged aquatic grasses meeting in early April was the last of the workshops for completing the coastal models before running them on hydrological scenarios. All of the coastal biological models (oyster, crab, trout, seagrass, and freshwater submerged grasses) were run repeatedly during April and May on alternative hydrological scenarios to examine different parameters in the models and the spatial outputs. The first meeting to select alternatives based on the biological models were held June 12-14. Model runs continued through September as new hydrologic inputs were provided by the US Army Corps of Engineers.

Early April work continued development of inland habitat models. The initial models were presented for comments to the NSG twice in May and from biologist at the GEER conference in early June. At the end of June all of the models (wading birds, amphibian communities, aquatic fauna communities, and large mammal connectivity and roadkill risk index) were operational, but untested.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>2006</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Work planned for FY 2007 and 2008 includes:

Coastal/Estuarine Model Expansion: The current estuarine forecasting model will be expanded to include Estero Bay and will include all species appropriate for that region. Models will be calibrated and refined for Estero Bay and new documentation will be developed where necessary.

Inland Forecasting Model calibration, refinement, and documentation: The HSI models that make up the inland forecasting model will be evaluated, refined, calibrated, and verified using available scientific data and local scientific knowledge as hydrologic output become available. HSI models will be documented in the accepted IMC format.

Alternative Assessment: Restoration alternatives (project designs) will be evaluated using the ecological forecasting models. In addition, a 2000 base run and a 2050 without project run will be performed. This process includes the capture of hydrologic data and the conversion of this data into a usable format. Modeled results will be delivered in an Excel format. In addition results will be integrated into a decision support system for further project alternative evaluation.

Training: University of Florida (UF)  will train district staff to operate modeling software for future modeling efforts.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>2008</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Frank J. Mazzotti</cntper>
                     <cntorg>University of Florida</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
                     <address>
University of Florida, Fort Lauderdale Research and Education Center

3205 College Ave.
</address>
                     <city>Davie</city>
                     <state>FL</state>
                     <postal>33314</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>954 577-6304</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>fjma@ufl.edu</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Frank J. Mazzotti</cntper>
               <cntorg>University of Florida</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>
University of Florida, Fort Lauderdale Research and Education Center

3205 College Ave.
</address>
               <city>Davie</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33314</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>954 577-6304</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>fjma@ufl.edu</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>models</resdesc>
      <distliab>The data have no explicit or implied guarantees.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <nondig>models</nondig>
         <fees>none</fees>
         <ordering>Contact Frank Mazzotti for information about and accessibility to model data and programs.</ordering>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20101103</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Heather Henkel</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth Street South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727 803-8747 ext 3028</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727 803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>sofia-metadata@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <metac>none</metac>
      <metuc>
The principal investigator for this project has declined to provide a review of the information in the metadata record.  Any questions about the information should be directed to the Point of Contact under Citation Information or the Process Contact(s).

This metadata record may have been copied from the SOFIA website and may not be the most recent version.  Please check http://sofia.usgs.gov/metadata to be sure you have the most recent version.
</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
