<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <pubdate>2013</pubdate>
            <title>USGS National Assessment of Oil and Gas Project - Shale Gas Assessment Units</title>
            <geoform>Downloadable GIS Data</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
               <publish>U. S. Geological Survey, Central Energy Resources Science Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/data/noga00/natl/spatial/shape/ShaleGasAU2012shp.zip</onlink>
            <onlink>http://energy.usgs.gov/OilGas/AssessmentsData/NationalOilGasAssessment.aspx</onlink>
            <onlink/>
            <onlink>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/data/noga00/natl/spatial/pmf/ShaleGas2012pmf.zip</onlink>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <pubdate>2013</pubdate>
                  <title>Map of Assessed Shale Gas in the United States, 2012</title>
                  <geoform>Digital Maps</geoform>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Digital Data Series</sername>
                     <issue>DDS-069-Z</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/dds/dds-069/dds-069-z/</onlink>
                  <origin>USGS National Assessment of Oil and Gas Resources Team</origin>
                  <origin>Laura R.H. Biewick</origin>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
            <origin>USGS National Assessment of Oil and Gas Resources Team</origin>
            <origin>Laura R.H. Biewick</origin>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The U.S. Geological Survey has compiled a map of shale gas assessments in the United States that were completed by 2012, such assessments having been included as part of the U.S. Geological Survey National Assessment of Oil and Gas Project. Using a geology-based assessment methodology, the U.S. Geological Survey quantitatively estimated potential volumes of undiscovered gas within shale-gas assessment units. These shale-gas assessment units are mapped, and square-mile cells are shown to represent proprietary shale-gas wells. The square-mile cells include gas-producing wells from shale intervals.

In some cases, shale gas formations contain gas in deeper parts of a basin and oil at shallower depths (for example, the Woodford Shale and the Eagle Ford Shale). Because a discussion of shale oil is beyond the scope of this report, only shale gas assessment units and cells are shown.

The map can be printed as a hardcopy map or downloaded for interactive analysis in a Geographic Information System data package using the ArcGIS map document (file extension MXD) and published map file (file extension PMF). Also available is a publications access table with hyperlinks to current U.S. Geological Survey shale gas assessment publications and web pages. Assessment results and geologic reports are available as completed at the U.S. Geological Survey Energy Resources Program Web Site, http://energy.usgs.gov/OilGas/AssessmentsData/NationalOilGasAssessment.aspx.

A historical perspective of shale gas activity in the United States is documented below and presented in a video clip included as a PowerPoint slideshow.
</abstract>
         <purpose>The Assessment Unit (AU) is the fundamental unit used in the National Assessment of Oil and Gas Project for the estimation of undiscovered oil and gas resources.  The AU is defined within the context of the higher-level Total Petroleum System.  The AU is shown here as a geographic boundary interpreted, defined, and mapped by the geologist responsible for the province and incorporates a set of known or postulated oil and (or) gas accumulations sharing similar geologic, geographic, and temporal properties within the Total Petroleum System, such as source rock, timing, migration pathways, trapping mechanism, and hydrocarbon type.  The AU boundary is defined geologically as the limits of reservoir rock, geologic structures, source rock, and seal lithologies.  The only exceptions to this are AUs that border the Federal-State water boundary.  In these cases, the Federal-State water boundary forms part of the Assessment Unit boundary.</purpose>
         <supplinf>For further information on shale gas, please visit http://energy.usgs.gov/OilGas/AssessmentsData/NationalOilGasAssessment.aspx</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>2012</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-165.</westbc>
            <eastbc>-73.</eastbc>
            <northbc>71.</northbc>
            <southbc>24.</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>National Assessment of Oil and Gas</themekey>
            <themekey>USGS World Energy Region 5</themekey>
            <themekey>Energy Resources</themekey>
            <themekey>Oil</themekey>
            <themekey>Natural Gas</themekey>
            <themekey>Resource Assessment</themekey>
            <themekey>Earth Science</themekey>
            <themekey>Natural Resources</themekey>
            <themekey>U.S. Geological Survey</themekey>
            <themekey>USGS</themekey>
            <themekey>Geology</themekey>
            <themekey>Assessment Unit</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ArcIMS Metadata Server Theme Codes</themekt>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>Gateway to the Earth draft 9 28-Jun-2002</themekt>
            <themekey>Shale gas resources</themekey>
            <themekey>Natural gas resources</themekey>
            <themekey>Economic geology</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>EnergyResourceActivities</themekt>
            <themekey>OilGas</themekey>
            <themekey>NOGA2000</themekey>
            <themekey>ShaleGas</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>USGS World Energy Region 5</placekey>
            <placekey>U.S.A.</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>Users of this geospatial database and geologic information derived therefrom should acknowledge the U.S. Geological Survey as the source of the data.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Christopher J. Schenk</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Central Energy Resources Science Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Geologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>U.S. Geological Survey, Box 25046, MS 939, Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(303) 236-5796</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>schenk@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/data/noga00/natl/graphic/ShaleGasAUs11g.jpg</browsen>
         <browset>
				JPEG
			</browset>
         <browsed>USGS Shale Gas AUs (2012)</browsed>
      </browse>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>One attribute for the Assessment Unit coverage is the eight digit number that identifies the USGS-specific Assessment Unit.  The first digit of the code indicates the World region number (5), the following three digits (5067) are the North America province number, the next two digits (506703) are the Total Petroleum System number, and the last two digits (50670365) are the Assessment Unit number.  The assessment results attributes include estimated volumes of undiscovered, technically recoverable gas and natural gas liquids.  For more detailed assessment results data, refer to the CD_ROM publications for the Provinces that are available at http://pubs.usgs.gov/dds/dds-069/ or the USGS Fact Sheets that are available for each Province at the National Oil and Gas Assessment website - http://energy.usgs.gov/OilGas/AssessmentsData/NationalOilGasAssessment.aspx.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>
The Assessment Unit boundary was defined on the basis of the surface and subsurface geology of the petroleum system elements, and oil and gas production, shows, and seeps related to the Assessment Unit.  The province geologist was required to defend the geologic boundaries of each Assessment Unit in a formal geologic and petroleum system review meeting.
</logic>
      <complete>
The Assessment Unit was mapped in part on the data contained in the IHS Energy Group, WHCS data base for wells, and the Nehring Significant Oil and Gas Field File.
</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>The Assessment Unit boundary represents the gross boundary of the combined geologic elements that comprise the Total Petroleum System.  The Assessment Unit boundary was mapped by the province geologist and the boundary line digitally transferred using ArcGIS.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey Assessment Teams</origin>
                  <pubdate>2000 to 2012</pubdate>
                  <title>
Petroleum Systems and Geologic Assessment of Oil and Gas in the United States 
</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Digital Data Series</sername>
                     <issue>DDS-69</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>CD-ROM</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2002-2012</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>USGS Assessment Teams</srccitea>
            <srccontr>USGS Province assessment, digital map data, undiscovered oil and gas resources</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
The province geologist mapped the Assessment Unit boundary on a hard copy or digital base map that contained data from IHS Energy Group, WHCS data base for wells, and the Nehring Significant Oil and Gas Field File.  The province geologist then plotted all other available geologic, geophysical and geochemical data and information on the base map to assist in mapping the Assessment Unit boundary.  Following review, the Assessment Unit boundary was digitally captured from the hard copy or digitial base map using ArcGIS.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>2000 to 2012</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The attributes were added from the assessment output data file.  These assessment results attributes are published on the National Assessment of Oil and Gas Fact Sheet for each Province.</procdesc>
            <procdate>2000 to 2012</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Vector</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>Complete chain</sdtstype>
         </sdtsterm>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
         </sdtsterm>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>GT-polygon composed of chains</sdtstype>
         </sdtsterm>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <latres>0.000001</latres>
            <longres>0.000001</longres>
            <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
         </geograph>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>World Geodetic System (WGS) of 1984</horizdn>
            <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.257223</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>au"assessunitnum and abbreviated name"</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Polygon Attribute Table.  For each assessment unit, "assessunitnum" is replaced with the assessment unit number, and is followed by an abbreviation of the assessment unit name.</enttypd>
            <enttypds>U.S. Geological Survey</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>REG_NUM</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Region Number</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Energy Resource World Regions</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>5</edomv>
                  <edomvd>North America</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>common knowledge</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>REG_NAME</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Region Name</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Energy Resource World Regions</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>North America</edomv>
                  <edomvd>country</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>common knowledge</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>PROVCODE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Province Code</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Energy Resource Provinces</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>72 provinces numbered 1 to 72</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>PROV_NAME</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Province Name</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Energy Resource Provinces</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>see http://energy.cr.usgs.gov/oilgas/noga/index.html</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>TPSCODE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Total Petroleum System Code</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Energy Resource Total Petroleum Systems</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>see http://energy.cr.usgs.gov/oilgas/noga/index.html</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>TPSNAME</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Total Petroleum System Name</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Energy Resource Total Petroleum Systems</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>see http://energy.cr.usgs.gov/oilgas/noga/index.html</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>ASSESSCODE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Assessment Unit Code</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Energy Resource Assessment Units</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>see http://energy.cr.usgs.gov/oilgas/noga/index.html</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>ASSESSNAME</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Assessment Unit Name</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Energy Resource Assessment Units</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>see http://energy.cr.usgs.gov/oilgas/noga/index.html</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>ASSESSTYPE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Assessment Unit Type</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Energy Resource Assessment Unit Types.  Both conventional and continuous accumulations are assessed.  All of the shale gas AUs are continuous gas.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Continuous Gas</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Type of resource</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>NAGAS_F95</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>95% probability of greater than this volume of undiscovered gas (non-associated gas) in gas accumulations in the assessment unit (in billions of cubic feet)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS DDS-69-B; USGS DDS-60, Chpt. AM; USGS Bulletin 2165</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>stored as a floating-point value</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>NAGAS_F50</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>50% probability of greater than this volume of undiscovered gas (non-associated gas) in gas accumulations in the assessment unit (in billions of cubic feet)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS DDS-69-B; USGS DDS-60, Chpt. AM; USGS Bulletin 2165</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>stored as a floating-point value</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>NAGAS_F5</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>5% probability of greater than this volume of undiscovered gas (non-associated gas) in gas accumulations in the assessment unit (in billions of cubic feet)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS DDS-69-B; USGS DDS-60, Chpt. AM; USGS Bulletin 2165</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>stored as a floating-point value</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>NAGASMEAN</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The mean estimate of volume of undiscovered gas (non-associated gas) in gas accumulations in the assessment unit (in billions of cubic feet)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS DDS-69-B; USGS DDS-60, Chpt. AM; USGS Bulletin 2165</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>stored as a floating-point value</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>NAGASSTDEV</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The standard deviation of the distribution of volume of undiscovered gas (non-associated gas) in gas accumulations in the assessment unit (in billions of cubic feet)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS DDS-69-B; USGS DDS-60, Chpt. AM; USGS Bulletin 2165</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>stored as a floating-point value</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>NAGL_F95</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>95% probability of greater than this volume of undiscovered liquids in gas accumulations in the assessment unit (in millions of barrels)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS DDS-69-B; USGS DDS-60, Chpt. AM; USGS Bulletin 2165</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>stored as a floating-point value</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>NAGL_F50</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>50% probability of greater than this volume of undiscovered liquids in gas accumulations in the assessment unit (in millions of barrels)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS DDS-69-B; USGS DDS-60, Chpt. AM; USGS Bulletin 2165</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>stored as a floating-point value</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>NAGL_F5</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>5% probability of greater than this volume of undiscovered liquids in gas accumulations in the assessment unit (in millions of barrels)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS DDS-69-B; USGS DDS-60, Chpt. AM; USGS Bulletin 2165</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>stored as a floating-point value</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>NAGLMEAN</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The mean estimate of volume of undiscovered liquids in gas accumulations in the assessment unit (in millions of barrels)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS DDS-69-B; USGS DDS-60, Chpt. AM; USGS Bulletin 2165</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>stored as a floating-point value</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>NAGLSTDEV</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The standard deviation of the distribution of volume of undiscovered liquids in gas accumulations in the assessment unit (in millions of barrels)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS DDS-69-B; USGS DDS-60, Chpt. AM; USGS Bulletin 2165</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>stored as a floating-point value</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Information Services</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Box 25286 Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-888-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>303-202-4693</cntfax>
            <cntemail>ask@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Shapefile</formname>
               <formcont>Assessment unit geographic features and attribute data</formcont>
               <filedec>unzip</filedec>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/data/noga00/natl/spatial/shape/ShaleGasAU2012shp.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>The URL above links to a compressed file containing shale gas Assessment Unit Boundaries.</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ArcGIS Geodatabase File</formname>
               <formvern>9.3</formvern>
               <formcont>Assessment unit geographic features and attribute data</formcont>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/data/noga00/natl/spatial/geodatabase/ShaleGasAU2012gdb.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>The URL above links to a compressed file containing shale gas Assessment Unit Boundaries.</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ArcGIS Published Map File Package</formname>
               <formcont>This file contains a data package and interactive map intended for use in any ArcGIS desktop product, including the no-cost ArcGIS Reader</formcont>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/data/noga00/natl/spatial/pmf/ShaleGas2012pmf.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>Download and unzip the package.  Open the mxd within the package using ArcGIS ArcMap 9.3.1 or later.  Open the pmf within the package using ArcGIS Reader or ArcGIS ArcMap.</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None</fees>
         <ordering>These products can be downloaded individually using any one of the Network_Resource_Name URLs above. Each of these URLs provide access to various formats of these data.</ordering>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>CD-ROM</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/dds/dds-069/dds-069-z/</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>send email request to eteamdisks@usgs.gov</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
               <offoptn>
                  <offmedia>CD-ROM</offmedia>
                  <recfmt>unknown</recfmt>
               </offoptn>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
      </stdorder>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  The U.S. Geological survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.  Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it may also contain copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items for other than personal use must be secured from the copyright owner.</distliab>
      <resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20120501</metd>
      <metrd>20110730</metrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Central Energy Resources Science Center</cntorg>
               <cntper>Laura R.H. Biewick</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Physical Scientist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>U.S. Geological Survey, Box 25046, MS 939, Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntemail>lbiewick@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <cntinst>For inquiries regarding this document, please include the metadata contact person's name, dataset name, and publication series and number.</cntinst>
            <cntvoice>303-236-7773</cntvoice>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
   <USGSErp>
      <SyncDataGov>y</SyncDataGov>
      <FileSystemMetadataPath>\\NETAPP1\public_data\noga00\natl\spatial\doc\ShaleGasAUs2012.xml</FileSystemMetadataPath>
      <ReferencingURLs/>
      <MetadataProblems/>
      <MetadataNotes/>
   </USGSErp>
</metadata>
