<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Douglas M. Hirschberg</origin>
            <origin>G. Stephen Pitts</origin>
            <pubdate>2000</pubdate>
            <title>Digital geologic map of Arizona: a digital databasederived from the 1983 printing of the Wilson, Moore,and Cooper 1:500,000-scale map</title>
            <edition>Digital Version 1.0</edition>
            <geoform>map</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>00-409</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Menlo Park, California</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2000/0409/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The Geologic Map of Arizona was compiled at a scale of 1:500,000 byEldred D. Wilson, Richard T. Moore and John R. Cooper, in 1969 andreprinted in 1977, 1981, and 1983.
Comparison of an acetate copy of the 1983 map with existing papercopies of earlier maps shows some updating of the original by 1983.This 1983 acetate was scanned and vectorized by Optronics Specialty Co., Inc.in 1998, and put into an Arc/Info geographic information system (GIS).The digital geologic map database can be queried in many ways toproduce a variety of derivative geologic maps.</abstract>
         <purpose>This database was developed to provide a GIS of the geologicmap of the State of Arizona for use at a scale of1:500,000 or smaller. This GIS is intended for use infuture spatial analysis by a variety of users.The geologic unit descriptions for this map may be updatedto reflect more current description of structures andthe geochronology of the map units.
This database is not meant to be used or displayed atany scale larger than 1:500,000 (e.g., 1:100,000 or1:24,000)</purpose>
         <supplinf>This GIS database consists of 4 Arc/Info datasets:one line and polygon file (azgeol)containing geologic contacts and structures (lines)and geologic map rock units (polygons),one line file (azfold) containing the folds andcrater boundaries,one point file (azptfeat) containing geologic features,cinder cones and diatremes.one point file (azptdec) containing decorations, and</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>2000</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Publication Date of Open-File Report 00-409</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>Uncertain, may update newer structure and geochronology in future</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-115.00</westbc>
            <eastbc>-108.75</eastbc>
            <northbc>37.00</northbc>
            <southbc>31.25</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>geology</themekey>
            <themekey>geologic maps</themekey>
            <themekey>bedrock geologic units</themekey>
            <themekey>geologic structure</themekey>
            <themekey>geospatial datasets</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Arizona</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Augmented FIPS 10-4 and FIPS 6-4</placekt>
            <placekey>US04 = Arizona</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>These data are not to be used at scales greater than 1:500,000.Any hardcopies utilizing these data sets shall clearly indicatetheir source. If the user has modified the data in any waythey are obligated to describe the types of modifications theyhave performed on the hardcopy map. User specifically agreesnot to misrepresent these data sets, nor to imply that changes theymade were approved by the U.S. Geological Survey.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>G. Stephen Pitts</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>GIS Lab coordinator, contractor</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>(mailing and physical address)</addrtype>
               <address>520 N. Park Ave, suite 355</address>
               <city>Tucson</city>
               <state>Arizona</state>
               <postal>85719</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-520-670-5511</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>1-520-670-5571</cntfax>
            <cntemail>bear@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>Eldred D. Wilson, Richard T. Moore, and John R. Coopercompiled the geologic map of which an acetate archivecopy of the separates were located in Reston VA.Robert Miller (USGS) attached fiducial tics to assure registrationaccuracy. Optronics Specialty Co., Inc. scanned the geologic mapand provided minimally attributed Arc/Info interchange-formatfiles to the USGS.
Douglas M. Hirschberg imported the files, transformed them toLambert Conformal Conic, attached and attributed an interim geologicmap data model, verified arc, point, and polygon attribution, added,re-positioned, or re-attributed features as needed, and assisted increating the look-up tables.
G. Stephen Pitts assisted with the design of the data model, enteredthe explanatory and source text, assisted in creating the look-uptables, and wrote the metadata.</datacred>
      <native>SunOS, 5.6, sun4u UNIXARC/INFO version 7.2.1</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>Accuracy of the Attribution was verified bymanual comparison of the sources withhard copy printouts and plots.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Polygon and chain-node topology present.
Polygons intersecting the neatline are closed along the border.Segments making up the outer and inner boundaries of a polygontie end-to-end to completely enclose the area. Line segments area set of sequentially numbered coordinate pairs. No duplicatefeatures exist nor duplicate points in a data string. Intersectinglines are separated into individual line segments at the point ofintersection. All nodes are represented by a single coordinatepair which indicates the beginning or end of a line segment.The map boundary came from the scan, was projected to LambertConformal Conic.</logic>
      <complete>The digital dataset was produced from a previouslypublished map (Wilson, Moore, &amp; Cooper, 1969) whichis considered to be a high quality cartographic product,generally speaking contacts exist where mapped, andthe best available at 1:500,000. From subsequent mapping,errors are known to exist with the structure and geochronology.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>The horizontal positional accuracy for the digital data may beno better than +/- 500 meters (1 mm at mapscale). It was testedby visual comparison of the source acetate and available papermaps with hard copy plots.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Eldred D. Wilson</origin>
                  <origin>Richard T. Moore</origin>
                  <origin>John R. Cooper</origin>
                  <pubdate>1983</pubdate>
                  <title>Geologic Map of Arizona</title>
                  <geoform>map</geoform>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>map series: G</sername>
                     <issue>81036</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>500000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>acetate separate</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1983</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>1983, date of publication</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Wilson and others (1983)</srccitea>
            <srccontr>geologic units, contact, and structure</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The original separates for this map were notlocatable in Menlo Park, CA, and after extensivesearch, thought to no longer exist. By thoroughinvestigation, two separates, the water layer andthe geologic units, were found in a map tube inReston, VA., and forwarded to Menlo Park, CA. whereRobert Miller attached Lat-Lon tics to the acetatelayer of the geologic units to assure registration accuracy</procdesc>
            <procdate>1998</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The registered acetate separate of the geologicunits, contacts, and structure was scanned, vectorized,minimally attributed, and exported to an Arc/Infointerchange-format by Optronics Specialty Co., Inc andfiles were given to the USGS in Tucson</procdesc>
            <procdate>1998</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The four coverages were transformed to Lambert ConformalConic projection using 28 tics which produced an RMS errorof 0.004. All linework, points, and attributions were verifiedby extensively comparison between printed versions of the map,the 1983 source acetate, and hard copy plots derived from thedatabase. Some very small polygons were not identifiable on theoriginal printed maps or the acetate, and were eliminated. Somesmall polygons were missing from the initial capture, and werere-captured by D.M. Hirschberg.
All faults were attributed as Throw Unknown, Normal,Thrust, or Strike Slip, as determined from visualinspection of attributions on the paper map.Faults where attributed, were identified as U/D, T,or, in two cases on the 1983 map, with the rightlateral strike slip decoration. Sense of up or downwas determined by placement of the letters U and Don the paper map. Sense of upper plate, lower platefor thrust faults was inconsistent, (T on side ofolder rock in some cases and on side of younger rocksin other), so no upper plate / lower plate attributionwas made on the Trust faults.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1999</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Creation of original metadata record</procdesc>
            <procdate>19990924</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntorgp>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                     <cntper>G. Stephen Pitts</cntper>
                  </cntorgp>
                  <cntpos>GIS lab manager, contractor</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>520 N. Park Ave, suite 355</address>
                     <city>Tucson</city>
                     <state>Arizona</state>
                     <postal>85719</postal>
                     <country>United States of America</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>520.670.5511</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>520.670.5571</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>bear@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Vector</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>10803</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>String</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>25546</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>GT-polygon composed of chains</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>10807</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <mapproj>
               <mapprojn>Lambert Conformal Conic</mapprojn>
               <lambertc>
                  <stdparll>33</stdparll>
                  <stdparll>45</stdparll>
                  <longcm>-112</longcm>
                  <latprjo>0</latprjo>
                  <feast>0.00000</feast>
                  <fnorth>0.00000</fnorth>
               </lambertc>
            </mapproj>
            <planci>
               <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>25.39368057251</absres>
                  <ordres>25.39368057251</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>Meters</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1927</horizdn>
            <ellips>Clarke 1866</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378206.4</semiaxis>
            <denflat>294.98</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <overview>
         <eaover>The 'Digital Geologic Map of Arizona; a digital databasefrom the 1983 printing of the Eldred D. Wilson andRichard T. Moore, and John R. Cooper 1:500,000-scale map'Open-File Report 00-409 contains a detailed descriptionof each attribute code and a reference to the associatedmap symbols on the map source materials.
This GIS database consists of four Arc/Info datasets:one line and polygon file, azgeol,containing geologic contacts and structures (lines)and geologic map rock units (polygons),one line file, azfold, containing the folds andcrater boundaries,one point file, azptfeat, containing geologic features,cinder cones and diatremes, andone point file, azptdec, containing decorations.
Azgeol contains an arc attribute table, azgeol.aat, whichrelates geologic linework arc attribution to the contactlook-up table, azgeol.con, the structural attribute table,azgeol.str and the source reference look-up table, sources.ref.
Azgeol also contains a polygon attribute table, azgeol.pat, whichrelates the polygons to the rock-unit look-up table, azgeol.ru,and the source reference look-up table, sources.ref.
Azfold contains an arc attribute table, azfold.aat, whichrelates to the structural attribute table, azfold.str, andthe source reference look-up table, sources.ref.
Azptfeat contains the point attribute table, azptfeat.pat, whichrelates the feature points to their descriptions in azptfeat.lut,and the source reference look-up table, sources.ref.
Azptdec contains the point attribute table, azptdec.pat, whichrelates the points to descriptions in the look-up table,azptdec.lut, and the source reference look-up table, sources.ref.</eaover>
         <eadetcit>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2000/0409/00readme.txt</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Information Services</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Open-File Reports, Box 25286</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>CO</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-303-202-4200</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>1-303-202-4693</cntfax>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>USGS Open-File Report 00-409</resdesc>
      <distliab>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) provides these geographic data "as is."The USGS makes no guarantee or warranty concerning the accuracy ofinformation contained in the geographic data. The USGS further makes nowarranties, either expressed or implied as to any other matter whatsoever,including, without limitation, the condition of the product, or itsfitness for any particular purpose. The burden for determining fitness foruse lies entirely with the user. Although these data have been processedsuccessfully on computers at the USGS, no warranty, expressed or implied,is made by the USGS regarding the use of these data on any other system,nor does the fact of distribution constitute or imply any such warranty.In no event shall the USGS have any liability whatsoever for paymentof any consequential, incidental, indirect, special, or tort damagesof any kind, including, but not limited to, any loss of profitsarising out of use of or reliance on the geographic data or arisingout of the delivery, installation, operation, or support by USGS.
This digital geologic map GIS of the Geologic Map of Arizonaat a scale of 1:500,000, is not meant to be used or displayedat any scale larger than 1:500,000 (e.g., 1:62,500 or 1:24,000).</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ARCE</formname>
               <formvern>7.x</formvern>
               <formcont>Geologic units, structural features, point measurements</formcont>
               <filedec>gzip -d and tar</filedec>
               <transize>37</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2000/0409/of00-409.tar.Z</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150202</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Peter N Schweitzer</cntper>
               <cntorg>USGS Midwest Area</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Collection manager, USGS Geoscience Data Clearinghouse, http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Mail Stop 95412201 Sunrise Valley Dr</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192-0002</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>703-648-6533</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>703-648-6252</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pschweitzer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
