<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Ray J. Weldon II</origin>
            <origin>D.K. Fletcher</origin>
            <origin>E.M. Weldon</origin>
            <origin>K.M. Scharer</origin>
            <origin>Patricia A. McCrory</origin>
            <pubdate>2002</pubdate>
            <title>An update of Quaternary faults of central and eastern Oregon</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>02-301</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/of02-301/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This publication updates previous fault maps of Oregon as acontribution to the larger U.S. Geological Survey effort to producedigital maps of active faults in the Pacific Northwest region.  The newmap is derived from the 1992 fault map of Pezzopane, Nakata, and Weldonthat has seen wide distribution and has been reproduced in essentiallyall subsequent compilations of active faults of Oregon.  Thispublication provides a substantial update of known active or suspectedactive faults east of the Cascades.  Improvements in the new mapinclude (1) many newly recognized active faults, (2) a linked ArcInfomap and reference database, (3) more precise locations for previouslyrecognized faults on shaded relief quadrangles generated from USGS 30-mdigital elevations models (DEM), (4) more uniform coverage resulting inmore consistent grouping of the ages of active faults, and (5) a newcategory of "possibly" active faults that share characteristics withknown active faults, but have not been studied adequately to assesstheir activity.  The distribution of active faults has not changedsubstantially from the original Pezzopane, Nakata and Weldon map.  Mostfaults occur in the south-central Basin and Range tectonic provincethat is located in the backarc portion of the Cascadia subductionmargin.  These faults occur in zones consisting of numerous shortfaults with similar rates, ages, and styles of movement.  Many activefaults strongly correlate with the most active volcanic centers ofOregon, including Newberry Craters and Crater Lake.</abstract>
         <purpose>Update the active fault map and database for central and eastern Oregonas a contribution to the larger U.S. Geological Survey effort toproduce digital maps of active faults in the Pacific Northwest region.The new map attempts to rectify a number of shortcomings in theoriginal 1:500,000-scale map of Pezzopane (1993) and to add fault dataacquired during subsequent investigations.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>2002</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>Irregular</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-122.868134</westbc>
            <eastbc>-116.886803</eastbc>
            <northbc>45.999989</northbc>
            <southbc>41.998665</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>Alexandria Digital Library Feature Type Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>faults</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>geology</themekey>
            <themekey>geologic structure</themekey>
            <themekey>geospatial datasets</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Central and Eastern Oregon</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Augmented FIPS 10-4 and FIPS 6-4</placekt>
            <placekey>41001 = Baker</placekey>
            <placekey>41005 = Clackamas</placekey>
            <placekey>41013 = Crook</placekey>
            <placekey>41017 = Deschutes</placekey>
            <placekey>41019 = Douglas</placekey>
            <placekey>41021 = Gilliam</placekey>
            <placekey>41023 = Grant</placekey>
            <placekey>41025 = Harney</placekey>
            <placekey>41027 = Hood River</placekey>
            <placekey>41029 = Jackson</placekey>
            <placekey>41031 = Jefferson</placekey>
            <placekey>41035 = Klamath</placekey>
            <placekey>41037 = Lake</placekey>
            <placekey>41039 = Lane</placekey>
            <placekey>41043 = Linn</placekey>
            <placekey>41045 = Malheur</placekey>
            <placekey>41047 = Marion</placekey>
            <placekey>41049 = Morrow</placekey>
            <placekey>41051 = Multnomah</placekey>
            <placekey>41055 = Sherman</placekey>
            <placekey>41059 = Umatilla</placekey>
            <placekey>41061 = Union</placekey>
            <placekey>41063 = Wallowa</placekey>
            <placekey>41065 = Wasco</placekey>
            <placekey>41069 = Wheeler</placekey>
         </place>
         <temporal>
            <tempkt>none</tempkt>
            <tempkey>Quaternary</tempkey>
         </temporal>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Ray J. Weldon II</cntper>
               <cntorg>Dept. of Geological Sciences, University of Oregon</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Professor of Geology</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Dept. of Geological Sciences, University of Oregon</address>
               <city>Eugene</city>
               <state>Oregon</state>
               <postal>97403-1272</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>541-346-4584</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>541-346-4692</cntfax>
            <cntemail>ray@newberry.uoregon.edu</cntemail>
            <cntinst>Secondary Contact:&gt;Patricia A. McCrory&gt;U.S. Geological Survey&gt;Research Geologist&gt;mailing address&gt;U.S.Geological Survey&gt;345 Middlefield Road&gt;Menlo Park&gt;California&gt;94025&gt;USA&gt;650-329-5677&gt;650-329-5163&gt;pmccrory@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <native>Microsoft Windows 2000 Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 1; ESRI ArcCatalog 8.3.0.800</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <complete>A literature search was undertaken to update the catalog of activefaults in central and eastern Oregon.  Those studies published in thepast decade are listed in the references (see 'Read-Me' file) and inthe ArcInfo database as attributes to the fault traces.  The ArcInfodatabase is linked to the 1:100,000 map sheets where individual faulttraces are keyed to the references that provide the line(s) of evidencefor their assigned activity.  To determine which faults were redrawnand which were simply compiled from a pre-existing digital database,one must also access the ArcInfo database, select the fault, and readits attributes.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>Faults taken from the digital State Geologic map (digital version of ref#8)were copied from 1:500,000 coverage, all other fault traces were drawn onto1:100,000 hill shade printouts of the DEM using 1:35,000 to 1:250,000 scalemaps and air photos as reference.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Vector</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>Complete chain</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>3912</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>4</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
         </geograph>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
            <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.257222</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>orqfaults_dd.aat</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Fault traces shown on the map</enttypd>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>LENGTH_METERS</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Length of the fault trace in meters (floating-point value)</attrdef>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>100.439</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>45952.850</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>meters</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>0.001</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>FAULT_ID</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Integer identifier without further scientific significance</attrdef>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>1</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>3913</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>COMMENT</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Name of the fault, fault zone, or other explanation (text of at most 64 characters)</attrdef>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Feature names or other explanatory text.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>REFERENCE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Comma-separated list of integers identifying the bibliographic reference; a combination of any of the values described here</attrdef>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Lineament across Quaternary unit from 1:100,000 shaded relief DEM.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Sherrod, D. R., and Pickthorn, L. G., 1992, Geologic map of the west half of the Klamath Falls 1¡ by 2¡ Quadrangle, south-central Oregon:  U.S. Geological Survey Miscellaneous Investigations Series Map I-1282, scale 1:250,000.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Bacon, C. R., Mastin, L. G., Scott, K. M., and Nathenson, M., 1997, Volcano and earthquake hazards in the Crater Lake region, Oregon:  U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 97-487, 32 p., 1 sheet.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>4</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Klinger, R. E., Vetter U. R., and Ryter, D. W., 1996, Seismotectonic study for Gerber Dam, Klamath Project, California-Oregon:  U.S. Bureau of Reclamation Seismotectonic Report 96-1.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>5</edomv>
                  <edomvd>MacLeod, N. S., and Sherrod, D. R., 1992, Reconnaissance geologic map of the west half of the Crescent 1¡ by 2¡ Quadrangle, central Oregon:  U.S. Geological Survey Miscellaneous Investigations Series Map I-2215, 1 sheet, scale 1:250,000.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>6</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Hawkins, F. F., LaForge, R. C., and Gilbert, J. D., 1989, Seismotectonic study for Wickiup and Crane Prairie Dams, Deschutes Project, Oregon: U.S. Bureau of Reclamation Seismotectonic Report 89-2.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>7</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Moring, B. C., 1983, Reconnaissance surficial geologic map of the Medford 1¡ by 2¡ Quadrangle, Oregon-California:  U.S. Geological Survey Miscellaneous Studies Map MF-1528, 2 sheets, scale 1:125,000.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>8</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Walker, G. W., and MacLeod, N. S., 1991, Geologic map of Oregon:  U.S. Geological Survey Special Geologic Map, 2 sheets, scale 1:500,000.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>9</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Bacon, C. R., Lanphere, M. A., and Champion, D. E., 1999, Late Quaternary slip rate and seismic hazards of the West Klamath Lake fault zone near Crater Lake, Oregon Cascades:  Geology, v. 27, p. 43-46.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>10</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Smith, J. G., 1988, Geologic map of the Pelican Butte Quadrangle, Klamath County, Oregon:  U.S. Geological Survey Geologic Quadrangle Map GQ-1653, 1 sheet, scale 1:62,500.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>11</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Carver, G. A., 1972, Glacial geology of the Mountain Lakes Wilderness and adjacent parts of the Cascade Range, Oregon, Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, 75 p.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>12</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Ake, J. P., and Hawkins, F. F., 1999, Preliminary probabilistic ground motion evaluation, Crescent Lake Dam, Crescent Lake Project, Oregon:  U.S. Department of Interior Technical Memorandum No. D8330-99-023.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>13</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Pezzopane, S. K., 1993, Active faults and earthquake ground motions in Oregon, Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Oregon, Eugene, Oregon, 250 p.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>14</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Sherrod, D. R., 1991, Geologic map of a part of the Cascade Range between latitudes 43¡ - 44¡, central Oregon: U.S. Geological Survey Miscellaneous Investigations Series I-1891, 14 p., 1 sheet, scale 1:125,000.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>15</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Langridge, R. M., 1996, Unpublished map accompanying Langridge, R. M., Weldon, R. J., II, Pezzopane, S. K., and Jellinek, A. M., 1996, Active faulting and tufa formation:  A possible kinematic link between Albert Rim and Viewpoint Faults:  Geological Society of America Abstracts with Programs, v. 28, n. 5, p. 74.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>16</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Ryter, D. W., and Vetter, U. R., 1993, Seismotectonic Study for Haystack Dam, Deschutes Project, Oregon:  Bureau of Reclamation Seismotectonic Report 93-1.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>17</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Wong, I. G., Dober, M., Hemphill-Haley, M. A., Naugler, W., and Silva, W. J., 1999, On probabilistic seismic hazard analysis and safety evaluation; earthquake ground motions, Bully Creek Dam, Vale Project, eastern Oregon:  U.S. Department of Interior Technical Memorandum No. D8330-99-28.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>18</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Hawkins, F. F., Gilbert, J. D., and LaForge, R. C., 1989, Seismotectonic Study for Warm-Springs Dam - Vale Project and Owyhee Dam - Owyhee Project, Oregon:  Bureau of Reclamation Seismotectonic Report 89-6.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>19</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Hawkins, F. F., LaForge, R. C., Templeton, M., and Gilbert, J. D., 1988, Seismotectonic study for Arthur R. Bowman and Ochoco Dams, Crooked River Project, Oregon:  Bureau of Reclamation Seismotectonic Report 88-10.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>20</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Narwold, C. F., 1999, Late Quaternary faulting in the Quinn River Fault Zone, a soils investigation:  Friends of the Pleistocene Field Trip Guide, Pacific Cell.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>21</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Mimura, K., 1992, Reconnaissance geologic map of the west half of the Bend and the east half of the Shelvin Park 7.5' Quadrangles, Deschutes County, Oregon:  U.S. Geological Survey Miscellaneous Field Studies Map MF-2189, 1 sheet, scale 1:24,000.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>22</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Taylor, E. M., 1981, Central High Cascade roadside geology, in Johnston, D. A., and Donnelly-Nolan, J., eds., Guides to Some Volcanic Terrains in Washington, Idaho, Oregon, and Northern California:  U.S. Geological Survey Circular 838, p. 55-83.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>23</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Hemphill-Haley, M. A., 1995, Unpublished data.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>24</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Hemphill-Haley, M. A., Page, W. D., Burke, R., and Carver, G. A., 1989, Holocene activity of the Alvord fault, Steens Mountain, southeastern Oregon:  Final Report to the U.S. Geological Survey under Grant No. 14-08-0001-61333, 45 p.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>25</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Hemphill-Haley, M. A., 1987, Quaternary stratigraphy and late Holocene faulting along the base of the eastern escarpment of Steens Mountain, southeastern Oregon, M.A. thesis, Humboldt State University, Arcata, California, 87 p.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>26</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Lindberg, D. N., 1999, A synopsis of late Pleistocene shorelines and faulting, Tule Springs Rims to Mickey Basin, Alvord Desert, Harney County, Oregon.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>27</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Weldon, E. M., Unpublished air photo mapping of the Hot Springs fault, Summer Lake Basin.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>28</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Simpson, G. D., Hemphill-Haley, M. A., Wong, I. G., Bott, J. D., Silva, W. J., and Lettis, W.R., 1993, Seismotectonic evaluation, Burnt River Project-Unity Dam and Baker Project-Thief Valley Dam, northwestern Oregon:  Final Report, prepared for U.S. Bureau of Reclamation.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>29</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Mann, G. M., and Meyer, G. E., 1993, Late Cenozoic structure and correlations to seismicity along the Olympic-Wallowa lineament, northwest United States:  Geological Society of America Bulletin, v. 105, p. 853-871.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>30</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Vetter, U. R., 1998, Preliminary seismic hazard evaluation Mason Dam, Baker Project, Oregon, Technical Memorandum No. D8330-98-015, prepared for the U.S. Bureau of Reclamation, Denver, Colorado.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>31</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Wong, I. G., Dober, M., Hemphill-Haley, M.A., Naugler, W., and Silva, W. J., 1999, On probabilistic seismic hazard analysis and safety evaluation; earthquake ground motions, Bully Creek Dam, Vale Project, eastern Oregon:  U.S. Department of Interior Technical Memorandum No. D8330-99-28.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>32</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Piety, L. A., LaForge, R. C., and Foley, L. L., 1990, Seismotectonic study for Cold Springs and McKay Dams, Umatilla Project, Oregon:  Seismotectonic Report 90-1, prepared for U.S. Bureau of Reclamation, Denver, Colorado.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>33</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Geomatrix Consultants, 1990, Seismotectionic evaluation, Waco Dam site:  Final Report, prepared for U.S. Bureau of Reclamation, 115 p.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>34</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Minor, S. A., 1986, Stratigraphy and structure of the Western Trout Creek and Northern Bilk Creek Mountains, Harney County, Oregon and Humboldt County, Nevada, M.S. thesis, University of Colorado, Boulder, Colorado.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>35</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Walker, G. W., 1973, Reconnaissance geologic map of the Pendleton Quadrangle, Oregon and Washington:  U.S. Geological Survey Miscellaneous Investigation Map I-727, 1 sheet, scale 1:250,000.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>36</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Walker, G. W., Peterson, N. V., and Greene, R. C., 1967, Reconnaissance geologic map of the east half of the Crescent Quadrangle, Lake, Deschutes, and Crook Counties, Oregon:  U.S. Geological Survey Miscellaneous Series Map I-493, 1 sheet, scale 1:250,000.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>37</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Weldon, R. J., II, Unpublished mapping.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>38</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Geomatrix Consultants, 1995, Seismic design mapping, State of Oregon:  Final Report, prepared for Oregon Department of Transportation, 252 p.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>39</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Swanson, D. A., 1969, Reconnaissance geologic map of the east half of the Bend quadrangle, Crook, Wheeler, Jefferson, Wasco, and Deschutes Counties, Oregon:  U.S. Geological Survey Miscellaneous Geologic Investigations Map I-568, scale 1:250,000.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>40</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Faults digitized from reference #36 that cut or bound Quaternary units.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>41</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Faults digitized from reference #36 that do not cut or bound Quaternary units, but are kinematically related to other active faults.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>42</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Faults drawn from DEM that do not cut or bound Quaternary units, but are kinematically related to other active faults.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>43</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Faults taken from digital Oregon State geologic map (digital version of reference #8) that bound or cut Quaternary units (little effort was made to check or redraw these faults).</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>44</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Faults with numbered references on Personius, S. F., Dart, R. L., Bradley, Lee-Ann, and Haller, K. M., 2003, Map and data for Quaternary faults and folds in Oregon:  U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 03-095, 579 p., 1 sheet, scale 1:750,000 [numbered references are in our fault attribute table].</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>45</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Faults digitized from the Oregon State map (reference #8) that cut a Quaternary (or possibly Quaternary) unit.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>46</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Faults digitized from the Oregon State map (reference #8) that bound a Quaternary (or possibly Quaternary) unit.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>47</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Clear continuation of a recognized active (or possibly active) fault.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>48</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Clearly part of a recognized active (or possibly active) fault zone.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>49</edomv>
                  <edomvd>May cut a Quaternary unit and appears to deflect a river course.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>50</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Has obvious geomorphic expression, but encounters no Quaternary units.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>51</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Has obvious geomorphic expression and kinematic relationship to other faults inferred to be active.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>52</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Possible buried fault, defined by aligned volcanic vents.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>53</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Same as reference #51, but trace taken from reference #8.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>ACTIVITY_CODE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>(integer)</attrdef>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>BLUE-Possibly active during the Quaternary</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>GREEN-Active during the Quaternary (&lt;1.6 Ma)</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>4</edomv>
                  <edomvd>YELLOW-Active during the middle to late Quaternary  (&lt;0.78 Ma)</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>5</edomv>
                  <edomvd>ORANGE-Active during the latest Quaternary (&lt;120,000 yrs)</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>6</edomv>
                  <edomvd>RED-Active during the Holocene (&lt;10,000 yrs) or post glacial (&lt;18,000 yrs)</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>DIP</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>General direction of dip and character of fault (text 50 at most characters wide)</attrdef>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>(no value)</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>N</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>DEX</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>E</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>N</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>N, Thrust</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>NE</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>NW</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>S</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>SE</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>SW</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>W</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>W, S</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>FAULT_SYMBOL</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>description of symbolization on map plot (text, 50 characters wide)</attrdef>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>blue</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>blue, inferred</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>green</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>orange</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>orange, approximately located</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>orange, concealed</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>red</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>red, approximately located</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>yellow</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>yellow, approximately located</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>yellow, concealed</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Information Services</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Box 25286 Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>CO</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>303-202-4700</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>303-202-4693</cntfax>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>USGS Open-File Report 02-301</resdesc>
      <distliab>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) provides these geographicdata "as is." The USGS makes no guarantee or warranty concerningthe accuracy of information contained in the geographic data.The USGS further makes no warranties, either expressed or impliedas to any other matter whatsoever, including, without limitation,the condition of the product, or its fitness for any particularpurpose. The burden for determining fitness for use lies entirelywith the user.  Although these data have been processedsuccessfully on computers at the USGS, no warranty, expressed orimplied, is made by the USGS regarding the use of these data onany other system, nor does the fact of distribution constitute orimply any such warranty.
In no event shall the USGS have any liability whatsoever forpayment of any consequential, incidental, indirect, special, ortort damages of any kind, including, but not limited to, any lossof profits arising out of use of or reliance on the geographicdata or arising out of the delivery, installation, operation, orsupport by USGS.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ARCE</formname>
               <formvern>8.3</formvern>
               <formcont>Fault traces</formcont>
               <filedec>tar and gzip</filedec>
               <transize>2</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/of02-301/faults/e00_files/orqfaults_dd.e00</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150204</metd>
      <metrd>20040726</metrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Peter N Schweitzer</cntper>
               <cntorg>USGS Midwest Area</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Collection manager, USGS Geoscience Data Clearinghouse, http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Mail Stop 95412201 Sunrise Valley Dr</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192-0002</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>703-648-6533</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>703-648-6252</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pschweitzer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
