<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Paula J. Helm</origin>
            <origin>Carol S. Breed</origin>
            <origin>Richard Tigges</origin>
            <origin>Patricia A. Garcia</origin>
            <pubdate>1995</pubdate>
            <title>Geometeorological data collected by the USGS Desert WindsProject at Gold Spring, Great Basin Desert, northeasternArizona, 1979 - 1992</title>
            <edition>1</edition>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>95-78</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Flagstaff, Arizona</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/1995/of95-078/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This data set contains meteorological data files pertaining tothe Gold Spring Geomet research site.  Documentation files anddata-accessing display software are also included.  Themeteorological data are wind speed, peak gust, wind direction,precipitation, air temperature, soil temperature, barometricpressure, and humidity.  Data from the monitoring station arevoluminous; 14 observations from each station are made asoften as ten times per hour, totalling more than a millionobservations per station per year.</abstract>
         <purpose>The primary purpose of this data set is to provide highresolution meteorological data and related surface geologicaland vegetation data for natural (e.g., uncultivated) desertsites where wind is or has been a major erosive ordepositional force.  The objectives are twofold: (1) toprovide the detailed field measurements needed to carry outquantitative studies of wind as an agent of surface geologicchange; and (2) to establish a baseline for defining the "normal" range of climatic conditions that can be expected tooccur on a decadal time scale, in areas consideredrepresentative of the major American deserts.  The Gold Springlocality was selected to represent that part of the GreatBasin Desert that extends into northeastern Arizona.  The long-term goal for acquiring and analyzing the Desert Winds Projectdata is to use them to address problems of land resourcedegradation by wind, whether resulting from climaticvariation (aridification) or human activities(desertification), or both.</purpose>
         <supplinf>Beginning in 1979, the USGS has been monitoring meteorologicaland surface processes in several desert areas of theSouthwestern United States.  These sophisticated monitoringstations combine observations of local weather and soilconditions, reporting as often as every six minutes, toprovide a comprehensive, detailed, long-term understanding ofthe processes affecting climate change in arid regions.Because they combine geological and meteorologicalobservations, the monitoring stations have been called "GEOMET" stations.  Five such stations have been installed andmaintained, as indicated in the following table:
&gt;Station       State       Latitude     Longitude   Open&gt;---------------------------------------------------------&gt;Gold Spring   Arizona     35.779167   -111.05500   791027&gt;Desert Wells  Arizona     33.702778   -113.81111   810109&gt;Yuma 1        Arizona     32.530556   -114.51250   820208&gt;Yuma 2        Arizona     32.530556   -114.51250   880521&gt;Owens Lake    California  36.355000   -117.94444   920519&gt;Jornada       New Mexico  32.575000   -106.78750   860918</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>19791027</begdate>
               <enddate>19921231</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>The stations used by the Desert Winds project are designed toprovide field-based physical data of sufficient resolution tosupport scientific studies of surface (mostly eolian)processes under monitored climatic conditions.  Because theycollect both geological and meteorological data, we refer tothem as Geomet stations. Located in remote areas, the stationsare automated and solar powered. They are unattended on adaily basis, but they do require scheduled servicing andrepair: weekly cleaning and checking by a custodian andperiodic servicing (including calibration) and repair,generally at 6-month intervals, by a skilled technician.  At1- or 2-hour intervals each station transmits digitaldata from its array of sensors to the GeostationaryOperational Environmental Satellite (GOES).  From GOES, thedata are relayed to (and stored at) the receiving station ofthe National Environmental Satellite Data Information Service(NESDIS) at Wallops Island, Virginia; NESDIS is operated by theNational Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration. From WallopsIsland, the data are transmitted via land lines to the U.S.Geological Survey computers at project headquarters inFlagstaff, Arizona.</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>Irregular</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-111.05500</westbc>
            <eastbc>-111.05500</eastbc>
            <northbc>35.779167</northbc>
            <southbc>35.779167</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>meteorology</themekey>
            <themekey>wind</themekey>
            <themekey>precipitation (atmospheric)</themekey>
            <themekey>air temperature</themekey>
            <themekey>soil temperature</themekey>
            <themekey>time series datasets</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>National Geologic Map Database Catalog themes, augmented</themekt>
            <themekey>0200 - Meteorology</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>Augmented FIPS 10-4 and FIPS 6-4</placekt>
            <placekey>04005 = Coconino</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Arizona</placekey>
            <placekey>NE 1/4 of Section 4 T27N R12E</placekey>
         </place>
         <temporal>
            <tempkt>None</tempkt>
            <tempkey>Present</tempkey>
         </temporal>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
               <cntper>Patricia A. Garcia</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Mail Stop 95802255 N. Gemini Drive</address>
               <city>Flagstaff</city>
               <state>AZ</state>
               <postal>86001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(520) 556-7246</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(520) 556-7090</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pgarcia@iflag2.wr.usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <native>This data set is provided on a single CD-ROM in ISO 9660 format.It was developed on a Sun SPARCstation 2 running SunOS 4.1.3 withOpenWindows version 3 and Sun C 2.01.</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>Quantitative attribute accuracy assessments are based on thenominal precision of the instruments used to measure themeteorological parameters.</attraccr>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>5.5</attraccv>
            <attracce>Degrees or 9.2% error in measured Wind Direction from19791027 through 19900808.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>2.5 to 5.0</attraccv>
            <attracce>Percent error in measured Wind Speed from 19791027 through19900808.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>2.5 to 5.0</attraccv>
            <attracce>Percent error in measured Peak Gust from 19791027 through19900808.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>0.01</attraccv>
            <attracce>Error in inches of measured Precipitation from 19791027through 19900808.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>1 to 2</attraccv>
            <attracce>Percent error in measured Soil and Air Temperature from19791027 through 19900808.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>3 to 5</attraccv>
            <attracce>Percent error in measured Relative Humidity from 19791027through 19900808.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>1 to 1.4</attraccv>
            <attracce>Percent error in measured Barometric Pressure from 19791027through 19900808.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>5</attraccv>
            <attracce>Percent error in measured Wind Direction from 19900809 through19921231.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>5</attraccv>
            <attracce>Percent error in measured Wind Speed from 19900809 through19921231.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>5</attraccv>
            <attracce>Percent error in measured Peak Gust from 19900809 through19921231.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>0.3</attraccv>
            <attracce>Percent error in measured Precipitation from 19900809 through19921231.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>0.2</attraccv>
            <attracce>Degrees error in measured Air Temperature when true valuelies between 0 and 60 degrees C, from 19900809 through19921231.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>0.6</attraccv>
            <attracce>Degrees C error in measured Air Temperature when true valuelies between -50 and 0 degrees C, from 19900809 through19921231.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>2</attraccv>
            <attracce>Percent error in measured Relative Humidity when true valuelies between 0 and 80%, from 19900809 through 19921231.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>0.1</attraccv>
            <attracce>Degrees C error in measured Soil Temperature when true valuelies between -20 and 50 degrees C, from 19900809 through19921231.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>0.6</attraccv>
            <attracce>Degrees C error in measured Soil Temperature when true valuelies between -50 and -20 degrees C, from 19900809 through19921231.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>0.3</attraccv>
            <attracce>Percent error in measured Barometric Pressure from 19900809through 19921231.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
      </attracc>
      <logic>The deposition or erosion of the sand cover causes a change indepth of the soil temperature probe over time.  The table belowshows the dates when the probe was checked, at what depth it wasfound, and the depth to which it was reset.
&gt;date  time event&gt;79300 0024 placed at 12.7 cm depth&gt;84046 1255 reset from depth of 30 cm to 12.7 cm&gt;88061 1331 reset from depth of 27.9 cm to 12.7 cm&gt;88089 1219 tip uncovered; reset to 12.7 cm depth&gt;88264 1207 tip uncovered; reset to 12.7 cm depth&gt;89081 1231 probe placed at new depth of 5 cm&gt;90235 1601 probe moved from a depth of 9 cm to 4 cm&gt;91164 1225 10cm depth sensor added to station&gt;91290 1225 20cm depth sensor added to station
The LaBarge Humidity sensor records numbers greater than 100percent because of a sensor calibration error.  Other instrumentchanges from LaBarge sensors to Handar sensors are listed below:
&gt;date  time sensor refitted&gt;90221 0001 Barometric Pressure&gt;90221 0001 Precipitation&gt;90270 1631 Wind direction&gt;90221 1419 Wind speed, Peak gust (6.1 m)&gt;91052 1437 Air temperature (1.2 m)&gt;91052 1525 Humidity
If the station is down, precipitation is not recorded, andtherefore, not added to the cumulative total.  If the station isoperating but transmissions are not received (missing), theprecipitation sensor is recording data at the site.  Once thetranmission problem is fixed and data are received, the cumulativeprecipitation value recorded is correct (although day and timeassociated with the rainfall is lost).</logic>
      <complete>Verification and correction of transmission errors and first-orderverification of some of the sensor values for accuracy andreliability are performed as the data are processed each day.
However, the data have not been error-checked on a file-by-filebasis at this time.  Also, because different sensor data are usedby different collaborators, some sensor data have not beenverified by the USGS staff of the Desert Winds Project.  Pleasecontact the DWP personnel if any problems are encountered withthis data.
The following facts about the data should be noted:
Loss of data due to transmission errors.  Occasionally, one ormore hours of data are not received because of transmission orother problems (see techinfo.doc).  Data are not interpolated tofill these lost data slots, and the time interval is not includedin the data file.  Therefore, some daily data files have less than24 hours of data.
Barometric pressure.  The elevation of the Gold Spring Geomet siteis relatively high (1667 m), and the  LaBarge barometric pressuresensor is not specifically calibrated for this site.  Thefollowing algorithm was used to convert Gold Spring barometricpressure values to inches of mercury at 0 m elevation (sea level)for the dates Oct 27, 1979 through Aug 8, 1990.  BP = BP + 5.5138
The following table shows the dates and times when sensors wereinoperative or for some other reason not reporting data.
&gt;beginning  ending&gt;date  time date  time inoperative sensors&gt;79323 0000 79323 2359 all&gt;79300 0024 79333 1024 Humidity&gt;80118 0000 80119 2359 all&gt;80122 0000 80122 2359 all&gt;80170 0000 80176 2359 all&gt;80285 0000 80287 2359 all&gt;80108 0000 81108 2359 all&gt;81158 0000 81159 2359 all&gt;81171 0000 81171 2359 all&gt;81176 0731 81188 0825 all&gt;81197 0931 81239 1225 all&gt;83176 1331 83179 1525 all&gt;83359 0000 83362 2359 all&gt;83179 0001 83196 1231 Wind direction&gt;83363 0001 83365 2355 Wind direction&gt;84108 1231 84158 1125 all&gt;84001 0000 84005 2359 Wind direction&gt;85228 1131 85276 1155 all&gt;85312 0000 85322 2359 all&gt;85324 0000 85337 2359 all&gt;86313 0531 86324 1225 all&gt;86148 1443 86325 1225 Barometric pressure&gt;87270 0000 87270 2359 all&gt;89248 1819 89324 1525 Precipitation&gt;89355 1537 89365 2355 all&gt;90001 0001 90087 1201 all&gt;90270 1725 90365 2355 Humidity&gt;91361 0000 91362 2359 all&gt;91001 0001 91052 1519 Humidity&gt;92345 0000 92365 2359 Wind speed and peak gust</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The original Gold Spring station was installed in 1979.This was a basic station, equipped with standard sensorsto record observations of a set of near-surface phenomena:average and peak-gust wind speeds, wind direction,precipitation, relative humidity, barometric pressure, airtemperature, and soil temperature.</procdesc>
            <procdate>19791027</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The Gold Spring site was retrofitted to superstationstatus in 1990.  The superstation has a much larger andmore varied complement of sensors than the basic station.
The current Geomet station at Gold Spring consists of twofree-standing towers, a solar power system, a data-collection platform (DCP) with a radio transmitter, andnineteen sensors that provide twenty-two parameters.</procdesc>
            <procdate>19900809</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Data collected from the automated sensors at each Geometsite must be directed through a series of steps within theDCP before becoming recognizable and usable for scientificresearch.  These steps are directed by a software programwithin the DCP.  Generally, one software "channel" foreach sensor controls the program actions required tomonitor it.  However, for the wind-speed sensors, twosoftware channels are needed for each hardware sensor; onechannel monitors average wind speed while the othermonitors peak gusts.  The user programs each channel byspecifying the monitoring schedule, the data-processingalgorithms, the location of the hardware sensor input tobe monitored, and the format in which the data are to betransmitted.  Once programmed, the DCP continuouslysamples data from each sensor on the programmed schedule.The original data signals are produced by the sensors invarious forms: some sensors produce analog voltages,others vary a resistance, and still others produceelectrical pulses.  Each signal is converted in real timeinto digital form by interface circuit cards.  Eachchannel's data-processing algorithm then converts thisdigital data into its final form (average, peak,temperature, count).  Lastly, the data are stored in theDCP memory, where they remain until transmitted on theGOES radio.
The GOES satellites are in geostationary orbit above theEarth and are nominally stationed 23,000 miles (37,000 km)above the equator.  The two available for our use are GOESEast, at approximately long 75 deg. W., and GOES West, atapproximately long 135 deg. W.  At present, the GoldSpring Geomet station is assigned a channel and time sloton GOES West.
Once an hour the DCP program collects Geomet data frommemory and formats them so that they can be transmitted inpseudo-binary form, a compression code that enablestransmission within the time frame allotted by NESDIS.Transmission to GOES is in the 401.7- to 402.0-Mhz band.GOES West receives this signal and retransmits it as an1694.5-MHz S-band signal to a receiving station at WallopsIsland, Virginia.  At Wallops Island, the Data CollectionSystem Automatic Processing Subsystem sorts and stores thedata in user files.  High-speed dedicated or low-speeddial-up lines transfer the data to Desert Winds projectheadquarters in Flagstaff, where software performs aseries of checks to document missing or erroneous data.Finally, software converts the pseudo-binary code toASCII, separates it by station and time, formats, andstores the data on disks and tapes for analysis byscientists.  Detailed coding of the data for quality,changes in sensors, and gaps due to NESDIS or Geometstation malfunctions is necessary to prepare the data forpublication.</procdesc>
            <procdate>19791027</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Point</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>1</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>GEOMET station data record</enttypl>
            <enttypd>The set of all measurements reported from a GEOMET stationhaving the same temporal coordinate.</enttypd>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>wind speed at 6.1m</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Velocity of the wind at the indicated height above theground at the station location.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>The anemometer consists of three cups mounted on a rotorshaft that rotates on instrument-quality stainless steelbearings.  A magnet on the rotor shaft moves near a reedswitch (basic station) or a Hall Effect transducer(superstation), which detects the field of the rotatingmagnet.  This detected field produces a pulse rate inproportion to the wind velocity.  A single anemometer ismounted to the top of the DCP tower mast at the basicstation.  Three anemometers are mounted on the wind towerat each superstation, at 1.2, 2.7, and 6.1 m above theground.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>150</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>miles per hour</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>0.01</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>-99</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The value -99 indicates a measurement that was notmade because the sensor was not functioningproperly, the station was not functioningproperly, the sensor was not installed, or thestation was configured to record this measurementat intervals other than that represented by thecurrent time.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Helm, P.J., Breed, C.S., Tigges, R., and Garcia,P.A., 1995, Geometeorological data collected bythe USGS Desert Winds Project at Gold Spring,Great Basin Desert, northeastern Arizona, 1979 -1992: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report95-78. File docfiles/techinfo.doc.</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <begdatea>19791027</begdatea>
            <enddatea>19921231</enddatea>
            <attrvai>
               <attrva>5</attrva>
               <attrvae>Attribute value accuracy given is the maximum expecteddeviation of the measured value from the true value,expressed as a percentage of the true value.
Operations of the anemometers are checked each timethey are rebuilt.  In 1993 we began calibration in awind tunnel, which produces a calibration constant foreach instrument.  This constant is entered into theDCP program upon installation of the instrument.  Whenplaced on a tower in the field, anemometers areconsidered to be working properly if the daily averageof anemometer readings at each of three heights plotsas a straight line on a log-height, linear average-wind-speed graph.  This field method, however, onlyinsures consistent operations between anemometers andis not a true calibration against a known standard.At present, anomalies in the wind-speed data arecommon, and it is difficult to distinguish signal fromnoise.</attrvae>
            </attrvai>
            <attrmfrq>30 minutes 19791027 through 198004246 minutes 19800425 through 19921231</attrmfrq>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>wind speed at 2.7m and 1.2m</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Velocity of the wind at the indicated height above theground at the station location.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>The anemometer consists of three cups mounted on a rotorshaft that rotates on instrument-quality stainless steelbearings.  A magnet on the rotor shaft moves near a reedswitch (basic station) or a Hall Effect transducer(superstation), which detects the field of the rotatingmagnet.  This detected field produces a pulse rate inproportion to the wind velocity.  A single anemometer ismounted to the top of the DCP tower mast at the basicstation.  Three anemometers are mounted on the wind towerat each superstation, at 1.2, 2.7, and 6.1 m above theground.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>150</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>miles per hour</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>0.01</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>-99</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The value -99 indicates a measurement that was notmade because the sensor was not functioningproperly, the station was not functioningproperly, the sensor was not installed, or thestation was configured to record this measurementat intervals other than that represented by thecurrent time.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Helm, P.J., Breed, C.S., Tigges, R., and Garcia,P.A., 1995, Geometeorological data collected bythe USGS Desert Winds Project at Gold Spring,Great Basin Desert, northeastern Arizona, 1979 -1992: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report95-78. File docfiles/techinfo.doc.</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>-77</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The value -77 indicates a measurement that wouldhave been made had a sensor that was later addedto the station been installed at the time.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Helm, P.J., Breed, C.S., Tigges, R., and Garcia,P.A., 1995, Geometeorological data collected bythe USGS Desert Winds Project at Gold Spring,Great Basin Desert, northeastern Arizona, 1979 -1992: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report95-78. File docfiles/techinfo.doc.</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <begdatea>19900809</begdatea>
            <enddatea>19921231</enddatea>
            <attrvai>
               <attrva>5</attrva>
               <attrvae>Attribute value accuracy given is the maximum expecteddeviation of the measured value from the true value,expressed as a percentage of the true value.
Operations of the anemometers are checked each timethey are rebuilt.  In 1993 we began calibration in awind tunnel, which produces a calibration constant foreach instrument.  This constant is entered into theDCP program upon installation of the instrument.  Whenplaced on a tower in the field, anemometers areconsidered to be working properly if the daily averageof anemometer readings at each of three heights plotsas a straight line on a log-height, linear average-wind-speed graph.  This field method, however, onlyinsures consistent operations between anemometers andis not a true calibration against a known standard.At present, anomalies in the wind-speed data arecommon, and it is difficult to distinguish signal fromnoise.</attrvae>
            </attrvai>
            <attrmfrq>30 minutes 19791027 through 198004246 minutes 19800425 through 19921231</attrmfrq>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>peak gust at 6.1m</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Maximum value of wind speed at the given height attainedsince the previous reported value.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>surmise</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>150</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>miles per hour</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>0.01</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>-99</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The value -99 indicates a measurement that was notmade because the sensor was not functioningproperly, the station was not functioningproperly, the sensor was not installed, or thestation was configured to record this measurementat intervals other than that represented by thecurrent time.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Helm, P.J., Breed, C.S., Tigges, R., and Garcia,P.A., 1995, Geometeorological data collected bythe USGS Desert Winds Project at Gold Spring,Great Basin Desert, northeastern Arizona, 1979 -1992: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report95-78. File docfiles/techinfo.doc.</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <begdatea>19791027</begdatea>
            <enddatea>19921231</enddatea>
            <attrmfrq>30 minutes 19791027 through 198004246 minutes 19800425 through 19921231</attrmfrq>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>peak gust at 1.2m</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Maximum value of wind speed at the given height attainedsince the previous reported value.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>surmise</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>150</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>miles per hour</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>0.01</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>-99</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The value -99 indicates a measurement that was notmade because the sensor was not functioningproperly, the station was not functioningproperly, the sensor was not installed, or thestation was configured to record this measurementat intervals other than that represented by thecurrent time.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Helm, P.J., Breed, C.S., Tigges, R., and Garcia,P.A., 1995, Geometeorological data collected bythe USGS Desert Winds Project at Gold Spring,Great Basin Desert, northeastern Arizona, 1979 -1992: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report95-78. File docfiles/techinfo.doc.</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>-77</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The value -77 indicates a measurement that wouldhave been made had a sensor that was later addedto the station been installed at the time.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Helm, P.J., Breed, C.S., Tigges, R., and Garcia,P.A., 1995, Geometeorological data collected bythe USGS Desert Winds Project at Gold Spring,Great Basin Desert, northeastern Arizona, 1979 -1992: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report95-78. File docfiles/techinfo.doc.</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <begdatea>19900809</begdatea>
            <enddatea>19921231</enddatea>
            <attrmfrq>6 minutes 19900809 through 19921231</attrmfrq>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>wind direction</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Direction from which the wind comes, with zero valuesindicating true north and positive values indicatingangular distance from true north clockwise (i.e. 90degrees is due east).</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>This instrument is a heavy-duty aluminum and stainlesssteel wind vane that is coupled to a precision micro-torque potentiometer, which has low rotational torque.The wire-wound potentiometer produces an output resistancethat varies in proportion to the wind direction.  The winddirection vane is mounted on the DCP tower at the top ofthe 6.1-m mast.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>359.9</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>degrees</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>0.01</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>-99</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The value -99 indicates a measurement that was notmade because the sensor was not functioningproperly, the station was not functioningproperly, the sensor was not installed, or thestation was configured to record this measurementat intervals other than that represented by thecurrent time.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Helm, P.J., Breed, C.S., Tigges, R., and Garcia,P.A., 1995, Geometeorological data collected bythe USGS Desert Winds Project at Gold Spring,Great Basin Desert, northeastern Arizona, 1979 -1992: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report95-78. File docfiles/techinfo.doc.</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <begdatea>19791027</begdatea>
            <enddatea>19921231</enddatea>
            <attrvai>
               <attrva>5.5</attrva>
               <attrvae>For measurements made from 19791027 through 19900808the attribute value accuracy is given as within 5.5degrees of the true value or 9.2 percent of the truevalue, whichever is greater.  For measurements madefrom 19900809 through 19921231 the accuracy is 5percent of the true value.</attrvae>
            </attrvai>
            <attrmfrq>30 minutes 19791027 through 198004246 minutes 19800425 through 19921231</attrmfrq>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>precipitation</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Cumulative yearly precipitation at the station site.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>The precipitation sensor is a funnel with a 20-cm-diameterorifice to collect and direct rain to a tipping bucketmechanism.  The funnel and mechanism are housed in a metalcylinder that is secured to a corner of the DCP tower,1.8m above the ground.  Coupled to the tipping bucket is amagnetically activated reed switch, which momentarilycloses each time the bucket tips; 0.25 mm of collectedwater causes the bucket to tip.  The water drains out thebottom of the gauge and a second bucket moves intoposition to collect more water; the procedure is repeateduntil no more is available for collection.  Switchclosures are counted by an interface circuit in the DCP.This hardware count is periodically added to a cumulativecount maintained by DCP software.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>99.9</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>inches</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>0.01</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>-99</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The value -99 indicates a measurement that was notmade because the sensor was not functioningproperly, the station was not functioningproperly, the sensor was not installed, or thestation was configured to record this measurementat intervals other than that represented by thecurrent time.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Helm, P.J., Breed, C.S., Tigges, R., and Garcia,P.A., 1995, Geometeorological data collected bythe USGS Desert Winds Project at Gold Spring,Great Basin Desert, northeastern Arizona, 1979 -1992: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report95-78. File docfiles/techinfo.doc.</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <begdatea>19791027</begdatea>
            <enddatea>19921231</enddatea>
            <attrvai>
               <attrva>0.01</attrva>
               <attrvae>Attribute value accuracy given indicates the maximumexpected deviation of the measured value from the truevalue, in inches, for the basic station (installedfrom 19791027 through 19900808).  For the period19900809 through 19921231, the maximum expected erroris 0.3 percent of the true value.</attrvae>
            </attrvai>
            <attrmfrq>30 minutes 19791027 through 198004246 minutes 19800425 through 1990080812 minutes 19900809 through 19921231</attrmfrq>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>air temperature at 6.1m and at 1.2m</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Temperature of ambient air at elevations 6.1 meters or 1.2meters above the base of the station.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>The air temperature sensor is a solid-state precisionlinear thermistor placed in a compact cylindricalassembly.  The resistance of the thermistor is inverselyproportional to the temperature.  The resistance ismeasured by a voltage divider circuit, and the result islinearized by a look-up-table routine.  A convection-aspirated shield around the thermistor reduces the effectof solar radiation on air temperature and protects thethermistor from precipitation. This instrument is mountedeither to the DCP tower at the 1.8 m-level (for the basicstation), or to the wind tower at the 1.2- and 6.1-mlevels (for the superstation).</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>-50</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>50</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>degrees Celsius</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>0.01</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>-99</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The value -99 indicates a measurement that was notmade because the sensor was not functioningproperly, the station was not functioningproperly, the sensor was not installed, or thestation was configured to record this measurementat intervals other than that represented by thecurrent time.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Helm, P.J., Breed, C.S., Tigges, R., and Garcia,P.A., 1995, Geometeorological data collected bythe USGS Desert Winds Project at Gold Spring,Great Basin Desert, northeastern Arizona, 1979 -1992: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report95-78. File docfiles/techinfo.doc.</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>-77</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The value -77 indicates a measurement that wouldhave been made had a sensor that was later addedto the station been installed at the time.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Helm, P.J., Breed, C.S., Tigges, R., and Garcia,P.A., 1995, Geometeorological data collected bythe USGS Desert Winds Project at Gold Spring,Great Basin Desert, northeastern Arizona, 1979 -1992: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report95-78. File docfiles/techinfo.doc.</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <begdatea>19900809</begdatea>
            <enddatea>19921231</enddatea>
            <attrvai>
               <attrva>0.6</attrva>
               <attrvae>Attribute value accuracy is the maximum expectederror (in degrees C) in the measured value of airtemperature when the true value of air temperaturelies between -50 and 0 degrees C.  When true airtemperature lies between 0 and 60 degrees C, themaximum expected error is 0.2 degrees C.</attrvae>
            </attrvai>
            <attrmfrq>12 minutes</attrmfrq>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>air temperature at 1.8m</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Temperature of ambient air 1.8 meters above the base ofthe station.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>same as for air temperature at 6.1m</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>-30</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>70</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>degrees Celsius</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>0.01</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>-99</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The value -99 indicates a measurement that was notmade because the sensor was not functioningproperly, the station was not functioningproperly, the sensor was not installed, or thestation was configured to record this measurementat intervals other than that represented by thecurrent time.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Helm, P.J., Breed, C.S., Tigges, R., and Garcia,P.A., 1995, Geometeorological data collected bythe USGS Desert Winds Project at Gold Spring,Great Basin Desert, northeastern Arizona, 1979 -1992: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report95-78. File docfiles/techinfo.doc.</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <begdatea>19791027</begdatea>
            <enddatea>19900808</enddatea>
            <attrvai>
               <attrva>2</attrva>
               <attrvae>Attribute value accuracy is the maximum expectederror (as a percentage of the true value) in themeasured value of air temperature.</attrvae>
            </attrvai>
            <attrmfrq>30 minutes 19791027 through 198004246 minutes 19800425 through 19900808</attrmfrq>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>humidity</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Relative humidity of the ambient air near the station.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Measurement of relative humidity requires a temperaturesensor combined with a humidity sensor.The temperature-sensor part of this combined instrument isthe same as the air-temperature sensor described above.The humidity sensor is a capacitor consisting of ametallic grid deposited on a glass plate and covered by ahygroscopic polymer film.  The dielectric constant of thepolymer material increases with the amount of waterabsorbed, such that capacitance depends on the relativehumidity.  The basic response to changes in humidity israpid (approximately 1 second to reach 90 percent of thefinal value).  However, a filter that protects the sensorfrom dust and physical damage slows the response to 20 to30 seconds.  The humidity-recording part of this sensor ismounted next to the air-temperature thermistor, so thatboth are sampling the same volume of air.  The instrumentis mounted on the base of the DCP tower (basic station) orat the 1.2-m level of the wind tower (superstation).</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>100</rdommax>
                  <attrmres>0.01</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>-99</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The value -99 indicates a measurement that was notmade because the sensor was not functioningproperly, the station was not functioningproperly, the sensor was not installed, or thestation was configured to record this measurementat intervals other than that represented by thecurrent time.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Helm, P.J., Breed, C.S., Tigges, R., and Garcia,P.A., 1995, Geometeorological data collected bythe USGS Desert Winds Project at Gold Spring,Great Basin Desert, northeastern Arizona, 1979 -1992: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report95-78. File docfiles/techinfo.doc.</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <begdatea>19791027</begdatea>
            <enddatea>19921231</enddatea>
            <attrvai>
               <attrva>5</attrva>
               <attrvae>Attribute value accuracy is the maximum expectederror (as a percentage of the true value) in themeasured value of relative humidity.  This maximumapplies to values from 19791027 through 19900808.For periods from 19900809 through 19921231, themaximum expected error is 2 percent when the truevalue is between 0 and 80.</attrvae>
            </attrvai>
            <attrmfrq>30 minutes 19791027 through 198004246 minutes 19800425 through 199008081 hour, 19900809 through 19921231</attrmfrq>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>barometric pressure</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Pressure of the ambient air near the station.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>The barometric-pressure sensor is an aneroid barometerthat utilizes an evacuated bellows sensitive to changes inabsolute pressure.  As pressure changes, motion of thebellows moves a contact across a precision potentiometer,producing an output resistance proportional to thebarometric pressure.  Housed in a weather-proof container,the barometer is mounted on the DCP tower base tripod.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>35</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>inches of mercury</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>0.001</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>-99</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The value -99 indicates a measurement that was notmade because the sensor was not functioningproperly, the station was not functioningproperly, the sensor was not installed, or thestation was configured to record this measurementat intervals other than that represented by thecurrent time.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Helm, P.J., Breed, C.S., Tigges, R., and Garcia,P.A., 1995, Geometeorological data collected bythe USGS Desert Winds Project at Gold Spring,Great Basin Desert, northeastern Arizona, 1979 -1992: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report95-78. File docfiles/techinfo.doc.</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <begdatea>19791027</begdatea>
            <enddatea>19921231</enddatea>
            <attrvai>
               <attrva>1.4</attrva>
               <attrvae>Attribute value accuracy is the maximum expectederror (as a percentage of the true value) in themeasured value of barometric pressure.  This maximumapplies to values from 19791027 through 19900808.For periods from 19900809 through 19921231, themaximum expected error is 0.3 percent of the truevalue.</attrvae>
            </attrvai>
            <attrmfrq>30 minutes 19791027 through 198004246 minutes 19800425 through 199008081 hour, 19900809 through 19921231</attrmfrq>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>soil temperature at 4cm, 10cm, and 20cm</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Temperature of the soil at the depths indicated below thestation.  From 19791027 through 19900808 the valuereported is soil temperature at 12.7cm (it is given in thedata files where the 10cm value is later stored).Occasional problems with instrument disturbance affectingthe depth of these sensors are described in the dataquality report.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>This sensor is a precision linear thermistor housed in awaterproof, stainless steel enclosure.  The resistance ofthe thermistor is inversely proportional to the soiltemperature.  Resistance is measured by a voltage dividercircuit, and the result is linearized by a look-up-tableroutine.  The probes lie in the soil at depths of 4cm,10cm, and 20 cm, and they are connected to the DCP byweather- and animal-proof cables.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>-50</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>70</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>degrees Celsius</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>0.01</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>-99</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The value -99 indicates a measurement that was notmade because the sensor was not functioningproperly, the station was not functioningproperly, the sensor was not installed, or thestation was configured to record this measurementat intervals other than that represented by thecurrent time.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Helm, P.J., Breed, C.S., Tigges, R., and Garcia,P.A., 1995, Geometeorological data collected bythe USGS Desert Winds Project at Gold Spring,Great Basin Desert, northeastern Arizona, 1979 -1992: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report95-78. File docfiles/techinfo.doc.</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>-77</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The value -77 indicates a measurement that wouldhave been made had a sensor that was later addedto the station been installed at the time.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Helm, P.J., Breed, C.S., Tigges, R., and Garcia,P.A., 1995, Geometeorological data collected bythe USGS Desert Winds Project at Gold Spring,Great Basin Desert, northeastern Arizona, 1979 -1992: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report95-78. File docfiles/techinfo.doc.</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <begdatea>19791027</begdatea>
            <enddatea>19921231</enddatea>
            <attrvai>
               <attrva>2</attrva>
               <attrvae>Attribute value accuracy is the maximum expectederror (as a percentage of the true value) in themeasured value of soil temperature.  This maximumapplies to values obtained from 19791027 through19900808.
For measurements between 19900809 and 19921231, themaximum expected error (in degrees C) in the measuredvalue of soil temperature when the true value liesbetween -50 and -20 degrees C is 0.6; when true airtemperature lies between -20 and 50 degrees C, themaximum expected error is 0.1 degrees C.</attrvae>
            </attrvai>
            <attrmfrq>30 minutes 19791027 through 198004246 minutes 19800425 through 199008081 hour, 19900809 through 19921231</attrmfrq>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Peter N. Schweitzer</cntper>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Mail Stop 918 National CenterU.S. Geological Survey12201 Sunrise Valley Drive</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(703) 648-6533</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(703) 648-6560</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pschweitzer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 95-78</resdesc>
      <distliab>Although all data and software published on this CD-ROM have beenused by the USGS, no warranty, expressed or implied, is made bythe USGS as to the accuracy of the data and related materials orthe functioning of the software.  The act of distribution shallnot constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumedby the USGS in the use of these data, software, or relatedmaterials.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>binary</formname>
               <formvern>0</formvern>
               <formspec>The binary format is provided to enable the data to bestored and accessed on systems with smaller capacity,and to speed retrieval of information from the files.No files in the binary format are provided on the CD-ROM.  The binary file format is as follows:
The first four bytes of the data files are used as asignature to identify the file format.  Signaturebytes are interpreted as follows:&gt;byte 0: 'D' for "Desert"&gt;byte 1: 'W' for "Winds"&gt;byte 2: 'b' if the file is binary, 'a' if ASCII&gt;byte 3: format version number and byte ordering scheme:
If file is ASCII, version number is a numeral '0'through '9'.
If file is binary, the high-order bit indicates thebyte ordering scheme of the data, and the rest of thebits indicate the version number.
If the high-order bit is set, the data are MSB-ordered ("big endian"); the high-order byte of a two-byte word is stored in the low-order address. (e.g.Macintosh, SUN)
If the high-order bit is clear, the data are LSB-ordered ("little endian"); the low-order byte of a two-byte word is stored in the low-order address. (e.g.Intel, VAX)
The version indicator in the file format allows up toten varieties of files to be read and written by thelow-level data handling routines.  Only version 0 ispresently supported.
Following the four-byte signature, the GEOMET stationlocation is given as degrees, minutes, and secondslatitude encoded as two-byte two's complement binaryintegers followed by  degrees, minutes, and secondslongitude encoded the same way.
Data records are fixed-length binary records eachcontaining 17 two-byte unsigned integers as follows:
&gt;01. Year&gt;02. Day&gt;03. Minute of the day, i.e. hour times sixty plus minute&gt;04. Humidity times 100&gt;05. Precipitation times 100&gt;06. Barometric pressure times 1000&gt;07. Wind direction times 100&gt;08. Wind speed at 6.1m times 100&gt;09. Peak gust at 6.1m times 100&gt;10. Wind speed at 2.7m times 100&gt;11. Wind speed at 1.2m times 100&gt;12. Peak gust at 1.2m times 100&gt;13. Air temperature at 6.1m plus 50, times 100&gt;14. Air temperature at 1.2m plus 50, times 100&gt;15. Soil temperature at 4cm depth plus 50, times 100&gt;16. Soil temperature at 10cm depth plus 50, times 100&gt;17. Soil temperature at 20cm depth plus 50, times 100
Note that if the byte ordering indicated by the filesignature is little-endian, all of the two-bytequantities will be encoded least-significant bytefirst, but if the byte ordering is big-endian, the two-byte quantities will be encoded most-significant bytefirst.</formspec>
               <formcont>Daily records of Gold Spring GEOMET station data from19791027 through 19921231</formcont>
               <transize>38</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/1995/of95-078/DATA/GS/</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150202</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Peter N. Schweitzer</cntper>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Collection manager, USGS Geoscience Data Clearinghouse, http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Mail Stop 918 National CenterU.S. Geological Survey12201 Sunrise Valley Drive</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(703) 648-6533</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(703) 648-6560</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pschweitzer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
