<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Lorenson, Thomas D.</origin>
            <origin>Kvenvolden, Keith A.</origin>
            <pubdate>1995</pubdate>
            <title>Methane in coastal sea water, sea ice, and bottomsediments, Beaufort Sea, Alaska</title>
            <edition>1</edition>
            <geoform>map</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>95-70</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Menlo Park, CA</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/1995/of95-070/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This report summarizes data acquired from 1990 to 1994 forthe gas-hydrate portion of the USGS project "Permafrostand gas hydrate as possible sources of methane" of theUSGS Global Change and Climate History program.  Theobjective of this project has been to test the hypothesisthat gas hydrate deposits of the Beaufort Sea continentalshelf are destabilized by the ~10°C temperature increasethat has resulted from the Holocene transgression of theArctic Ocean.  To test this idea we have selected an areaoff the north coast of Alaska centered on Harrison Bay. Wehave measured the concentration of methane in surficialsediments, in the water column when ice is present andabsent, and in seasonal sea ice. Our results show thatmore methane is present in the water when ice is presentthan when ice is absent, and that methane is also presentwithin the ice itself, often at higher concentrations thanin the water.  Thus the Beaufort Sea shelf of Alaska is aseasonal source of methane.  The primary source of thismethane has not yet been defined, but gas hydrate is areasonable candidate.</abstract>
         <purpose>The objective of this project has been to test thehypothesis that gas hydrate deposits of the Beaufort Seacontinental shelf are destabilized by the ~10°Ctemperature increase that has resulted from the Holocenetransgression of the Arctic Ocean.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>19920501</begdate>
               <enddate>19940826</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>The surveys were undertaken during the last week of Apriland first week of May 1992, the middle of April 1993, thelatter portion of April 1994, the second week of September1993, and the later portion of August 1994.</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-152.20717</westbc>
            <eastbc>-144.99833</eastbc>
            <northbc>72.64800</northbc>
            <southbc>70.05267</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>marine chemistry</themekey>
            <themekey>gas hydrate resources</themekey>
            <themekey>petroleum</themekey>
            <themekey>sea ice concentration</themekey>
            <themekey>geospatial datasets</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>methane</themekey>
            <themekey>gas hydrate</themekey>
            <themekey>petroleum</themekey>
            <themekey>sea ice</themekey>
            <themekey>sea water</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>National Geologic Map Database Catalog themes, augmented</themekt>
            <themekey>1300 - Marine Geology</themekey>
            <themekey>1900 - Geochemistry</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>Augmented FIPS 10-4 and FIPS 6-4</placekt>
            <placekey>02185 = North Slope</placekey>
            <placekey>OC10 = Arctic</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Beaufort Sea</placekey>
            <placekey>Alaska</placekey>
            <placekey>AK</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Thomas D. Lorenson</cntper>
               <cntorg>Branch of Pacific Marine Geology</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Mail Stop 999U.S. Geological Survey345 Middlefield Road</address>
               <city>Menlo Park</city>
               <state>CA</state>
               <postal>94025</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(415) 354-3094</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(415) 354-3191</cntfax>
            <cntemail>lorenson@octopus.wr.usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/1995/of95-070/core/meta/figure2.gif</browsen>
         <browsed>The study area showing six north-south transects with thewater and ice station locations.</browsed>
         <browset>GIF</browset>
      </browse>
      <datacred>The project has been conducted in collaboration with theUniversity of Washington and the University of Hawaii. Wethank (1) M.D. Lilley, E.J. Olson, and E. McLaughlin, Schoolof Oceanography, University of Washington, for the informationon methane concentrations, methane oxidation rates, andnutrient concentrations in seawater; (2) B.N. Popp, F. J.Sansone, and T. Rust, SOEST, University of Hawaii, for theisotopic analyses of methane. We are grateful to (1) P.W.Barnes, U.S. Geological Survey, for guidence in Arcticoperations, and (2) E. Reimnitz for help in collectingsediment samples for gas analyses. This work is supported bythe USGS Global Change and Climate History Program.</datacred>
      <native>Macintosh</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>See process descriptions for analytical methods.  For moreinformation about attribute accuracy, users are urged tocontact the authors.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>CTD (conductivity, temperature, depth) casts were made at eachstation. CTD data was recorded internally by a Seacat 19 CTDprobe made by Sea Bird of Seattle Washington. The data wasdownloaded onto a computer where it was processed usingSeasoft Version 4.016. The sub-programs LOOPEDIT, BINAVE, thenDERIVE were utilized to process the raw data. The data wereaveraged into 0.5m intervals. The upcast and downcast wereevaluated, and only one cast is plotted. In general the upcastwas used because the sensors showed less fluctuation.</logic>
      <complete>Methane oxidation rate is given only for samples collected in1992 and 1993.  Isotopic compositions are given only forsamples collected in 1994.  Nutrients are given only forsamples collected in 1992.</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Measurements of sea water.In our survey, we measured methane concentration insea water under the ice on six primary transects fromnearshore to the shelf break at water depths rangingfrom 2.5 to 88m from Cape Halkett east to MikkelsenBay, Alaska. Other surface water samples were taken atvarious locations where water depths ranged from 2 to20m within the area between Camden Bay and theColville River Delta. One oceanic surface water samplewas also collected in April 1993 at 72° 38' N.latitude . The surveys were undertaken during the lastweek of April and first week of May 1992, the middleof April 1993, the latter portion of April 1994, thesecond week of September 1993, and the later portionof August 1994. At each station in April and May, a 23-cm diameter hole was drilled through the 2-m thickfirst-year ice. Niskin bottles (1.7 l) were attachedat intervals to a line lowered to the seafloor andsubsequently tripped to collect water samples formethane determinations. In September 1993 and August1994, when no ice was present, a boat was used totransit to stations. As each Niskin bottle wasrecovered, 100 cm3 of water was transferred to a 140cm3 syringe. A heat lamp to prevent the water fromfreezing during April and May surveys. In thelaboratory at the end of each day's field work, 40 cm3of ultra-pure nitrogen were added to each of thesyringes, and methane was extracted from the waterinto the nitrogen at room temperature by shaking thesyringe, following a method modified from McAullife(1971). A portion of the resulting gas mixture wasmeasured for methane content by gas chromatography.Multiple extractions were used on several samples todetermine an empirical extraction efficiencycoefficient which was utilized with the remainder ofthe samples that were extracted only once. Ouranalyzed gas standard contained 10 ppm ±2% methane innitrogen. Duplicate samples were analyzed for eachwater depth with an average standard deviationof ±0.6nM.
CTD (conductivity, temperature, depth) casts were madeat each station. CTD data was recorded internally by aSeacat 19 CTD probe made by Sea Bird of SeattleWashington. The data was downloaded onto a computerwhere it was processed using Seasoft Version 4.016.The sub-programs LOOPEDIT, BINAVE, then DERIVE wereutilized to process the raw data. The data wereaveraged into 0.5m intervals. The upcast and downcastwere evaluated, and only one cast is plotted. Ingeneral the upcast was used because the sensors showedless fluctuation.
The methods utilized to measure nutrients in thisstudy were adapted from older colorimetric proceduresand are described in detail by Whitledge and others,(1981). A basic description of each method, conductedon a Technicon Autoanalyzer System, follows.Phosphate is determined as phosphomolybdic acid whichin its reduced form in the presence of antimony has anabsorption maximum at 880 nm. The method is basicallyan automated version of the procedure of Murphy andRiley (1962).
Orthosilicic acid is determined by its reaction withmolybdate in aqueous acidic solution to formsilicomolybdic acid. In this procedure, which isbasically that of Armstrong and others, (1967),stannous chloride is used to reduce silicomolybdicacid to the heteropolic acid which has an absorptionmaximum at 820 nm.
Nitrite is determined by the Greiss reaction in whichsulfanilamide and N-(1-Napthyl)ethylenediaminedihydrochloride react with nitrite in aqueous acidicsolution to form an intensely pink diazo dye with anabsorption maximum at 540 nm (Bendschneider andRobinson, 1952). Nitrate, after it is reduced tonitrite by passage through a column of copperizedcadmium filings, is determined in an identical mannerto nitrite (Wood and others 1967). This analysis givesthe sum of nitrate + nitrite, and nitrate isdetermined by difference.
Ammonium is determined by the Berthelot reaction inwhich hypochlorous acid and phenol react with ammoniumin aqueous alkaline solution to form indophenol blue,an intensely blue chromophore with an absorptionmaximum at 637 nm. The method utilized is amodification of the procedure reported by Slawyk andMacIsaac (1972).</procdesc>
            <procdate>1994</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Measurements of sea ice.The methane content of sea ice was measured at 51stations in 1993 and 1994. A 1m long by 7.6 cmdiameter ice corer with an extension was used to corethrough the ice to sea water. The ice core was laidout on the sea ice, measured and cut into 10 cmsections. Selected intervals were chosen, then placedin 1-liter friction sealed cans equipped with 2 septaports, sealed, and kept frozen. At the fieldlaboratory, each sample was weighed, then theheadspace within the can was purged with ultra purenitrogen for 5 minutes at flow rates exceeding 200ml/min. Tests on the methane content of the purgedheadspace with the frozen ice core inside yieldedconcentrations less than 0.1 ppm. The cans containingice samples were placed in hot water baths andstabilized at approximately 20°C. Each can was shakenby hand for about 30 seconds to partition thedissolved methane between the water and the nitrogenheadspace. Next, a syringe containing 30 ml of ultrapure grade nitrogen was injected into the can, then 30ml of the resulting mixture of headspace and gas wasremoved and analyzed for methane content in the samemanner as described for sea water samples. The volumeof headspace in the can was determined by the weightof the ice sample, assuming that once melted the wateroccupied a volume of 1 ml/gm.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1994</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Measurements of sea-floor sediment.Sediment samples were taken in May 1992 operating fromthe ice canopy. A hole was augured in the ice, throughwhich a 45 x 7.5 cm core barrel with an auger cuttinghead was lowered. The core barrel was attached to1.5-m long connecting stems in series up to a maximumlength of 15.5 m. Once on the ocean bottom, the corebarrel was rotated by hand with the aid of a T-baruntil no further penetration was achieved. Uponretrieval, the liner containing sediment was extrudedonto the ice. The least disturbed 10-cm long (a volumeof about 450 ml wet sediment) section of the core waschosen and placed in a septa-equipped 1-liter samplecan. Seawater was added to the brim of the can, then200 ml of water was removed, creating a 200 mlheadspace. About 2-3 grams of sodium azide was addedas a biocide. The can was sealed, then purged withhelium at a flow rate estimated to be greater then 300ml/min for 5 minutes. The samples were kept frozenuntil analysis at our Menlo Park laboratories.</procdesc>
            <procdate>199205</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Measurements of methane isotopic composition.A limited number of measurements of the carbonisotopic composition of methane were made at theUniversity of Hawaii. The results reveal a wide rangeof values from -31.1 to -80.5 o/oo.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1995</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Brian N. Popp</cntper>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
                     <address>2525 Correa Road, HIG 415University of Hawai`i-Manoa</address>
                     <city>Honolulu</city>
                     <state>HI</state>
                     <postal>96822</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>(808) 956-6206</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>(808) 956-2538</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>popp@kiawe.soest.hawaii.edu</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Point</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>Entity Point</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>88</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <latres>0.00016667</latres>
            <longres>0.00016667</longres>
            <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
         </geograph>
      </horizsys>
      <vertdef>
         <depthsys>
            <depthdn>mean sea-level</depthdn>
            <depthres>1</depthres>
            <depthdu>meters</depthdu>
            <depthem>Attribute values</depthem>
         </depthsys>
      </vertdef>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>water sample</enttypl>
            <enttypds>USGS OFR 95-70</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Station</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Identifier for the sample locality, composed asYYMsssR where YY is the last two digits of the year,M is the month (no samples were taken from Octoberthrough December, thus one digit suffices), sss is thesite number, and R (literally) is present to indicatethat the site was occupied at an earlier date.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Latitude</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>North latitude of the sample locality.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>FIPS 70-1</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>90</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>decimal degrees</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>0.00016667</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Longitude</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Longitude of the sample locality.  Negative values aremeasured westward from the Prime Meridian, positivevalues are measured eastward from the Prime Meridian.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>FIPS 70-1</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>180</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>decimal degrees</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>0.00016667</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Date</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Calendar date when sample was collected, expressed asa FIPS date using the form YYYYMMDD where YYYYsignifies the year, MM the month, and DD the day(month and day beginning with 1).</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>FIPS 4-1</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>19920501</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>19940824</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>Calendar days</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>1</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Sample depth (m)</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Depth in meters at which water was sampled,measured from sea-surface.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>88</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>meters</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>0.5</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Methane (nM)</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Dissolved methane concentration in the water.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>275</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>nM</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>0.1</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Methane Isotopic Composition (ppt)</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Carbon isotopic composition (delta-13C) relativeto PDB</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>-80.5</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>-31.1</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>Parts per thousand by weight</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>0.1</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Methane Specific Oxidation</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Rate of microbial oxidation of methane.This "specific oxidation rate" is really just thefirst order rate constant for methane uptake and hasthe units (1/day) because the oxidation rate (nM/day)is divided by the concentration (nM).</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <attrunit>1/day</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Methane Oxidation Rate (nM/day)</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The first order rate constant for the microbialoxidation of methane.
We measure methane oxidation by first removing (viashaking) most of the methane from the collectedsamples.  We then spike the samples with a knownamount of labeled methane which is somewhere near theconcentration of methane in the natural sample.  Wemeasure the rate of methane oxidation by watchinglabeled carbon dioxide grow in.  Some methane isconverted to biomass and we get at this part byfiltering and counting the amount of labeledparticulate carbon.
Once we have these numbers, we calculate what iscalled the "specific oxidation rate".  This is simplythe measured rate divided by the concentration ofmethane in the incubation vials.  This "specificoxidation rate" is really just the first order rateconstant for methane uptake and has the units (1/day)because the oxidation rate (nM/day) is divided by theconcentration (nM).
We can then derive what we call the "ambient oxidationrate" by multipling the "specific oxidation rate" bythe concentration of methane actually measured in thesamples.  This obviously only works if first orderkinetics are followed but we have found this to be thecase in all of the environments we have studied.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <attrunit>nM per day</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Comments</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Descriptive information about the water samplesor the analyses of them.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>PO4</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Phosphate concentration in water samples.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Phosphate is determined as phosphomolybdic acid whichin its reduced form in the presence of antimony has anabsorption maximum at 880 nm.The method is basically an automated version of theprocedure of Murphy and Riley (1962).</attrdefs>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Si</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Silica concentration in water sample.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Orthosilicic acid is determined by its reaction withmolybdate in aqueous acidic solution to formsilicomolybdic acid.
In this procedure, which is basically that ofArmstrong and others, (1967), stannous chloride isused to reduce silicomolybdic acid to the heteropolicacid which has an absorption maximum at 820 nm.</attrdefs>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>NO3</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Nitrate concentration in water samples.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Nitrate, after it is reduced to nitrite by passagethrough a column of copperized cadmium filings, isdetermined in an identical manner to nitrite (Wood andothers 1967). This analysis gives the sum of nitrate +nitrite, and nitrate is determined by difference.</attrdefs>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>NO2</attrlabl>
            <attrdefs>Nitrite is determined by the Greiss reaction in whichsulfanilamide and N-(1-Napthyl)ethylenediaminedihydrochloride react with nitrite in aqueous acidicsolution to form an intensely pink diazo dye with anabsorption maximum at 540 nm (Bendschneider andRobinson, 1952).</attrdefs>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>NH4</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Ammonium concentration in water samples.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Ammonium is determined by the Berthelot reaction inwhich hypochlorous acid and phenol react with ammoniumin aqueous alkaline solution to form indophenol blue,an intensely blue chromophore with an absorptionmaximum at 637 nm. The method utilized is amodification of the procedure reported by Slawyk andMacIsaac (1972).</attrdefs>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>CTD cast</enttypl>
            <enttypds>USGS OFR 95-70</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Temperature</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>In situ water temperature.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>CTD (conductivity, temperature, depth) casts were madeat each station. CTD data was recorded internally by aSeacat 19 CTD probe made by Sea Bird of SeattleWashington. The data was downloaded onto a computerwhere it was processed using Seasoft Version 4.016.The sub-programs LOOPEDIT, BINAVE, then DERIVE wereutilized to process the raw data.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <attrunit>degrees Celsius</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Salinity</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Salinity of the water as determined from theconductivity measurements recorded by the CTDinstrument.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>CTD (conductivity, temperature, depth) casts were madeat each station. CTD data was recorded internally by aSeacat 19 CTD probe made by Sea Bird of SeattleWashington. The data was downloaded onto a computerwhere it was processed using Seasoft Version 4.016.The sub-programs LOOPEDIT, BINAVE, then DERIVE wereutilized to process the raw data.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <attrunit>Parts per thousand by weight</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Depth</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Depth of the CTD instrument when temperature andconductivity were recorded.  This parameter isderived internally by the CTD instrument by usingambient hydrostatic pressure.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>CTD (conductivity, temperature, depth) casts were madeat each station. CTD data was recorded internally by aSeacat 19 CTD probe made by Sea Bird of SeattleWashington. The data was downloaded onto a computerwhere it was processed using Seasoft Version 4.016.The sub-programs LOOPEDIT, BINAVE, then DERIVE wereutilized to process the raw data.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <attrunit>meters</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Conductivity</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Conductivity of water as determined by the CTDinstrument.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>CTD (conductivity, temperature, depth) casts were madeat each station. CTD data was recorded internally by aSeacat 19 CTD probe made by Sea Bird of SeattleWashington. The data was downloaded onto a computerwhere it was processed using Seasoft Version 4.016.The sub-programs LOOPEDIT, BINAVE, then DERIVE wereutilized to process the raw data.</attrdefs>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>ice sample</enttypl>
            <enttypds>USGS OFR 95-70</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Core interval (cm)</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The length of the part of the ice core that wasanalyzed.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <attrunit>centimeters</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Can Wt. gm</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Weight in grams of the container before placingthe sample into it.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <attrunit>grams</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Can+sample Wt. gm</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Weight in grams of the sample with the container.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <attrunit>grams</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Sample Wt. gm</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Difference between variable "Can+sample Wt. gm"and variable "Can Wt. gm".</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <attrunit>grams</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Headspace Liters</attrlabl>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <attrunit>liters</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Methane ppm</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Concentration of methane in the ice-core sample,as a proportion of the weight of the sample.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <attrunit>pars per million by weight</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Methane (nM)</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Concentration of methane in the ice-core sample,in absolute rather than relative terms.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <attrunit>nM</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Carbon Isotopic Composition (ppt)</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Carbon isotopic composition of the methane in the ice-core sample (delta-13C) relative to PDB</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <attrunit>Parts per thousand relative to the PDB standard.</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Carbon Isotopic Composition (ppt) duplicate</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>same as Carbon Isotopic Composition (ppt)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <attrunit>Parts per thousand relative to the PDB standard.</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Description</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Textual description of the locality.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>sediment sample</enttypl>
            <enttypds>USGS OFR 95-70</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Top (of sampled interval in core)</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Distance from top of sediment core to top of thesampled interval.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <attrunit>centimeters</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Bottom (of sampled interval in core)</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Distance from top of sediment core to bottom of thesampled interval.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Lithology</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Short description of the sediment.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Methane (uL/L wet sediment)</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Concentration of methane in the sediment as aproportion of the volume of the wet sediment.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS OFR 95-70</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <attrunit>microliters of methane per liter of wet sediment</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Peter N. Schweitzer</cntper>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Mail Stop 918 National CenterU.S. Geological Survey12201 Sunrise Valley Drive</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(703) 648-6533</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(703) 648-6560</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pschweitzer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 95-70</resdesc>
      <distliab>This report is preliminary and has not been reviewed forconformity with U.S. Geological Survey editorial standards (orwith the North American Stratigraphic Code).  Any use of trade,product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and doesnot imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ASCII</formname>
               <formspec>tab-delimited</formspec>
               <formcont>Gas hydrate station data</formcont>
               <filedec>tar</filedec>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/openfile/of95-070/core/raw/table1.txt</networkr>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/openfile/of95-070/core/raw/table2.txt</networkr>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/openfile/of95-070/core/raw/table3.txt</networkr>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/openfile/of95-070/core/raw/table4.txt</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ASCII</formname>
               <formspec>tab-delimited</formspec>
               <formcont>CTD casts</formcont>
               <filedec>tar</filedec>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/openfile/of95-070/core/raw/appendix1/ctd.tar</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150202</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Peter N. Schweitzer</cntper>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Collection manager, USGS Geoscience Data Clearinghouse, http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Mail Stop 91812201 Sunrise Valley Drive</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(703) 648-6533</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(703) 648-6560</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pschweitzer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
