<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Clark, J.C.</origin>
            <origin>Brabb, E.E.</origin>
            <origin>Rosenberg, L.I.</origin>
            <origin>Goss, H.V.</origin>
            <origin>Watkins, S.E.</origin>
            <pubdate>2000</pubdate>
            <title>Geologic map and map database of the Spreckels 7.5-minutequadrangle, Monterey County, California</title>
            <edition>1.0</edition>
            <geoform>map</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Miscellaneous Field Studies Map</sername>
               <issue>2349</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Menlo Park, CA</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/mf/2001/2349/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This digital map database, compiled from previously published andunpublished data, and new mapping by the authors, represents thegeneral distribution of bedrock and surficial deposits in the mapped area.Together with the accompanying text file (skmf.txt, skmf.pdf, orskmf.ps), it provides current information on the geologic structure andstratigraphy of the area covered.  The database delineates map units thatare identified by general age and lithology following the stratigraphicnomenclature of the U.S. Geological Survey.  The scale of the source mapslimits the spatial resolution (scale) of the database to 1:24,000 orsmaller.</abstract>
         <purpose>This database and accompanying plot files depict the distribution ofgeologic materials and structures at a scale of 1:24,000.  Thereport is intended to provide geologic information for the regional studyof materials properties, earthquake shaking, landslide potential,mineral hazards, seismic velocity, and earthquake faults.  In addition,the report contains new information and interpretations about theregional geologic history and framework.  However, the regional scaleof this report does not provide sufficientdetail for site development purposes.  In addition, this map does nottake the place of fault-rupture hazard zones designated by theCalifornia State Geologist (Hart and Bryant, 1997).  Similarly, thedatabase cannot be used to accurately identify or delineate landslides inthe region.</purpose>
         <supplinf>This report consists of a set of geologic map database files (Arc/Infocoverages) and supporting text and plotfiles.  In addition, the reportincludes two sets of plotfiles (PostScript and PDF format) that willgenerate map sheets and pamphlets similar to a traditional USGSMiscellaneous Field Studies Report.  These files are described below:
&gt;ARC/INFO     Resultant    Description of Coverage&gt;export file  Coverage&gt;-----------  -----------  --------------------------------&gt;sk-geol.e00  sk-geol/     Polygon and line coverage showing&gt;                          faults, depositional contacts, and&gt;                          rock units in the map area.&gt;&gt;sk-strc.e00  sk-strc/     Point and line coverage showing&gt;                          strike and dip information and fold axes.&gt;&gt;sk-lnds.e00  sk-lnds/     Point and line coverage showing arrows&gt;                          indicating landslide directions as well&gt;                          as the locations of wells and springs&gt;                          not included in the topographic base map.
ASCII text files, including explanatory text, ARC/INFO key files,PostScript and PDF plot files, and a ARC Macro Language file forconversion of ARC export files into ARC coverages:
&gt;skmf.ps                 A PostScript plot file of the pamphlet&gt;                        containing detailed unit descriptions&gt;                        and geological information, a description&gt;                        of the digital files associated with the&gt;                        publication, plus references cited.&gt;&gt;skmf.pdf                A PDF version of mamf.ps.&gt;&gt;skmf.txt                A text-only file containing an unformatted&gt;                        version of skmf.ps.&gt;&gt;import.aml              ASCII text file in ARC Macro Language to&gt;                        convert ARC export files to ARC coverages&gt;                        in ARC/INFO.&gt;&gt;skmap.ps                A PostScript plottable file containing&gt;                        an image of the geologic map and base&gt;                        maps at a scale of 1:24,000, along with&gt;                        a simple map key.&gt;&gt;skmap.pdf               A PDF file containing an image of the&gt;                        geologic map and base maps at a scale&gt;                        of 1:24,000, along with a simple map key.
Base maps
Base Map layers used in the preparation of the geologic map plotfileswere derived from published digital maps (Aitken, 1997). The basemap digital files are not included in the digital database package.
Other_References_Cited:
Barron, J.A., 1976, Marine diatom and silicoflagellate biostratigraphyof the type Delmontian Stage and the type Bolivina obliqua Zone,California: U.S. Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 4, no. 3, p.339-351.
Bowen, O.E., Jr., 1965, Stratigraphy, structure, and oil possibilitiesin Monterey and Salinas quadrangles, California, in Rennie, E.W. Jr., ed.,Symposium of papers presented at the fortieth annual Pacific SectionA.A.P.G. convention: American Association of Petroleum Geologists, PacificSection, Bakersfield, Calif., p. 48-67.
_____[1969], Geologic map of the Spreckels 7.5-minute quadrangle:California Division of Mines and Geology unpublished map, scale 1:24,000.
Bryant, W.A., 1985, Faults in the southern Monterey Bay area, MontereyCounty, California: California Division of Mines and Geology FaultEvaluation Report FER-167, 13 p., 5 map sheets, scale 1:24,000.
Cassell, G.K., 1949, Variation in the Monterey Formation near the typelocality: Stanford, Calif., Stanford University M.S. thesis.
Clark, J.C., Dupré, W.R., and Rosenberg, L.I., 1997, Geologic map ofthe Monterey and Seaside 7.5-minute quadrangles, Monterey County,California: a digital database: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report97-30, 32 p., 2 sheets, scale 1:24,000.
Cotton, William, and Associates, 1983, Preliminary geotechnicalevaluation, San Benancio Canyon landslide, Monterey County, California:unpublished report to Monterey County Department of Public Works, 3 p.
Curry, R.R., 1984, Observations on Quaternary and recent fault activity,central coastal California: Monterey Peninsula Water Management Districtopen-file report, 11 p.
Dibblee, T.W., Jr., 1973, Geologic map of the Salinas 15-minutequadrangle, Monterey County, California: U.S. Geological Survey Open-FileReport 74-1021, scale 1:62,500.
Dupré, W.R., 1990a, Maps showing geology and liquefactionsusceptibility of Quaternary deposits in the Monterey, Seaside,Spreckels, and Carmel Valley quadrangles, Monterey County, California:U.S. Geological Survey Miscellaneous Field Studies Map MF-2096, 2 sheets,scale 1:24,000.
_____1990b, Quaternary geology of the Monterey Bay region, California,in Garrison, R.E., Greene, H.G., Hicks, K.R., Weber, G.E., and Wright,T.L., eds., Geology and tectonics of the central California coastalregion, San Francisco to Monterey: American Association of PetroleumGeologists, Volume and Guidebook GB67, Pacific Section, Bakersfield,Calif., p. 185-191.
Dupré, W.R., and Tinsley, J.C., III, 1980, Maps showing geology andliquefaction potential of northern Monterey and southern Santa CruzCounties, California: U.S. Geological Survey Miscellaneous Field StudiesMap MF-1199, 2 sheets, scale 1:62,500.
Fiedler, W.M., 1944, Geology of the Jamesburg quadrangle, MontereyCounty, California: California Division of Mines, Report XL of the StateMineralogist, v. 40, no. 2, p. 177-250, 2 map sheets, scale 1:62,500.
Govean, F.M., and Garrison, R.E., 1981, Significance of laminated andmassive diatomites in the upper part of the Monterey Formation,California, in Garrison, R.E., and Douglas, R.G., eds., The MontereyFormation and related siliceous rocks of California: Los Angeles, Calif.,Society of Economic Paleontologists and Mineralogists, Pacific Section, p.181-198.
Herold, C.L., 1935, Preliminary report on the geology of the Salinasquadrangle, California: Berkeley, University of California M.S. thesis,143 p., 2 sheets, scale 1:62,500.
Jacobson, C.E., Barth, A.P., and Grove, Marty, 2000, Late Cretaceousprotolith age and provenance of the Pelona and Orocopia Schists, southernCalifornia: Implications for evolution of the Cordilleran margin: Geology,v. 28, no. 3, p. 219-222.
Lawson, A.C., chairman, 1908, The California earthquake of April 18,1906: Report of the California State Earthquake Investigation Commission:Washington D.C., Carnegie Institution of Washington, Publication 87, v. 1,2 parts, 451 p.
McCulloch, D.S., and Greene, H.G., 1989, Geologic map of the centralCalifornia continental margin, in Greene, H.G., and Kennedy, M.P., eds.,Geology of the central California continental margin: California Divisionof Mines and Geology California Continental Margin Geologic Map Series,Map 5A, scale 1:250,000.
Petersen, M.D., Bryant, W.A., Cramer, C.H., Cao, T., Reichle, M.S.,Frankel,   A.D., Lienkaemper, J.J., McCrory, P.A., and Schwartz, D.P.,1996, Probabilistic seismic hazard assessment for the State of California:California Division of Mines and Geology Open-File Report 96-08 and U.S.Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-706, 33 p., 2 appendices.
Rosenberg, L.I., and Clark, J.C., 1994, Quaternary faulting of thegreater Monterey area, California: U.S. Geological Survey Final TechnicalReport 1434-94-G-2443, 45 p., 3 appendices, 4 sheets, scale 1:24,000.
Ross, D.C., 1976a, Reconnaissance geologic map of pre-Cenozoic basementrocks, northern Santa Lucia Range, Monterey County, California: U.S.Geological Survey Miscellaneous Field Studies Map MF-750, 7 p., 2 sheets,scale 1:125,000.
_____1976b, Metagraywacke in the Salinian block, central Coast Ranges,California-and a possible correlative across the San Andreas fault: U.S.Geological Survey Journal of Research, v. 4, no. 6, p. 683-696.
_____1977, Maps showing sample localities and ternary plots and graphsshowing modal and chemical data for granitic rocks of the Santa LuciaRange, Salinian block, California Coast Ranges: U.S. Geological SurveyMiscellaneous Field Studies Map MF-799, 16 p., 3 plates.
Staal, Gardner &amp; Dunne, 1988, Phase II hydrogeologic investigation,Laguna Seca subarea, Monterey County, California: Monterey County HealthDepartment open-file report, 33 p., 6 appendices, 8 sheets, scale1:12,000.
_____1991a, Hydrogeologic update, El Toro area, Monterey County,California: Monterey County Water Resources Agency open-file report, 53p., 4 appendices.
_____1991b, Laguna Seca Ranch, supplemental hydrogeologic assessment:unpublished letter report to Kimball Small Properties, 7 p.
Terratech, 1989, Supplemental fault investigation, Las Palmas RanchDevelopment, Monterey County, California: Monterey County Planning andBuilding Inspection open-file report, 3 p.
Thorup, R.R., 1980, Groundwater evaluation of the Flause property,Corral de Tierra Valley, Monterey County, California: unpublished reportto Robert Flause, 19 p.
Tinsley, J.C., III, 1975, Quaternary geology of the northern SalinasValley, Monterey County, California: Stanford, Calif., Stanford UniversityPh.D. dissertation, 195 p., 2 sheets, scale 1:62,500.
Tuzon, Brandy, 1997, Mud ravages San Benancio homes: Salinas, Calif.,The Californian, January 29, 1997, p. 1A.
Younse, G.A., 1980, The stratigraphy and phosphoritic rocks of theRobinson Canyon-Laureles Grade area, Monterey County, California: U.S.Geological Survey Open-File Report 80-318, 127 p., 5 sheets.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <dsstruct>
         <dspart>
            <dsptname>GIS data</dsptname>
            <dspttype>file</dspttype>
            <dsptdesc>ArcInfo GIS-ready data layers in .e00 format</dsptdesc>
            <dspart>
               <dsptname>sk-geol.e00</dsptname>
               <dspttype>Arc/Info export file</dspttype>
               <dsptdesc>Polygon and line coverage showing faults, depositional contacts, and rock units in the map area.</dsptdesc>
            </dspart>
            <dspart>
               <dsptname>sk-strc.e00</dsptname>
               <dspttype>Arc/Info export file</dspttype>
               <dsptdesc>Point and line coverage showing strike and dip information and fold axes.</dsptdesc>
            </dspart>
            <dspart>
               <dsptname>sk-lnds.e00</dsptname>
               <dspttype>Arc/Info export file</dspttype>
               <dsptdesc>Point and line coverage showing arrows indicating landslide directions as well as the locations of wells and springs not included in the topographic base map.</dsptdesc>
            </dspart>
         </dspart>
         <dspart>
            <dsptname>Ancilliary data</dsptname>
            <dspttype>file</dspttype>
            <dsptdesc>ASCII text files, including explanatory text, ARC/INFO key files,PostScript and PDF plot files, and a ARC Macro Language file forconversion of ARC export files into ARC coverages:</dsptdesc>
            <dspart>
               <dsptname>skmf.ps</dsptname>
               <dspttype>file, PostScript</dspttype>
               <dsptdesc>A PostScript plot file of the pamphlet containing detailed unit descriptions and geological information, a description of the digital files associated with the publication, plus references cited.</dsptdesc>
            </dspart>
            <dspart>
               <dsptname>skmf.pdf</dsptname>
               <dspttype>file, PDF</dspttype>
               <dsptdesc>A PDF version of mamf.ps.</dsptdesc>
            </dspart>
            <dspart>
               <dsptname>skmf.txt</dsptname>
               <dspttype>file, ASCII</dspttype>
               <dsptdesc>A text-only file containing an unformatted version of skmf.ps.</dsptdesc>
            </dspart>
            <dspart>
               <dsptname>import.aml</dsptname>
               <dspttype>file, text (AML)</dspttype>
               <dsptdesc>ASCII text file in ARC Macro Language to convert ARC export files to ARC coverages in ARC/INFO.</dsptdesc>
            </dspart>
            <dspart>
               <dsptname>skmap.ps</dsptname>
               <dspttype>file, PostScript</dspttype>
               <dsptdesc>A PostScript plottable file containing an image of the geologic map and base maps at a scale of 1:24,000, along with a simple map key.</dsptdesc>
            </dspart>
            <dspart>
               <dsptname>skmap.pdf</dsptname>
               <dspttype>file, PDF</dspttype>
               <dsptdesc>A PDF file containing an image of the geologic map and base maps at a scale of 1:24,000, along with a simple map key.</dsptdesc>
            </dspart>
         </dspart>
      </dsstruct>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>2000</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>The date given is the publication date.  The information in the reportis the most up-to-date available at the time of publication.</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-121.7500000</westbc>
            <eastbc>-121.6216666</eastbc>
            <northbc>36.62166666</northbc>
            <southbc>36.75000000</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>structural geology</themekey>
            <themekey>stratigraphy</themekey>
            <themekey>faulting (geologic)</themekey>
            <themekey>geologic maps</themekey>
            <themekey>bedrock geologic units</themekey>
            <themekey>surficial geologic units</themekey>
            <themekey>landslides</themekey>
            <themekey>lithostratigraphy</themekey>
            <themekey>tectonic processes</themekey>
            <themekey>geospatial datasets</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>geology</themekey>
            <themekey>bedrock geology</themekey>
            <themekey>surficial geology</themekey>
            <themekey>geologic history</themekey>
            <themekey>tertiary paleontology</themekey>
            <themekey>fault geometry</themekey>
            <themekey>fault activity</themekey>
            <themekey>terranes</themekey>
            <themekey>geologic structures</themekey>
            <themekey>oil wells</themekey>
            <themekey>Laureles fault</themekey>
            <themekey>Chupines fault</themekey>
            <themekey>Corral de Tierra fault</themekey>
            <themekey>Harper fault</themekey>
            <themekey>Las Palmas fault</themekey>
            <themekey>Santa Margarita sandstone</themekey>
            <themekey>Monterey formation</themekey>
            <themekey>landslides</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>United States of America</placekey>
            <placekey>California</placekey>
            <placekey>Monterey County</placekey>
         </place>
         <stratum>
            <stratkt>None</stratkt>
            <stratkey>Artificial fill</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Basin deposits</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Alluvial deposits, undivided</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Younger flood-plain deposits</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Older flood-plain deposits</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Colluvium</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Abandoned channel fill deposits</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Landslide deposits</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Terrace deposits, undivided</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Older eolian deposits</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Alluvial fan deposits of Chualar</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Alluvial fan deposits of Placentia</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Alluvial fan deposits of Gloria</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Continental deposits, undivided</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Santa Margarita Sandstone</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Monterey Formation, diatomite</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Monterey Formation, porcelinite</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Unnamed sandstone</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Unnamed sandstone, undifferentiated</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Unnamed conglomerate</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Granodiorite of Cachagua of Ross</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Garnetiferous quartz monzonite of Pine Canyon of Ross</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Hornblende-biotite quartz diorite and diorite of Corral de Tierra</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Schist of the Sierra de Salinas of Ross</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Quartzofeldspathic rocks</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Marble</stratkey>
         </stratum>
         <temporal>
            <tempkt>None</tempkt>
            <tempkey>Pre-Cretaceous</tempkey>
            <tempkey>Cretaceous</tempkey>
            <tempkey>Cenozoic</tempkey>
            <tempkey>Tertiary</tempkey>
            <tempkey>Miocene</tempkey>
            <tempkey>Pliocene</tempkey>
            <tempkey>Quaternary</tempkey>
            <tempkey>Pleistocene</tempkey>
            <tempkey>Holocene</tempkey>
         </temporal>
         <place>
            <placekt>Augmented FIPS 10-4 and FIPS 6-4</placekt>
            <placekey>06053 = Monterey</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>Uses of this digital geologic map should not violate the spatialresolution of the data.  Although the digital form of the data removesthe constraint imposed by the scale of a paper map, the detail andaccuracy inherent in map scale are also present in the digital data.The fact that this database was edited for a scale of 1:24,000 meansthat higher resolution information is not present in the dataset.Plotting at scales larger than 1:24,000 will not yield greater realdetail, although it may reveal fine-scale irregularities below theintended resolution of the database.  Similarly, where this databaseis used in combination with other data of higher resolution, theresolution of the combined output will be limited by the lowerresolution of these data.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Western Geologic Mapping Team</cntorg>
               <cntper>Database coordinator</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>345 Middlefield Road, MS 975</address>
               <city>Menlo Park</city>
               <state>CA</state>
               <postal>94025</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://pubs.usgs.gov/mf/2001/2349/skmap.pdf</browsen>
         <browsed>A PDF representation of the geologic map and base maps at a scale of1:24,000 (Sheet 1).  7.6 megabytes.</browsed>
         <browset>PDF</browset>
      </browse>
      <datacred>David L. Wagner of the California Division of Mines and Geology (CDMG) provided Clark and Rosenberg with funding for their 1998field mapping. Wagner also coordinated the work of Sarah E.Watkins (CDMG), who digitized the geologic map for incorporationinto the geologic map of the Monterey 1:100,000-scale quadrangle,which is in preparation.
Andrei Sarna-Wojcicki (USGS) analyzed and correlated Miocene ashbeds from the quadrangle.  Charles Powell, II (USGS) identifiedand interpreted mollusks collected from the quadrangle by Brabband Clark.  He also examined and interpreted mollusks at theCalifornia Academy of Science collected by Bowen and at the Museumof Paleontology, University of California, Berkeley that had beencollected and reported by Herold (1935).  Kristin McDougall (USGS)identified and interpreted Miocene foraminifers.  VictoriaLangenheim (USGS) and Robert Jachens (USGS) kindly providedunpublished gravity and aeromagnetic data with an interpretationof regional faulting.  Special thanks go to Richard R. Thorup forsharing his extensive knowledge of the geology of the quadrangle.
Heather V. Goss (USGS and Environmental Careers Organization)added a structure layer, including strikes and dips and fold axes,to the digital map file, annotated and formatted the map toconform to USGS publication standards, and made corrections to themap after technical reviews.  She wrote the metadata for thedigital file, formatted the text to conform to USGS publicationstandards, and changed and added information after technicalreview.</datacred>
      <native>SunOS, 5.5.1, sun4u UNIX, ARC/INFO version 7.2.1</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>This report has undergone two scientific peer reviews, one digitaldatabase review, one review for conformity with geologic names policy,and review of the plotfiles for conformity with USGS map standards.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Polygon and chain-node topology present</logic>
      <complete>The report is intended to describe completely the bedrock geology at1:24,000 scale.  Geologic information only mappable at larger scale hasbeen omitted.  In addition, landslide deposits are for the most part notrecorded.  Further, Quaternary surficial deposits in many areas have beenintentionally undifferentiated.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>Well located data items are intended to have a horizontal positionalaccuracy within .62 mm at 1:24,000 scale, or within 15 meters onthe ground.  The general positional accuracy of each line in thedatabase is indicated within the LTYPE field in the Arc AttributeTable (see below).  Points in the database are generally consideredto be well located.  The position of each data item is derived fromthe USGS topographic base map, and therefore additional inaccuraciesarising from inaccuracies in the base map may also be encountered.See Aitken (1997) for information regarding the horizontal positionalaccuracy of the basemaps.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
         <vertacc>
            <vertaccr>No vertical positional data recorded.  See Aitken (1997) for informationregarding the vertical positional accuracy of the basemaps used tocreate the plotfiles of the geologic maps.</vertaccr>
         </vertacc>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Ross, D.C.</origin>
                  <pubdate>1976</pubdate>
                  <title>Reconnaissance geologic map of pre-Cenozoic basement rocks, northern Santa Lucia Range, Monterey County, California</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Miscellaneous Field Studies Map</sername>
                     <issue>MF-750</issue>
                  </serinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>125000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>paper</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1976</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Ross, 1976</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Source map for basement rock distribution</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Dupre, W.R.</origin>
                  <pubdate>1990</pubdate>
                  <title>Maps showing geology and liquefaction susceptibility of Quaternary deposits in the Monterey, Seaside, Spreckels, and Carmel Valley quadrangles, Monterey County, California</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Miscellaneous Field Studies Map</sername>
                     <issue>MF-2096</issue>
                  </serinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>paper</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1990</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Dupre, 1990</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Source map for Quaternery deposits</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Rosenberg, L.I.</origin>
                  <pubdate>(unpublished)</pubdate>
                  <title>unpublished geologic investigations</title>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>paper</typesrc>
            <srccitea>Rosenberg (unpublished)</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Source for information on Quaternary deposits</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Brabb, E.E.</origin>
                  <pubdate>(unpublished)</pubdate>
                  <title>unpublished geologic investigations</title>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>paper</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1998</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>date material incoporated</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Brabb (unpublished)</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Source for information on landslide locations</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Bowen, O.E., Jr.</origin>
                  <pubdate>1969</pubdate>
                  <title>Geologic map of the Spreckels 7.5-minute quadrangle, unpublished</title>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <publish>California Division of Mines and Geology</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>paper</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1969</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Bowen, 1969</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Source map for geology</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Dibblee, T.W., Jr.</origin>
                  <pubdate>1973</pubdate>
                  <title>Geologic map of the Salinas 15-minute quadrangle, Monterey County, California</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
                     <issue>74-1021</issue>
                  </serinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>62500</srcscale>
            <typesrc>paper</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1973</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Dibblee, 1973</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Source map for geology</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The databases in this report were compiled in ARC/INFO, a commercialGeographic Information System (Environmental Systems Research Institute,Redlands, California), with version 3.0 of the menu interface ALACARTE(Fitzgibbon and Wentworth, 1991, Fitzgibbon, 1991, Wentworth andFitzgibbon, 1991).  The files are in either GRID (ARC/INFO raster data)format or COVERAGE (ARC/INFO vector data) format.  Coverages are stored inuncompressed ARC export format (ARC/INFO version 7.x).  ARC/INFO exportfiles (files with the .e00 extension) can be converted into ARC/INFOcoverages in ARC/INFO (see below) and can be read by some other GeographicInformation Systems, such as MapInfo via ArcLink and ESRI's ArcView(version 1.0 for Windows 3.1 to 3.11 is available for free from ESRI's website:  http://www.esri.com). The digital compilation was done in version7.1.1 of ARC/INFO with version 3.0 of the menu interface ALACARTE(Fitzgibbon and Wentworth, 1991, Fitzgibbon, 1991, Wentworth andFitzgibbon, 1991).
The geologic map information was digitized from a stable original of thegeologic map at 1:24,000 scale.  The author manuscript (pen on mylar)was scanned using a Altek monochrome scanner with a resolution of 800dots per inch.  The scanned image was vectorized and transformed fromscanner coordinates to projection coordinates with  digital tics placedby hand at quadrangle corners.  The scanned lines were editedinteractively by hand using ALACARTE, color boundarieswere tagged as appropriate, and scanning artifacts visible at 1:24,000were removed.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1999</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Creation of original metadata record</procdesc>
            <procdate>20010130</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Graymer, Russell W</cntper>
                     <cntorg>USGS-GEO-WRG-NGM</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>Mail Stop 975, USGS345 Middlefield Road</address>
                     <city>Menlo Park</city>
                     <state>CA</state>
                     <postal>94025</postal>
                     <country>US</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>650-329-4988</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>rgraymer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Vector</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>375</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>String</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>1105</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>GT-polygon composed of chains</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>376</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <gridsys>
               <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
               <utm>
                  <utmzone>10</utmzone>
                  <transmer>
                     <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
                     <longcm>-123</longcm>
                     <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
                     <feast>500000</feast>
                     <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
                  </transmer>
               </utm>
            </gridsys>
            <planci>
               <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>1.0</absres>
                  <ordres>1.0</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>METERS</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>Unknown</horizdn>
            <ellips>Clarke 1866</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378206.4</semiaxis>
            <denflat>294.98</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>SK-GEOL.PAT</enttypl>
            <enttypd>polygon attribute table</enttypd>
            <enttypds>ARC/INFO</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>PTYPE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Labels of geologic units and areas of water.</attrdef>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qaf</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Artificial fill</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qb</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Basin deposits</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qal</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Alluvial deposits, undivided</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qyf</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Younger flood-plain deposits</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qof</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Older flood-plain deposits</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qc</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Colluvium</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qcf</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Abandoned channel fill deposits</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qls</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Landslide deposits</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qt</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Terrace deposits, undivided</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qoe</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Older eolian deposits</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qch</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Alluvial fan deposits of Chualar</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qp</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Alluvial fan deposits of Placentia</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qgl</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Alluvial fan deposits of Gloria</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>QTc</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Continental deposits, undivided</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Tsm</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Santa Margarita Sandstone</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Tmd</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Monterey Formation, diatomite</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Tm</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Monterey Formation, porcelinite</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Tus</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Unnamed sandstone</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Tuss</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Unnamed sandstone, undifferentiated</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Tuc</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Unnamed conglomerate</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Kgd</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Granodiorite of Cachagua of Ross</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Kqm</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Garnetiferous quartz monzonite of Pine Canyon of Ross</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Khqd</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Hornblende-biotite quartz diorite and diorite of Corral de Tierra</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>msc</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Schist of the Sierra de Salinas of Ross</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>ms</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Quartzofeldspathic rocks</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>ml</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Marble</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>water</edomv>
                  <edomvd>water</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>SK-GEOL.AAT</enttypl>
            <enttypd>arc attribute table</enttypd>
            <enttypds>ARC/INFO</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>LTYPE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The type of lines used in the geology layer.Includes all faults, as well as lines bounding polygons that definegeologic units.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>contact, certain</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Boundary between two mapped unitsthat retains the original depositional or intrusive relationship(i.e. not faulted).  The contact has been observed or is closelyconstrained, so it is well-located as described in Positional_Accuracy.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>contact, approx. located</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Boundary between two mapped unitsthat retains the original depositional or intrusive relationship(i.e. not faulted).  The contact has not been observed, so it isnot well-located as described in Positional_Accuracy, but thelocation is constrained to be within about 1.25 mm at map scale(1:24,000) or within about 30 meters on the ground.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>contact, inferred, queried</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Boundary between two mapped unitsthat retains the original depositional or intrusive relationship(i.e. not faulted).  The contact has not been observed, so it isnot well-located as described in Positional_Accuracy, but thelocation is constrained to be within about 1.25 mm at map scale(1:24,000) or within about 30 meters on the ground.  The existenceof the contact is inferred from structural and stratigraphicrelationships observed elsewhere.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>contact, sed_terrace, approx. located</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Inner edge of a terrace deposit at the break in slope onthe landward side of either a coastal terrace (shorelineangle) or a stream terrace. The contact has not beenobserved, so it is not well-located as described inPositional_Accuracy, but the location is constrained to bewithin about 1.25 mm at map scale (1:24,000) or withinabout 30 meters on the ground.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>contact, sed_terrace, certain</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Inner edge of a terrace deposit at the break in slope onthe landward side of either a coastal terrace (shorelineangle) or a stream terrace.  The contact has been observedor is closely constrained, so it is well-located asdescribed in Positional_Accuracy.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>fault, approx. located</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Structural boundary betweenmapped units or structural discontinuity within a mapped unitthat has experienced relative offset between the rock bodies oneither side of the fault. The fault has not been observed, so itis not well-located as described in Positional_Accuracy, but thelocation is constrained to be within about 1.25 mm at map scale(1:24,000) or within about 30 meters on the ground.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>fault, certain</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Structural boundary betweenmapped units or structural discontinuity within a mapped unitthat has experienced relative offset between the rock bodies oneither side of the fault. The fault has been observed or is closelyconstrained, so it is well-located as described in positional_Accuracy.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>fault, concealed</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Structural boundary betweenmapped units or structural discontinuity within a mapped unitthat has experienced relative offset between the rock bodies oneither side of the fault. The fault is obscured by overlyingmapped units, so it is not well-located as described inPositional_Accuracy, but the location is constrained to be withinabout 2.5 mm at map scale (1:24,000) or within about 60 meters onthe ground.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>fault, concealed, queried</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Structural boundary betweenmapped units or structural discontinuity within a mapped unitthat has experienced relative offset between the rock bodies oneither side of the fault. The fault is obscured by overlyingmapped units, so it is not well-located as described inPositional_Accuracy, but the location is constrained to be withinabout 2.5 mm at map scale (1:24,000) or within about 60 meters onthe ground.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>map boundary,</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Edge of the mapped area.  Usedprimarily to bound polygons at the edge of the map database.The location of the boundary is well located as described inPositional_Accuracy.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>SK-STRC.PAT</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Attribute table of SK-STRC.</enttypd>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>PTTYPE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The type of planar feature which was observedand the orientation of which was measured at this point.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>ash bedding</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Ash bed too thin to appear on map.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>bedding</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Originally horizontal sedimentarylayers were observed at this point.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>flat bedding</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Sedimentary layers that retain their original horizontal position were observed at this point.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>foliation</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Metamorphic foliation wasobserved at this point.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>ot bedding</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Originally horizontal sedimentarylayers were observed at this point.  Evidence that the beds areoverturned was observed, although that observation may not havebeen made at this point.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>vert bedding</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Originally horizontal sedimentarylayers were observed at this point.  These layers are now vertical.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>vert foliation</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Vertical metamorphic foliation wasobserved at this point.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>DIP</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The inclination of planar structures measured indegrees down from horizontal.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>90</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>degrees</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>1</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>STRIKE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The orientation of a horizontal line in an inclined planarstructure measured in degrees clockwise from north.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>359</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>degrees</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>1</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>SK-STRC.AAT</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Attribute table of SK-STRC.</enttypd>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>LTYPE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The type of fold axis or other structural linearfeature that does not bound geologic units.  Faults are described in aseparate coverage, but some contacts are described in this coverage.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>contact, certain</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Boundary between two mapped unitsthat retains the original depositional or intrusive relationship(i.e. not faulted).  The contact has been observed, so it iswell-located as described in Positional_Accuracy.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>f.a., anticline, certain</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The surface trace of the axis of an anticline.  The axis isnot well-located as described in Positional_Accuracy, butthe location is constrained to be within about 2.5 mm atmap scale (1:24,000) or within about 60 meters on theground.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>f.a., anticline, concealed</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The surface trace of the axis of an anticline.  The axis isobscured by overlying mapped units, so it is not well-located as described in Positional_Accuracy, but thelocation is constrained to be within about 2.5 mm at mapscale (1:24,000) or within about 60 meters on the ground.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>f.a., anticline, approx. located</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The surface trace of the axis of an anticline.  The axishas not been observed, so it is not well-located asdescribed in Positional_Accuracy, but the location isconstrained to be within about 3.75 mm at map scale (1:24,000) or within about 90 meters on the ground.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>f.a., syncline, certain</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The surface trace of the axis of a syncline.  The axis isnot well-located as described in Positional_Accuracy, butthe location is constrained to be within about 2.5 mm atmap scale (1:24,000) or within about 60 meters on theground.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>f.a., syncline, concealed</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The surface trace of the axis of a syncline.  The axis isobscured by overlying mapped units, so it is not well-located as described in Positional_Accuracy, but thelocation is constrained to be within about 2.5 mm at mapscale (1:24,000) or within about 60 meters on the ground.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>f.a., syncline, approx. located</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The surface trace of the axis of a syncline.  The axis hasnot been observed, so it is not well-located as describedin Positional_Accuracy, but the location is constrained tobe within about 3.75 mm at map scale (1:24,000) or withinabout 90 meters on the ground.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>PLUNGE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Database item added in order to plot plunge arrows on plunging fold axes.</attrdef>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>arrowhead</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The plunging end of a fold axis.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>0</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Not a plunging fold axis.</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>SK-LNDS.PAT</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Attribute table of SK-LNDS.</enttypd>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>PTTYPE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Feature observed at this point</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>author</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>oil well</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Dry hole drilled for hydrocarbon exploration</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>spring</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Spring</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>water well</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Water well</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <overview>
         <eaover>The databases in this report were compiled in ARC/INFO, a commercialGeographic Information System (Environmental Systems ResearchInstitute, Redlands, California).  Almost all the attributes in thevarious attribute tables of the coverages included in the report areset or calculated by Arc/Info.  The exceptions are "coveragename"-ID,LTYPE, PTYPE, PTTYPE, STRIKE, and DIP.
"coveragename"-ID is required by internal policy to be sequential.This ensures the highest compatibility of our databases with other GISs.Therefore "coveragename"-ID is calculated equal to "coveragename"#,which is a unique, sequential integer assigned by Arc/Info to eachdata record.
LTYPE, PTYPE, and PTTYPE are author added items to the coverage AATor PAT that are used to describe the type of line (LTYPE), area (PTYPE),or point (PTTYPE) being recorded.  All coverages with AAT and PATpresent include these items in the data structure, although in somecases these items are not used.  Each has WIDTH 35, OUTPUT 35, TYPE C.STRIKE and DIP are author added items to the coverage PAT that recordinformation about the orientation of planar geologic structures.  Bothhave WIDTH 3, OUTPUT 3, TYPE I.  These items are only recorded in thetable SK-STRC.PAT</eaover>
         <eadetcit>This report, skmf.txt, skmf.pdf, or skmf.ps</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Information Services</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Box 25248, Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>CO</state>
               <postal>80255-0286</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-888-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>1-303-202-4693</cntfax>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>USGS MF-2349</resdesc>
      <distliab>Commercial entities named in the texts of this report are cited for descriptive purposes, not to constitute an endorsement of those products.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ARCE</formname>
               <formvern>7.x</formvern>
               <filedec>gzip -d and tar</filedec>
               <transize>0.5</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/mf/2001/2349/mf2349c.t.gz</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150202</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Peter N Schweitzer</cntper>
               <cntorg>USGS Midwest Area</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Collection manager, USGS Geoscience Data Clearinghouse, http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Mail Stop 95412201 Sunrise Valley Dr</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192-0002</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>703-648-6533</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>703-648-6252</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pschweitzer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <metextns>
         <onlink>http://geology.usgs.gov/tools/metadata/tools/ext/parts.ext</onlink>
      </metextns>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
