<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Jonathan C. Matti</origin>
            <origin>Douglas C. Morton</origin>
            <origin>Brett F. Cox</origin>
            <origin>Scott E. Carson</origin>
            <origin>Thomas J. Yetter</origin>
            <pubdate>2003</pubdate>
            <title>Geologic map and digital database of the Yucaipa 7.5' quadrangle, San Bernardino andRiverside Counties, California</title>
            <edition>Version 1.0</edition>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>United States Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>03-301</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Menlo Park, California</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2003/0301/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The Yucaipa 7.5' quadrangle is located at the southeastern margin of the SanBernardino Basin, an extensional region situated within a right-step-over zonebetween the San Jacinto and San Andreas Fault zones.  The quadrangle is traversed byseveral faults of the San Andreas system, including (from oldest to youngest) theBanning Fault and the Wilson Creek, Mission Creek, Mill Creek, and San BernardinoStrands of the San Andreas Fault.
The Mill Creek Strand of the San Andreas Fault is the easternmost strand of the SanAndreas in the Yucaipa quadrangle.  It separates granitic and metamorphic rocks ofthe San Bernardino Mountains block from a thin slice of similar rocks on YucaipaRidge, and thus has only a small amount of strike-slip displacement.
The Wilson Creek Strand traverses Yucaipa Ridge and converges toward the Mlll CreekStrand in the Santa Ana river Canyon.  The fault has juxtaposed an igneous andmetamorphic complex (Wilson Creek block) and overlying nonmarine sedimentary rocks(Mill Creek Formation of Gibson, 1971) against rocks of San BernardinoMountains-type, and thus has significant strike-slip displacement.
The Mission Creek Strand is inferred to lie beneath Quaternary surficial depositsalong the southwestern base of the San Bernardino Mountains.  This fault is themajor strand of the San Andreas Fault zone, and has juxtaposed crystalline rocks ofSan Gabriel Mountains-type (including Pelona Schist overlain by the Vincent Thrustand associated upper-plate crystalline rocks) against the Wilson Creek block and theSan Bernardino Mountains.
The San Bernardino Strand defines the modern trace of the San Andreas Fault.  Thestrand forms primary fault features in all but the youngest Quaternary surficialunits, and is thought to have evolved in the last 125,000 years or so based onregional fault relations.
Complications within the San Andreas Fault system over the last several hundredthousand years have created a landscape setting in which Quaternary surficialmaterials of the Yucaipa quadrangle have accumulated.  Crustal extension throughoutthe San Bernardino Basin region led to uplift of the Crafton Hills block anddown-dropping of the Yucaipa Valley region on faults of the Crafton Hills andChicken Hill complex.  Subsequent middle and late Quaternary streamflows depositedseveral generations of axial-valley and alluvial-fan sediment in the down-droppedlowlands.  These deposits and the older San Timoteo beds they overlie record thehistory of Quaternary fault movements, and form reservoirs for ground water in theYucaipa quadrangle.
Digital Data:
The geologic database of the Yucaipa 1:24,000-scale 7.5' quadrangle, San Bernardinoand Riverside Counties, California, was prepared by the Southern California ArealMapping Project (SCAMP), a regional geologic-mapping project sponsored jointly bythe U.S. Geological Survey and the California Geological Survey.  The database wascreated in ARC/INFO (Environmental Systems Research Institute, ESRI), and includesthe following files: (1) a readme.txt file, (2) this metadata file, (3) coveragescontaining geologic data and station-location data, (4) associated INFO attributedata files, (5) a browse graphic (.pdf) of the geologic-map plot and map-marginalexplanatory information, (6) a PostScript graphics file of the geologic-map plotwith map-marginal explanatory information, and (7) .pdf text files describing themap units of the Yucaipa quadrangle (Description of Map Units) and their geologicage and correlation (Correlation of Map Units).</abstract>
         <purpose>The geologic database for the Yucaipa quadrangle was developed as a contribution tothe National Cooperative Geologic Mapping Program's National Geologic Map Database,and is intended to provide a general geologic setting of the quadrangle.  TheYucaipa database provides information about geologic materials and structures,including the modern trace of the San Andreas fault and associated faults that havedeveloped in the map area due to complexities in the San Andreas stress field.
Geologic information contained in the Yucaipa database is general-purpose data thatare applicable to land-related investigations in the earth and biological sciences.The term "general-purpose" means that all geologic-feature classes have minimalinformation content adequate to characterize their general geologic characteristicsand to interpret their general geologic history.  However, no single feature class mayhave enough information to definitively characterize its properties and origin.  Forthis reason the database cannot be used for site-specific geologic evaluations,although it can be used to plan and guide investigations at the site-specific level.</purpose>
         <supplinf>This database is an updated, digital release of an analog map of the Yucaipaquadrangle released previously in the U.S.  Geological Survey Open-file Report (OF)series in 1992 (Matti, J.C., Morton, D.M., Cox, B.F., Carson, S.E., and Yetter,T.J.,1992, Geologic map of the Yucaipa quadrangle, southern California: U.S. GeologicalSurvey Open-File Report 92-445, scale 1:24,000, 14 p.).  Version 1.0 retains much ofthe geologic linear and point data and map-unit information represented in the analogrelease.  However, digital version 1.0 differs from the 1992 analog release in severalimportant ways:
(1) Quaternary surficial materials in the NW part of the quadrangle (Sec.  7, 8, 17,18, 19, 20) and SE corner of the quadrangle (Sec.  7, 8, 11, 12, and unsurveyed) havebeen reinterpreted based on analysis of 1938 and 1953 Department of Agriculture(Agricultural Stabilization and Conservation Service, ASCS) aerial photography.
(2) In digital version 1.0, units in the Qa series (Qa, Qya, Qoa, and Qvoa) areidentified as "axial-valley deposits".  In the 1992 analog version, these units weredescribed as "deposits of alluvial plains".  These changes do not affect the geologicinterpretation or information content of the map.  Rather, they are merelynomenclatuaral changes that are the consequence of the U.S.  Geological Survey'scontinued efforts to refine the classification of Quaternary surficial materials in theSan Bernardino-Yucaipa region.
(3) For some faults, digital version 1.0 provides new, geologic data and interpretations.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>1930</begdate>
               <enddate>1998</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Time period of information content for geologic data in the Yucaipa database reflects (1)the vintage (1930, 1938, 1952, 1966, 1975) of archival aerial photographs used tointerpret geologic features and (2) ground observations made by the map authors between1977 and 1998.</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-117.12509183</westbc>
            <eastbc>-116.99990817</eastbc>
            <northbc>34.12499996</northbc>
            <southbc>33.99998412</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>geology</themekey>
            <themekey>geologic maps</themekey>
            <themekey>bedrock geologic units</themekey>
            <themekey>surficial geologic units</themekey>
            <themekey>faulting (geologic)</themekey>
            <themekey>geologic structure</themekey>
            <themekey>landslides</themekey>
            <themekey>geospatial datasets</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>geologic maps</themekey>
            <themekey>geology</themekey>
            <themekey>surficial geologic units</themekey>
            <themekey>bedrock geologic units</themekey>
            <themekey>San Andreas Fault</themekey>
            <themekey>Banning Fault</themekey>
            <themekey>Vincent Thrust</themekey>
            <themekey>Crafton Hills Fault Zone</themekey>
            <themekey>Chicken Hill Fault</themekey>
            <themekey>faults (geologic)</themekey>
            <themekey>landslides</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>California</placekey>
            <placekey>San Bernardino County</placekey>
            <placekey>Riverside County</placekey>
            <placekey>Yucaipa 7.5' quadrangle</placekey>
            <placekey>Yucaipa</placekey>
            <placekey>Calimesa</placekey>
            <placekey>Mentone</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Augmented FIPS 10-4 and FIPS 6-4</placekt>
            <placekey>06065 = Riverside</placekey>
            <placekey>06071 = San Bernardino</placekey>
         </place>
         <stratum>
            <stratkt>None</stratkt>
            <stratkey>Mill Creek Formation of Gibson (1971)</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Pelona Schist</stratkey>
            <stratkey>San Timoteo beds of Frick (1921)</stratkey>
            <stratkey>Formation of Warm Springs Canyon</stratkey>
         </stratum>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>The Yucaipa 7.5' geologic-map database should be used to evaluate and understand thegeologic character of the Yucaipa quadrangle as a whole.  It should not be used as adetailed map for purposes of site-specific land-use planning or site-specific geologicevaluations.
The database is sufficiently detailed to identify and characterize many actual andpotential geologic hazards represented by faults and landslides and posed by groundsubsidence and earthquake-generated ground shaking.  However, it is not sufficientlydetailed for site-specific determinations or evaluations of these features.  Faultsshown do not take the place of fault-rupture hazard zones designated by the CaliforniaState Geologist (see Hart, 1988).
Use of the Yucaipa geologic-map database should not violate the spatial resolution ofthe data.  Although the digital form of the data allows the scale to be manipulated atthe discretion of the user, detail and accuracy issues that are inherent to map-scalelimitations similarly exist in the digital data.  The fact that this database wasconstructed and edited at a scale of 1:24,000 means that higher-resolution datagenerally are not present in the dataset.  Therefore, plotting at scales larger than1:24,000 will not yield greater, real detail, although enlarged plots may revealfine-scale (artificial) irregularities beyond the intended resolution of the database.Although higher-resolution data may be incorporated at a few places, the resolution ofthe entire database output is limited by the lower-resolution data.
Hart, E. W., 1988, Fault-rupture zones in California; Alquist-Priolo Special StudiesZones Act of 1972 with index to special studies zones maps: California Division of Minesand Geology Special Publication 42</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Jonathan C. Matti</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Western Region, Earth Surface Processes Team</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Project geologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>U.S. Geological Survey520 North Park Avenue, Rm 355</address>
               <city>Tucson</city>
               <state>Arizona</state>
               <postal>85719</postal>
               <country>United States of America</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>520-670-5577</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>520-670-5113</cntfax>
            <cntemail>jmatti@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2003/0301/images/yuc_map.gif</browsen>
         <browsed>Reduced-size image of the entire map sheet, 425x300 pixels, 43k bytes. 475x334 pixels, 56k bytes.</browsed>
         <browset>GIF</browset>
      </browse>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2003/0301/yuc_map.pdf</browsen>
         <browsed>Navigable portable document format file (.pdf) image of the geologic map, topographicbase, Correlation of Map Units, Description of Map Units and key to point and linesymbols.</browsed>
         <browset>PDF</browset>
      </browse>
      <datacred>Photogrammetric Geologic Compilation:  The U.S. Geological Survey's PhotogrammetricPlotter Laboratory in Denver, Colorado (James Messerich, photogrammetrist) provided KernPG-2 stereographic plotters that enabled the high-precision, high-accuracy transfer ofgeologic linework and point data from aerial photographs to a scale-stable cartographicbase.
Scientific Peer Review:  The database and plot file benefitted from technical reviews byR.F. Yerkes, P.  Stone, F.K. Miller, and D.  Bedford.  We thank Peter M.  Sadler andMichael O. Woodbourne for discussions of the stratigraphy and structure of rocks in theYucaipa quadrangle.
Programmatic Credit:  Geologic mapping, topical studies, and digital preparation forthis database were sponsored jointly by the following: (1) the U.S. Geological Survey'sNational Cooperative Geologic Mapping Program, the National Earthquake Hazards Program,and the Mineral Resources Program; (2) California Geological Survey; (3) San BernardinoValley Municipal Water District provided funding support for database development; (4)U.S.  Forest Service (San Bernardino National Forest). Mr. Raj Daniel of the SanBernardino National Forest facilitated funding support of this database.</datacred>
      <native>SunOS, 5.6, sun4u UNIXARC/INFO version 7.2.1</native>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Jonathan C. Matti</origin>
            <origin>Douglas M. Morton</origin>
            <origin>Brett F. Cox</origin>
            <origin>Katherine J. Kendrick</origin>
            <pubdate>2003</pubdate>
            <title>Geologic map and digital database of the Redlands 7.5' quadrangle, San Bernardino andRiverside Counties, California</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>03-302</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Menlo Park, California</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2003/0302/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>The combination of detailed and reconnaissance techniques used to generate the Yucaipaquadrangle database yielded a data set whose quality necessarily varies from location tolocation.  Some areas were examined in great detail in order to solve specific geologicproblems or to clarify the description or geologic relations of a particular map unit.Other areas were examined less carefully or were not examined at all.  As a result, someparts of the Yucaipa data set have greater attribute accuracy and attribute confidencethan others.
ATTRIBUTE ACCURACY
The attribute-accuracy statement for the Yuciapa database incorporates four elements:(1) map-unit description and attribution, (2) geotechnical standards against which theobservations are measured, (3) map-unit identification, and (4) description of linearand planar geologic structures.
Map-unit description and attribution:
Geologic-map units in the Yucaipa quadrangle database were described using standardfield methods (see Process_Description 1 of 6).  Consistent with these methods andconsistent with the time available to assemble the data set, the database authors haveassigned standard geologic attributes to geologic lines, points, and polygons identifiedin the database.
Geotechnical standards for geologic descriptions:
Plutonic rock classification:  Plutonic rocks and their deformed equivalents areclassified in accordance with the International Union of Geological SciencesSubcommission on the Systematics of Igneous Rocks (1973; Streckeisen, 1976).
Sedimentary rock classifications:  Sandstones are classified in accordance with thescheme suggested by Friedman and Sanders (1978, Table 7-4).  For all sedimentarymaterials, bedding-thickness classification follows Ingram (1954) and grain-sizeclassification follows Wentworth (1922).
Surficial-materials classification:  Surficial materials are mapped and classifiedaccording to a southern California-wide classification scheme being developed by theSouthern California Areal Mapping Project (SCAMP).
Terminology for slope-failure deposits (landslides and other slope-failure types)follows Varnes (1978).
Color classification:  The matrix color of surficial materials and their pedogenic soilsis classified according to the Munsell soil-color charts (Munsell, 1975).  Bedrockcolors also are classified according to the Munsell system, supplemented by theRock-Color Chart distributed by the Geological Society of America (reprinted 1970).
Map-unit identification
Geologic-map units in the Yucaipa quadrangle represent packages of geologic materialswhose overall physical properties differ sufficiently from other such units as toconstitute discrete mappable entities.  From localities where map units in thequadrangle first were recognized and defined, they were extended to other areas througha mapping process that includes (a) direct outcrop observation, (b) interpretation ofsubsurface boring logs, and (c) aerial-photographic extrapolation into areas where siteobservation was not conducted.  The data contained in the coverage yuc_obs indicates thedensity of observation and data localities in the Yucaipa quadrangle, and is a measureof whether a map unit at a particular location was identified on the basis of hands-ondata or extrapolation.
Map-unit boundaries (geologic contacts) and faults identified along mapping traversestypically were extended laterally by using aerial photographs and binoculars to projector interpolate the contact or fault to its next recorded occurrence along a nearbytraverse.  Only rarely were individual geologic contacts or fault lines walked out todetermine their variability and character throughout the map area.  The boundingcontacts of each surficial unit and the location of fault scarps that traverse the unitswere plotted by using a PG-2 photogrammetric plotter that allows location accuracyequivalent to the accuracy standard for the topographic-contour base.
Description of geologic structures
Geologic structures (planar structures displayed as lines, and structures at specificpoints) in the Yucaipa quadrangle are described and attributed according to the schemedescribed by Matti and others (1997a,b).  These classifications generally followconventional schemes for classifying geologic lines and points (Reynolds and others,1995).
ATTRIBUTE CONFIDENCE
For digital version 1.0 of the database, the coverage yuc_obs is a proxy for attributeconfidence:  the number of direct observations within a map unit from place to place inthe quadrangle proxies for the confidence with which the unit and its attributes arebelieved to be accurately identified.  Future releases of the Yucaipa data set willdelineate a more objective, empirical basis for map-unit identification and attributeaccuracy (map-unit and attribute confidence).
Friedman, G.M., and Sanders, J.E., 1978, Principles of sedimentology:  New York, JohnWiley &amp; Sons, 792 p.
Ingram, R.L., 1954, Terminology for the thickness of stratification and parting units insedimentary rocks: Geological Society of America Bulletin, v. 65, p. 937-938.
International Union of Geological Sciences Subcommission on the Systematics of IgneousRocks, 1973, Plutonic rocks:  Geotimes, v.  18, no. 10, p. 26-30.
Matti, J.C., Powell, R.E., Miller, F.K., Kennedy, S.A., Ruppert, K.R., Morton, G.L., andCossette, P.M., 1997a, Geologic-line attributes for digital geologic-map databasesproduced by the Southern California Areal Mapping Project (SCAMP), Version 1.0:U.S.Geological Survey Open-File Report 97-861
Matti, J.C., Miller, F.K., Powell, R.E., Kennedy, S.A., Bunyapanasarn, T.P., Koukladas,Catherine, Hauser, R.M., and Cossette, P.M., 1997b, Geologic-point attributes fordigital geologic-map databases produced by the Southern California Areal Mapping Project(SCAMP), Version 1.0: U.S.Geological Survey Open-File Report 97-859
Munsell Color, 1975, Munsell soil color charts, 1975 edition   Baltimore, Maryland,Macbeth Division of Kollmorgen Corporation.
Reynolds, M.W., Queen, J.E., and Taylor, R.B., 1995, Cartographic and digital standardfor geologic map information:  U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 95-525
Streckeisen A., 1976, To each plutonic rock its proper name: Earth Science Reviews, v.12, p. 1-33.
Varnes, D.J., 1978, Slope movement types and processes, in Schuster, R.L., and Krizek,R.J., eds., Landslides: analysis and control:  Washington, D.C., Transportation ResearchBoard, National Academy of Sciences, Special Report 176, p. 11-33.
Wentworth, C.K., 1922, A scale of grade and class terms for clastic sediments:  Journalof Geology, v. 30, p.  377-392.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Polygon and chain-node topology present.
The areal extent of the map is represented digitally by an appropriately projected(Polyconic projection), mathematically generated box.  Consequently, polygons intersectingthe lines that comprise the map boundary are closed by that boundary.  Polygons internalto the map boundary are completely enclosed by line segments that are themselves a set ofsequentially numbered coordinate pairs.  Point data are represented by coordinate pairs.</logic>
      <complete>The geologic map and digital database of the Yucaipa 7.5' quadrangle contain new datathat have been subjected to scientific peer review and are a substantially completerepresentation of the current state of knowledge concerning the geology of thequadrangle.
Information for geologic units, geologic contacts, and faults by necessity isgeneralized.  Although derived from data collected at individual observation stations,the characteristics of map units, their bounding contacts, and faults have been averagedand reduced to attributes that describe each map unit and each line element as a whole.This averaging process is necessary because of the intrinsic variability that geologicunits, contacts, and faults display spatially: in detail, their characteristicsnecessarily vary geographically, although certain core attributes persist.  To accountfor this variability and yet still characterize the major defining attributes ofgeologic entities, the database authors have selected and archived certain geologiccharacteristics but omitted others.  In such cases, details were sacrificed in theinterest of defining the average character of the geologic features.
Map-unit completeness: For map-unit polygons, version 1.0 of the Yucaipa database doesnot exploit the full potential afforded by the data-model and attribute scheme proposedby Matti and others (1997a).  The file yuc_geo.pat contains limited information aboutpolygon themes such as geologic name and the thickness of geologic-map units, as well asinformation about unique attributes that distinguish a map unit within a polygon or aparticular subset of polygons.  Additional lithologic-attribute data are available inthe INFO data table yuc_summ.rel, including age-related data and major rock type.  Otherthan this minimal information, however, the Yucaipa database for geologic-map units(yuc_geo) lacks the comprehensive information content of the .pdf files (yuc_dmu.pdf andyuc_cmu.pdf).
Line and Point Completeness: For line and point data, the Yucaipa database exploits theattribution scheme proposed by Matti and others (1997a,b).  This scheme allows geologicelements represented as lines (geologic contacts, faults, fold axes, geomorphicfeatures) and points (bedding orientations, foliation orientations, fault dips) to beassigned a full spectrum of attributes ranging from contact and fault type to geologicage of linear and point features.  Some of these attributes are embedded directly withinthe line and point data bases (.aat and .pat, respectively).  Most line and pointattributes are stored as codes in two INFO data tables (lines.rel and points.rel).
A complete description of the SCAMP polygon, line, and point data coding schemes isavailable in U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Reports OF-97-859, OF-97-860, andOF-97-861 (full source citations follow):
Matti, J.C., Powell, R.E., Miller, F.K., Kennedy, S.A., Ruppert, K.R., Morton, G.L., andCossette, P.M., 1997a, Geologic-line attributes for digital geologic-map databasesproduced by the Southern California Areal Mapping Project (SCAMP), Version 1.0: U.S.Geological Survey Open-File Report 97-861http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/1997/0861/
Matti, J.C., Miller, F.K., Powell, R.E., Kennedy, S.A., Bunyapanasarn, T.P., Koukladas,Catherine, Hauser, R.M., and Cossette, P.M., 1997b, Geologic-point attributes fordigital geologic-map databases produced by the Southern California Areal Mapping Project(SCAMP), Version 1.0: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 97-859http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/1997/0859/
Matti, J.C., Miller, F.K., Powell, R.E., Kennedy, S.A., and Cossette, P.M., 1997c,Geologic-polygon attributes for digital geologic-map databases produced by the SouthernCalifornia Areal Mapping Project (SCAMP), Version 1.0: U.S. Geological Survey Open-FileReport 97-860http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/1997/0860/</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>Nationwide geologic-map accuracy standards for geologic line and point features have notbeen developed and adopted by the U.S.  Geological Survey and other earth-scienceentities.  Until such standards are developed, the Southern California Areal MappingProject (SCAMP) uses internal map-accuracy standards for 1:24,000-scale geologic mapsproduced by the project.
In the Yucaipa 1:24,000 scale quadrangle, geologic lines are judged to meet themap-accuracy standard if they are located to within &#x98;+/-15 meters relative to topographicor cultural features on the base map.  Within the database, line data that are judged tomeet the map-accuracy standard are denoted in the data table lines.rel by the attributecode .MEE. (meets); line data that may not meet the map-accuracy standard are denoted bythe attribute code .MNM. (may not meet).  On geologic-map plots and other plotsgenerated from the geologic database, line data that are judged to meet the map-accuracystandard are denoted by solid lines; line data that may not meet the map-accuracystandard are denoted by dashed or dotted lines.
In the database and on geologic-map plots, no cartographic device exists for denotingthe map-accuracy for geologic-point data (symbols for bedding, foliation, lineations,etc.).
Three sources of positional error exist for geologic elements in the Yucaipa quadrangledatabase:
(1) Positional accuracy of field observations: observation stations (data localities)were located either on aerial photographs or on the topographic basemap of the Yucaipaquadrangle by referencing hypsographic and planimetric features on the basemap.
(2) Transfer of line and point data from aerial photographs to the topographic base:For bedrock geologic materials, point data, contacts, and faults were visuallytransferred to scale-stable copies of the topographic base map.  For most surficialgeologic materials, geologic contacts and fault scarps were transferred to the base mapthrough the use of a PG-2 sterographic plotter that allows geologic elements to belocated with an accuracy and precision equivalent to the standard for thetopographic-contour base.
(3) Positional fidelity during digital data processing: the maximum transformation RootMean Square (RMS) error acceptable for 7.5' quadrangle transformation and data input is0.003 (1.8 meters).  The horizontal positional accuracy of line and point entities waschecked by visual comparison of hard-copy plots with base-stable source data.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
                  <pubdate>1967, photorevised 1980</pubdate>
                  <title>Topographic basemap of the Yucaipa quadrangle, southernCalifornia</title>
                  <geoform>map</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Reston, Virginia</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>Stable base material (greenline chronoflex for geologic compilation; .007 mil clearfilmblackline for topographic basemap image)</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1967</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Topographic basemap</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>USGS Yucaipa, 1967</srccitea>
            <srccontr>The Yucaipa topographic basemap served as the reference standard by which the databaseauthors located the position of observation stations and geologic structures (geologiccontacts, faults, fold axes).  Scale-stable copies of the basemap also were used totransfer geologic information from aerial photographs to basemap using a PG-2stereographic plotter.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Pictorial Crafts, Inc. (contracted to the U.S. Geological Survey)</origin>
                  <pubdate>1975</pubdate>
                  <title>Pictorial Crafts aerial photography</title>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>Paper true-color aerial photographs</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <rngdates>
                     <begdate>197505</begdate>
                     <enddate>197506</enddate>
                  </rngdates>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Paper true-color aerial photographs</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Pictorial Crafts, Inc., 1975</srccitea>
            <srccontr>The Pictorial Crafts aerial photography provides true-color rendering of geologic andgeomorphic features in the Yucaipa quadrangle and throughout the San Bernardino Basin.The E-W flight lines were the primary aerial-photography resource used by the authors tolocate the position of observation stations and to plot the positions of geologicstructures (geologic contacts, faults, fold axes).  Although their 1975 vintage post-datesurbanization that obscures some geologic features, the photography was helpful inrecognizing geologic features whose color is a distinguishing characteristic.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Stabilization and Conservation Service</origin>
                  <pubdate>1952</pubdate>
                  <title>U.S. Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Stabilization and Conservation Service, 1952photography (Symbol AXM, AXL)</title>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>20000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>Paper black-and-white aerial photographs</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1952</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>1952 date imprint on positive print</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>ASCS 1952 photography (Symbol AXM, AXL)</srccitea>
            <srccontr>The ASCS photography provides systematic aerial-photographic cover of the Yucaipaquadrangle and the rest of the San Bernardino Basin, along N-S flight lines.  Thisorientation contrasts with the typical E-W orientation of most photographic series, andprovides a different perspective of geologic and geomorphic features.  Because the ASCSphotography pre-dates much urbanization that obscures land-form features, it was helpfulin recognizing geologic and geomorphic features that have been obliterated by humanactivities in the last 50 years or so.  The database authors used the 1952 ASCSphotography to augment and refine observations made using the 1975 Pictorial Craftsphotography, and to delineate features in the Yucaipa Valley and Mentone areas.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Department of Interior, Geological Survey</origin>
                  <pubdate>1966</pubdate>
                  <title>U.S. Department of Interior, Geological Survey 1966 photography (symbol GS-VBNS)</title>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>30000 (approximately)</srcscale>
            <typesrc>Paper black-and-white aerial photographs</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1966</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>1966 date imprint on positive print</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>USGS 1966 photography (symbol GS-VBNS)</srccitea>
            <srccontr>The USGS photography (symbol GS-VBNS) provides systematic aerial photographic coverage ofthe Yucaipa quadrangle and the rest of the San Bernardino Basin, along E-W flight lines.Although their 1966 vintage post-dates some urbanization that obscures geologic features,moderate vertical exaggeration in this photo series enhances subtle geologic andgeomorphic features not easily recognized in other photoseries. The database authors usedthe 1966 GS-VBNS photography to augment and refine observations made using the 1975Pictorial Crafts photography, and especially to delineate subtle features in the Mentoneand northern Yucaipa Valley areas.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Stabilization and Conservation Service</origin>
                  <pubdate>1938</pubdate>
                  <title>U.S. Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Stabilization and Conservation Service, 1938photography (Symbol AXM, AXL)</title>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>20000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>Paper black-and-white aerial photographs</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1938</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>1938 date imprint on positive print</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>ASCS 1938 photography (Symbol AXM, AXL)</srccitea>
            <srccontr>The 1938 ASCS photography provides the most regionally extensive early-vintage aerialimages available for southern California, including the Yucaipa quadrangle.  The 1938photography pre-dates much urbanization that obscures land-form features, and thus washelpful in recognizing geologic and geomorphic features that have been obliterated byhuman activities in the last 60 years or so.  The database authors used the 1938photography to augment and refine observations made using the 1975 Pictorial Craftsphotography, and to delineate pre-urbanization features in the Yucaipa Valley and Mentoneareas.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Spence Airplane Photos, Los Angeles (flown under contract to the U.S.  Geological Survey)</origin>
                  <pubdate>1930</pubdate>
                  <title>Spence aerial photography, 1930</title>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>18000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>Paper black-and-white aerial photographs</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1930</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>1930 date imprint on positive print</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Spence Aerial Photography, 1930</srccitea>
            <srccontr>The Spence aerial photography consists of a single flight line flown along the San AndreasFault in southern California, including the Yucaipa quadrangle.  The 1930 photographypre-dates much urbanization that obscures land-form features, and thus was helpful indelineating geologic and geomorphic features (fault scarps, shutter ridges, lineaments)that have been obliterated by human activities in the last 70 years or so.  The databaseauthors used the 1930 Spence photography to interpret geomorphic details of the SanAndreas Fault Zone (San Bernardino Strand).</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Matti, J.C.</origin>
                  <origin>Morton, D.M.</origin>
                  <origin>Cox, B.F.</origin>
                  <origin>Carson, S.E.</origin>
                  <origin>Yetter, T.J.</origin>
                  <pubdate>1992</pubdate>
                  <title>Geologic map of the Yucaipa quadrangle, southern California</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
                     <issue>92-445</issue>
                  </serinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>stable base material</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <rngdates>
                     <begdate>1930</begdate>
                     <enddate>1991</enddate>
                  </rngdates>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication dataTime period of information content for geologic information in the 1992 Yucaipa quadranglemap reflects (1) the vintage (1930, 1938, 1953, 1966, 1975) of archival aerial photographsused to interpret geologic features and (2) ground observations made by the map authorsbetween 1977 and 1992.</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Matti and others, 1992</srccitea>
            <srccontr>The 1992 analog geologic map of the Yucaipa quadrangle is the source of much of thegeologic line, point, and map-unit data represented in digital version 1.0.  Lithologic,structural, and stratigraphic data for sedimentary deposits of the San Timoteo beds ofFrick (1921) are retained, as are boundaries and structural orientations of crystallinebedrock units.  Most faults are the same as in the analog version,
The information content of digital version 1.0 of the Yucaipa quadrangle database differsin some important ways from that of the analog version (Matti and others, 1992).  Asdescribed in Process_Step 4 of 6, between 1994 and 1998 one of the database authors (J.C.Matti) reinterpreted some of the Quaternary surficial materials and some faultrelationships.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Smith, R. E.</origin>
                  <pubdate>1959</pubdate>
                  <title>Geology of the Mill Creek area, San Bernardino County, California</title>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Los Angeles, California</pubplace>
                     <publish>University of California</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>unpublished M.A. thesis, 95 p.</othercit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>20000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>paper</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1959</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication dataTime period of information content for geologic information in the report by Smith (1959)reflects the date that the thesis was approved by the thesis committee and submitted tothe University of California, Los Angeles.</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Smith (1959)</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Smith (1959) is the source of structural-attitude data (bedding orientation) in two smallparts of the Yucaipa quadrangle: (1) in the NE 1/4 Sec. 17, T1S R1W, and (2) northwest ofMorton Peak, north and south of the boundary between Sec. 1 and 12, T1S R2W.  These areidentified in the database and on the geologic-map plot.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Geologic mapping for analog map (Matti and others, 1992)
Geologic data for the Yucaipa quadrangle were collected in the field by the data-setauthors.  The field data were plotted on aerial photographs and on a 1:24,000-scalebasemap (U.S. Geological Survey, Yucaipa 7.5' quadrangle, 1967, photorevised, 1980).
Bedrock map units were described, mapped, and interpreted on the basis oftraverse-mapping methods.  Observations were recorded along each traverse, locations forwhich are stored in the coverage yuc_obs. Information recorded at these stationsprovides the basis for the identification and characterization of each bedrock mapunit..  Map-unit boundaries (geologic contacts) and faults identified along eachtraverse typically were extended laterally by using aerial photographs and binoculars toproject or interpolate the fault or contact to its next recorded occurrence along anearby traverse.  A few sedimentary-layering attitudes were determined through binocularobservation rather than from site determinations; these are identified in the data baseand on the geologic-map plot.
Surficial-materials map units were described, mapped, and interpreted on the basis ofaerial-photographic interpretation augmented by observations at specific stations.  Thebounding contacts of each surficial unit and the location of fault scarps that traversethe units were plotted by using a PG-2 photogrammetric plotter that allows locationaccuracy equivalent to the accuracy standard for the topographic-contour base.  Thecoverage yuc_obs shows the position of observation stations data from which were used todetermine geologic characteristics of the surficial map units.
GEOLOGIC CONTRIBUTIONS BY AUTHORS:
Jonathan C. Matti - mapped and interpreted Quaternary surficial materials; faults of theSan Timoteo Canyon, Crafton Hills, Chicken Hill, Yucaipa Valley graben complex, and SanAndreas zones; San Timoteo Canyon formation; crystalline rocks in the Santa Ana RiverCanyon and areas to the west; crystalline rocks in the southeast corner of thequadrangle - 1979, 1985-1986, 1988, 1991.
Douglas M. Morton - mapped crystalline rocks in the Crafton Hills area - 1977.
Brett F. Cox - mapped crystalline rocks in the Crafton Hills area, in the east-centralmargin of the quadrangle, and between the Wilson Creek and San Bernardino strands of theSan Andreas fault; mapped the Warm Springs Canyon formation in Mill Creek Canyon;Quaternary materials and faults adjacent to the San Bernardino Strand between Mill Creekand Santa Ana River - 1979 to 1980.
Scott E. Carson - mapped crystalline rocks in the vicinity of Morton Peak and Santa AnaRiver Canyon; described Quaternary surficial Materials in Yucaipa Valley - 1979 through1981.
Thomas J. Yetter - mapped crystalline rocks in the vicinity of Morton Peak and Santa AnaRiver Canyon; beds of the Mill Creek Formation in lower Mill Creek Canyon - 1979.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1977 through 1991</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Analog geologic-map preparation (Matti and others, 1992)
The 1992 geologic-map product was produced from geologic linework drafted on a1:24,000-scale greenline chronoflex of the Yucaipa 7.5' quadrangle.  Source materials werepaper field sheets produced by each map author, and pencil linework generated by a PG-2stereographic plotter on a scale-stable 1:24,000-scale chronoflex of the Yucaipa 7.5'quadrangle.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1991</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Post-1992 revision of Yucaipa quadrangle geologic map
After the 1992 geologic map of the Yucaipa quadrangle was released (Matti and others,1992), additional observation and interpretation by J.C. Matti led to revisions of thatversion.  Changes included: (1) re-interpretation of fault-line relations for the SanBernardino Strand of the San Andreas Fault west of the mouth of Santa Ana River Canyon;(2) re-interpretation of surficial geologic materials in the vicinity of Mentone and alongthe drainage of Wildwood Canyon along its entire extent; and (3) reinterpretation of thesouth end of the Chicken Hill Fault in the vicinity of Interstate Highway 10, includingthe recognition of a probable fault scarp that was obliterated by construction of theHighway right-of-way.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1995-1998</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Digital processing of Topographic Base Map
The basemap image (yuc.tif) was prepared by scanning a scale-stable right-reading,blackline .007-mil clear-film positive of the U.S.  Geological Survey, 1:24,000-scaleYucaipa 7.5' quadrangle topographic map (1967, photorevised, 1980).  Scanning was doneusing an Anatech Eagle 4080 monochrome 800 dots-per-inch scanner at a resolution of 500dpi.  The raster scan was converted to a monochromatic image in ARC/INFO.  No elements ofthe base layer are attributed.  The base map is provided for reference only.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1996</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Digital Preparation of Geologic-map Information
Geologic line and point data on scale-stable greenline chronoflex copies of the Yucaipa7.5' quadrangle were digitized and simultaneously converted to ARC/INFO coveragesthrough the application and utilization of the graphical user interface ALACARTEdeveloped by the USGS (Fitzgibbon, 1991; Fitzgibbon and Wentworth, 1991; Wentworth andFitzgibbon, 1991) running on a Data General Aviion workstation.  The databasesubsequently was edited and tagged on a Sun SPARC20 computer system running Solaris v.2.4 and ARC/INFO v. 7.0.4 and v.  7.1.1.  Geologic point data were captured usingALACARTE and ARC/INFO v.7.0.4.
CONTRIBUTIONS BY DATABASE EDITORS:
Pamela M. Cossette - responsible for final geologic database editing, assembling thedatabase and plot-file products, and production of metadata
Bradley Jones - responsible for significant data capture
Melinda C. Wright - responsible for geologic point-data capture and preliminary databaseediting
Stephen A. Kennedy - responsible for initial database editing
Fitzgibbon, T.T., 1991, ALACARTE installation and system manual (version 1.0): U.S.Geological Survey, Open-File Report 91-587B.
Fitzgibbon, T.T., and Wentworth, C.M., 1991, ALACARTE user interface - AML code anddemonstration maps (version 1.0): U.S. Geological Survey, Open-File Report 91-587A.
Wentworth, C.M., and Fitzgibbon, T.T., 1991, ALACARTE user manual (version 1.0): U. S.Geological Survey Open-File Report 91-587C.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1995-2000</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Observation-station coverage yuc_obs
The coverage yuc_obs contains the locations of observation stations that the datasetauthors used to describe geologic materials and geologic structures in the Yucaipaquadrangle.  Several kinds of observation stations are included:
(1) Field observations made by the dataset authors.  These are represented by theauthor's name (e.g., Jonathan C.  Matti), and the station ID (e.g., JF, which representsJ.C. Matti, notebook F);
(2) Subsurface borings obtained by the California Department of Transportation atoverpassing and underpassing right-of-ways along the Interstate and State Highwaysystems;
(3) Subsurface borings obtained by the U.S. Geological Survey's Water Resources Division(WRD);
(4) Subsurface borings obtained by various private geotechnical-engineering firms;
(5) Soil-profile descriptions obtained by the Natural Resources and Conservation Service(Woodruff and Brock, 1980, sheet 10);
Woodruff, G.A., and Brock, W.Z., 1980, Soil survey of San Bernardino County,southwestern part, California:  U.S.  Department of Agriculture, Soil ConservationService, 64 p., scale 1:24,000.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1995-2000</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Preliminary metadata documentation for version 1.0 of the Yucaipa quadrangle geologicdatabase was prepared by Pamela M.  Cossette using FGDCMETA.AML ver. 1.2 05/14/98 onARC/INFO data set /gis_3/scamp/arccovers/sanber/yucaipa/yuc1216a.  The metadata hasundergone several revisions as the Yucaipa 7.5' quadrangle data was refined.</procdesc>
            <procdate>2000</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Creation of original metadata record</procdesc>
            <procdate>20030827</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntorgp>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                     <cntper>Pamela M. Cossette</cntper>
                  </cntorgp>
                  <cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
                     <address>U.S. Geological SurveyRoom 202West 904 Riverside Avenue</address>
                     <city>Spokane</city>
                     <state>Washington</state>
                     <postal>99201-1087</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>509-368-3123</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>509-368-3199</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>pcossette@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Vector</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>1484</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>String</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>4062</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>GT-polygon composed of chains</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>1485</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <mapproj>
               <mapprojn>Polyconic</mapprojn>
               <polycon>
                  <longcm>-117.0625</longcm>
                  <latprjo>34.00</latprjo>
                  <feast>0.0</feast>
                  <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
               </polycon>
            </mapproj>
            <planci>
               <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>0.0027671901044</absres>
                  <ordres>0.0027671901044</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>Meters</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1927</horizdn>
            <ellips>Clarke 1866</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378206.4</semiaxis>
            <denflat>294.98</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <overview>
         <eaover>The ARC/INFO version of the digital geologic database of the Yucaipa 7.5'quadrangleconsists of five coverages:&gt;yuc_geo (geologic map units and linear geologic entities)&gt;yuc_pts (geologic point features)&gt;yuc_obs (distribution of data stations)&gt;yuc_ptsorn (geologic line ornamentation)&gt;yuc_ldr (map-unit label leaders).Three additional INFO tables are included in the data set:yuc_summ.rel (provides general information about each geologic-map unit, includinggeneral lithologic features, geologic age, and geologic origin which applies to allpolygons of a specified map unit)
lines.rel - (provides information about geologic features displayed as lines on the map.For a complete description of attributes in lines.rel, refer to USGS Open-File Report97-861: see Entity_and_Attribute_Detail_Citation)
points.rel - (provides information about geologic features displayed as points on themap.  For a complete description of attributes in points.rel, refer to USGS Open-FileReport 97-859: see Entity_and_Attribute_Detail_Citation)
1)  The coverage yuc_geo contains information about geologic-map units (represented bypolygons) and planar geologic features that bound or break them (e.g. geologic contactsand faults) represented by lines.  The polygons have cartographic and geologicattributes contained in yuc_geo.pat; the lines have cartographic and geologic attributescontained in yuc_geo.aat.  For display purposes, the geology coverage contains twoannotation subclasses: geo contains unit labels, and fault contains formal fault names.
2)  The coverage yuc_pts contains analyzable structural data, including information thatdescribes the types and orientation of planar and linear geologic features such asbedding, foliation, fault-plane dip, and fold-hinge plunge. One annotation subclass isincluded in the geologic points coverage which displays the respective dip and plungevalues associated with individual point data.
3)  The coverage yuc_obs contains point data that repesent the locality of data stationsassociated with multiple authors and sources, all of which have contributed geologicdata.  The locality data represented in yuc_obs serves several purposes: (1) as a proxyfor author confidence in unit identification, (2) as a means of identifying eachauthor's contribution, and (3) as a means of identifying data from sources other thanthe USGS authors.  One annotation subclass, obs, identifies five particular locations:four Natural Resources Conservation Service (NRCS) soil profile description localitiesand one USGS Water Resource Division (WRD) well-log data locality.
4)  The coverage yuc_ptsorn stores point data that represent ornamentation for geologiclines (e.g. strike slip arrows, bar and ball on down-thrown block, etc.)
5)  The coverage yuc_ldr contains annotation leaders that point to unit labels that areplaced outside the perimeter of a particular geologic polygon.  These cartographic lineentities are attributed with only  a single attribute, L-SYMB, and all have the samevalue, 1.</eaover>
         <eadetcit>A complete description of the polygon, line, and point data coding schemes is availablein U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Reports OF-97-859, OF-97-860, and OF-97-861 (fullsource citations follow):
Matti, J.C., Miller, F.K., Powell, R.E., Kennedy, S.A., Bunyapanasarn, T.P., Koukladas,Catherine, Hauser, R.M., and Cossette, P.M., 1997b, Geologic-point attributes fordigital geologic-map databases produced by the Southern California Areal Mapping Project(SCAMP), Version 1.0: U.S.Geological Survey Open-File Report 97-859
Matti, J.C., Miller, F.K., Powell, R.E., Kennedy, S.A., and Cossette, P.M., 1997c,Geologic-polygon attributes for digital geologic-map databases produced by the SouthernCalifornia Areal Mapping Project (SCAMP), Version 1.0: U.S.Geological Survey Open-FileReport 97-860
Matti, J.C., Powell, R.E., Miller, F.K., Kennedy, S.A., Ruppert, K.R., Morton, G.L., andCossette, P.M., 1997a, Geologic-line attributes for digital geologic-map databasesproduced by the Southern California Areal Mapping Project (SCAMP), Version 1.0:U.S.Geological Survey Open-File Report 97-861</eadetcit>
      </overview>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>yuc_geo.pat</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Geologic units shown on geologic map in Postscript (.ps) and Portable DocumentFormat (.pdf) files</enttypd>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>TAG</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>A reference label for subgroups of polygons of the geologic-map unit identified by LABL.Every polygon subgroup has certain attributes in common with all other polygons of the mapunit, but each subgroup has unique, distinguishing attributes that warrant recognition inthe database although those distinguishing characteristics do not provide a basis forrecognizing new map units (for example, geographic variations in properties such as grainsize, thickness, and clast compositiion).
TAG serves one additional purpose: it functions as the relate item that associates eachpolygon with its attributes stored in the polygon-attribute data table, YUC_SUMM.REL.
TAG is defined as LABL followed by an upper-case letter, e.g., QwA, QwB, or QwC, etc.Most map units in the Yucaipa databse have only one TAG designation, TAG A; map unitshaving polygon subsets representing characteristics sufficiently distinct from those ofthe overall unit include: Qw (QwA, QwB), Qf (QfA, QfB), Qya4 (Qya4A, Qya4B), Qya5(Qya5A, Qya5B), Qvof3 (Qvof3A, Qvof3B0, Tgr (TgrA, TgrB).</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>LABL</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Geologic map unit label. Plain text is substituted for specialized geologic age symbols.</attrdef>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Kao</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Granodiorite of Angeles Oaks</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Kcc</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Monzogranite of City Creek</edomv>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Mzc</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Diorite of Cram Peak</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Mzd</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Diorite</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Mzfg</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Foliated granitoid rock</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Mzg</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Granitoid rock</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Mzga</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Orthogneiss of Alger Creek</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Mzgr</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Mesocratic granitoid rock</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Mzi</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Inclusion-rich granitoid rock</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Mzmg</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Mylonitic and cataclastic granitoid rock</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Mzmm</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Mixed mafic rocks</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Mzpsg</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Pelona Schist, greenstone unit</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Mzpsm</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Pelona schist, muscovite schist</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>QTstu</edomv>
                  <edomvd>San Timoteo beds of Frick (1921), upper member</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qvya</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Very young axial-valley deposits (latest Holocene)</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qvyc</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Very young colluvial deposits (latest Holocene)</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qvyf</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Very young alluvial-fan deposits (latest Holocene)</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qvyls</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Very young landslide deposits (latest Holocene)</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qoa1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Old axial-valley deposits, Unit 1</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qoa2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Old axial-valley deposits, Unit 2</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qoa3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Old axial-valley deposits, Unit 3</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qof</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Old alluvial-fan deposits</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qof1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Old alluvial-fan deposits, Unit 1</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qof2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Old alluvial-fan deposits, Unit 2</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qof3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Old alluvial-fan deposits, Unit 3</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qols</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Old landslide deposits</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qvoa3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Very old axial-valley deposits, Unit 3</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qvof3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Very old alluvial-fan deposits, Unit 3</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qvos</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Very old surficial deposits, undifferentiated</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qvyw</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Very young wash deposits, active (latest Holocene)</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qvyw1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Very young wash deposits, Unit 1 (latest Holocene)</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qvyw2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Very young wash deposits, Unit 2 (latest Holocene)</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qya</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Young deposits of axial-valley floors</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qya1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Young axial-valley deposits, Unit 1</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qya3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Young axial-valley deposits, Unit 3</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qya4</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Young axial-valley deposits, Unit 4</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qya5</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Young axial-valley deposits, Unit 5</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qyf</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Young alluvial-fan deposits</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qyf1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Young alluvial-fan deposits, Unit 1</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qyf2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Young alluvial-fan deposits, Unit 2</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qyf3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Young alluvial-fan deposits, Unit 3</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qyf4</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Young alluvial-fan deposits, Unit 4</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qyf5</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Young alluvial-fan deposits, Unit 5</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Qyls</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Young landslide deposits</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Ta</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Andesite to dacite</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Tgr</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Granodiorite</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Tma</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Mill Creek Formation of Gibson (1971), arkose unit</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Tmcp</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Mill Creek Formation of Gibson (1971), Pelona Schist-bearing conglomerate unit</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Tmcv</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Mill Creek Formation of Gibson (1971), volcanic-clast-bearing unit</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Tmm</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Mill Creek Formation of Gibson (1971), mudrock unit</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Tms</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Mill Creek Formation of Gibson (1971), sandstone unit</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Trm</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Porphyritic monzogranite</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>Tw</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Formation of Warm Springs Canyon</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>gg</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Gneissose granitoid rock and gneiss</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>PLABL</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Coded geologic map unit label used to generate plot labels using appropriate stratigraphicsymbols. Geologic units having LABL Mzc, Mzd, Mzfg, Mzg, Mzga, Mzgg, Mzgr, Mzi, Mzmg,Mzmm, Mzpsg, Mzpsm, (Mesozoic), appear in the item PLABL as }c, }d etc.; unit label Trm(Triassic) appears as ^m,  in the item PLABL.  The replacement characters call upstratigraphic age symbols from the GeoAge Font Group.  Map unit labels will plot onderivative  map plots with appropriate stratigraphic symbols if PLABL is used as thesource of unit labels.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>SHDFIL</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Polygon fill pattern from shadeset geology2.shd (included in the data package)</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>SHDPS</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Polygon color from shadeset scamp2.shd (included in the data package) and used to generatethe map plotfile</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>THICK</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Thickness data for geologic unit (sedimentary and surficial), where relevant</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>NAME</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Name of each geologic-map unit</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>UNIQUE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Allows for the description of geologic properties that are unique to a particular polygonor group of polygons</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>SOURCE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Allows identification of sources from which polygon data have been compiled other than theU.S. Geological Survey authors of this database</attrdef>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>yuc_summ.rel</enttypl>
            <enttypd>INFO table containing general information about each geologic-map unit, includinglithologic features, geologic age, and geologic origin which applies to all polygons of aspecified map unit.</enttypd>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>TAG</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The data-base item that relates polygon subgroups to their associated map unit identifiedin the polygon feature attribute table, yuc_geo.pat.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AGEMIN</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The minimum age (youngest possible age) for a geologic-map unit. Data include mimimumestimates for (1) age of formation of sedimentary and igneous rocks and surficialmaterials, (2) metamorphic age for geologic materials that have been metamorphosed, (3)deformation age for geologic materials that have been deformed (folded, faulted,penetratively deformed, brecciated, fractured), and (4) age of alteration for stained andaltered geologic materials.  Data is represented by coded entries (Matti and others,1997b).</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AGEMAX</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The maximum age (oldest possible age) for a geologic-map unit.  Data include maximumestimates for (1) age of formation of sedimentary and igneous rocks and surficialmaterials, (2) metamorphic age  for geologic materials that have been metamorphosed, (3)deformation age for geologic materials that have been deformed (folded, faulted,penetratively deformed, brecciated, fractured), and (4) age of alteration for stained andaltered geologic materials.  Data is represented by coded entries (Matti and others,1997b).</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AGECON</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Indicates the basis for assigning a geologic age to a map unit and the confidence withwhich that age is assigned.  Data is represented by coded entries (Matti and others,1997b).</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>TYPE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Provides a hierarchical classification of the general lithologic types occurring in ageologic-map unit, including whether a particular map unit is a bedrock unit or asurficial unit.  Data is represented by coded entries (Matti and others, 1997b).</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>CLASS</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Provides the stratigraphic classification of a rock unit in terms of the North AmericanCode of Stratigraphic Nomenclature.  Data is represented by coded entries (Matti andothers, 1997b).</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>SURFACE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Identifies geologic and geomorphic characteristics of the upper surface of surficialgeologic units.  Data is represented by coded entries (Matti and others, 1997b).</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>ORIGIN</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Provides coded information for the geologic origin of a map unit.  Data is represented bycoded entries (Matti and others, 1997b).</attrdef>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>yuc_geo.aat</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Geologic lines, which include features such as faults, contacts, and terraces.  (Acomplete description of each line type is available in the data table, lines.rel.)</enttypd>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>L-SYMB</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Calls up the appropriate line symbol from the lineset geoscamp2.lin (included in the datapackage)</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>L-TAG</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Consists of a character and numerical value e.g. C17 which allows the user to relate theline entity to its corresponding definition in the INFO table lines.rel.
Geologic-line types in yuc_geo and their corresponding definitions in lines.rel include(abbreviated from Matti and others, 1997c):</attrdef>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C18</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.contact.landslide.location may not meet accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C26</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.contact.landslide.crown scarp.location may not meet map accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C29</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.contact.sedimentary.location meets map accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C30</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.contact.sedimentary.location may not meet map accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C32</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.contact.sedimentary.location inferred beneath mapped covering unit.location may not meetmap accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C37</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.contact.sedimentary.separates terraced alluvial units.  location meets accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C38</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.contact.sedimentary.separates terraced alluvial units.  location may not meet accuracystandard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C50</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.contact.igneous.location may not meet accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C51</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.contact.igneous.inferred.location may not meet accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C99</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.contact.igneous.scratch boundary</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>CL1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.cartographic line.map boundary</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F10</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.high-angle.normal slip.location observable.may not meet accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F178</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.low-angle.thrust slip.location observable.may not meet map accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F180</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.low-angle.thrust slip.location inferred beneath mapped covering unit.may not meetmap accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F13</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.high-angle.unspecified slip.location inferred.may not meet map accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F19</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.high-angle.unspecified slip.location observable.may not meet map accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.high-angle.strike slip.right lateral.location observable.meets map accuracystandard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F20</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.high-angle.strike slip.right lateral.location observable.may not meet accuracystandard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F22</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.high-angle.normal slip.location observable.may not meet map accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F23</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.high-angle.reverse slip.location observable.may not meet map accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F4</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.high-angle.normal slip.location observable.meets map accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F37</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.high-angle.unspecified slip.questionable existence.may not meet map accuracystandard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F50</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.high-angle.strike slip.right lateral.scarp.meets map accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F52</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.high-angle.normal slip.fault scarp.meets map accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F53</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.high-angle.reverse slip.fault scarp.meets map accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F58</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.high-angle.normal slip.fault scarp.location may not meet map accuracy standard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F67N</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.high-angle.normal slip.fault scarp.identity questionable</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F67R</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.high-angle.normal slip.scarp.identity questionable</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F7</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.high-angle.unspecified slip.location observable.may not not meet map accuracystandard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F8</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault.high-angle.strike slip.right lateral.location observable.may not meet map accuracystandard</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>L-AGECON</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Indicates the confidence with which a geologic age has been assigned to each linear entity</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>L-NAME</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Formal name, where applicable, of linear geologic features</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>L-UNIQUE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Allows for the description of attributes that are unique to a particular linear feature orsegment of a feature, e.g.  faults having associated seismicity</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>L-SOURCE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Allows identification of sources other than the U.S.  Geological Survey authors of thisSCAMP products from which line data have been compiled</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>L-AGEMAX</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Coded statement of the maximum age (oldest age) estimated for geologic contacts and faultsor for segments of such features</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>L-AGEMIN</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Coded statement of the minimum age (youngest age) estimated for geologic contacts andfaults or for segments of such features</attrdef>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>yuc_pts.pat</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Structural point data.</enttypd>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-SYMB</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Calls the point-type from the markerset geoscamp2.mrk (included in the data package)</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-TAG</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Consists of a character(s) and numerical value e.g. FN42 which allows the user to relatethe point entity to its corresponding definition in the INFO table points.rel.</attrdef>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>B19</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.bedding attitude.sedimentary.inclined.binocular observation</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>B2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.bedding attitude.sedimentary.inclined.original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>B23</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.bedding attitude.sedimentary.inclined.compiled data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>B4</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.bedding attitude.sedimentary.vertical.original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>B6</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.bedding attitude.sedimentary.overturned.original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>FC4</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.fault dip direction</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>FN13</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.foliation attitude.igneous.inclined.original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>FN14</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.foliation attitude.igneous.vertical.original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>FN2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.foliation attitude.origin not determined.inclined.original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>FN3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.foliation attitude.origin not determined.vertical.original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>FN31</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.foliation attitude.strain dominated.inclined.original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>FN32</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.foliation attitude.strian dominated.vertical.original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>FN42</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.foliation attitude.metamorphic.inclined.original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>L1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.lineation.origin not determined.original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>L14</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.lineation.high-strain.crushed and streaked minerals.original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>L17</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.lineation.high-strain.aligned mineral grains.original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>L19</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.lineation.metamorphic.crushed and streaked minerals.original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>L37</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.lineation.minor-fold axis.geometry not determined.original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>L40</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.lineation.minor-fold axis.dextral rotation.original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>L43</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.lineation.minor-fold axis.kink band fold.original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>L59</edomv>
                  <edomvd>.lineation. minor-fold axis. sinistral rotation. original data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-SOURCE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Allows identification of all sources of geologic data represented in the Yucaipa geologicmap database</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-UNIQUE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Allows for the description of attributes uniquely associated with a particular point datumlocation</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-AGECON</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Indicates the confidence with which a geologic age is assigned to a point feature</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-DIP</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Dip of planar point features</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-STRIKE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Azimuth strike of planar features</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-DIPDIR</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Azimuthal direction of dip
Note: To date, there is no other way to indicate to the user the cardinal direction of dipusing the traditional convention (traditional geologic notation allows a quadrantdesignation following the dip value).</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-PLUNGE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Lineation plunge value</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-BEARING</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Azimuthal direction of lineation bearing</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-AGEMIN</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Coded statement of the minimum age (youngest age) estimated for geologic featuresrepresented by point data</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-AGEMAX</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Coded statement of the maximum age (oldest age) estimated for geologic featuresrepresented by point data</attrdef>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>yuc_obs.pat</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Data that repesent the locality of data stations associated with multiple authors andsources</enttypd>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-SYMB</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Calls the point-type from the markerset geoscamp2.mrk (included in the data package)</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-TAG</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Point tag which consists of a character(s) and numerical value; allows the user to relatethe point entity to its corresponding definition in the data table, points.rel</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-SOURCE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Allows identification of sources from which point data have been compiled other than theU.S. Geological Survey authors of this product</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-UNIQUE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Allows for the description of attributes uniquely associated with a particular point datumlocation</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-STAT</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Alphanumeric identification of a particular datum location</attrdef>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>NRCS-SWSB-22</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Natural Resources Conservation Service pit/soil profile description</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>NRCS-SWSB-14</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Natural Resources Conservation Service pit/soil profile description</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>NRCS-SWSB-12</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Natural Resources Conservation Service pit/soil profile description</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>NRCS-SWSB-23</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Natural Resources Conservation Service pit/soil profile description</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>WRD-EP</edomv>
                  <edomvd>USGS Water Resources Division well/well-log data</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>yuc_ptsorn.pat</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Line ornamentation</enttypd>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-SYMB</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Calls the point-type from the markerset geoscamp2.mrk (included in the data package)</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>P-TAG</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Point tag which consists of a character(s) and numerical value; allows the user to relatethe point entity to its corresponding definition in the data table, points.rel</attrdef>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>yuc_ldr.aat</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Unit label annotation leaders</enttypd>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>L-SYMB</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Coded integer symbol (1) that calls up the apprporiate line symbol in linesetgeoscamp2.lin</attrdef>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Information Services</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Box 25286 Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>CO</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>303-202-4700</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>303-202-4693</cntfax>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>USGS Open-File Report 03-301</resdesc>
      <distliab>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) provides these geographic data "as is." The USGS makesno guarantee or warranty concerning the accuracy of information contained in thegeographic data.  The USGS further makes no warranties, either expressed or implied asto any other matter whatsoever, including, without limitation, the condition of theproduct, or its fitness for any particular purpose. The burden for determining fitnessfor use lies entirely with the user.  Although these data have been processedsuccessfully on computers at the USGS, no warranty, expressed or implied, is made by theUSGS regarding the use of these data on any other system, nor does the fact ofdistribution constitute or imply any such warranty.
In no event shall the USGS have any liability whatsoever for payment of anyconsequential, incidental, indirect, special, or tort damages of any kind, including,but not limited to, any loss of profits arising out of use of or reliance on thegeographic data or arising out of the delivery, installation, operation, or support byUSGS.
This digital, geologic map database of the Yucaipa 7.5' quadrangle, 1:24,000 map-scale,and any derivative maps thereof, is not meant to be used or displayed at any scalelarger than 1:24,000 (e.g., 1:12,000).</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ARCE</formname>
               <formvern>7.2.1</formvern>
               <formcont>Geologic units and structural features</formcont>
               <filedec>tar and gzip</filedec>
               <transize>2.1</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2003/0301/yuc.tar.gz</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150204</metd>
      <metrd>20040726</metrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Peter N Schweitzer</cntper>
               <cntorg>USGS Midwest Area</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Collection manager, USGS Geoscience Data Clearinghouse, http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Mail Stop 95412201 Sunrise Valley Dr</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192-0002</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>703-648-6533</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>703-648-6252</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pschweitzer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <metac>none</metac>
      <metuc>none</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
