<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>2003</pubdate>
            <title>Sea floor topography and backscatter intensity of the historic area remediation site</title>
            <geoform>remote-sensing image and raster digital data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>01-470</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Woods Hole, MA</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2001/of01-470/</onlink>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Butman, Bradford</origin>
                  <origin>Gutierrez, Benjamin T.</origin>
                  <origin>ten Brink, Marilyn Buchholtz</origin>
                  <origin>Schwab, William C.</origin>
                  <origin>Blackwood, Dann S.</origin>
                  <origin>Mecray, Ellen L.</origin>
                  <origin>Middleton, Tammie J.</origin>
                  <pubdate>2003</pubdate>
                  <title>Photographs of the sea floor offshore of New York and New Jersey</title>
                  <geoform>map, raster digital data, remote-sensing image, tabular digital data, vector digital data</geoform>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
                     <issue>01-470</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Woods Hole, MA</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2001/of01-470/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This data set includes topography and backscatter intensity of the sea floor of the Historic Area Remediation Site (HARS), located offshore of New York and New Jersey.  The data were collected with a multibeam sea floor mapping system on surveys conducted November 23 - December 3, 1996, October 26 - November 11, 1998, and April 6 - 30, 2000.  The surveys were conducted using a Simrad EM 1000 multibeam echo sounder mounted aboard the Canadian Hydrographic Service vessel Frederick G. Creed.  This multibeam system utilizes 60 electronically aimed receive beams spaced at intervals of 2.5 degrees that insonify a strip of sea floor up to 7.5 times the water depth (swath width of 100 to 200 m within the survey area).  The horizontal resolution of the beam on the sea floor is approximately 10% of the water depth (3-5 meters in the survey region).  Vertical resolution is approximately 1 percent of the water depth, or 0.3 m.    Maps derived from the mulitbeam observations show sea floor topography, shaded relief, and backscatter intensity (a measure of sea floor texture and roughness) at a spatial resolution of 3 m/pixel.  These data have been reprocessed from those presented in Butman and others (2002) (see cross reference) to correct for an error in the software that projected the data on a sphere rather than on the WGS84 ellipsoid, and to stretch the backscatter intensity and shaded relief images to match the Hudson Shelf Valley images.  The horizontal error in placement of the data published by Butman and others (2002) was 0 in the northwestern corner of the HARS, and reached about 12 m in the southeastern corner.  Further work is needed to match the backscatter intensity for the 1996, 1998, and 2000 surveys.</abstract>
         <purpose>These data are included in this publication to provide bathymetry and backscatter intensity of the sea floor for maps showing the locations of images and samples obtained in the New York Bight.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <dsstruct>
         <dspart>
            <dspttype>remote-sensing images</dspttype>
            <dsptname>Sun illuminated topography</dsptname>
            <dsptdesc>The shaded relief image (3 m pixel size) was created by vertically exaggerating the topography four times and then artificially illuminating the relief by a light source positioned 45 degrees above the horizon from the north. In the resulting image, topographic features are enhanced by strong illumination on the northward-facing slopes and by shadows cast on southern slopes. The image also accentuates small features (relief of a few meters) that could not be effectively shown as contours alone at this scale. Unnatural-looking features or patterns oriented parallel or perpendicular to survey tracklines (tracklines run north-south) are artifacts of data collection and environmental conditions.</dsptdesc>
         </dspart>
         <dspart>
            <dspttype>remote-sensing image</dspttype>
            <dsptname>har96sun.tif</dsptname>
            <dsptdesc>This is a 3 meter resolution tiff image representing sea floor topography with an artificial illumination source. It was compiled from multibeam echosounder data collected in 1996. There is a corresponding tiff world file (.tfw) for georeferencing purposes.</dsptdesc>
         </dspart>
         <dspart>
            <dspttype>remote-sensing image</dspttype>
            <dsptname>har98sun.tif</dsptname>
            <dsptdesc>This is a 3 meter resolution tiff image representing sea floor topography with an artificial illumination source. It was compiled from multibeam echosounder data collected in 1998. There is a corresponding tiff world file (.tfw) for georeferencing purposes.</dsptdesc>
         </dspart>
         <dspart>
            <dspttype>remote-sensing image</dspttype>
            <dsptname>har00sun.tif</dsptname>
            <dsptdesc>This is a 3 meter resolution tiff image representing sea floor topography with an artificial illumination source. It was compiled from multibeam echosounder data collected in 2000. There is a corresponding tiff world file (.tfw) for georeferencing purposes.</dsptdesc>
         </dspart>
         <dspart>
            <dspttype>remote-sensing images and raster digital data</dspttype>
            <dsptname>Backscatter Intensity</dsptname>
            <dsptdesc>Backscatter intensity, the intensity of the acoustic return from the sea floor from the multibeam system, is a function of the properties of the surficial sediments and of the bottom roughness.  Generally, a strong return (light gray tones) is associated with rock or coarse-grained sediment, and a weak return (dark gray tones) with fine-grained sediments.  However, the micro-topography, such as ripples, burrows, and benthic populations also affect the reflectivity of the sea floor.  Direct observations, using bottom photography or video, and surface samples, are needed to verify interpretations of the backscatter intensity data.  The backscatter data have a weak striping that runs parallel to the ship&#x92;s track.  Some of the striping is the result of poor data return at nadir that appears as evenly-spaced thin speckled lines. Some striping is also due to critical angle effects, where the intensity of return varies as a function of the angle of incidence of the incoming sound on the sea floor (Hughes-Clark and others, 1997).</dsptdesc>
         </dspart>
         <dspart>
            <dspttype>remote-sensing image</dspttype>
            <dsptname>har96mos.tif</dsptname>
            <dsptdesc>This is a 3 meter resolution tiff image representing backscatter intensity.  It was compiled from multibeam echosounder data collected in 1996.  There is a corresponding tiff world file (.tfw) for georeferencing purposes.</dsptdesc>
         </dspart>
         <dspart>
            <dspttype>remote-sensing image</dspttype>
            <dsptname>har98mos.tif</dsptname>
            <dsptdesc>This is a 3 meter resolution tiff image representing backscatter intensity.  It was compiled from multibeam echosounder data collected in 1998.  There is a corresponding tiff world file (.tfw) for georeferencing purposes.</dsptdesc>
         </dspart>
         <dspart>
            <dspttype>remote-sensing image</dspttype>
            <dsptname>har00mos.tif</dsptname>
            <dsptdesc>This is a 3 meter resolution tiff image representing backscatter intensity.  It was compiled from multibeam echosounder data collected in 2000.  There is a corresponding tiff world file (.tfw) for georeferencing purposes.</dsptdesc>
         </dspart>
         <dspart>
            <dspttype>remote-sensing image</dspttype>
            <dsptname>Pseudocolored Backscatter Intensity</dsptname>
            <dsptdesc>The backscatter intensity is combined with the topography to display the distribution of intensity in relation to the topography.  In the image shown here, the backscatter intensity is represented by a suite of eight colors ranging from blue, which represents low intensity, to red, which represents high intensity. These data are draped over a shaded relief image created by vertically exaggerating the topography four times and then artificially illuminating the relief by a light source positioned 45 degrees above the horizon from an azimuth of 350 degrees.  The resulting image displays light and dark intensities within each color band that result from a feature's position with respect to the light source.  For example, north-facing slopes, receiving strong illumination, show as a light intensity within a color band, whereas south-facing slopes, being in shadow, show as a dark intensity within a color band.</dsptdesc>
         </dspart>
         <dspart>
            <dspttype>remote-sensing image</dspttype>
            <dsptname>har96psu.tif</dsptname>
            <dsptdesc>This is a 3 meter resolution tiff image representing backscatter intensity with a RGB color scale.  It was compiled from multibeam echosounder data collected in 1996.  There is a corresponding tiff world file (.tfw) for georeferencing purposes.</dsptdesc>
         </dspart>
         <dspart>
            <dspttype>remote-sensing image</dspttype>
            <dsptname>har98psu.tif</dsptname>
            <dsptdesc>This is a 3 meter resolution tiff image representing backscatter intensity with a RGB color scale.  It was compiled from multibeam echosounder data collected in 1998.  There is a corresponding tiff world file (.tfw) for georeferencing purposes.</dsptdesc>
         </dspart>
         <dspart>
            <dspttype>remote-sensing image</dspttype>
            <dsptname>har00psu.tif</dsptname>
            <dsptdesc>This is a 3 meter resolution tiff image representing backscatter intensity with a RGB color scale.  It was compiled from multibeam echosounder data collected in 2000.  There is a corresponding tiff world file (.tfw) for georeferencing purposes.</dsptdesc>
         </dspart>
      </dsstruct>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>1996</begdate>
               <enddate>2000</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-73.900124</westbc>
            <eastbc>-73.812264</eastbc>
            <northbc>40.433605</northbc>
            <southbc>40.349975</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>marine geology</themekey>
            <themekey>marine geophysics</themekey>
            <themekey>seismic reflection methods</themekey>
            <themekey>sea-floor characteristics</themekey>
            <themekey>geospatial datasets</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>Sea floor photographs</themekey>
            <themekey>Bottom photography</themekey>
            <themekey>Sea floor video</themekey>
            <themekey>Sediment texture</themekey>
            <themekey>Sediment grain size</themekey>
            <themekey>Seabed Observation and sampling system</themekey>
            <themekey>SEABOSS</themekey>
            <themekey>R/V Oceanus</themekey>
            <themekey>R/V Endeavor</themekey>
            <themekey>R/V Seaward Explorer</themekey>
            <themekey>F/V Alpha and Omega</themekey>
            <themekey>Woods Hole Field Center</themekey>
            <themekey>WHFC</themekey>
            <themekey>United States Geological Survey</themekey>
            <themekey>USGS</themekey>
            <themekey>Geographic Information Systems</themekey>
            <themekey>GIS</themekey>
            <themekey>Simrad Subsea EM1000</themekey>
            <themekey>Sea Floor Mapping</themekey>
            <themekey>Multibeam Echo Sounder</themekey>
            <themekey>Multibeam</themekey>
            <themekey>Topographic data</themekey>
            <themekey>Sea floor topography</themekey>
            <themekey>Bathymetry</themekey>
            <themekey>Backscatter intensity</themekey>
            <themekey>Sea floor geology</themekey>
            <themekey>Surficial geology</themekey>
            <themekey>Dredged material</themekey>
            <themekey>Ocean disposal</themekey>
            <themekey>Contaminated sediments</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>New York</placekey>
            <placekey>New York Harbor</placekey>
            <placekey>NY</placekey>
            <placekey>New Jersey</placekey>
            <placekey>NJ</placekey>
            <placekey>Mud Disposal Site</placekey>
            <placekey>MDS</placekey>
            <placekey>Historic Area Remediation Site</placekey>
            <placekey>HARS</placekey>
            <placekey>Hudson Shelf Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Hudson Canyon</placekey>
            <placekey>New York Bight</placekey>
            <placekey>New York Bight Apex</placekey>
            <placekey>Mid-Atlantic Bight</placekey>
            <placekey>Exclusive Economic Zone</placekey>
            <placekey>EEZ</placekey>
            <placekey>Atlantic Ocean</placekey>
            <placekey>Ocean</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>This information is not for navigational purposes.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U. S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
               <cntper>Bradford Butman</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Oceanographer</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>384 Woods Hole Rd</address>
               <city>Woods Hole</city>
               <state>MA</state>
               <postal>02543-1598</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>508-548-8700 x2212</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>508-457-2309</cntfax>
            <cntemail>bbutman@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>The multibeam observations in the HARS were originally published in Butman and others (2002), U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 00-503 (see cross-reference citation).  These data  have been reprocessed  to correct for an error in the software that projected the data on a sphere rather than on the WGS84 ellipsoid, and to stretch the backscatter intensity and shaded relief images the same as the Hudson Shelf Valley images.</datacred>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Butman, Bradford</origin>
            <origin>Danforth, William W.</origin>
            <origin>Knowles, Stephen C.</origin>
            <origin>May, Brian</origin>
            <origin>Serrett, Laurie</origin>
            <pubdate>2002</pubdate>
            <title>Sea floor topography and backscatter intensity of the Historic Area Remediation Site (HARS), offshore of New York, based on multibeam surveys conducted in 1996, 1998, and 2000.</title>
            <geoform>map, raster digital data, remote-sensing image, tabular digital data, vector digital data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>00-503</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Woods Hole, MA</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2000/of00-503/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <complete>No further processing or modifications will be made to these data.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>These data were navigated with a Differential GlobalPositioning System (DGPS); they are accurate to +/- 3meters, horizontally.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
         <vertacc>
            <vertaccr>These data have been corrected for vessel motion(roll, pitch, heave, yaw) and tidal offsets, and referenced tomean lower low water.  The theoretical vertical resolutionof the Simrad EM-1000 multibeam echosounder is 1 % ofwater depth; roughly 30 - 50 cm within the study area.However, the working vertical resolution of the system, isroughly +/- 50 cm.</vertaccr>
         </vertacc>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>(1) Data and acquisition processing at sea.After the echo sounder data were logged onto the hard disk of the Sun workstation, a suite of processing software developed by the Ocean Mapping Group (www.omg.unb.ca/~jhc/SwathEd.html) was used to correct for artifacts and errors that may have been introduced during data collection. This software also enhanced the corrected data by resolving beam pattern and aspect ratio distortions and by imposing a linear contrast stretch before it generated bathymetric and sidescan sonar image mosaicks in a Mercator projection. All data processing described here is initiated using Silicon Graphics workstations as soon as each acquisition file isclosed by the Simrad Mermaid workstation (usually at theend of each survey line).  Additional processing was done in the lab to correct for fluctuations in sea level during the survey and for artifacts in the data files that were not corrected in the field (see below). The processing and editing steps on board the ship were:
(A.) Demultiplex, or unravel, the acquired Simraddata files using RT to generate separate files containingnavigation, depth soundings, sidescan sonar backscattervalues, and sound velocity information.
(B.) Automatically reject bad data(autoRejectSoundings). For the multibeam soundings,reject data outside expected depth ranges (operator'sdecision based on nautical chart data); for navigation data, reject fixes with poor GPS statistics.
(C.) Edit the navigation data on-screen using jview toremove undesirable points, including turns at the ends ofsurvey lines.
(D.) Edit the multibeam soundings on-screen usingswathed to remove individual anomalous soundings.
(E). Merge tidal information and the correctednavigation back (mergetide and mergenav) into the datafiles. Tidal information was obtained from the NOAA tideserver using tide station 8531680 located at Sandy Hook,Final tidal corrections were made in the lab using a different procedure (see below).
(F.) Map the bathymetric soundings from eachprocessed data file onto a Mercator grid using weigh_gridwith node spacings and scale selected by the operator.
(G.) Map the extracted sidescan sonar backscattervalues onto a digital mosaic using mos2 in the Mercatorprojection at a scale selected by the user.
(H.) Using addSUN, generate bathymetric raster filesusing the mapped grid node information to depict the depthinformation in a shaded relief Mercator map.  A Mercatorprojection allows individual map areas to be joined edge toedge when creating a composite image. The shaded reliefimages were generated using a sun elevation angle of 45degrees from an azimuth of 0 degrees, and a verticalexaggeration of four times to emphasize sea floor features.
(I.) Generate a false colored image using mix_ci bycombining the bathymetric and backscatter raster mosaicsinto a single image, also in the Mercator projection.
(2) Data processing and analysis in the lab included:
(A.) Removing sound refraction artifacts from the data (using the refraction tool in swathed) due to insufficient sound velocity profile information and varying water masses within the study area.
(B.) The measured elevations were adjusted for fluctuations in sea level during the survey by subtracting tidal elevations predicted by a tidal model and low-frequency sea level observed at the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Sandy Hook tide station located at 40 degrees 28 minutes N., 74 degrees 0.6 minutes W.  The tidal model utilized 9 constituents derived from a 4-month bottom pressure record obtained at Station A, located at 40 degrees 23.4 minutes N., 73 degrees 47.1 minutes W. in 38 m water depth about 2.7 km east of the HARS, during the winter of 1999-2000.  An estimate of the error due to sea level remaining in the multibeam observations after the sea level correction is about 3 cm.
(C.) Two corrections have been made to the HARS multibeam data as published in Butman and others (2002). (1) The backscatter intensity data between 180-220 was stretched to 0-255 (The data published in 2002 between 180-225 was stretched to 0-255).  The shaded relief data between 150-200 was stretched to 0-255 (as in the 2002 data).  Aging of the multibeam transducer and software changes implemented to correct the near-nadir response make the backscatter intensity observed in 1996, 1998, and 2000 not directly comparable.  Further work is needed to match the backscatter intensities between the 1996, 1998 and 2000 surveys.  (2) The data were also reprocessed to correct for an error in the UNB software that projected the data on a sphere rather than on the WGS84 ellipsoid.  The horizontal error in placement of the data published by Butman and others (2002) was 0 in the northwestern corner of the HARS, and reached about 12 m in the southeastern corner.
All mapped files are in the Mercator projection, having acentral longitude of -75 degrees West, a latitude of true scale of 40 degrees north and the horizontal datum is WGS84.  The vertical datum is mean lower low water.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1996 to 2003</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>William Danforth</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntpos>Operational Geologist</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>384 Woods Hole Road</address>
                     <city>Woods Hole</city>
                     <state>MA</state>
                     <postal>02543-1598</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>508-548-8700 x2274</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>508-457-2310</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>bdanforth@usgs.gov</cntemail>
                  <hours>8 a.m. to 5 p.m. EST</hours>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Creation of original metadata record</procdesc>
            <procdate>20021216</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Brad Butman</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntpos>Oceanographer</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>384 Woods Hole Road</address>
                     <city>Woods Hole</city>
                     <state>MA</state>
                     <postal>02543-1598</postal>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>508-457-2212</cntvoice>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Pixel</rasttype>
         <rowcount>2487</rowcount>
         <colcount>3098</colcount>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <mapproj>
               <mapprojn>Mercator</mapprojn>
               <mercator>
                  <stdparll>40.0</stdparll>
                  <longcm>-75</longcm>
                  <feast>0</feast>
                  <fnorth>0</fnorth>
               </mercator>
            </mapproj>
            <planci>
               <plance>row and column</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>3</absres>
                  <ordres>3</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>meters</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <ellips>World Geodetic System 84</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.257</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
      <vertdef>
         <depthsys>
            <depthdn>Mean lower low water</depthdn>
            <depthres>0.3</depthres>
            <depthdu>Meters</depthdu>
            <depthem>Explicit depth coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</depthem>
         </depthsys>
      </vertdef>
   </spref>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Bradford Butman</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Oceanographer</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>384 Woods Hole Road</address>
               <city>Woods Hole</city>
               <state>Massachusetts</state>
               <postal>02543-1598</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>508-548-8700 x2212</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>508-457-2309</cntfax>
            <cntemail>bbutman@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>These data were prepared by an agency of the United States Government. Neither the United States Government nor any agency thereof, nor any of their employees, make any warranty, expressed or implied, or assumes any legal liability or responsibility for the accuracy, completeness, or usefulness of any information, apparatus, product, or process disclosed in this report, or represents that its use would not infringe privately owned rights. Reference therein to any specific commercial product, process, or service by trade name, trademark, manufacturer, or otherwise does not necessarily constitute or imply its endorsement, recommendation, or favoring by the United States Government or any agency thereof. Any views and opinions of authors expressed herein do not necessarily state or reflect those of the United States Government or any agency thereof. Although all data have been used by the USGS, no warranty, expressed or implied, is made by the USGS as to the accuracy of the data and/or related materials. The act of distribution shall not constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumed by the USGS in the use of these data or related materials.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>TIFF</formname>
               <formvern>6</formvern>
               <formcont>Processed imagery depicting characteristics of the sea floor</formcont>
               <filedec>unzip</filedec>
               <transize>45</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2001/of01-470/nybgis/gis/downloads/harsmulti.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150204</metd>
      <metrd>20040722</metrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Peter N Schweitzer</cntper>
               <cntorg>USGS Midwest Area</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Collection manager, USGS Geoscience Data Clearinghouse, http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Mail Stop 95412201 Sunrise Valley Dr</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192-0002</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>703-648-6533</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>703-648-6252</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pschweitzer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <metextns>
         <onlink>http://geology.usgs.gov/tools/metadata/tools/ext/parts.ext</onlink>
      </metextns>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
