<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Schweitzer, Peter N.</origin>
            <pubdate>1995</pubdate>
            <title>Monthly average polar sea-ice concentration 1978 through 1991</title>
            <edition>2.0</edition>
            <geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Digital Data Series</sername>
               <issue>DDS-27</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Reston, Virginia</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/dds/dds27/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This data set represents the results of calculations carriedout on sea-ice-concentration data from the SMMR and SSM/Iinstruments.  The original data were obtained from theNational Snow and Ice Data Center (NSIDC). The data set alsocontains the source code of the programs that made thecalculations.  The objective was to derive monthly averagesfor the whole 13.25-year series (1978-1991) and to derive acomposite series of monthly averages representing thevariation of an average year.  The resulting file set containsmonthly images for each of the polar regions for each year,yielding 160 files for each pole, and composite monthlyaverages in which the years are combined, yielding 12 morefiles.  Averaging the images in this way tends to reduce thenumber of grid cells that lack valid data; the compositeaverages are designed to suppress interannual variability.
Also included in the data set are programs that can retrieveseasonal ice-concentration profiles at user-specifiedlocations.  These nongraphical data retrieval programs areprovided in  versions for UNIX, extended DOS, and Macintoshcomputers.  Graphical browse utilities are included for thesame computing platforms but require more sophisticateddisplay systems.</abstract>
         <purpose>The purpose of this data set is to provide paleoclimateresearchers with a tool for estimating the average seasonalvariation in sea-ice concentration in the modern polar oceansand for estimating the modern monthly sea-ice concentration atany given polar oceanic location.  It is expected that thesedata will be compared with paleoclimate data derived fromgeological proxy measures such as faunal census analyses andstable-isotope analyses. The results can then be used toconstrain general circulation models of climate change.</purpose>
         <supplinf>The data contained in this data set are derived from theScanning Multichannel Microwave Radiometer (SMMR) and SpecialSensor Microwave/ Imager (SSM/I) data produced by the NationalSnow and Ice Data Center (NSIDC) at the University of Coloradoin cooperation with the U.S. National Aeronautics and SpaceAdministration (NASA) and the U.S. National Oceanic andAtmospheric Administration (NOAA).  The basic data come fromsatellites of the U.S. Air Force Defense MeteorologicalSatellite Program.  NSIDC distributes three collections of sea-ice-concentration grids on CD-ROM: data from the Nimbus-7 SMMR(October 25, 1978 through August 20, 1987) are provided onvolume 7 of the SMMR Polar Data series (NASA, 1992); data fromthe SSM/I are provided on two separate volumes, covering theperiods from July 9 of 1987 to December 31 of 1989, and fromJanuary 1 of 1990 through December 31 of 1991, respectively.The NASATEAM data from revision 2 of the SSM/I CD-ROM's wereused to create the present data set.  SMMR images werecollected every 2 to 3 days, whereas SSM/I data are providedin daily ice-concentration grids.  Apart from a number ofsmall gaps (5 or fewer days) in the record, the only longperiod for which no data are available is December 3 of 1987through January 12 of 1988, inclusive.
As ancillary data, the ETOPO5 global gridded elevation andbathymetry data (Edwards, 1989) were interpolated to theresolution of the NSIDC data; the interpolated topographicdata are included.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>19781025</begdate>
               <enddate>19911231</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>SMMR aboard Nimbus-7 satellite became fully operational on781025; that instrument was replaced but the observations werecontinued by the SSM/I aboard DMSP F8 satellite.</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>Irregular</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-180.0</westbc>
            <eastbc>180.0</eastbc>
            <northbc>90.0</northbc>
            <southbc>-90.0</southbc>
         </bounding>
         <dsgpoly>
            <dsgpolyo>
               <gring>168.35,30.98 135.00,39.43 102.34,31.37 45.00,56.35 -9.97,34.35 -45.00,43.28 -80.74,33.92 -135.00,55.50</gring>
            </dsgpolyo>
         </dsgpoly>
         <dsgpoly>
            <dsgpolyo>
               <gring>-39.23,-42.24 -51.32,0.00 -39.23,42.24 -54.66,90.00 -41.45,135.00 -54.66,180.00 -41.45,-135.00 -54.66,-90.00</gring>
            </dsgpolyo>
         </dsgpoly>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>oceanography</themekey>
            <themekey>sea ice concentration</themekey>
            <themekey>geospatial datasets</themekey>
            <themekey>SSM/I</themekey>
            <themekey>SMMR</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
            <themekey>oceans</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Arctic Ocean</placekey>
            <placekey>Southern Ocean</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Augmented FIPS 10-4 and FIPS 6-4</placekt>
            <placekey>OC10 = Arctic</placekey>
            <placekey>OC50 = Southern</placekey>
         </place>
         <temporal>
            <tempkt>None</tempkt>
            <tempkey>Present</tempkey>
         </temporal>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Peter N. Schweitzer</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Mail Stop 954 National CenterU.S. Geological Survey12201 Sunrise Valley Drive</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(703) 648-6533</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(703) 648-6252</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pschweitzer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/metadata/digital-data/27/02n.gif</browsen>
         <browsed>Average February Northern Hemisphere sea-ice concentrationplotted on a polar stereographic projection of the North Pole</browsed>
         <browset>GIF</browset>
      </browse>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/metadata/digital-data/27/02s.gif</browsen>
         <browsed>Average February Southern Hemisphere sea-ice concentrationplotted on a polar stereographic projection of the South Pole</browsed>
         <browset>GIF</browset>
      </browse>
      <native>Originally compiled using UNIX, data remain the same.  Thegraphical software has been rewritten in Tcl/Tk to promoteportability across operating systems.</native>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Peter N. Schweitzer</origin>
            <pubdate>1993</pubdate>
            <title>Modern Average Global Sea-Surface Temperature</title>
            <geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
            <edition>2.0</edition>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Digital Data Series</sername>
               <issue>DDS-10</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <othercit>Library of Congress Cataloging-in-Publication Number 93-9075</othercit>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/dds/dds10/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>Calculation of sea-ice-concentration values from brightnesstemperatures is described extensively in the user's guides ofthe source data products and in the NASA publication dealingwith the SMMR data.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Included in the data set are the UNIX shell scripts and makefilesthat were used to derive the averages and create the tables andimages.  Source code is provided for all programs written by theauthor.</logic>
      <complete>Included in the data set is a table enumerating the days for whichsea-ice-concentration data were available in the source material.In general, images were available every 2 days during the timeperiod from 781025 through 870709, when the SMMR was used, andimages were available every day during the period 870709 through911231, when the SSM/I was used.  A large gap (871202 through880113) occurred when the SSM/I became temporarily inoperative.Other gaps in the SSM/I record were not longer than fiveconsecutive days.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>The grids provided in the source data (supplied by NSIDC)are described in the user's guides of the relevantproducts, and the positional accuracy of the pixels isdealt with both in the user's guides and in the NASAreport on the SMMR data.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>NASA</origin>
                  <pubdate>1992</pubdate>
                  <title>Radiances on a North Polar Stereographic Grid4/1/ 87 - 8/20/87 and Arctic and Antarctic Sea IceConcentrations 10/25/78 - 8/20/87 volume 7 ofNimbus-7 Scanning Multichannel MicrowaveRadiometer (SMMR) Polar Data</title>
                  <geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>Goddard Space Flight Center SMMR Polar Data</sername>
                     <issue>volume 7</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <othercit>The volume also contains brightness temperature datafrom 870401 through 870820.  The CD-ROM is labelledUSA_NASA_971_SMR_0007.  The data are distributed byNSIDC Distributed Active Archive Center, CooperativeInstitute for Research in Environmental Sciences(CIRES), University of Colorado, Boulder, CO 80309-0049.</othercit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srccitea>SMMR CD-ROM from NSIDC</srccitea>
            <typesrc>CD-ROM</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <rngdates>
                     <begdate>19781025</begdate>
                     <enddate>19870820</enddate>
                  </rngdates>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>National Snow and Ice Data Center, 1994, Nimbus-7 SMMRpolar radiances and Arctic and Antarctic sea iceconcentrations on CD-ROM user's guide, version 3:Boulder, Colorado, National Snow and Ice Data Center, 23 p.</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccontr>Monthly average sea-ice-concentration files in the presentdata set for the period 781025 through 870820 were derivedfrom these Nimbus-7 SMMR ice-concentration data.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>NSIDC</origin>
                  <pubdate>1992</pubdate>
                  <title>DMSP SSM/I ice concentration grids for the polarregions</title>
                  <geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>DMSP SSM/I brightness temperature and sea-iceconcentration grids for the polar regions on CD-ROM</sername>
                     <issue>volume 1, revision 2</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <othercit>The data are distributed by NSIDC Distributed ActiveArchive Center, Cooperative Institute for Research inEnvironmental Sciences (CIRES), University ofColorado, Boulder, CO 80309-0049.</othercit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srccitea>DMSP/SSMI ICE Grids volume 1</srccitea>
            <typesrc>CD-ROM</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <rngdates>
                     <begdate>19870709</begdate>
                     <enddate>19891231</enddate>
                  </rngdates>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>National Snow and Ice Data Center, 1992, DMSP SSM/Ibrightness temperature and sea ice concentration gridsfor the polar regions on CD-ROM, User's guide:National Snow and Ice Data Center Special Report 1, [300 p].</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccontr>Monthly average sea-ice-concentration files in the presentdata set for the period 19870709 through 19891231 werederived from these DMSP F8 SSM/I ice-concentration data.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>NSIDC</origin>
                  <pubdate>1993</pubdate>
                  <title>DMSP SSM/I ice concentration grids for the polarregions</title>
                  <geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>DMSP SSM/I brightness temperature and sea-iceconcentration grids for the polar regions on CD-ROM</sername>
                     <issue>volume 2, revision 2.</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <othercit>The data are distributed by NSIDC Distributed ActiveArchive Center, Cooperative Institute for Research inEnvironmental Sciences (CIRES), University ofColorado, Boulder, CO 80309-0049.</othercit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srccitea>DMSP/SSMI ICE Grids volume 2</srccitea>
            <typesrc>CD-ROM</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <rngdates>
                     <begdate>19900101</begdate>
                     <enddate>19911231</enddate>
                  </rngdates>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>National Snow and Ice Data Center, 1992, DMSP SSM/Ibrightness temperature and sea ice concentration gridsfor the polar regions on CD-ROM, User's guide:National Snow and Ice Data Center Special Report 1, [300 p].</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccontr>Monthly average sea-ice-concentration files in the presentdata set for the period 19900101 through 19911231 werederived from these DMSP F8 SSM/I ice-concentration data.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Edwards, Margaret H.</origin>
                  <pubdate>1989</pubdate>
                  <title>Global gridded elevation and bathymetry (ETOPO5):Digital raster data on a 5-minute geographic(lat/long) 2160x4320 (centroid-registered) grid</title>
                  <geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Boulder, Colorado</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. National Oceanic and AtmosphericAdministration, National Geophysical DataCenter</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srccitea>ETOPO5</srccitea>
            <typesrc>CD-ROM</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <rngdates>
                     <begdate>1950</begdate>
                     <enddate>1989</enddate>
                  </rngdates>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>The data set was published in 1989.  Documentationprovided by NGDC indicates the data were derived fromsources produced during the period 1950 through 1980.</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccontr>Elevation and bathymetry used in the graphical dataretrieval programs of DDS-27 were derived from ETOPO5.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Calculate monthly averages and composite monthly averages.
The Bourne shell script do_avgs describes the manner inwhich the program average was used to calculate themonthly and composite monthly average sea-iceconcentration files.  The program average is given a listof sea-ice-concentration data files in HDF format.  Foreach grid cell in the images, it calculates the arithmeticaverage of the corresponding cell in the input files andwrites the average image into a new file.  This program isrun once for each month of each year represented in theoriginal data to yield monthly averages.  Then thecomposite monthly averages are calculated using themonthly averages for each year.</procdesc>
            <srcused>DMSP/SSMI Ice Grids volume 1</srcused>
            <srcused>DMSP/SSMI Ice Grids volume 2</srcused>
            <procdate>1994</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Create GIF and PICT images of monthly and compositemonthly averages.
The Bourne shell script do_imgs converts the monthlyaverage and composite monthly average files into GIF andPICT images.  This script uses two programs from thefreely available PbmPlus toolkit developed by JeffPoskanzer.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1994</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Regrid ETOPO5 elevation and bathymetry data to fit sea-iceconcentration grid.
The ETOPO5 global gridded elevation and bathymetry dataset describes world topography on a grid whose cellsmeasure 5 minutes of latitude by 5 minutes of longitude.Since the ice-concentration data are given in a polarstereographic projection, the elevation of cells in theice-concentration grid must be determined by appropriatelysampling or interpolating the ETOPO5 data.  Because theETOPO5 grid is finer than the ice-concentration grid, asampling algorithm was combined with a spatial averagingscheme to derive the desired elevation data. The programthat implements this algorithm is called topo.c; itsstrategy is to find the ice grid cell coordinates of thecenter of each ETOPO5 cell and to calculate the averagedepth of all of the ETOPO5 cells that fall within an icegrid cell.  The results are two 16-bit images with big-endian byte ordering in which each signed 16-bit worddescribes the average depth or elevation in meters (sealevel is zero) of a cell in the ice-concentration grid.
Along with the 16-bit depth data files, displayable imagesare created using depthppm.c in portable pixmap format,and from that intermediate stage, GIF and PICT images arecreated using the PbmPlus toolkit.  Depthppm reduces thecomplexity of the depth data by assigning one color to arange of depths.  The relationship between depth rangesand colors is given in the source-code file depthppm.c.
The Bourne shell script do_topo carries out these operations.</procdesc>
            <srcused>ETOPO5</srcused>
            <procdate>1994</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Create 2-degree by 2-degree gridded ASCII data files.
One of the principal derivative products of this data setis a set of ice-concentration grids in which the grid cellsize and position match those produced by the USGS PRISMproject for its reconstruction of the climate of thePliocene, a warm interval about 3 million years beforepresent.  These grids are tab-delimited ASCII filessuitable for use in spreadsheet programs; each cell of thespreadsheet represents the ice-concentration value of onegrid cell measuring 2 degrees latitude by 2 degreeslongitude.  This calculation is carried out by the Bourneshell script do_tabs.
The procedure is to use a list of the geographiccoordinates of the grid cell centers as the request filefor the program u_rtrv.  The result is a table where eachrow is a grid cell, and columns 3 through 14 represent theice-concentration profile for each grid cell (columns 1and 2 reiterate the grid cell coordinates).
The grid cell centers are given in the files grid_n.2x2and grid_s.2x2 for the Northern and Southern Hemispheres,respectively.  The output of u_rtrv is stored in the filesarctic.2x2 and antarctic.2x2.
By using the UNIX cut command, the columns themselves wereisolated in separate files, and the program table.c wasused to rearrange each column into a tab-delimited ASCIItable suitable for entry into a spreadsheet.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1994</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Graphical viewer software rewritten using Tcl/Tk to enablethe viewer to run on current operating systems: MicrosoftWindows and Linux.</procdesc>
            <procdate>20040510</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Fixed a serious bug in u_rtrv.c in which the program requiredthe HDF data file name to contain ".s" in order to considerthe data to be southern-hemisphere data.  This caused pixelcoordinates calculated from geographic locations in the southpolar region to be incorrect.  The gridded data files wereaffected by this bug, so the files in Derived/grid/southhave been rebuilt with corrected information.  Thanks toDr. Simon H.H. Nielsen (post-doc at Univ Florida) for pointingout the problem.</procdesc>
            <procdate>20040728</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Pixel</rasttype>
         <rowcount>304</rowcount>
         <colcount>448</colcount>
      </rastinfo>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Pixel</rasttype>
         <rowcount>316</rowcount>
         <colcount>332</colcount>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <mapproj>
               <mapprojn>Polar Stereographic</mapprojn>
               <polarst>
                  <svlong>135.0</svlong>
                  <stdparll>70.0</stdparll>
                  <feast>0.0</feast>
                  <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
               </polarst>
            </mapproj>
            <planci>
               <plance>row and column</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>25000</absres>
                  <ordres>25000</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>meters</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <planar>
            <mapproj>
               <mapprojn>Polar Stereographic</mapprojn>
               <polarst>
                  <svlong>0.0</svlong>
                  <stdparll>-70.0</stdparll>
                  <feast>0.0</feast>
                  <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
               </polarst>
            </mapproj>
            <planci>
               <plance>row and column</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>25000</absres>
                  <ordres>25000</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>meters</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <ellips>Hughes</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378.273</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.27941</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>Ice-concentration grid cell</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Any of the one-byte data elements in the sea-ice-concentration files</enttypd>
            <enttypds>self-evident</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Ice-concentration grid cell value</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The proportion of the ocean area represented by the gridcell that is covered with sea ice.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Calibrations of the SMMR and SSM/I instruments aredescribed in the following three publications:
Gloersen, P., Campbell, W.J., Cavalieri, D.J., Comiso,J.C., Parkinson, C.L., and Zwally, H.J., 1993, Arctic andAntarctic sea-ice, 1978-1987: Satellite passive-microwaveobservations and analysis: NASA Special Publication no.511, 290 p.
National Snow and Ice Data Center, 1994, Nimbus-7 SMMRpolar radiances and Arctic and Antarctic sea iceconcentrations on CD-ROM user's guide, version 3: Boulder,Colorado, National Snow and Ice Data Center, 23 p.
National Snow and Ice Data Center, 1992, DMSP SSM/Ibrightness temperature and sea ice concentration grids forthe polar regions on CD-ROM, User's guide: National Snowand Ice Data Center Special Report 1, [300 p].</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>100</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>percent sea-ice cover</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>1</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>-99</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Missing data</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>NSIDC</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>-88</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Land area</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>NSIDC</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>ETOPO5 grid cell</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Any of the two-byte data elements in the files etopo5.nand etopo5.s</enttypd>
            <enttypds>self-evident</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>ETOPO5 grid cell value</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Height of the land surface or depth of the sea floor,relative to mean sea level.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>NOAA/NGDC. 1992. Integrated Global Elevation andBathymetry. Digital Data. NOAA/NGDC/WDC-A, Boulder,Colorado. Digital raster data on a 5-minute geographic(lat/long) 2160x4320 grid. In: Global Ecosystems DatabaseVersion 1.0: Disc A. Boulder, CO: NOAA NationalGeophysical Data Center. 1 independent single-attributespatial layer on CD-ROM. 18.6 MB. [First published in1989.]</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>-10783</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>8000</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>meters</attrunit>
                  <attrmres>1</attrmres>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Peter N. Schweitzer</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Mail Stop 954 National CenterU.S. Geological Survey12201 Sunrise Valley Drive</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(703) 648-6533</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(703) 648-6252</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pschweitzer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>U.S. Geological Survey Digital Data Series DDS-27</resdesc>
      <distliab>Although all data and software published on this CD-ROM have beenused by the USGS, no warranty, expressed or implied, is made bythe USGS as to the accuracy of the data and related materials orthe functioning of the software.  The act of distribution shallnot constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumedby the USGS in the use of these data, software, or relatedmaterials.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>GIF</formname>
               <formvern>89a</formvern>
               <formcont>Sea-ice concentration</formcont>
               <filedec>unzip</filedec>
               <transize>1.5</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/metadata/digital-data/27/dds27.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>starkit</formname>
               <formspec>Stand-alone runtime (Tcl/Tk starkit, usable with Linux x86, Microsoft Windows, and MacOSX, requires tclkit to run)</formspec>
               <formcont>Sea-ice concentration display application</formcont>
               <filedec>tclkit ice.kit</filedec>
               <transize>1.5</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/metadata/digital-data/27/ice.kit</networkr>
                        <networkr>http://www.equi4.com/tclkit/download.html (get tclkit here to run ice.kit)</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>EXE</formname>
               <formspec>Stand-alone runtime (Tcl/Tk starpack executable, UPX compressed) for Microsoft Windows</formspec>
               <formcont>Sea-ice concentration display application</formcont>
               <filedec>execute</filedec>
               <transize>1.5</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/metadata/digital-data/27/ice.bin</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ELF</formname>
               <formspec>Stand-alone runtime (Tcl/Tk starpack executable, UPX compressed) for Linux x86</formspec>
               <formcont>Sea-ice concentration display application</formcont>
               <filedec>execute from a Linux command shell</filedec>
               <transize>1.5</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/metadata/digital-data/27/ice.bin</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Compressed disk image</formname>
               <formspec>Compressed disk image containing the application</formspec>
               <formcont>Sea-ice concentration display application</formcont>
               <filedec>gzip -d</filedec>
               <transize>1.5</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/metadata/digital-data/27/ice-viewer.dmg.gz</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150202</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Peter N. Schweitzer</cntper>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Collection manager, USGS Geoscience Data Clearinghouse, http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Mail Stop 954 National CenterU.S. Geological Survey12201 Sunrise Valley Drive</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(703) 648-6533</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(703) 648-6252</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pschweitzer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
