<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Jill Cress</origin>
            <origin>Roger Sayre</origin>
            <origin>Patrick Comer</origin>
            <origin>Harumi Warner</origin>
            <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
            <title>Terrestrial Ecosystems - Land Surface Forms of the Conterminous United States</title>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Map</sername>
               <issue>3085</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>1 sheet</othercit>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3085</onlink>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/pp/1768</onlink>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>
Roger Sayre
Patrick Comer
Jill Cress
Harumi Warner
</origin>
                  <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
                  <title>Terrestrial ecosystems of the conterminous United States</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Map</sername>
                     <issue>3106</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>
scale 1:5,000,000
1 sheet
</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3106/</onlink>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3106/pdf/SIM3106.pdf</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>
The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) has generated land surface form classes for the contiguous United States. These land surface form classes were created as part of an effort to map standardized, terrestrial ecosystems for the nation using a classification developed by NatureServe (Comer and others, 2003). Ecosystem distributions were modeled using a biophysical stratification approach developed for South America (Sayre and others, 2008) and now being implemented globally (Sayre and others, 2007). Land surface forms strongly influence the differentiation and distribution of terrestrial ecosystems, and are one of the key input layers in the ecosystem delineation process.

The methodology used to produce these land surface form classes was developed by the Missouri Resource Assessment Partnership (MoRAP). MoRAP made modifications to Hammond's (1964a, 1964b) land surface form classification, which allowed the use of 30-meter source data and a 1 km2 window for neighborhood analysis (True 2002, True and others, 2000). While Hammond's methodology was based on three variables, slope, local relief, and profile type, MoRAP's methodology uses only slope and local relief (True 2002). Slope is classified as gently sloping or not gently sloping using a slope threshold of 8%, local relief is classified into five classes (0-15m, 15-30m, 30-90m, 90-150m, and &gt;150m), and eight landform classes (flat plains, smooth plains, irregular plains, escarpments, low hills, hills, breaks, and low mountains) were derived by combining slope class and local relief. The USGS implementation of the MoRAP methodology was executed using the USGS 30-meter National Elevation Dataset (NED) and an existing USGS slope dataset. In this implementation, a new land surface form class, the high mountains/deep canyons class, was identified by using an additional local relief class (&gt; 400m).

The drainage channels class was derived independently from the other land surface form classes. This class was derived using two of Andrew Weiss's slope position classes, "valley" and "lower slope" (Weiss 2001, Jenness 2006). The USGS implemented Weiss's algorithm using the 30-meter NED and a 1 km2 neighborhood analysis window. The resultant drainage channel class was combined into the final land surface forms dataset.
</abstract>
         <purpose>This dataset was created as part of an effort to map ecological system footprints for the contiguous United States.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>2009</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Publication Date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-125.000000</westbc>
            <eastbc>-65.999444</eastbc>
            <northbc>49.500204</northbc>
            <southbc>23.999926</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>land surface forms</themekey>
            <themekey>Group on Earth Observations</themekey>
            <themekey>GEO</themekey>
            <themekey>Global Earth Observation System of Systems</themekey>
            <themekey>GEOSS</themekey>
            <themekey>biophysical stratification</themekey>
            <themekey>slope</themekey>
            <themekey>local relief</themekey>
            <themekey>profile type</themekey>
            <themekey>landform</themekey>
            <themekey>National Elevation Dataset</themekey>
            <themekey>NED</themekey>
            <themekey>slope position</themekey>
            <themekey>ecosystem</themekey>
            <themekey>Geological Survey</themekey>
            <themekey>United States Geological Survey</themekey>
            <themekey>USGS</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>None</placekt>
            <placekey>United States of America</placekey>
            <placekey>conterminous United States</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>
We make every effort to provide and maintain accurate, complete, usable, and timely information on our Web sites. However, some U. S. Geological Survey data and information accessed through these pages may, of necessity, be preliminary in nature and presented prior to final review and approval by the Director of the U. S. Geological Survey. These data and information are provided with the understanding that they are not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Users are cautioned to consider carefully the provisional nature of these data and information before using them for decisions that concern personal or public safety or the conduct of business that involves substantial monetary or operational consequences. Conclusions drawn from, or actions undertaken on the basis of, such data and information are the sole responsibility of the user.

Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.

Any use of trade, product or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U. S. Government.
</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Jill Cress, Computer Scientist</cntper>
               <cntorg>US Geological Survey, Geosciences and Environmental Change Science Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing</addrtype>
               <address>US Geological Survey, Geosciences and Environmental Change Science Center, Box 25046, DFC, MS 980</address>
               <city>Lakewood</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>303-236-1248</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>jjcress@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
J. Cress
D. Soller
R. Sayre
P. Comer
H. Warner
</origin>
            <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
            <title>Terrestrial Ecosystems—Surficial Lithology of the Conterminous United States</title>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Map</sername>
               <issue>3126</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>
1 sheet.
Data Used: Surficial Materials in the Conterminous United States (Soller, D.R., and Reheis, M.C., compilers, 2004, Surficial materials in the conterminous United States: U.S. Geological Survey Open-file Report 03-275, scale 1:5,000,000.)  http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2003/of03-275/
</othercit>
            <onlink>http://rmgsc.cr.usgs.gov/outgoing/ecosystems/USdata/lithology_1km.zip</onlink>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3126</onlink>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>
Roger Sayre
Patrick Comer
Jill Cress
Harumi Warner
</origin>
                  <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
                  <title>Terrestrial ecosystems of the conterminous United States</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Map</sername>
                     <issue>3106</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>
scale 1:5,000,000
1 sheet
</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3106/</onlink>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3106/pdf/SIM3106.pdf</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
J. Cress
R. Sayre
P. Comer
H. Warner
</origin>
            <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
            <title>Terrestrial Ecosystems—Topographic Moisture Potential of the Conterminous United States</title>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Map</sername>
               <issue>3086</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>Data Used: Compound Topographic Index (CTI), EDNA (Elevation Derivative for National Applications), US Geological Survey, http://edna.usgs.gov/edna/datalayers/cti.asp</othercit>
            <onlink>http://rmgsc.cr.usgs.gov/outgoing/ecosystems/USdata/topo_moist_potential_30m.zip</onlink>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3086</onlink>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>
Roger Sayre
Patrick Comer
Jill Cress
Harumi Warner
</origin>
                  <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
                  <title>Terrestrial ecosystems of the conterminous United States</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Map</sername>
                     <issue>3106</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>
scale 1:5,000,000
1 sheet
</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3106/</onlink>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3106/pdf/SIM3106.pdf</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Jill Cress
Roger Sayre
Patrick Comer
Harumi Warner
</origin>
            <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
            <title>Terrestrial Ecosystems—Isobioclimates of the Conterminous United States</title>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Map</sername>
               <issue>3084</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>
scale 1:5,000,000
1 sheet
</othercit>
            <onlink>http://rmgsc.cr.usgs.gov/outgoing/ecosystems/USdata/isobioclimates_1km.zip</onlink>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3084</onlink>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>
Roger Sayre
Patrick Comer
Jill Cress
Harumi Warner
</origin>
                  <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
                  <title>Terrestrial ecosystems of the conterminous United States</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Map</sername>
                     <issue>3106</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>
scale 1:5,000,000
1 sheet
</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3106/</onlink>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3106/pdf/SIM3106.pdf</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>
This is an interim product generated as an input layer in the geospatial delineation of ecosystems and should not be construed, in and of itself, as a "definitive" product. This product could be improved in terms of strength of concept, quality of source data, and spatial resolution and should therefore be considered as representative of a first iteration attempt to use best available data for modeling standardized ecosystems.

This effort to map standardized, meso-scale ecosystems for both the conterminous United States and Africa is the first of its kind, and represents a biophysical stratification. The data developed for this mapping process were not all of the same quality or spatial resolution, but each dataset obtained and used for the mapping was considered to be "best available data" for that theme at a National extent. The primary goal for the first round of this mapping effort was to utilize the best source data currently available to generate a first iteration of ecosystems as quickly as possible. This goal was framed on the logic that reasonably robust and satisfactory results could be obtained from this method without a multi-year, million-plus dollar investment, and the methodology would therefore prove suitable for application in the global ecosystems mapping project under GEOSS.

Based on the nature of this first iteration of products, the following potential issue has already been identified for the Land Surface Forms data layer generated for the conterminous United States:

This dataset was derived from the NED based on various neighborhood analysis using a 1-km2 analysis window. However, it was determined that the NED did not include sufficient elevation data on Canadian side of the northwestern U.S.–Canada border. As a result, in the areas within approximately 600-meters to the south of this border, neighborhood analysis were run with insufficient input data therefore land surface form classes in this area are expected to have lower accuracy.
</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>see the attribute accuracy report</logic>
      <complete>see the attribute accuracy report</complete>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>E. H. Hammond</origin>
                  <pubdate>1964</pubdate>
                  <title>Analysis of Properties in Land Form Geography—An Application to Broad-Scale Land Form Mapping</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>Annals of the Association of American Geographers</sername>
                     <issue>v. 54, no. 1, p. 11–19.</issue>
                  </serinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>paper journal publication</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1964</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Hammond 1964a</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Original land surface form classification which was modified by the Missouri Resource Assessment Partnership (MoRAP).</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>E. H. Hammond</origin>
                  <pubdate>1964</pubdate>
                  <title>Classes of land surface form in the forty-eight states</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S.A. Annals of the Association of American Geographers</sername>
                     <issue>54(1): map supplement no. 4</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <othercit>1: 5,000,000</othercit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>map supplement to a paper publication in a journal</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1964</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Hammond, 1964b</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Original land surface form classification which was modified by the Missouri Resource Assessment Partnership (MoRAP).</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>E. H. Hammond</origin>
                  <pubdate>1964</pubdate>
                  <title>Classes of land surface form in the forty-eight states</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S.A. Annals of the Association of American Geographers</sername>
                     <issue>54(1): map supplement no. 4</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <othercit>1: 5,000,000</othercit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>map supplement to a paper publication in a journal</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1964</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Hammond, 1964b</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Original land surface form classification which was modified by the Missouri Resource Assessment Partnership (MoRAP).</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>
D. True
T. Gordon
D. Diamond
</origin>
                  <pubdate>2000</pubdate>
                  <title>How the size of a sliding Window impacts the generation of landforms</title>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Columbia, Missouri</pubplace>
                     <publish>Missouri Resource Assessment Partnership</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://www.cerc.usgs.gov/morap/Content/UploadedFiles/Projects/landform_model/landforms2001_files/frame.htm</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2000</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>True and others, 2000</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Contributed to the neighborhood analysis used to generate the Land Surface Forms (Cress and others, 2009b)</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
                  <pubdate>2004</pubdate>
                  <title>National Elevation Dataset (NED)</title>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Reston, Virginia</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>Last accessed January, 2006</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://seamless.usgs.gov/index.php</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2004</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>USGS 30-meter National Elevation Dataset (NED)</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Provided 30 elevation data as part of the development of Land Surface Forms (Cress and others, 2009b).</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Andrew Weiss</origin>
                  <pubdate>2001</pubdate>
                  <title>Topographic position and landforms analysis—Poster presentation</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>Environmental Sciences Research Institute User Conference</sername>
                     <issue>July 2001, San Diego, Calif.</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>San Diego, California</pubplace>
                     <publish>Environmental Sciences Research Institute</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Poster presentation</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2001</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Weiss, 2001</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Contributed to defining the slope position classes representing areas positioned lower than the surrounding areas, valley and lower slope, as a step in the Land Surface Forms (Cress and others, 2009b) generation.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Jeff Jenness</origin>
                  <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
                  <title>Topographic Position Index (TPI) extension for ArcView 3.x</title>
                  <edition>v. 1.2</edition>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Flagstaff, Arizona</pubplace>
                     <publish>Jenness Enterprises</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>Accessed June 2006</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://jennessent.com/arcview/arcview_extensions.htm</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Provided tools for defining topographic positions.</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2006</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Jenness, 2006</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Contributed to defining the slope position classes representing areas positioned lower than the surrounding areas, valley and lower slope, as a step in the Land Surface Forms (Cress and others, 2009b) generation.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Land surface forms for the conterminous United States were generated as part of the ecosystems modeling effort (Cress and others, 2009b - see "larger work citation"). After extensive investigation into various land surface form methodologies, the decision was made to use the methodology developed by the Missouri Resource Assessment Partnership (MoRAP). MoRAP made modifications to Hammond's (1964a, 1964b) land surface form classification, which allowed the use of 30-meter source data and a 1-km2 window for analyzing the data cell and its surrounding cells (neighborhood analysis) (True, 2002; True and others, 2000). While Hammond's methodology was based on three topographic variables, slope, local relief, and profile type, MoRAP's methodology uses only slope and local relief (True, 2002). Using the MoRAP method, slope is classified as gently sloping when more than 50 percent of the area in a 1-km2 neighborhood has slope less than 8 percent, otherwise the area is not gently sloping, that is, steeply sloped. Local relief, which is the difference between the maximum and minimum elevation in a neighborhood, is classified into five groups: 0-15 m, 15-30 m, 30-90 m, 90-150 m, and &gt;150 m. The land surface form classes are derived by combining slope and local relief which creates eight landform classes: flat plains (gently sloping and local relief &lt;= 15 m), smooth plains (gently sloping and 15 m &lt; local relief &lt;= 30 m), irregular plains (gently sloping and 30 m &lt; local relief &lt;= 90 m), escarpments (gently sloping and local relief &gt; 90 m), low hills (not gently sloping and local relief &lt;= 30 m), hills (not gently sloping and 30 m &lt; local relief &lt;= 90 m), breaks/foothills (not gently sloping and 90 m &lt; local relief &lt;= 150 m), and low mountains (not gently sloping and local relief &gt; 150 m). However, in the USGS application of the MoRAP methodology, an additional local relief group was used (&gt; 400 m). As a result, low mountains were redefined as not gently sloping and 150 m &lt; local relief &lt; 400 m, and a new land surface from class, high mountains/deep canyons, was identified as not gently sloping and local relief &gt; 400 m. The final application of the MoRAP methodology was preformed using the USGS 30-meter National Elevation Dataset (NED), and an existing USGS slope dataset that had been derived by calculating the slope from the NED in Universal Transverse Mercator (UTM) coordinates in each UTM zone, and then combining all of the zones into a national dataset.

As a final step, an additional class called drainage channels was derived independently from the other land surface form classes and was used to identify wet and dry river channels, which were not specifically represented by any of the other classifications. This class was based on the two Andrew Weiss's slope position classes that represented areas positioned lower than the surrounding areas, valley and lower slope (Weiss, 2001; Jenness, 2006). The USGS applied Weiss's algorithm to the 30-meter NED data using a 1-km2 neighborhood analysis window and then the resultant drainage channel class was added to the land surface forms dataset. Thus, the final land surface forms dataset contains ten classes: flat plains, smooth plains, irregular plains, escarpments, low hills, hills, breaks/foothills, low mountains, high mountains/deep canyons, and drainage channels.
</procdesc>
            <srcused>Hammond, 1964a</srcused>
            <srcused>Hammond, 1964b</srcused>
            <srcused>True, 2002</srcused>
            <srcused>True and others, 2000</srcused>
            <srcused>USGS 30-meter National Elevation Dataset (NED)</srcused>
            <srcused>Weiss, 2001</srcused>
            <srcused>Jenness, 2006</srcused>
            <procdate>2008</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Pixel</rasttype>
         <rowcount>91801</rowcount>
         <colcount>212402</colcount>
         <vrtcount>1</vrtcount>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <latres>0.000278</latres>
            <longres>0.000278</longres>
            <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
         </geograph>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
            <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.257222</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>Land Surface Forms</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Classes of land surface forms</enttypd>
            <enttypds>unknown</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Type of land surface form</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>names of land surface forms</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>unknown</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Flat Plains</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>unknown</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Smooth Plains</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>unknown</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Irregular Plains</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>unknown</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>4</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Escarpments</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>unknown</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>5</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Low Hills</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>unknown</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>6</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Hills</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>unknown</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>7</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Breaks/Foothills</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>unknown</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>8</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Low Mountains</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>unknown</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>9</edomv>
                  <edomvd>High Mountains/Deep Canyons</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>unknown</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>10</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Drainage Channels</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>unknown</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
               <cntper>Jill Cress</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
               <address>US Geological Survey, Geosciences and Environmental Change Science Center, Box 25046, DFC, MS 980</address>
               <city>Lakewood</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>303-236-1248</cntvoice>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>zipped "ERDAS" .img files</formname>
               <formverd>20090504</formverd>
               <transize>579</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://rmgsc.cr.usgs.gov/outgoing/ecosystems/USdata/land_surface_forms_30m.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20141024</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Roger Sayre</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Land Change Science Program</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Senior Scientist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>physical address</addrtype>
               <address>519 National Center</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
               <country>U.S.A.</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(703) 648-4529</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>rsayre@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>"FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata"</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <metac>None</metac>
      <metuc>None</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
