<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>United States Geological Survey (USGS)</origin>
            <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
            <title>National Assessment of Oil and Gas Project, Northern Alaska Province (001). Petroleum Systems and Geologic Assessment of Gas Hydrates in Northern Alaska &#x96; 2008. Limits of the Gas Hydrate stability zone contour lines</title>
            <geoform>Downloadable GIS Data</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
               <publish>U. S. Geological Survey, Energy Resources Science Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Collett, Timothy S.</origin>
                  <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                  <title>Assessment of Gas Hydrate Resources on the North Slope, Alaska</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>USGS Fact Sheet</sername>
                     <issue>FS-2008-3073</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Central Energy Resources Team</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/fs/2008/3073/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
            <onlink>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/data/noga00/prov01/spatial/shape/GHstabZone.zip</onlink>
            <onlink>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/noga/broker.jsp?theProvince=01&amp;thePage=gis&amp;theServlet=NogaNewGISResultsServ</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The limits of Gas Hydrate (GH) stability zone contour lines (GH stability thickness zero) shown here is a geographic boundary defined and mapped on basis of U.S. Geological Survey Digital Data Series DDS-35 Gas Hydrate assessment contours that were created in Support of the 1995 National Assessment of United States Oil and Gas Resources.  The 1995 CD-ROM released digital map data, figures, and text used in the "1995 National Assessment of United States Oil and Gas Resources -- Results, Methodology, and Supporting Data," U.S. Geological Survey Digital Data DDS-30 (Gautier and others, 1995). The 1995 Assessment Gas Hydrate thickness boundaries were revised and updated according to recent methane hydrate stability zone studies done in  Northern Alaska. In-house well log data/surveys study with geochemical sampling on evidence of thermo gas, resistivity-temperature from Lachenbruch et al and seismic facies were mapped and used as a guide for the gas hydrate stability zone thickness. The original (1995) Gas Hydrate stability data was given as the thickness of the hydrate stability field in meters (200 meters intervals). Contours were regridded using editing surface tools of the ArcMap and applied spline surface analysis tools in order to create contour interval in feet. The zero contour line was separated into individual shapefile and presented here in order to show Gas Hydrates Assessment limits of the North Slope. The offshore extent of the gas-hydrate stability zone is not well established.</abstract>
         <purpose>The data intended to provide a useful summary of the North Slope Alaska data for understanding the overall geologic framework of the Brooks Range foreland basin and for assisting in research studies concerning the oil and gas potential of the region.</purpose>
         <supplinf>GIS Data Download Page for Province 5001   http://pubs.usgs.gov/fs/2008/3073/ - Assessment of Gas Hydrate Resources on the North Slope, Alaska, 2008, USGS FS 2008-3073 http://energy.usgs.gov/other/gashydrates/ - Other Energy Resources - Gas Hydrates http://energy.cr.usgs.gov/oilgas/noga/ - National Assessment of Oil and Gas Home Page (NOGA Online).  Published Reports: U.S. Geological Survey Digital Data Series DDS-35 CD-ROM http://pubs.usgs.gov/dds/dds-035/ (The folder containing this shape file has DDS-35 related chapter for the metadata information on that digital data series.) The temperature data were obtained from Lachenbruch et al http://esp.cr.usgs.gov/data/bht/alaska/  and/or http://esp.cr.usgs.gov/data/bht/alaska/sites/;  Lachenbruch, A.H., Sass, J.H., Lawver, L.A., Brewer, M.C., Marshall, B.V., Munroe, R.J., Kennelly, J.P., Jr., Galanis, S.P., Jr., and Moses, T.H., Jr., 1987, Temperature and depth of permafrost on the Alaskan North Slope, in Tailleur, I.L., and Weimer, Paul, eds., Alaskan North Slope Geology: Bakersfield, California, Pacific Section, Society of Economic Paleontologists and Mineralogists and the Alaska Geological Society, Book 50, v. 2, p. 545-558;  Gas Hydrate stability conditions described in Collett, T.S., 2009, AAPG Memoir 89.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>2008</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>
-161.632394</westbc>
            <eastbc>
-139.813050</eastbc>
            <northbc>
71.642985</northbc>
            <southbc>
68.305476</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>Central Energy Resources Team Keyword Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>National Assessment of Oil and Gas</themekey>
            <themekey>USGS World Energy Region 5</themekey>
            <themekey>Energy Resources</themekey>
            <themekey>Natural Gas</themekey>
            <themekey>Gas Hydrate</themekey>
            <themekey>Resource Assessment</themekey>
            <themekey>Earth Science</themekey>
            <themekey>Natural Resources</themekey>
            <themekey>U.S. Geological Survey</themekey>
            <themekey>USGS</themekey>
            <themekey>Geology</themekey>
            <themekey>Gas Hydrate stability</themekey>
            <themekey>Collett, Timothy S.</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ArcIMS Metadata Server Theme Codes</themekt>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>Gateway to the Earth draft 9 28-Jun-2002</themekt>
            <themekey>Oil shale resources</themekey>
            <themekey>Oil sand resources</themekey>
            <themekey>Natural gas resources</themekey>
            <themekey>Economic geology</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>North Slope Alaska</placekey>
            <placekey>USGS World Energy Region 5</placekey>
            <placekey>Northern Alaska</placekey>
            <placekey>North Slope</placekey>
            <placekey>AK</placekey>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Augmented FIPS 10-4 and FIPS 6-4, version 1.0</placekt>
            <placekey>US02 = Alaska</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>USGS Oil and Gas Provinces (NOGA-95)</placekt>
            <placekey>Northern Alaska Province</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>USGS Oil and Gas Assessment Units (NOGA-2008)</placekt>
            <placekey>Gas Hydrate stability zone</placekey>
         </place>
         <theme>
            <themekt>EnergyResourceActivities</themekt>
            <themekey>OilGas</themekey>
            <themekey>NOGA2000</themekey>
            <themekey>NOGANAlaska</themekey>
            <themekey>GasHydrates</themekey>
            <themekey>AlaskaRoom</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Central Energy Resources Team</cntorg>
               <cntper>Christopher J. Schenk</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Geologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>U.S. Geological Survey, Box 25046, MS 939, Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(303) 236-5796</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>schenk@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/data/noga00/prov01/graphic/fs-2008-3073.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Graphical representation of gas hyrdrate stability zone limits in Northern Alaska Province</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <datacred>U.S. Geological Survey</datacred>
      <native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.0.1770</native>
      <native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.0.1770</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>The GH stability limit boundary was initially defined on the basis of The 1995 Assessment Gas Hydrate thickness boundaries. The original contour line locations were revised and adjusted according to recent Gas Hydrate studies done in North Slope area of Alaska.</logic>
      <complete>The in-house well data study with geochemical sampling on evidence of thermo gas, resistivity-temperature from Lachenbruch et al and seismic facies were mapped and used as a guide for the Gas Hydrate stability zone limits. The original (1995) Gas Hydrate stability data was given as the thickness of the hydrate stability field in meters (200 meters intervals). Contours were re-gridded using editing surface tools of the ArcMap and applied spline surface analysis tools in order to create contour intervals in feet. The zero contour line was separated into individual shapefile and presented here in order to show Gas Hydrates Assessment project limits.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>For the GH stability zero (limits) thickness boundary in 1995 NOGA Assessment, mylar base maps were compiled from maps ranging in scale from approximately 1:100,000 to 1:20,000,000. Maps were scanned, edited and re-projected into Albers Equal Area projection using ARC/INFO. The GH stability limits represent area where the conditions are favorable for gas hydrate stability zone.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Original data for gas hydrate contours were loaded from USGS DDS-35 digital CD-ROM report. These original gas hydrate coverages were presented as converted into ASCII files tables that consist of x, y coordinates for every vertex and a header for every line segment.  The header represents isolines having measurement units appropriate to the data type. File AKON_HYS.LIN (See DDS-35 metadata files) was converted to polygon shape ArcGIS format file. The attribute ID contained contour information in 200 interval meters and recalculated to feet into new attribute ID_FT.  The contours were gridded using Xtools Pro moduli Surface tools. Surface was analyzed and interpolated with spline method. Created grid surface was contoured using 600 feet intervals to get the best match to the original contour lines. Additional zero GH stability polygons within main area were determined during multiple in-house GH projects using OpenWorks Landmark &#x99; Software were exported as series of latitude longitude points. The x, y coordinates table was imported into ArcMAp, converted to polygons and incorporated into working shapefile.</procdesc>
            <procdate>2008</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Dataset copied.</procdesc>
            <srcused>\\netapp1\NTHOME\rita\GAS_HYDRATE\Limit_stabzone_GH</srcused>
            <procdate>20100407</procdate>
            <proctime>10255600</proctime>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Dataset copied.</procdesc>
            <srcused>\\netapp1\noga00\prov01\spatial\shape\Limit_stabzone_GH</srcused>
            <procdate>20100407</procdate>
            <proctime>10304900</proctime>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Dataset moved.</procdesc>
            <srcused>\\netapp1\public_data\noga00\prov01\spatial\shape\Limit_stabzone_GH</srcused>
            <procdate>20100407</procdate>
            <proctime>13553900</proctime>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc Sync="TRUE">Dataset copied.</procdesc>
            <srcused Sync="TRUE">D:\Limit_stabzone_GH</srcused>
            <procdate Sync="TRUE">20100407</procdate>
            <proctime Sync="TRUE">13594400</proctime>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Vector</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>String</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>3</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <mapproj>
               <mapprojn>Albers Conical Equal Area</mapprojn>
               <albers>
                  <stdparll>55.000000</stdparll>
                  <stdparll>65.000000</stdparll>
                  <longcm>-154.000000</longcm>
                  <latprjo>50.000000</latprjo>
                  <feast>0.000000</feast>
                  <fnorth>0.000000</fnorth>
               </albers>
            </mapproj>
            <planci>
               <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>0.000000</absres>
                  <ordres>0.000000</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>meters</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
            <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.257222</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>
Limit_stabzone_GH</enttypl>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>FID</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>ID</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Contour_ft</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Contour intervals in feet</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Energy Resource World Regions</attrdefs>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>NAME</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Limit of gas hydrate stability zone</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey Energy Resource World Regions</attrdefs>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Information Services</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Box 25286 Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-888-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>303-202-4693</cntfax>
            <cntemail>ask@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <cntinst>The dataset is available at NOGA Online - &lt;http://energy.cr.usgs.gov/oilgas/noga/&gt;</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  The U.S. Geological survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.  Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it may also contain copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items for other than personal use must be secured from the copyright owner.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Shapefile</formname>
               <formcont>Assessment unit geographic features and attribute data</formcont>
               <filedec>zip</filedec>
               <transize>0.068</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/data/noga00/prov01/spatial/shape/GHstabZone.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>The URL above links to a compressed file containing one or more limits of Gas Hydrate stability Boundaries.</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Interactive Mapping Applications</formname>
               <formcont>Online application available to view map services</formcont>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://certmapper.cr.usgs.gov/noga/servlet/NogaMapViewerBroker?province=01&amp;Vintage=2000</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>This URL links to a web-based interactive mapping system that accesses an ArcIMS Image Map Service.  The mapservice can also be accessed using any custom client that adheres to the protocol specified through ArcXML.</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None</fees>
         <ordering>These products can be accessed freely using any one of the Network_Resource_Name URLs above. Each of these provide access to various formats of these data.</ordering>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>Send email to datamgt@usgs.gov or call the USGS Central Energy Team main office at 303-236-1644.</custom>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>2008</metd>
      <metrd>2008</metrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Central Energy Resources Team</cntorg>
               <cntper>Margarita Zyrianova</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Geophysicist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>U.S. Geological Survey, Box 25046, MS 939, Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntemail>datamgt@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <cntinst>For inquiries regarding this document, please include the metadata contact person's name, dataset name, and publication series and number.</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
      <metextns>
         <onlink>http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink>
         <metprof>ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof>
      </metextns>
   </metainfo>
   <Esri>
      <MetaID>{9D321F24-BEE0-488B-886B-0843FD161518}</MetaID>
      <CreaDate>20100407</CreaDate>
      <CreaTime>14004000</CreaTime>
      <SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce>
      <PublishedDocID>{0392F547-BC02-46D2-9E86-F664EED2F093}</PublishedDocID>
      <PublishStatus>Published</PublishStatus>
      <ModDate>20100526</ModDate>
      <ModTime>13010100</ModTime>
   </Esri>
   <distInfo>
      <distributor>
         <distorTran>
            <onLineSrc>
               <linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\netapp1\public_data\noga00\prov01\spatial\doc\Limit_stabzone_GH</linkage>
               <protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol>
            </onLineSrc>
         </distorTran>
      </distributor>
   </distInfo>
   <USGSErp>
      <SyncDataGov>y</SyncDataGov>
      <FileSystemMetadataPath>\\netapp1\public_data/noga00/prov01/spatial/shape/GHstabZone.shp.xml</FileSystemMetadataPath>
      <ReferencingURLs>noga broker, NOGA online database.</ReferencingURLs>
      <MetadataProblems/>
      <MetadataNotes/>
   </USGSErp>
</metadata>
