<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata xmlns="http://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/csdgm" xml:lang="en">
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
            <title>CCB_SWATH_BS_1M: One meter backscatter mosaic acquired by the U.S. Geological Survey with the 117- kHz SEA Ltd. SWATHplus interferometric sonar offshore of Massachusetts within northern Cape Cod Bay (GeoTIFF IMAGE, UTM19 N).</title>
            <geoform Sync="TRUE">remote-sensing image</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>2010-1006</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Woods Hole Coastal and Marine Science Center, Woods Hole, Massachusetts</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Coastal and Marine Geology Program</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2010/1006/GIS/raster/backscatter/CCB_Swath_bs_1m.zip</onlink>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2010/1006/html/appendix1.html</onlink>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Brian D. Andrews</origin>
                  <origin>Seth D. Ackerman</origin>
                  <origin>Wayne E. Baldwin</origin>
                  <origin>Walter A. Barnhardt</origin>
                  <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
                  <title>Geophysical and Sampling Data from the Inner Continental Shelf: Northern Cape Cod Bay, Massachusetts.</title>
                  <edition>1.0</edition>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>Open-File Report</sername>
                     <issue>2010-1006</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Woods Hole Coastal and Marine Science Center, Woods Hole, Massachusetts</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Coastal and Marine Geology Program</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2010/1006/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>
These data were collected under a cooperative agreement with the Massachusetts Office of Coastal Zone Management (CZM) and the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), Coastal and Marine Geology Program, Woods Hole Coastal and Marine Science Center (WHCMSC). Initiated in 2003, the primary objective of this program is to develop regional geologic framework information for the management of coastal and marine resources. Accurate data and maps of sea-floor geology are important first steps toward protecting fish habitat, delineating marine resources, and assessing environmental changes due to natural or human impacts. The project is focused on the inshore waters of coastal Massachusetts, primarily in water depths of 3-30 meters deep. Data collected for the mapping cooperative have been released in a series of USGS Open-File Reports (http://woodshole.er.usgs.gov/project-pages/coastal_mass/html/current_map.html). The data collected in the study area located in Northern Cape Cod Bay Massachusetts includes high-resolution geophysics (bathymetry, backscatter intensity, and seismic reflection), and ground validation (sediment samples, video tracklines, and bottom photographs). The data were collected during five separate surveys conducted between 2006 and 2008 and cover 480 square kilometers of the inner continental shelf.

More information about the individual USGS surveys conducted as part of the northern Cape Cod Bay project can be found on the Woods Hole Coastal and Marine Science Center Field Activity webpage: 

06012: http://quashnet.er.usgs.gov/data/2006/06012/
07001: http://quashnet.er.usgs.gov/data/2007/07001/
07002: http://quashnet.er.usgs.gov/data/2007/07002/
07003: http://quashnet.er.usgs.gov/data/2007/07003/
08002: http://quashnet.er.usgs.gov/data/2008/08002/
</abstract>
         <purpose>The purpose of this GeoTIFF is to publish the acoustic backscatter of the seafloor acquired with the 117-kHz SWATHplus interferometric sonar offshore of Massachusetts within northern Cape Cod Bay. The Klein 3000 sidescan sonar was primary sonar used to acquire acoustic backscatter during surveys 06012, 07001, 07002, and 08002. However, during August 1-2, 2007 (07002), the winch used to deploy the Klein 3000 sidescan sonar towfish was inoperable. The acoustic backscatter acquired with the 117-kHz SWATHplus interferometric sonar was processed to cover this data gap in the Klein 3000 backscatter data.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>20070801</begdate>
               <enddate>20070802</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc Sync="TRUE">-70.603122</westbc>
            <eastbc Sync="TRUE">-70.480408</eastbc>
            <northbc Sync="TRUE">42.081631</northbc>
            <southbc Sync="TRUE">41.925067</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>General</themekt>
            <themekey>U.S. Geological Survey</themekey>
            <themekey>USGS</themekey>
            <themekey>Coastal and Marine Geology Program</themekey>
            <themekey>CMGP</themekey>
            <themekey>Woods Hole Coastal and Marine Science Center</themekey>
            <themekey>WHCMSC</themekey>
            <themekey>Backscatter</themekey>
            <themekey>Sidescan</themekey>
            <themekey>Sonar</themekey>
            <themekey>Seafloor</themekey>
            <themekey>Marine Geology</themekey>
            <themekey>Mosaic</themekey>
            <themekey>Interferometric Sonar</themekey>
            <themekey>SWATHplus</themekey>
            <themekey>SEA</themekey>
            <themekey>117 kHz</themekey>
            <themekey>GeoTIFF</themekey>
            <themekey>field activity serial number 07002</themekey>
            <themekey>field activity number 2007-002-FA</themekey>
            <themekey>R/V Megan T. Miller</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>oceans</themekey>
            <themekey>oceans and coastal</themekey>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
            <themekey>oceans and estuaries</themekey>
            <themekey>imageryBaseMapsEarthCover</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>General</placekt>
            <placekey>North America</placekey>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>Atlantic Ocean</placekey>
            <placekey>Gulf of Maine</placekey>
            <placekey>Cape Cod Bay</placekey>
            <placekey>Massachusetts Bay</placekey>
            <placekey>Duxbury</placekey>
            <placekey>Provincetown</placekey>
         </place>
         <stratum>
            <stratkt>General</stratkt>
            <stratkey>Seafloor</stratkey>
         </stratum>
         <temporal>
            <tempkt>General</tempkt>
            <tempkey>2007</tempkey>
         </temporal>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None.</accconst>
      <useconst>These data are not for navigational use. Public domain data from the U.S. Government are freely redistributable with proper metadata and source attribution. Please recognize the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) as the source of this information.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Brian Andrews</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>384 Woods Hole Rd.</address>
               <city>Woods Hole</city>
               <state>MA</state>
               <postal>02543-1598</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>508-548-8700 x2348</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>508-457-2310</cntfax>
            <cntemail>bandrews@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2010/1006/GIS/browse_jpg/CCB_Swath_bs_1m.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>gray-scale thumbnail image of SWATHplus backscatter collected offshore of Massachusetts within the northern Cape Cod Bay.</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <native Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows 2000 Version 5.2 (Build 3790) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.1850</native>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Walter A. Barnhardt</origin>
            <origin>Brian D. Andrews</origin>
            <origin>Bradford Butman</origin>
            <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
            <title>High-Resolution Mapping of the Inner Continental Shelf: Nahant to Gloucester, Massachusetts</title>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>2005-1293</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Woods Hole Science Center, Woods Hole, Massachusetts</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Coastal and Marine Geology Program</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2005/1293/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Seth D. Ackerman</origin>
            <origin>Bradford Butman</origin>
            <origin>Walter A. Barnhardt</origin>
            <origin>William W. Danforth</origin>
            <origin>James M. Crocker</origin>
            <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
            <title>High-Resolution Geologic Mapping of the Inner Continental Shelf: Boston Harbor and Approaches, Massachusetts</title>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>2006-1008</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Woods Hole Science Center, Woods Hole, Massachusetts</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Coastal and Marine Geology Program</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2006/1008/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Walter A. Barnhardt</origin>
            <origin>Brian D. Andrews</origin>
            <origin>Seth D. Ackerman</origin>
            <origin>Wayne E. Baldwin</origin>
            <origin>Christopher J. Hein</origin>
            <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
            <title>High-Resolution Geological Mapping of the Inner Continental Shelf: Cape Ann to Salisbury Beach, Massachusetts</title>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>2007-1373</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Woods Hole Science Center, Woods Hole, Massachusetts</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Coastal and Marine Geology Program</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2007/1373/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Walter A. Barnhardt</origin>
            <origin>Seth D. Ackerman</origin>
            <origin>Brian D. Andrews</origin>
            <origin>Wayne E. Baldwin</origin>
            <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
            <title>Geophysical and Sampling Data from the Inner Continental Shelf: Duxbury to Hull, Massachusetts</title>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>2009-1072</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Woods Hole Science Center, Woods Hole, Massachusetts</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Coastal and Marine Geology Program</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2009/1072/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>Image pixel values contain acoustic reflectivity values normalized to an 8-bit data range (0-255). Low-backscatter is represented by dark tones (low values) and high-backscatter is represented by bright tones (high values). No data value is set to 255.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <complete>This image does not include all backscatter data collected with the SWATHplus (117 kHz)  interferometric sonar. It includes only SWATHplus backscatter data collected during JD 213-214 covering the data gap in the towed Klein sidescan-sonar backscatter data.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>The SWATHplus transducers were mounted on a rigid pole, approximately 2.6 m below the water line, along the starboard side of the R/V Megan T. Miller. Position data were provided by the Z-Surveyor Extreme for real-time kinematic (RTK) navigation (the Ashtech BR2G Differential Global Positioning System (DGPS) was used as a backup navigation system) and recorded to the raw data files (SXR) via SWATHplus (version 2.07) on the acquisition computer.  A conservative estimate of positional accuracy is estimated to be 10 m although when the system was recording RTK navigation the positional accuracy may be &lt;1 m as RTK-GPS provides horizontal positional accuracies on the decimeter scale (http://www.noaa.gov; http://www.nos.noaa.gov; http://www.ngs.noaa.gov).</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccontr>
Sonar Configuration:
Bathymetry data were acquired with a Systems Engineering and Assessment Ltd. (SEA) SWATHplus 117 kHz interferometric sonar. Survey lines were run at an average speed of 5 knots and were spaced 150 m apart to obtain overlapping swaths of data and full coverage of the seafloor.
The transducers were mounted on a rigid pole on the starboard side of the R/V Megan Miller, about 2.6 m below the waterline. A Coda Octopus F-180 inertial-motion unit, mounted directly above the transducers, measured true heading, vertical displacement (heave) and attitude (pitch and roll) of the vessel during acquisition.

Navigation:
Navigation was based on a Real-Time Kinematic Global Positioning System (RTK-GPS); the RTK-GPS antenna was mounted directly above the interferometric sonar head. The RTK-corrected GPS signal was sent to the ship from a base station established by the USGS on land. Horizontal (x and y) and vertical (z) offsets between the transducers and motion sensor and antenna and motion sensor were precisely measured and recorded within the SWATHplus acquisition software (SEA Swath Processor (2005)). These offsets are used to establish the motion sensor as the common reference point for data acquisition. 

Speed of Sound:
Additionally, the depth of the transducers below the water surface was measured and recorded within the SEA Swath Processor acquisition software. This depth was used to derive the speed of sound profile and acoustic ray path based on speed of sound profiles collected within the survey area. Sound-velocity profiles were collected approximately every 2 hours by a hand-casted Applied MicroSystems SV Plus sound velocimeter.
</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Step 1: Raw to Processed Conversion: Each raw SWATHplus bathymetric sonar file (sxr) was converted to a SWATHplus processed file (sxp) using SEA SWATHplus Swath Processor (ver.3.6). During the conversion process, sound velocity profiles were used to minimize potential refraction artifacts from fluctuations in the speed of sound within the water column. Various bathymetric filters were applied to flag sounding outliers however all data (flagged/unflagged) were converted to the processed file. During this conversion process the tidal information from the previous process step was merged into the new processed file (sxp).</procdesc>
            <procdate>200910</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Brian Andrews</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>384 Woods Hole Rd.</address>
                     <city>Woods Hole</city>
                     <state>MA</state>
                     <postal>02543-1598</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>508-548-8700 x2348</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>508-457-2310</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>bandrews@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Step 2: SXP Tools: Each sxp file was processed through a java-based SXPTools (version date 17 Sep 09) developed by David Finlayson at USGS. This routine was developed to look at all the soundings and normalize the data. Parameters are below: Command: sxpeng -insxp -outsxp_bs.</procdesc>
            <procdate>200910</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Brian Andrews</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>384 Woods Hole Rd</address>
                     <city>Woods Hole</city>
                     <state>MA</state>
                     <postal>02543-1598</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>508-548-8700 x2348</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>508-457-2310</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>bandrews@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Step 3:CARIS Import-geoTIFF export: Import each of the sxp processed files into CARIS ver 6.1 using the generic data parser. Once each of the sxps were converted to a CARIS line file, a mosaic using the amplitude option was made for each line. A separate GeoTIFF image was produced for each of the 6 line files.</procdesc>
            <procdate>200910</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Brian Andrews</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>384 Woods Hole Rd</address>
                     <city>Woods Hole</city>
                     <state>MA</state>
                     <postal>02543-1598</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>508-548-8700 x2348</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>508-457-2310</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>bandrews@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>PCI Mosaic: The odd and even tiff images were then imported into PCI Geomatica Software (version 10.1) and digitally mosaicked at a 1.0-m pixel resolution using PCI's OrthoEngine. The composite mosaic was registered in the UTM (Zone 19N, WGS84, meters) coordinate system and exported as a GeoTIFF image. A TIFF world file (tfw) was also generated for those who can't read a GeoTIFF.</procdesc>
            <procdate>200910</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Brian Andrews</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>384 Woods Hole Rd</address>
                     <city>Woods Hole</city>
                     <state>MA</state>
                     <postal>02543-1598</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>508-548-8700 x2348</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>508-457-2310</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>bandrews@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct Sync="TRUE">Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype Sync="TRUE">Pixel</rasttype>
         <rowcount Sync="TRUE">17212</rowcount>
         <colcount Sync="TRUE">9856</colcount>
         <vrtcount Sync="TRUE">1</vrtcount>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <mapproj>
               <mapprojn Sync="TRUE">Transverse Mercator</mapprojn>
               <transmer>
                  <sfctrmer Sync="TRUE">0.999600</sfctrmer>
                  <longcm Sync="TRUE">-69.000000</longcm>
                  <latprjo Sync="TRUE">0.000000</latprjo>
                  <feast Sync="TRUE">500000.000000</feast>
                  <fnorth Sync="TRUE">0.000000</fnorth>
               </transmer>
            </mapproj>
            <planci>
               <plance Sync="TRUE">row and column</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres Sync="TRUE">1.000000</absres>
                  <ordres Sync="TRUE">1.000000</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu Sync="TRUE">meters</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>D_WGS_1984</horizdn>
            <ellips Sync="TRUE">WGS_1984</ellips>
            <semiaxis Sync="TRUE">6378137.000000</semiaxis>
            <denflat Sync="TRUE">298.257224</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <overview>
         <eaover>There are no attributes associated with a GeoTIFF image. Image pixel values contain acoustic reflectivity values normalized to an 8-bit data range (0-255) with the data range 1-255. Low-backscatter is represented by dark tones (low values) and high-backscatter is represented by bright tones (high values). The background color is set to 0 and can be turned off without removing data values.</eaover>
         <eadetcit>U.S. Geological Survey</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Brian Andrews</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>384 Woods Hole Rd.</address>
               <city>Woods Hole</city>
               <state>MA</state>
               <postal>02543</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>508-548-8700 x2348</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>bandrews@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc Sync="TRUE">Downloadable Data</resdesc>
      <distliab>Neither the U.S. Government, the Department of the Interior, nor the USGS, nor any of their employees, contractors, or subcontractors, make any warranty, express or implied, nor assume any legal liability or responsibility for the accuracy, completeness, or usefulness of any information, apparatus, product, or process disclosed, nor represent that its use would not infringe on privately owned rights. The act of distribution shall not constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumed by the USGS in the use of these data or related materials. Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>WinZip</formname>
               <formvern>9.0</formvern>
               <formspec>GeoTIFF</formspec>
               <formcont>WinZip file containing a GeoTIFF backscatter collected by the U.S. Geological Survey with a SEA 117 kHz interferometric sonar offshore of Massachusetts within Northern Cape Cod Bay.</formcont>
               <filedec>WinZip</filedec>
               <transize>16.0 Mb</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2010/1006/GIS/raster/backscatter/CCB_Swath_bs_1m.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
               <offoptn>
                  <offmedia>DVD-ROM</offmedia>
                  <reccap>
                     <recden>4.75</recden>
                     <recdenu>Gbytes</recdenu>
                  </reccap>
                  <recfmt>UDF</recfmt>
               </offoptn>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None</fees>
      </stdorder>
      <techpreq>This Zip file contains a GeoTIFF image and world file. To utilize these data the user must have an image viewer, image processing or GIS software package capable of importing a GeoTIFF image.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd Sync="TRUE">20100930</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Brian Andrews</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>384 Woods Hole Rd.</address>
               <city>Woods Hole</city>
               <state>MA</state>
               <postal>02543-1598</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>508-548-8700 x2348</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>508-457-2310</cntfax>
            <cntemail>bandrews@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn Sync="TRUE">FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv Sync="TRUE">FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <mettc Sync="TRUE">local time</mettc>
      <metextns>
         <onlink Sync="TRUE">http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink>
         <metprof Sync="TRUE">ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof>
      </metextns>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
