<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Bruce M. Davis</origin>
            <origin>Patrick L. Hudson</origin>
            <origin>S. Jerrine Nichols</origin>
            <origin>Cynthia M. Tomcko</origin>
            <pubdate>198602</pubdate>
            <title>Environmental Studies of Macrozoobenthos, Aquatic Macrophytes, and Juvenile Fishes in the St. Clair-Detroit River System, 1983-1984: Ponar Sampling Record for Macrozoobenthos</title>
            <geoform>Tabular Digital Data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>GLSC Administrative Reports</sername>
               <issue>86-7</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/544a4b8be4b04d2014abfb8c</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This ponar sampling record for macrozoobenthos data set was collected for use in the administrative report entitled "Environmental Studies of Macrozoobenthos, Aquatic Macrophytes, and Juvenile Fishes in the St. Clair-Detroit River System, 1983-1984".  It is a portion of the data collected for this administrative report, which provided information needed by the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers for preparation of a Supplemental Environmental Impact Statement addressing the winter operation of the lock facilities at Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan, and the subsequent extension of the navigation season in the St. Clair-Detroit River system (SCDRS) to January-February. The following is excerpted from the original report's abstract:  We describe the distribution and abundance of macrozoobenthos, aquatic macrophytes and juvenile fishes during the 1983 and 1984 open water season, and attempt to predict or evaluate the potential environmental impact of an extended navigation season on the biota of SCDRS. Fauna and flora were diverse and abundant; we identified more than 300 taxa of macrozoobenthos, 30 taxa of submergent and emergent macrophytes, and 36 species of fish. The diversity and abundance of macrozoobenthos were generally highest in the St. Clair River. Abundance and diversity of submersed macrophytes were similar in the two rivers, but Chara dominated in the St. Clair River and Vallisneria americana in the Detroit River. We collected more total fish in the Detroit River but more species in the St. Clair River. Yellow perch and rock bass dominated most catches in both rivers. An ice jam in the St. Clair River in spring 1984 appeared to affect two of the three groups studied--macroinvertebrates and submersed macrophytes. Of the 24 abundant taxa of macroinvertebrates, 9 were seemingly less abundant in spring in 1984 than in 1983 in the St. Clair River; however the densities of 6 of these taxa had recovered by fall 1984 to levels equal to or exceeding those in fall 1983 and the other 3 were within 30% of those in 1983. Cover of the bottom with submersed macrophytes was somewhat reduced in spring of 1984--particularly in the St. Clair River--but recovered to 1983 levels by fall 1984. Plant biomass levels varied between years and locations; no consistent differences could be attributed to the ice jam. Catches of fish were lower in 1984 than in 1983 but differences between locations and months were inconsistent. Observed differences in the plant community could be attributed to reduced temperatures, and ice-scour may have reduced the density of several taxa of macrozoobenthos. Evaluation of the potential environmental impacts of an extended navigation season on the biota of SCDRS was not attempted.</abstract>
         <purpose>The data describes the distribution and abundance of macrozoobenthos, and attempt to predict or evaluate the potential environmental impact of an extended navigation season on the biota of SCDR. These data were collected for a USACOE Supplemental Environmental Impact Statement addressing the winter operation of the lock facilities at Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan, and the subsequent extension of the navigation season in the St. Clair-Detroit River system (SCDRS) to January-February. </purpose>
         <supplinf>This ponar sampling record for macrozoobenthos data set was created for the use in the titled report to administration; this data set used in report's Appendix F: "Macrozoobenthos Physical Data".  It shows the distribution of different macrozoobenthos species resulting from a total of 756 macrozoobenthos samples collected with a standard Ponar grab (484 cm2) along 21 transects at locations specified in the data set.  The samples were processed at the Great Lakes Fishery laboratory and summarized in Appendix G: "Macrozoobenthos Physical Data - A Summary" of titled report.  Related biomass data is also available in Appendix E: "Macrozoobenthos Ponar Grab Biomass Data" and summarized in "Density and Total Biomass of Macrozoobenthos -A Summary by Year, Month, Transect, and Station" of titled report.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>19830503</begdate>
               <enddate>19841017</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-83.2781982421903</westbc>
            <eastbc>-82.257794189456</eastbc>
            <northbc>43.1264495084208</northbc>
            <southbc>42.052355024737</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>USGS Biocomplexity Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>Freshwater ecosystems</themekey>
            <themekey>Benthos</themekey>
            <themekey>Macrophytes</themekey>
            <themekey>Freshwater fishes</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>GLSC Science Theme</themekt>
            <themekey>Restoration Ecology</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>GNIS</placekt>
            <placekey>Saint Clair River</placekey>
            <placekey>Detroit River</placekey>
            <placekey>Lake Saint Clair</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None. Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</accconst>
      <useconst>
This data was collected for reporting to the Department of the Army, U.S. Army Corps of Engineers,
Detroit-District, Detroit, Michigan 48231.   The scientific review process for this report may differ from other publication types.  Users are advised to read the data set's metadata thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.
</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Midwest Region - Great Lakes Science Center</cntorg>
               <cntper>Scott R Nelson</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Information Technology Specialist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>1451 Green Rd</address>
               <city>Ann Arbor</city>
               <state>MI</state>
               <postal>48105</postal>
               <country>US</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>734-214-7243</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>734-994-8780</cntfax>
            <cntemail>snelson@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>Great Lakes Fishery Laboratory, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</datacred>
      <native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; ESRI ArcCatalog 10.2 (Build 3552) Service Pack [N/A] (Build [N/A])</native>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Bruce M. Davis</origin>
            <origin>Patrick L. Hudson</origin>
            <origin>S. Jerrine Nichols</origin>
            <origin>Cynthia M. Tomcko</origin>
            <pubdate>198602</pubdate>
            <title>Environmental Studies of Macrozoobenthos, Aquatic Macrophytes, and Juvenile Fishes in the St. Clair-Detroit River System, 1983-1984: Sample Processing Record for Macrozoobenthos</title>
            <geoform>Tabular Digital Data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>GLSC Administrative Reports</sername>
               <issue>86-7</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F70P0X31</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Bruce M. Davis</origin>
            <origin>Patrick L. Hudson</origin>
            <origin>S. Jerrine Nichols</origin>
            <origin>Cynthia M. Tomcko</origin>
            <pubdate>198602</pubdate>
            <title>Environmental Studies of Macrozoobenthos, Aquatic Macrophytes, and Juvenile Fishes in the St. Clair-Detroit River System, 1983-1984: Hoopnet Sampling Record for Fish</title>
            <geoform>Tabular Digital Data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>GLSC Administrative Reports</sername>
               <issue>86-7</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7NC5Z7X</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Bruce M. Davis</origin>
            <origin>Patrick L. Hudson</origin>
            <origin>S. Jerrine Nichols</origin>
            <origin>Cynthia M. Tomcko</origin>
            <pubdate>198602</pubdate>
            <title>Environmental Studies of Macrozoobenthos, Aquatic Macrophytes, and Juvenile Fishes in the St. Clair-Detroit River System, 1983-1984: Hoopnet Sampling Record for Macrophytes</title>
            <geoform>Tabular Digital Data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>GLSC Administrative Reports</sername>
               <issue>86-7</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7HM56G4</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Bruce M. Davis</origin>
            <origin>Patrick L. Hudson</origin>
            <origin>S. Jerrine Nichols</origin>
            <origin>Cynthia M. Tomcko</origin>
            <pubdate>198602</pubdate>
            <title>Environmental Studies of Macrozoobenthos, Aquatic Macrophytes, and Juvenile Fishes in the St. Clair-Detroit River System, 1983-1984: Grapnel Sampling Record for Macrophytes</title>
            <geoform>Tabular Digital Data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>GLSC Administrative Reports</sername>
               <issue>86-7</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7RB72NW</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Bruce M. Davis</origin>
            <origin>Patrick L. Hudson</origin>
            <origin>S. Jerrine Nichols</origin>
            <origin>Cynthia M. Tomcko</origin>
            <pubdate>198602</pubdate>
            <title>Environmental Studies of Macrozoobenthos, Aquatic Macrophytes, and Juvenile Fishes in the St. Clair-Detroit River System, 1983-1984: Macrophyte Sample Processing Record</title>
            <geoform>Tabular Digital Data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>GLSC Administrative Reports</sername>
               <issue>86-7</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7CV4FSV</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Bruce M. Davis</origin>
            <origin>Patrick L. Hudson</origin>
            <origin>S. Jerrine Nichols</origin>
            <origin>Cynthia M. Tomcko</origin>
            <pubdate>198602</pubdate>
            <title>Environmental Studies of Macrozoobenthos, Aquatic Macrophytes, and Juvenile Fishes in the St. Clair-Detroit River System, 1983-1984: Ponar and Hand-Harvested Quadrat Sampling Record for Macrophytes</title>
            <geoform>Tabular Digital Data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>GLSC Administrative Reports</sername>
               <issue>86-7</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7862DG5</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic>
      <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
         <vertacc>
            <vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr>
         </vertacc>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Development of the data set by the agency / individuals identified in the 'Originator' element in the Identification Info section of the record.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo/>
   <spref/>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd>
            <enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>FILENAME</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>File names of original electronic data sources</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>EE254_SC.DAT</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Data file associated with ECO field data form 254</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>EE254Y84.DAT</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Data file associated with ECO field data form 254</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>EJ254834.DAT</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Data file associated with ECO field data form 254</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>FORM_NO</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Field data form number</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>3-digit number representing the form used to collect original data in the field</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>LAKE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Lake or river where sample was taken</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>4</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Lake Saint Clair</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>8</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Saint Clair River</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>9</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Detroit River</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>OP_DATE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Sample collection date</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Date format M(M)DDYYYY</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>TRANSECT</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Transect number where sample collected</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>upper St. Clair River; headwaters-in line with buoys number 1 and 2 at the head of the St. Clair River</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>upper St. Clair River; mainland littoral- about 4.5 miles downstream from transect 1 and is in line with a peninsular piece of land on U.S. side and a flare on the property of Dow Chemical of Canada, Ltd</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>upper St. Clair River; island shoals- head of Stag Island, about 4 miles downstream from transect 2. The transect extends from the upstream tip of the island to buoy RB</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>4</edomv>
                  <edomvd>
upper St. Clair River; island shoals - head of Fawn Island and is about 13
miles downstream from transect III. It extends due west
from an unnamed east-west road on the Canadian shore
</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>5</edomv>
                  <edomvd>upper St. Clair River; island shoals - head of Russell Island about 5.5 miles downstream from transect IV. It extends from the upstream tip of the island to buoy SR</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>6</edomv>
                  <edomvd>lower St. Clair River; shoreline of the South Channel and St. Clair Cutoff Channel in the St. Clair River delta area - in the South Channel in line with buoys number 26 and 27 about 2.2 miles downstream from transect V.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>7</edomv>
                  <edomvd>lower St. Clair River; shoreline of the South Channel and St. Clair Cutoff Channel in the St. Clair River delta area - in the South Channel in line with buoys 17 and 20 about 2.9 miles downstream from transect VI</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>8</edomv>
                  <edomvd>lower St. Clair River; shoreline of the South Channel and St. Clair Cutoff Channel in the St. Clair River delta area - in the St. Clair Cut-off Channel in line with Lights 7 and 8 about 3.2 miles downstream from transect 7</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>9</edomv>
                  <edomvd>lower St. Clair River;St. Clair Cutoff Channel in the St. Clair River delta area - in the St. Clair Cut-off Channel, in line with Lights 5 and 6</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>10</edomv>
                  <edomvd>lower St. Clair River; St. Clair Cutoff Channel in the St. Clair River delta area - in the St. Clair Cut-off Channel, in line with Lights 3 and 4</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>11</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Lake St. Clair; deepest part of the lake -  in line with buoys 25 and 26 about 4.5 miles downstream from transect 10</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>12</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Lake St. Clair; deepest part of the lake - in line with buoy 24 and a stationary light</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>13</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Lake St. Clair; deepest part of the lake - in line with buoys 21 and 22</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>14</edomv>
                  <edomvd>upper Detroit River; headwaters - near the head of the Detroit River on a bearing of 4° from the Peach Island Range Tower</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>15</edomv>
                  <edomvd>upper Detroit River; headwaters - in the Detroit River on a bearing of 187° from buoy 8 on the north side of Peach Island</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>16</edomv>
                  <edomvd>upper Detroit River; Belle Isle area - south side of Belle Isle about 1.8 miles downstream from transect 15. The transect extends on a bearing of 172° from a point on the shoreline midway between the entrance to the Coast Guard Station vessel slip and the base of the Michigan Department of Natural Resources fishing pier.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>17</edomv>
                  <edomvd>upper Detroit River; Belle Isle area - below Belle Isle between buoy RB and a road intersection on Belle Isle about 2.5 miles downstream from transect 16</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>18</edomv>
                  <edomvd>lower Detroit River; east side of the tip of Point Hennepin on a bearing of 275° from buoy 7 about 12.6 miles downstream from transect 16</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>19</edomv>
                  <edomvd>lower Detroit River; adjacent to the Fighting Island Channel on a line between buoy 87 and the Thorofare Canal</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>20</edomv>
                  <edomvd>lower Detroit River; adjacent to the Ballards Reef Channel on a line between buoy 83 and Church Road on Grosse Isle</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>21</edomv>
                  <edomvd>lower Detroit River; adjacent to the Livingstone Channel on a bearing of 98° from Ferry Road on Grosse Isle</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>STATION</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Station number; the part of the river where sample was collected</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>shallow depth; on the sloping side of the shipping channel (channel stations)</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>middle depth; immediately adjacent to the channel on the crest of the channel slope (near-channel stations)</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>deep depth; between the crest of the channel slope and the adjacent shoreline (off-channel stations)</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>UPPER_LORAN</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Upper LORAN coordinate</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>6-digit coordinate number</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>LOWER_LORAN</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Lower LORAN coordinate</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>6-digit coordinate number</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>WATER_DEPTH</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Water depth; need to multiply by (0.1) for actual depth in ft</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>30</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>280</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>0.1 feet</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>BOTTOM_TYPE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Primary material composition of bottom</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Each value represents a bottom type of one of the following:  clay, silty clay, sandy clay, gravel, silty gravel, sandy gravel, sand, sandy silt, silt, organic debris.  See corresponding report's Appendix F: Macrozoobenthos Physical Data to reliably match bottom types to each sample.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>WATER_TEMP_SURFACE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Surface water temperature (Celcius); need to multiply by (0.1) for actual units</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>-1</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>152</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>0.1 degrees Celcius</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>WATER_TEMP_BOTTOM</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Bottom water temperature; need to multiply by (0.1) for actual units</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>-1</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>151</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>0.1 degrees Celcius</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>WATER_VELOCITY_SURFACE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Surface water velocity (ft/sec);  need to multiply by (0.1) for actual rate</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>-1</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>31</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>0.1 feet/seconds</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>WATER_VELOCITY_BOTTOM</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Bottom water velocity (ft/sec);  need to multiply by (0.1) for actual rate</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>-1</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>28</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>0.1 feet/seconds</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>INCIDENT_LIGHT_SURFACE_READ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>incident light surface reading (used to calculater ft. candles)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>1</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>95</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>INCIDENT_LIGHT_SURFACE_EXP</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>incident light surface exposure (used to calculate ft. candles)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>4</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>INCIDENT_LIGHT_BOTTOM_READ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>incident light bottom reading (used to calculater ft. candles)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>98</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>INCIDENT_LIGHT_BOTTOM_EXP</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>incident light bottom exposure (used to calculater ft. candles)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>4</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>SAMPLE_REPL_COLLECTED</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The number of  replicates collected for each sample</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>whole number</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <overview>
         <eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes the tabular data associated with the data set. Please review the detailed descriptions that are provided (the individual attribute descriptions) for information on the values that appear as fields/table entries of the data set.</eaover>
         <eadetcit>The entity and attribute information was generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Please review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Midwest Region - Great Lakes Science Center</cntorg>
               <cntper>Scott R Nelson</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Information Technology Specialist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>1451 Green Rd</address>
               <city>Ann Arbor</city>
               <state>MI</state>
               <postal>48105</postal>
               <country>US</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>734-214-7243</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>734-994-8780</cntfax>
            <cntemail>snelson@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Distributor assumes no liability for misuse of data.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Tabular Digital Data</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F74F1NSW</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20141010</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Alana Schaffer</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Midwest Region - Great Lakes Science Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Science Records Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>1451 Green Rd</address>
               <city>Ann Arbor</city>
               <state>MI</state>
               <postal>48105</postal>
               <country>US</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>734-214-7243</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>734-994-8780</cntfax>
            <cntemail>snelson@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
