<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>20130122</pubdate>
            <pubtime>000000</pubtime>
            <title>LandCarbon Conterminous United States Burned Area and Severity Mosaics 2001-2050 Metadata</title>
            <edition>1.0</edition>
            <geoform>raster digital data</geoform>
            <serinfo/>
            <onlink>http://landcarbon.org/categories/burn-area/download/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>
        The burn area and severity data were stochastically generated using a probabilistic ignition model and mechanistic fire-spread model. The ignition model consisted of a general linear model with a binary response, constructed by relating daily ignition locations in the monitoring trends in burn severity database (MTBS; Eidenshink et al 2007) to predictor variables including daily weather, fuel moisture, fire behavior indices, monthly and seasonal climate variables, and vegetation and land cover. In the simulations, the ignition model was used to stochastically generate ignition locations. After a location was generated, fires were spread using the minimum-travel time algorithm (MTT; Finney 2002) which generates spatially-explicit burn scars in relation to weather and fuel moisture conditions, fuels, and topography. Simulations were first calibrated using historic, observed weather data from 1984-2008 (Maurer et al. 2002) and then future projections were made using downscaled GCM data (Maurer et al. 2007). For this assessment, the climate change projections included data produced by the CCCma CGCM 3.1, CSIRO–Mk3.0, MIROC 3.2-medres GCMs for the A1B, A2, and B1 scenarios. Fuels and vegetation data were provided by the LANDFIRE project (Rollins 2008). Detailed information about the methods used to simulate burned area can be found in Hawbaker and Zhu (2012).

        Eidenshink, J., B. Schwind, K. Brewer, Z Zhu, B. Quayle and S. Howard, 2007, A project for monitoring trends in burn severity: Fire Ecology, v. 3, no. 1, p. 3–21, doi:10.4996/fireecology.0301003.

        Finney, M.A., 2002, Fire growth using minimum travel time methods: Canadian Journal of Forest Research, v. 32, no. 8, p. 1420–1424, doi:10.1139/x02-068.

        Hawbaker, T. and Z. Zhu. 2012. Projected Future Wildland Fires and Emissions for the Western United States. Chapter 8 in Zhu, Zhiliang, and Reed, B.C., eds., 2012, Baseline and projected future carbon storage and greenhouse-gas fluxes in ecosystems of the Western United States: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 1797, 192 p. (Also available at http://pubs.usgs.gov/pp/1797/.)

        Maurer, E.P., L. Brekke, T. Pruitt, and P.B. Duffy, 2007, Fine-resolution climate projections enhance regional climate change impact studies: Eos, v. 88, no. 47, p. 504.

        Maurer, E.P., A.W. Wood, J.C. Adam, D.P. Lettenmaier, and B. Nijssen, 2002, A long-term hydrologically based dataset of land surface fluxes and states for the conterminous United States: Journal of Climate, v. 15, no. 22, p. 3237–3251, doi:10.1175/1520-0442(2002)0152.0.CO;2.

        Rollins, M.G., 2009, LANDFIRE; A nationally consistent vegetation, wildland fire, and fuel assessment: International Journal of Wildland Fire, v. 18, no. 3, p. 235–249, doi:10.1071/WF08088.
      </abstract>
         <purpose>This raster-based map of projected wildfire burned area and severity was prepared by the U.S. Geological Survey's LandCarbon team, as part of the methodology to model future carbon storage capacity in the Nation's major ecological regions under three future scenarios based on the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Chage's (IPCC) Special Report on Emissions Scenarios (SRES). This is temporary metadata information (as of January 2013) until final metadata is compiled for full public release of the LandCarbon Burned Area and Severity mosaics from 2001-2050 for four IPCC-SRES Scenarios (A1b, A2, and B1)</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>20010101</begdate>
               <begtime>000000</begtime>
               <enddate>20500101</enddate>
               <endtime>000000</endtime>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>20130122</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-127.922278</westbc>
            <eastbc>-74.013589</eastbc>
            <northbc>47.975864</northbc>
            <southbc>22.754100</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>wildfire</themekey>
            <themekey>burned area</themekey>
            <themekey>burn severity</themekey>
            <themekey>projections</themekey>
            <themekey>IPCC</themekey>
            <themekey>SRES</themekey>
            <themekey>scenarios</themekey>
            <themekey>ecoregions</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>
      There are no limitations on the use of these raster maps. A statement of the data source when citing, copying, or reprinting USGS data or images is requested. The USGS cautions that users understand the limits of these data before proceeding with personal, academic, and/or governmental use. We also ask users to be aware of the interpretive nature of these data and how they represent a single, plausible land-use and land-cover outcome out of many plausible outcomes. Data users should read USGS Open File Report 2012-1252 and the regional LandCarbon reports (USGS Professional Papers 1787 and 1797 to become familiar with the methods used to produce the dataset.
      Zhu, Z., (editor), B. Bergamaschi, R. Bernknopf, D. Clow, D. Dye, S. Faulkner, W. Forney, R. Gleason, T. Hawbaker, J. Liu, S. Liu, S. Prisley, B. Reed, M. Reeves, M. G. Rollins, B. Sleeter, T. L. Sohl, S. Stackpoole, S. Stehman, R. Striegl, A. Wein, and Z. Zhu. 2010. A method for assessing carbon stocks, carbon sequestration, and greenhouse-gas fluxes in ecosystems of the United States under present conditions and future scenarios: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report, 2010-1144. (Also available at http://pubs.usgs.gov/sir/2010/5233)
      Zhiliang Z. (editor), M. Bouchard, D. Butman, T. Hawbaker, Z. Li, J. Liu, S. Liu, C. McDonald, R. Reker, K. Sayler, B. Sleeter, T. Sohl, S. Stackpoole, A. Wein, and Z. Zhu. 2011. Baseline and Projected Future Carbon Storage and Greenhouse-Gas Fluxes in the Great Plains Region of the United States. U.S. Geological Survey Profession Paper 1787, 28p. (Also available at http://pubs.usgs.gov/pp/1787)
      Z. Zhu and B. Reed (editors), Baseline and projected future carbon storage and greenhouse-gas fluxes in ecosystems of the Western United States: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 1797. 192 p. (Also available at http://pubs.usgs.gov/pp/1797)
    </useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
               <cntper>Todd J. Hawbaker</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Research Ecologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>unknown</addrtype>
               <address>P.O. Box 25046, DFC, MS 980</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>CO</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>US</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>303-236-1371</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>tjhawbaker@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>Todd J. Hawbaker and Zhiliang Zhu</datacred>
   </idinfo>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Grid Cell</rasttype>
         <rowcount>5296</rowcount>
         <colcount>1783</colcount>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <mapproj>
               <mapprojn>Albers Conical Equal Area</mapprojn>
               <albers>
                  <stdparll>29.5</stdparll>
                  <stdparll>45.5</stdparll>
                  <longcm>-96.0</longcm>
                  <latprjo>23.0</latprjo>
                  <feast>0.0</feast>
                  <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
               </albers>
            </mapproj>
            <planci>
               <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>0.0000000037527980722984474</absres>
                  <ordres>0.0000000037527980722984474</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>1{Standard_Parallel}2 + Longitude_of_Central_Meridian + Latitude_of_Projection_Origin + False_Easting + False_Northing</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>D North American 1983</horizdn>
            <ellips>GRS 1980</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>LandCarbon Conterminous United States Burned Area and Severity Mosaics 2001-2050</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Attribute table for projected burned area and severity map</enttypd>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Value</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Unique values for burned area and severity classes</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>0</edomv>
                  <edomvd>unburned</edomvd>
               </edom>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>11</edomv>
                  <edomvd>low severity burn/surface fire</edomvd>
               </edom>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>12</edomv>
                  <edomvd>moderate severity burn/torching trees or passive crown fire</edomvd>
               </edom>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>13</edomv>
                  <edomvd>high severity burn/active crown fire</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20141010</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
               <cntper>Todd J. Hawbaker</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Research Ecologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>unknown</addrtype>
               <address>P.O. Box 25046, DFC, MS 980</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>CO</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>US</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>303-236-1371</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>tjhawbaker@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
