<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>20130122</pubdate>
            <pubtime>000000</pubtime>
            <title>Net Ecosystem Carbon Flux</title>
            <edition>1.0</edition>
            <geoform>raster digital data</geoform>
            <serinfo/>
            <onlink>
          http://landcarbon.org/categories/net-ecosystem-c-balance/download/
        </onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>
        Net Ecosystem Carbon Flux is defined as the year-over-year change in Total Ecosystem Carbon Stock, or the net rate of carbon exchange between an ecosystem and the atmosphere.  The data of this variable were generated by the USGS LandCarbon project using the General Ensemble Biogeochemical Modeling System (GEMS) based on selected IPCC emissions scenarios, biogeochemical models, and climate datasets.  The spatial extent is the conterminous United States and the temporal extent is from 1993 through 2050.  These data are projected to Albers Equal Area in the NAD83 datum at a resolution of 2000 meters and are spatially gridded in GeoTiff format.  Units of measure are expressed in g Carbon/m2/yr.  Positive values indicate sequestration of carbon from the atmosphere (carbon sink).
      </abstract>
         <purpose>
        The USGS LandCarbon Project is developing methodology and conducting an assessment of the nation's ecosystems for carbon storage, carbon sequestration, and fluxes of greenhouse gases as mandated in Section 712 of the Energy Independence and Security Act (2007). The Land Carbon Data Management System maintains historic data and projected data using scenarios established by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC).
      </purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>20010101</begdate>
               <begtime>000000</begtime>
               <enddate>20500101</enddate>
               <endtime>000000</endtime>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>20130122</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-127.922278</westbc>
            <eastbc>-74.013589</eastbc>
            <northbc>47.975864</northbc>
            <southbc>22.754100</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>projections</themekey>
            <themekey>IPCC</themekey>
            <themekey>SRES</themekey>
            <themekey>scenarios</themekey>
            <themekey>ecoregions</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>
      There are no limitations on the use of these raster maps. A statement of the data source when citing, copying, or reprinting USGS data or images is requested. The USGS cautions that users understand the limits of these data before proceeding with personal, academic, and/or governmental use. We also ask users to be aware of the interpretive nature of these data and how they represent a single, plausible land-use and land-cover outcome out of many plausible outcomes. Data users should read USGS Open File Report 2012-1252 and the regional LandCarbon reports (USGS Professional Papers 1787 and 1797 to become familiar with the methods used to produce the dataset.
      Zhu, Z., (editor), B. Bergamaschi, R. Bernknopf, D. Clow, D. Dye, S. Faulkner, W. Forney, R. Gleason, T. Hawbaker, J. Liu, S. Liu, S. Prisley, B. Reed, M. Reeves, M. G. Rollins, B. Sleeter, T. L. Sohl, S. Stackpoole, S. Stehman, R. Striegl, A. Wein, and Z. Zhu. 2010. A method for assessing carbon stocks, carbon sequestration, and greenhouse-gas fluxes in ecosystems of the United States under present conditions and future scenarios: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report, 2010-1144. (Also available at http://pubs.usgs.gov/sir/2010/5233)
      Zhiliang Z. (editor), M. Bouchard, D. Butman, T. Hawbaker, Z. Li, J. Liu, S. Liu, C. McDonald, R. Reker, K. Sayler, B. Sleeter, T. Sohl, S. Stackpoole, A. Wein, and Z. Zhu. 2011. Baseline and Projected Future Carbon Storage and Greenhouse-Gas Fluxes in the Great Plains Region of the United States. U.S. Geological Survey Profession Paper 1787, 28p. (Also available at http://pubs.usgs.gov/pp/1787)
      Z. Zhu and B. Reed (editors), Baseline and projected future carbon storage and greenhouse-gas fluxes in ecosystems of the Western United States: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 1797. 192 p. (Also available at http://pubs.usgs.gov/pp/1797)
    </useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
               <cntper>Shuguang (Leo) Liu</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Research Ecologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>unknown</addrtype>
               <address/>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198</postal>
               <country>US</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>605-594-6168</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>sliu@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred/>
   </idinfo>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Grid Cell</rasttype>
         <rowcount>5296</rowcount>
         <colcount>1783</colcount>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <mapproj>
               <mapprojn>Albers Conical Equal Area</mapprojn>
               <albers>
                  <stdparll>29.5</stdparll>
                  <stdparll>45.5</stdparll>
                  <longcm>-96.0</longcm>
                  <latprjo>23.0</latprjo>
                  <feast>0.0</feast>
                  <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
               </albers>
            </mapproj>
            <planci>
               <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>0.0000000037527980722984474</absres>
                  <ordres>0.0000000037527980722984474</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>1{Standard_Parallel}2 + Longitude_of_Central_Meridian + Latitude_of_Projection_Origin + False_Easting + False_Northing</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>D North American 1983</horizdn>
            <ellips>GRS 1980</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20141010</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Shuguang (Leo) Liu</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Research Ecologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>605-594-6168</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>sliu@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
