<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Western Association of Fish and Wildlife Agencies; National Sage-grouse Conservation Planning Framework Team</origin>
            <pubdate>Unpublished Material</pubdate>
            <title>Ordination of major sagebrush taxa in the Intermountain Region</title>
            <othercit>The table containing information pertaining to sagebrush species and soil temperature and soil moisture gradients can be found in Table 5.1, Chapter 5, p. 5-24, in Connelly, J. W., S. T. Knick, M. A. Schroeder, and S. J. Stiver.  2004.  Conservation assessment of Greater Sage-grouse and sagebrush habitats.  Western Association of Fish and Wildlife Agencies.  Unpublished Report.  Cheyenne, Wyoming.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://sagemap.wr.usgs.gov/FTP/regional/USGS/Fig_5.1_sgca.pdf</onlink>
            <olink>http://srfs.wr.usgs.gov/Fresc_ScienceData/fig_5_1.zip</olink>
            <olink>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/542dabf2e4b092f17defca58</olink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>Schematic displaying the major sagebrush species against soil temperature and soil moisture gradients.  It is a portion of chapter 5: Sagebrush Ecosystems: Dynamics of Primary Sagebrush Habitats in the larger document:  Conservation and Assessment of Greater sage-grouse and Sagebrush Habitat. Western Associations of Fish and Wildlife Agencies. 2004.</abstract>
         <purpose>To supply a visualization of the soil temperature and soil moisture gradients against the major sagebrush species.  Where along these two gradients do particular species of sagebrush exist.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>2004</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-123.73288</westbc>
            <eastbc>-102.269813</eastbc>
            <northbc>49.999432</northbc>
            <southbc>35.723732</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>REQUIRED: Reference to a formally registered thesaurus or a similar authoritative source of theme keywords.</themekt>
            <themekey>Ecosystems</themekey>
            <themekey>Vegetation</themekey>
            <themekey>Sagebrush</themekey>
            <themekey>Soil Gradient</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekey>Sagebrush Biome</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None.</accconst>
      <useconst>None, but the user assumes all responsibility for appropriate use of the data.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Snake River Field Station</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>970 Lusk Street</address>
               <city>Boise</city>
               <state>ID</state>
               <postal>83702</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>208 426-5200</cntvoice>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <native>Microsoft Windows 2000 Version 5.0 (Build 2195) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.0.0.535</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>NA</logic>
      <complete>complete</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Figure was adapted for use in the Sagebrush Ecosystems chapter (chp. 5) from West and Young, 2002.  Additions were made by the authors from Robertson et al. 1966 and McArthur, 1983.    Further, sagebrush ordinance along elevation, slope, salinity and precipitation gradients were determined from field samples collected throughout the biome.</procdesc>
            <procdate>20040515</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Snake River Field Station</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>970 Lusk Street</address>
               <city>Boise</city>
               <state>ID</state>
               <postal>83706</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>208-426-5204</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>208-426-5210</cntfax>
            <cntemail>tzarriel@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
      <distliab>We make every effort to provide and maintain accurate, complete, usable, and timely information on our web sites. However, some USGS data and information accessed through these pages may, of necessity, be preliminary in nature and presented prior to final review and approval by the Director of the USGS. These data and information are provided with the understanding that they are not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Users are cautioned to consider carefully the provisional nature of these data and information before using them for decisions that concern personal or public safety or the conduct of business that involves substantial monetary or operational consequences. Conclusions drawn from, or actions undertaken on the basis of, such data and information are the sole responsibility of the user.</distliab>
   </distinfo>
   <distinfo>
- <distrib>
- <cntinfo>
- <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Communications and Information Program</cntpos> 
- <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>777 NW 9th Street, Suite 400</address>
               <city>Corvallis</city>
               <state>Oregon</state>
               <postal>97300</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>541-750-1030</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a U.S. Geological Survey server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
   </distinfo>
- <metainfo>
      <metd>20111003</metd> 
- <metc>
- <cntinfo>
- <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Communications and Information Program</cntpos> 
- <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>777 NW 9th Street, Suite 400</address>
               <city>Corvallis</city>
               <state>Oregon</state>
               <postal>97330</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>541-750-1030</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20050624</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Sean Finn/Bonnie Hunt</cntper>
               <cntorg>USGS Snake River Field Station</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>GIS Specialist/Tech</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>REQUIRED: The mailing and/or physical address for the organization or individual.</addrtype>
               <city>REQUIRED: The city of the address.</city>
               <state>REQUIRED: The state or province of the address.</state>
               <postal>REQUIRED: The ZIP or other postal code of the address.</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>208-426-5212  426-2697</cntvoice>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
      <metextns>
         <onlink>http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink>
         <metprof>ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof>
      </metextns>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
