<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, Department of Interior and the
National Geophysical Data Center, NOAA</origin>
            <pubdate>2001</pubdate>
            <title>Airborne geophysical survey: West Charlotte, North Carolina</title>
            <geoform>tabular digital data</geoform>
            <onlink>http://mrdata.usgs.gov/magnetic/show-survey.php?id=3074</onlink>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, Department of the Interior, and the
National Geophysical Data Center</origin>
                  <pubdate>2001</pubdate>
                  <title>Digital flight-line aeromagnetic data sets of the
Conterminous United States, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
                     <issue>OFR 02-0361</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>Aeromagnetic data were collected along flight lines by instruments in an
aircraft that recorded magnetic-field values and locations.  This dataset
presents latitude, longitude, altitude, and magnetic-field values.</abstract>
         <purpose>Aeromagnetic surveys are used for geophysical prospecting.  Some
variations in magnetic measurements are caused by rocks that
contain significant amounts of magnetic minerals (magnetite being
the most common).  These anomalies reflect variations in the
amount and type of magnetic material and the shape and depth of
the body of rock.
Aeromagnetic anomaly maps are important tools in mapping
surficial and buried igneous rocks.  The features and patterns
of aeromagnetic anomalies can also be used to delineate details
of subsurface geology including the locations of buried faults and
the thickness of surficial sedimentary rocks.</purpose>
         <supplinf>The U.S. Geological Survey has contracted or flown numerous
airborne surveys over a long period (1950's to present).  Not
all flight-line data have been released to the public
because of lack of personnel to reformat data and service the
requests.  With the improvement in digital communication
and the ability to store and transmit large data sets, the
USGS is now able to release the flight-line data in a
common format.
A companion CD-ROM/web site has been released containing
magnetic data that were generated by digitizing analog maps.
Digital flight-line data used to create the analog maps are
unavailable.  Reference is in the Cross-Reference section of
this metadata file.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>197508</begdate>
               <enddate>197511</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>complete</progress>
         <update>none planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-82.00</westbc>
            <eastbc>-81.00</eastbc>
            <northbc>36.00</northbc>
            <southbc>35.05</southbc>
         </bounding>
         <dsgpoly>
            <dsgpolyo>
               <gring>-82.00 36.00, -81.00 36.00, -81.00 35.06,
-81.05 35.05, -81.06 35.15, -82.00 35.19,
-82.00 36.00</gring>
            </dsgpolyo>
         </dsgpoly>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>geophysical surveys</themekey>
            <themekey>aeromagnetic data</themekey>
            <themekey>airborne surveys</themekey>
            <themekey>magnetic surveys</themekey>
            <themekey>residual magnetic field</themekey>
            <themekey>total field</themekey>
            <themekey>magnetic</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>geophysics</themekey>
            <themekey>geospatial datasets</themekey>
            <themekey>magnetic field (earth)</themekey>
            <themekey>aeromagnetic surveying</themekey>
            <themekey>field monitoring stations</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>North Carolina</placekey>
            <placekey>NC</placekey>
            <placekey>West Charlotte</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Common Geographic Areas</placekt>
            <placekey>f37003 = Alexander</placekey>
            <placekey>f37011 = Avery</placekey>
            <placekey>f37023 = Burke</placekey>
            <placekey>f37027 = Caldwell</placekey>
            <placekey>f37035 = Catawba</placekey>
            <placekey>f37045 = Cleveland</placekey>
            <placekey>f37071 = Gaston</placekey>
            <placekey>f37097 = Iredell</placekey>
            <placekey>f37109 = Lincoln</placekey>
            <placekey>f37111 = McDowell</placekey>
            <placekey>f37119 = Mecklenburg</placekey>
            <placekey>f37121 = Mitchell</placekey>
            <placekey>f37149 = Polk</placekey>
            <placekey>f37161 = Rutherford</placekey>
            <placekey>f37193 = Wilkes</placekey>
            <placekey>f45021 = Cherokee</placekey>
            <placekey>f45083 = Spartanburg</placekey>
            <placekey>f45091 = York</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none.  Acknowledgement of the U.S. Geological Survey and the
National Geophysical Data Center would be appreciated
in products derived from these data.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Gravity and Magnetics Contact</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>U.S. Geological Survey
Box 25046  Mail Stop 964
Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>CO</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>303-236-1343</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>grav_mag@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://mrdata.usgs.gov/geophysics/surveys/geophysics2/NC/NC_3074.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Reduced-size image depicting the data, 675 x 620 pixels, 77,671 bytes</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <datacred>These USGS employees contributed to reformatting and archiving these data:
Viki Bankey, Carol Finn, Pat Hill, Holly Hindle,
Bob Kucks, Vicki Rystrom, Sarah Shearer
Cooperating contributors from the National Geophysical Data Center are:
Ronald Buhmann, David Dater, Susan McLean,
Stewart Racey</datacred>
      <native>These data were originally recorded on 9-track
magnetic tapes and were transferred to CD-ROM.
Data processing took place on an HP workstation
running a Windows NT operating system.  Data
were reformatted using the Geosoft, Inc., program
Oasis Montaj version 4.3.</native>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>1999</pubdate>
            <title>Digitized Aeromagnetic Datasets of the Conterminous United States,
Hawaii, and Puerto Rico</title>
            <geoform>raster digital data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>OFR 99-557</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Denver CO</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>CD-ROM or online files
Complements this publication with analog data</othercit>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/1999/ofr-99-0557/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>1978</pubdate>
            <title>Aeromagnetic map of West Charlotte, North Carolina, OFR 78-1088</title>
            <geoform>map</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>OFR 78-1088</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>map scale 1:250,000</othercit>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>The data in this file have been processed using various formulas and
methods that are not usually documented but that represent
industry standard practices for airborne data reduction.  For example,
position is listed as latitude and longitude, but these values
were derived from the raw navigation data depending on the system used.
(see notes under horizontal accuracy). Line numbers were added to
records, and unusable data at flight-line ends were discarded
(as aircraft slowed and turned around). Separate recordings were
correlated by time and assigned to the correct location.
The exact accuracies of these processing steps may not be known.
They are discussed in the sections on attribute or positional
accuracies.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>The data in this file were collected by a single contractor or group
who were responsible for collecting and processing the data.
The data from this survey were collected using the same instruments
(magnetometers, altimeters, navigational systems) throughout
the survey and were collected in a normal length of time with no long
delays between survey beginning and end.
Survey contracts specified the conditions and specifications under which
these data were collected.  Standard industry practices of the time
were followed in data collection and processing.</logic>
      <complete>Loss of data due to poor transmission, channel dropout, obvious spiking,
missing channels, and other obvious errors were replaced with the
value -9999.9, such as the radar and barom channels.
The original data did not have radar altimeter (radar) or barometric
altimeter (barom) channels.
Line 1.1 was renamed line 60, and line 55.1 was renamed line 61 in order to
make a distinction from lines 1 and 55, respectively.
Residual magnetic values were adjusted on the following lines to eliminate
obvious datum shifts within or between lines:
Line number	Shift (nT)
4		+20
9		+10
16		+15
29		+20
30		+10
48		+25
50		+18
51		+16
52		+14
53		+7
54		+5</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>Flight Path Recovery
Horizontal position of the survey aircraft used to collect
data were determined by reconciling down-looking photographs
(recorded on continuous-strip film) with topographic maps
and orthophotoquadrangle maps.  Fiducial numbers and marks,
impressed on any paper strips that were recording data or
added to magnetic tape records, were included
as a function of time to further reconcile location with
instrumentation.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
         <vertacc>
            <vertaccr>The aircraft vertical position was determined using the
navigational positioning equipment on the aircraft, which
were radar altimeter and barometric altimeter.
Radar altimeters are estimated to have an error
of 2-5% of the altitude (Richard Hansen, PRJ, Inc.,
written communication).
Barometric altimeters are quite accurate, but are
typically operated in an uncorrected mode.  The
diurnal variation in air pressure over the course of
a flight can produce a 50-100 ft error in the
barometric altimeter reading.  In addition, pressure microcells
create short-period air pressure changes equivalent
to about 10 ft under typical conditions (Richard
Hansen, PRJ, Inc., written communication).
This data set was collected at a draped survey having a
average terrain clearance of 500 ft.  Because aircraft,
especially airplanes, cannot safely maintain a constant
terrain clearance, error in vertical position is
introduced.</vertaccr>
         </vertacc>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Conversion of measured values to geographic position and
magnetic values was performed by the contractor using
industry standard practices.
Details are found under Attribute Accuracy Report,
Horizontal_Position_Accuracy_Report, and
Vertical_Position_Accuracy_Report
Unless noted, conversion processes were not reported to the USGS.
Unpublished products generated by the contractor included magnetic
tapes, a map of residual or total field magnetics, and perhaps some
written documentation.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1975</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>USGS reformatting of contractor data to standard format.
USGS personnel used the software package Oasis Montaj version 4.3 by
Geosoft, Inc., to read in the original contractor's data.
Latitude, longitude, altitude, and magnetic values were
checked for obvious errors or spikes and values of -9999.9
were given where the value could not be reasonably corrected.
Other errors in the data were not corrected.  Horizontal positions
were converted to latitude and longitude if the original values
were UTM meters.  Elevations were converted from meters to feet
(1 m = 3.2808 ft).  Information was added that was missing from the
data file but was recorded elsewhere.  The reformatted data file was
written in the format described in the section on
Entity_and_Attribute_Overview.</procdesc>
            <procdate>20010824</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>point</direct>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <latres>.0001</latres>
            <longres>.0001</longres>
            <geogunit>decimal degrees</geogunit>
         </geograph>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1927</horizdn>
            <ellips>Clarke 1866</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6,378,206.4</semiaxis>
            <denflat>294.98</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
      <vertdef>
         <altsys>
            <altdatum>National Geodetic Vertical Datum of 1929</altdatum>
            <altres>1</altres>
            <altunits>feet</altunits>
            <altenc>Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc>
         </altsys>
      </vertdef>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>record for one magnetic data point</enttypl>
            <enttypd>The set of all measurements reported for a magnetic data point
having the same spatial location.</enttypd>
            <enttypds>Standard aeromagnetic data collection procedures as written in
the contract for survey collection.</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>line_no</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>flight line number</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>often assigned by airborne survey crew</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>1</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>103</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>alphanumeric value</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>directn</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>direction of flight line, azimuth degrees
clockwise from north</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>self evident</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>270</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>degrees</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>longitud</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>longitude - geographic coordinate</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>self evident</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>-82.0206</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>-80.9695</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>decimal degrees</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>latitude</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>latitude - geographic coordinate</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>self evident</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>35.1501</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>36.0045</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>decimal degrees</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>year</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>year of data point collection</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>self evident</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>1975</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>1975</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>jul_day</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Julian day, where Jan. 1 = 1 and
Dec. 31 = 365 or 366 (leap year)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>self evident</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>232</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>308</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrvai>
               <attrva>31</attrva>
               <attrvae>Both beginning and end julian
dates were taken from dataset.</attrvae>
            </attrvai>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>fiducial</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>A fiducial number is a mark which indicates points of
simultaneity.  It is a user-defined integer used during
airborne operations to correlate recording devices (magnetometers)
with navigational records (altimeters, camera film, strip charts)
that were recorded at the same time.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sheriff, R.E., 1984, Encyclopedic dictionary of
exploration geophysics: Tulsa, OK, Society of
Exploration Geophysicists, p. 89.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>1300</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>160500</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>radar</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>radar altimetry reading, in feet
An aircraft navigational system in which short electromagnetic waves
are transmitted, and the energy scattered back by reflection
is detected.  From this measurement, the distance between the aircraft
and the ground is calculated and recorded as radar altimetry.
Values of -9999.9 indicate missing data.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sheriff, R.E., 1984, Encyclopedic dictionary of exploration geophysics:
Tulsa, OK, Society of Exploration Geophysicists, p. 89.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>-9999.9</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>-9999.9</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>barom</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>altitude above mean sea level, in feet, measured using the
barometer that is part of the aircraft navigation system
Values of -9999.9 indicate missing data.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>self evident</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>-9999.9</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>-9999.9</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>feet</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>totmag</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Raw magnetic value with base magnetometer corrections applied.
Because the magnetic field of the earth varies diurnally,
a stationary base magnetometer is maintained on the ground
during airborne surveying.  The base magnetometer records
changes in the magnetic field (in nanoTeslas) as a function
of time.  The magnetic changes may have an amplitude of 20
to 50 nanoTeslas.  If changes are more severe, as would
occur from a magnetic storm, surveying is discontinued or
the data recorded are not used.
Diurnal variations are then removed from the airborne magnetic
data based on the common time.
Values of -9999.9 indicate missing data.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>see: Nettleton, L.L., 1971, Elementary Gravity and Magnetics for
Geologists and Seismologists: Society of Exploration Geophysicists
Monograph Series No. 1, p. 83-87.
A description of magnetometers and how they measure
the total magnetic field can be found in:
Dobrin, M.B., 1976, Introduction to Geophysical
Prospecting: New York, McGraw-Hill Book Company,
p. 505-517.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>53795.61</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>55681.55</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>nanoTeslas</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrvai>
               <attrva>2</attrva>
               <attrvae>The airborne magnetometer is accurate to about 1 nanoTesla,
and the base magnetometer has the same accuracy.  The accuracy
of the base-corrected airborne value therefore is near 2 nanoTeslas
or better.</attrvae>
            </attrvai>
            <attrmfrq>The magnetometer has a recharging interval of 0.5
seconds.  The data were recorded at unknown intervals.</attrmfrq>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>resmag</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>residual magnetic value
The total magnetic value minus a geomagnetic reference field (GRF),
which is a long-wavelength regional magnetic field.  The most commonly
used reference field is determined from a model developed by the
International Association of Geomagnetism and Aeronomy (IAGA).  The
International Geomagnetic Reference Field (IGRF), is a predictive model
adopted at the beginning of a model period
(e.g. in 1989 for 1990-1995).  After the model period, a revised
definitive model is adopted, the DGRF. This is the preferred model to
use for removing regional magnetic fields.
Temporal variations cannot be completely predicted, thus error arises
in the application of the IGRF reductions.  These errors cannot be
evaluated until the release of the DGRF, a minimum of five years after
the IGRF release.  This field is issued to best describe the
configuration of the earth's past magnetic field.
Accuracy of the DGRF calculations is dependent on the quality of the
survey data and sensitive to changes in air pressure.  Through
processing experimentation and experience, USGS personnel found that
significant flight altitude changes produced small changes (0.01-0.03
nT) in DGRF values regardless of the altitude source used (e.g. radar
altimeter, barometric altimeter).  If radar altimeter data are
complete, a terrain channel was calculated using Oasis Montaj DAP
(Data Access Protocol), USGS 1:250,000 terrain data, or USGS 15 second
terrain data.  DAP is the easiest to use but suffers from inconvenient
dummy values at sea level.  In such cases, 15 second terrain data was
used.
For this survey, the field removed was the DGRF 1975 calculated using
the date and DAP terrain data added to an altitude datum of 152 meters
(500 feet).
Values of -9999.9 indicate missing data.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Nettleton, L.L., 1971, Elementary Gravity and Magnetics for
Geologists and Seismologists: Society of Exploration Geophysicists
Monograph Series No. 1, p. 83-87.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>-785.25</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>1122.48</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>nanoTeslas</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrvai>
               <attrva>2</attrva>
               <attrvae>The Geomagnetic Reference Field that was subtracted from
the total magnetic value is based on a model, which was
updated to the date of the survey.  New models are
available at five year intervals.  These models have
varying degrees of accuracy in determining the local
reference field.</attrvae>
            </attrvai>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <overview>
         <eaover>Airborne survey specifications
These items are constant for the entire survey
Project number: 3074
Project name: West Charlotte, North Carolina
Survey flown by: Airmag Surveys, Inc.
Survey compiled by: LKB Resources, Inc.
Survey flown for: U.S. Geological Survey
Approx. no. of line miles: 3440
Survey height: 500 ft
Altitude method: Draped over terrain
Flight-line spacing: 1 mi
Flight-line direction: E-W
Aircraft used: modified twin engine Cessna 320A
Airport - arrival: unknown
Airport - departure: unknown
Magnetometer used: Airmag MK-IV or modified ASQ-8 fluxgate system
Sensor tow distance: unknown</eaover>
         <eadetcit>Nettleton, L.L., 1971, Elementary Gravity and Magnetics for
Geologists and Seismologists: Society of Exploration Geophysicists
Monograph Series No. 1, p. 83-87.
Dobrin, M.B., 1976, Introduction to Geophysical
Prospecting: New York, McGraw-Hill Book Company,
p. 505-517.</eadetcit>
      </overview>
      <overview>
         <eaover>Each record contains the following 11 attributes:
No abbrev.name contents
1  line_no     flight line number
2  directn     flight line direction, azimuth degrees from north
(integer)
3  longitud    longitude (decimal degrees)
4  latitude    latitude (decimal degrees)
5  year        year flown (integer)
6  jul_day     Julian day flown (integer)
7  fiducial    fiducial number (integer)
8  radar       radar altimeter reading above ground (feet)
9  barom       altitude above mean sea level (feet)
10 totmag      corrected magnetic value (nT)
11 resmag      residual magnetic value (nT)</eaover>
         <eadetcit>Nettleton, L.L., 1971, Elementary Gravity and Magnetics for
Geologists and Seismologists: Society of Exploration Geophysicists
Monograph Series No. 1, p. 83-87.
Dobrin, M.B., 1976, Introduction to Geophysical
Prospecting: New York, McGraw-Hill Book Company,
p. 505-517.</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>CD-ROM distributor: USGS Information Services</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Box 25286, Building 810
Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>CO</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>303-202-4700
or 1-888-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>www.usgs.gov/pubprod</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>USGS Open-File Report OFR 02-0361</resdesc>
      <distliab>Although all data published on this CD-ROM have been used by the USGS,
no warranty, expressed or implied, is made by the USGS as to the
accuracy of the data and related materials.  The act of distribution
shall not constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is
assumed by the USGS in the use of these data or related materials.
Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes
only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ASCII</formname>
               <formcont>Each line contains data in the following format,
beginning with line 1(no header included):
line_no       I5
directn       I4
longitud      F11.4
latitude      F9.4
year          I5
jul_day       I4
fiducial      I7
radar         F8.1
barom         F8.1
totmag        F9.2
resmag        F9.2, 1X</formcont>
               <filedec>gunzip</filedec>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <offoptn>
                  <offmedia>CD-ROM</offmedia>
                  <recfmt>ISO 9660</recfmt>
               </offoptn>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>CD-ROM prices are subject to change. Please call or see
http://mapping.usgs.gov/esic/prices/</fees>
         <ordering>Detailed instructions can be found at
www.usgs.gov/pubprod</ordering>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Web site administration: U.S Geological Survey
Central Publications Group</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Central Publications Group
USGS MS 902, Box 25046 DFC</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>CO</state>
               <postal>80225-0046</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>303-236-5486</cntvoice>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>USGS Open-File Report OFR 02-0361</resdesc>
      <distliab>Although all data published on this CD-ROM have been used by the USGS,
no warranty, expressed or implied, is made by the USGS as to the
accuracy of the data and related materials.  The act of distribution
shall not constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is
assumed by the USGS in the use of these data or related materials.
Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes
only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ASCII</formname>
               <formvern>3.1</formvern>
               <formspec>Each line contains data in the following format,
beginning with line 1 (no header included):
line_no       I5
directn       I4
longitud      F11.4
latitude      F9.4
year          I5
jul_day       I4
fiducial      I7
radar         F8.1
barom         F8.1
totmag        F9.2
resmag        F9.2, 1X</formspec>
               <filedec>gunzip</filedec>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/ofr-02-361/</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <oncomp>Hewlett Packard 9000/K220
UNIX server running HPUX 11.00</oncomp>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Peter N Schweitzer</cntper>
               <cntorg>USGS Eastern Mineral and Environmental Resources Science Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Geologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>12201 Sunrise Valley Drive</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192-0002</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>703-648-6533</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>703-648-6252</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pschweitzer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>NC_3074_meta.txt</resdesc>
      <distliab>This dataset was prepared by an agency of the United States
Government.  Neither the United States Government nor any agency
thereof, nor any of their employees, make any warranty, expressed or
implied, or assumes any legal liability or responsibility for the
accuracy, completeness,  or usefulness of any information, apparatus,
product, or process disclosed in this report, or represents that its
use would not infringe privately owned rights.  Reference therein to
any specific commercial product, process, or service by trade name,
trademark, manufacturer, or otherwise does not necessarily constitute
or imply its endorsement, recommendation, or favoring by the United
States Government or any agency thereof.  Any views and opinions of
authors expressed herein do not necessarily state or reflect those of
the United States Government or any agency thereof.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>CSV</formname>
               <formcont>Flight-line airborne magnetic anomaly measurements</formcont>
               <filedec>unzip</filedec>
               <transize>1.096435546875</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://mrdata.usgs.gov/geophysics/surveys/geophysics2/NC/NC_3074.ZIP</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20141205</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Gravity and Magnetics contact</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>U.S. Geological Survey
Box 25046 Mail Stop 964
Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>CO</state>
               <postal>80225-0046</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>303-236-1343</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>grav_mag@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
