<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, Department of Interior and the
National Geophysical Data Center, NOAA</origin>
            <pubdate>2012</pubdate>
            <title>Airborne geophysical survey: Mauna Loa Northeast Rift, Hawaii</title>
            <geoform>tabular digital data</geoform>
            <onlink>http://mrdata.usgs.gov/magnetic/show-survey.php?id=1069</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>Aeromagnetic data were collected along flight lines by instruments in an
aircraft that recorded magnetic-field values and locations.  This dataset
presents latitude, longitude, altitude, and magnetic-field values.</abstract>
         <purpose>Aeromagnetic surveys are used for geophysical prospecting.  Some variations in
magnetic measurements are caused by rocks that contain significant amounts of
magnetic minerals (magnetite being the most common).  These anomalies reflect
variations in the amount and type of magnetic material and the shape and depth
of the body of rock. The features and patterns of aeromagnetic anomalies can
also be used to delineate details of subsurface geology including the locations
of buried faults and the thickness of surficial sedimentary rocks.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>197803</begdate>
               <enddate>197803</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>complete</progress>
         <update>none planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-155.62</westbc>
            <eastbc>-155.27</eastbc>
            <northbc>19.68</northbc>
            <southbc>19.37</southbc>
         </bounding>
         <dsgpoly>
            <dsgpolyo>
               <gring>-155.62 19.68, -155.27 19.68, -155.27 19.37,
-155.62 19.37, -155.62 19.68</gring>
            </dsgpolyo>
         </dsgpoly>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>geophysical surveys</themekey>
            <themekey>aeromagnetic data</themekey>
            <themekey>airborne surveys</themekey>
            <themekey>magnetic surveys</themekey>
            <themekey>residual magnetic field</themekey>
            <themekey>total field</themekey>
            <themekey>magnetic</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>geophysics</themekey>
            <themekey>geospatial datasets</themekey>
            <themekey>magnetic field (earth)</themekey>
            <themekey>aeromagnetic surveying</themekey>
            <themekey>field monitoring stations</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>Hawaii</placekey>
            <placekey>HI</placekey>
            <placekey>Mauna Loa Rift</placekey>
            <placekey>Mauna Loa</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Common Geographic Areas</placekt>
            <placekey>f15001 = Hawaii</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none.  Acknowledgement of the U.S. Geological Survey and the
National Geophysical Data Center would be appreciated
in products derived from these data.</useconst>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://mrdata.usgs.gov/geophysics/surveys/geophysics2/HI/HI_1069.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Reduced-size image depicting the data, 714 x 682 pixels, 171,590 bytes</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <datacred>These USGS employees contributed to reformatting and archiving these data:
Viki Bankey, David Daniels, Carol Finn, Pat Hill, Holly Hindle,
Bob Kucks, Vicki Rystrom, Sarah Shearer
Cooperating contributors from the National Geophysical Data Center are:
Ronald Buhmann, David Dater, Susan McLean, Stewart Racey</datacred>
      <native>These data were originally recorded on 9-track magnetic tapes and
were transferred to CD-ROM.
Data processing took place on an HP workstation and a Dell personal
computer running a Windows NT or XP operating system.  Data were
reformatted using the Geosoft, Inc., Oasis Montaj program.</native>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>1986</pubdate>
            <title>Aeromagnetic map of the Rift systems of Kilauea and
Mauna Loa volcanoes, Island of Hawaii, Hawaii</title>
            <geoform>map</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Miscellaneous Field Study</sername>
               <issue>MF-1845A</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>Flanigan, V.J. and others
map scale 1:100,000</othercit>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>The data in this file have been processed using various formulas and
methods that are not usually documented but that represent industry
standard practices for airborne data reduction.  For example, position
is listed as latitude and longitude, but these values were derived
from the raw navigation data depending on the system used.  (see notes
under horizontal accuracy). Line numbers were added to records, and
unusable data at flight-line ends were discarded (as aircraft slowed
and turned around). Separate recordings were correlated by time and
assigned to the correct location.
The exact accuracies of these processing steps may not be known.  They
are discussed in the sections on attribute or positional accuracies.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>The data in this file were collected by a single contractor or group
who were responsible for collecting and processing the data.
The data from this survey were collected using the same instruments
(magnetometers, altimeters, navigational systems) throughout the survey
and were collected in a normal length of time with no long delays
between survey beginning and end.
Survey layouts specified the conditions and specifications under which
these data were collected.  Standard industry practices of the time
were followed in data collection and processing.</logic>
      <complete>Loss of data due to poor transmission, channel dropout, obvious spiking,
missing channels, and other obvious errors were replaced with the value
-9999.9, such as in the radar and barom channels. Sometimes channels were
added and filled with dummy values (-9999.9) to comply with the
established format.  Some records that had no usable data were deleted.
The database did not have flight line direction (directn), year (year),
Julian day (day), fiducial (fiducial), or radar altimeter (radar)
channels. A dummy value of -1 was used in the directn channel in order to
conform to the established template.
The lines were renumbered (1-31) during USGS processing in order to conform
to the established template.
The values in the fiducial channel were generated based on latitude, using
Oasis montaj.
The values in the residual magnetics (resmag) channel were calculated based
on the following formula:  resmag=total magnetics (totmag) - DGRF
It was found that the survey was flown from March-April, 1978.  The first
of March has been assigned as the date of the survey, but this does not
reflect the actual date that each line was flown.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>Flight Path Recovery
Horizontal positions of the survey aircraft used to collect data were
determined by reconciling down-looking photographs (recorded on
continuous-strip film) with topographic maps and orthophotoquadrangle
maps.  Fiducial numbers and marks, impressed on any paper strips that
were recording data or added to magnetic tape records, were included
as a function of time to further reconcile location with instrumentation.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
         <vertacc>
            <vertaccr>The aircraft vertical position was determined using the navigational
positioning equipment on the aircraft, which were radar altimeter
and barometric altimeter.
Radar altimeters are estimated to have an error of 2-5% of the
altitude (Richard Hansen, PRJ, Inc., written communication).
Barometric altimeters are quite accurate, but are typically operated
in an uncorrected mode.  The diurnal variation in air pressure over
the course of a flight can produce a 50-100 ft error in the barometric
altimeter reading.  In addition, pressure microcells create short-
period air pressure changes equivalent to about 10 ft. under typical
conditions (Richard Hansen, PRJ, Inc., written communication)
This data set was collected as a draped survey having an average
terrain clearance of 300 ft.  Because aircraft, especially airplanes,
cannot safely maintain a constant terrain clearance, error in vertical
position is introduced.</vertaccr>
         </vertacc>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Conversion of measured values to geographic position and magnetic
values was performed by the contractor using industry standard
practices.
Details are found under Horizontal_Position_Accuracy_Report, and
Vertical_Position_Accuracy_Report
Unless noted, conversion processes were not reported. Unpublished
products generated by USGS included magnetic tapes, a map of residual
or total field magnetics, and perhaps some written documentation.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1978</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>USGS reformatting of data to standard format.
USGS personnel used the software package Oasis Montaj by
Geosoft, Inc., to read in the original contractor's data.
Latitude, longitude, altitude, and magnetic values were checked
for obvious errors or spikes and values of -9999.9 were given
where the value could not be reasonably corrected. Other errors
in the data were not corrected.  Horizontal positions were
converted to latitude and longitude if the original values were
UTM meters.  Elevations were converted from meters to feet
(1 m = 3.2808 ft).
Often the digital data did not contain date information and only the
month and year flown or just a starting date were stated in the
written documentation.  In these cases, the first day of the month
or the date the survey began was used as the Julian date and added
to the digital data.
Other information was added that was missing from the data file
but was recorded elsewhere.  The reformatted data were written in
the format described in the section on Digital_Transfer_Information.
Entity_and_Attribute_Overview.</procdesc>
            <procdate>200208</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>point</direct>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <latres>0.0001</latres>
            <longres>0.0001</longres>
            <geogunit>decimal degrees</geogunit>
         </geograph>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1927</horizdn>
            <ellips>Clarke 1866</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6,378,206.4</semiaxis>
            <denflat>294.98</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
      <vertdef>
         <altsys>
            <altdatum>National Geodetic Vertical Datum of 1929</altdatum>
            <altres>1</altres>
            <altunits>feet</altunits>
            <altenc>Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc>
         </altsys>
      </vertdef>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <overview>
         <eaover>Airborne survey specifications
These items are constant for the entire survey
Project number: 1069
Project name: Mauna Loa Northeast Rift, Hawaii
Survey flown by: U.S. Geological Survey
Survey flown for: U.S. Geological Survey
Approx. no. of line miles: 255
Survey height: 300 ft
Altitude method: Draped over terrain
Flight-line spacing: 1 mi
Flight-line direction: N14W
Aircraft used: Fairchild Porter PC 6/C-H2
Airport - arrival: Hilo, HI
Airport - departure: Hilo, HI
Sensor tow distance: unknown
Magnetometer used: 6-803
Data recording interval: 1 second
Regional field removed: no field was removed from original data</eaover>
         <eadetcit>Nettleton, L.L., 1971, Elementary Gravity and Magnetics for
Geologists and Seismologists: Society of Exploration Geophysicists
Monograph Series No. 1.
Dobrin, M.B., 1976, Introduction to Geophysical Prospecting:
New York, McGraw-Hill Book Company,
Sheriff, R.E., 1984, Encyclopedic dictionary of exploration
geophysics: Tulsa, OK, Society of Exploration Geophysicists.</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Web site administration: U.S Geological Survey
Publishing Service Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Publishing Service Center
USGS MS 902, Box 25046 DFC</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>CO</state>
               <postal>80225-0046</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>303-236-5486</cntvoice>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although all data published on this web site have been used by the USGS,
no warranty, expressed or implied, is made by the USGS as to the
accuracy of the data and related materials.  The act of distribution
shall not constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is
assumed by the USGS in the use of these data or related materials.
Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes
only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ASCII</formname>
               <formvern>4.1</formvern>
               <formspec>Each line contains data in the following format,
beginning with line 1 (no header included):
line_no       I5          flight line number
directn       I4          flight line direction, azimuth degrees
from north
longitud      F11.4       longitude (decimal degrees)
latitude      F9.4        latitude (decimal degrees)
year          I5          year flown
jul_day       I4          Julian day flown
fiducial      I7          fiducial number
radar         F8.1        radar altitude above ground (feet)
barom         F8.1        barometric altitude above mean sea
level (feet)
totmag        F9.2        corrected total field magnetic value (nT)
resmag        F9.2, 1X    residual magnetic value (nT)</formspec>
               <filedec>gunzip</filedec>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://crustal.usgs.gov/geophysics/index.html  for link to report</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Peter N Schweitzer</cntper>
               <cntorg>USGS Eastern Mineral and Environmental Resources Science Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Geologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>12201 Sunrise Valley Drive</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192-0002</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>703-648-6533</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>703-648-6252</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pschweitzer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>HI_1069_meta.txt</resdesc>
      <distliab>This dataset was prepared by an agency of the United States
Government.  Neither the United States Government nor any agency
thereof, nor any of their employees, make any warranty, expressed or
implied, or assumes any legal liability or responsibility for the
accuracy, completeness,  or usefulness of any information, apparatus,
product, or process disclosed in this report, or represents that its
use would not infringe privately owned rights.  Reference therein to
any specific commercial product, process, or service by trade name,
trademark, manufacturer, or otherwise does not necessarily constitute
or imply its endorsement, recommendation, or favoring by the United
States Government or any agency thereof.  Any views and opinions of
authors expressed herein do not necessarily state or reflect those of
the United States Government or any agency thereof.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>CSV</formname>
               <formcont>Flight-line airborne magnetic anomaly measurements</formcont>
               <filedec>unzip</filedec>
               <transize>0.20583820343018</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://mrdata.usgs.gov/geophysics/surveys/geophysics2/HI/HI_1069.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20141205</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Crustal Geophysics and Geochemistry Science Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Magnetic and Gravity Information
U.S. Geological Survey
Box 25046 Mail Stop 964
Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>CO</state>
               <postal>80225-0046</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>303-236-5652</cntvoice>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
