<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) </origin>
            <pubdate>20150415</pubdate>
            <title>Advanced Solid-State Array Spectrometer</title>
            <geoform>hyperspectral, multiangle, airborne remote sensing </geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Sioux Falls, South Dakota</pubplace>
               <publish>USGS Earth Resources Observations and Science Center (EROS)</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The Advanced Solid-State Array Spectroradiometer (ASAS) data collection contains data collected by the ASAS sensor flown aboard NASA aircraft.  A fundamental use of ASAS data is to characterize and understand the directional variability in solar energy scattered by various land surface cover types (e.g.,crops, forests, prairie grass, snow, or bare soil).  The sensor's Bidirectional Reflectance Distribution Function determines the variation in the reflectance of a surface as a function of both the view zenith angle and solar illumination angle. 

The ASAS sensor is a hyperspectral, multiangle, airborne remote sensing instrument maintained and operated by the Laboratory for Terrestrial Physics at NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Maryland. The ASAS instrument is mounted on the underside of either NASA C-130 or NASA P-3 aircraft and is capable of off-nadir pointing from approximately 70 degrees forward to 55 degrees aft along the direction of flight.  The aircraft is flown at an altitude of 5000 - 6000 meters (approximately 16,000 - 20,000 ft.). 

Data in the ASAS collection primarily cover areas over the continental United States, but some ASAS data are also available over areas in Canada and western Africa.  The ASAS data were collected between 1988 and 1994.  
</abstract>
         <purpose>Some applications of ASAS data include validating forest canopy reflectance models, estimating biophysical parameters used in forest ecosystem models, deriving vegetation algorithms, and retrieving information on atmospheric properties.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Ground Condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>As Needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-123.9</westbc>
            <eastbc>2.7</eastbc>
            <northbc>48.8</northbc>
            <southbc>13.2</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>Image Map</themekey>
            <themekey>imagery</themekey>
            <themekey>EROS</themekey>
            <themekey>US Geological Survey</themekey>
            <themekey>USGS</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>Any downloading and use of these data signifies a user's agreement to comprehension and compliance of the USGS Standard Disclaimer.  Insure all portions of metadata are read and clearly understood before using these data in order to protect both user and USGS interests.</accconst>
      <useconst> There is no guarantee of warranty concerning the accuracy of these data.  Users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since the data was collected and that some parts of these data may no longer represent actual surface conditions.  Users should not use these data for critical applications without a full awareness of their limitations.  Acknowledgement of the originating agencies would be appreciated in products derived from these data.  Any user who modifies the data set is obligated to describe the types of modifications they perform.  User specifically agrees not to misrepresent the data set, nor to imply that changes made were approved or endorsed by the U.S. Geological Survey.  Please refer to http://www.usgs.gov/privacy.html for the USGS disclaimer.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <secinfo>
         <secsys>none</secsys>
         <secclass>unclassified</secclass>
         <sechandl>none</sechandl>
      </secinfo>
      <native>Oracle</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>The identification of features is provided by the distinct electromagnetic energy it emits, reflects, or otherwise transmits.  This is called the spectral signature.  Other signatures such as tone (lightness or darkness), texture (surface roughness or smoothness), pattern, shadow, shape, and size are as important.  </attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>None</logic>
      <complete>None</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>This  image collection was produced under strict military guidelines and initially used to produce maps and charts, providing stereo-optical coverage of selected areas, for the U.S. Department of Defense. </procdesc>
            <procdate>19940325</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
                     <city>Sioux Falls</city>
                     <state>SD</state>
                     <postal>57198-0001</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
                  <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
      <cloud>Unknown</cloud>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>raster</direct>
   </spdoinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a 
computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty 
expressed or implied is made by the USGS regarding the use 
of the data on any other system, nor does the act of distribution 
constitute any such warranty.  </distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>CAL</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>Typically, all data available from USGS/EROS are downloadable at no cost to the user.</fees>
         <ordering>Consult the data sets product page for specific information.</ordering>
         <turnarnd>A majority of the data are available for immediate downloading.  Specific data processing may take 24 to 48 hours and film scanning service requests involving payment to USGS can require 3 - 4 weeks upon successful payment of the request.</turnarnd>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>_</custom>
      <techpreq>Adequate computer capability is the only technical prerequisite for viewing data in digital form. </techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150415</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998, Version 2</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
