<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>USGS Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</origin>
            <pubdate>20150423</pubdate>
            <title>Earth Observing One - Advanced Land Imager (2001 - present)</title>
            <geoform>Remote-sensing image</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Sioux Falls, SD  USA</pubplace>
               <publish>USGS Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The Earth Observing-1(EO-1)satellite was launched on November 21, 2000 by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA)as a one-year technology demonstration mission to evaluate the performance of advanced capabilities for future space missions.  The EO-1 mission validated highly integrated multispectral data from the Advanced Land Imager (ALI) sensor and hyperspectral imaging data from the Hyperion sensor. After the initial technology mission was accomplished, NASA and the USGS agreed to continue the EO-1 program due to high interest in the specialized data from scientific communities. EO-1 Data products consist of imagery collected during the original one-year mission, as well as more recent Data Acquisition Requests (DARs) from the EO-1 Extended Mission. EO-1 scenes are processed to Level 1Gst (L1Gst) and images with adequate ground control points are processed to Level 1T (L1T). L1Gst and L1T products are provided in GeoTIFF format.  Scenes that have  been processed to L1T are also available as Full Resolution Browse and GIS Ready Bundle products in  JPEG format.  Level 1R (L1R) products in HDF format are only available for Hyperion data. </abstract>
         <purpose>The ALI sensor provides image data from ten spectral bands. 
The instrument operates in a pushbroom fashion, with a spatial resolution of 30 meters for the multispectral bands and 10 meters for the panchromatic band. ALI has a scene width of 37 kilometers and a standard length of 42 kilometers with an optional increased length of 185 kilometers. Additional information is available at http://eo1.usgs.gov, and http://eo1.gsfc.nasa.gov.</purpose>
         <supplinf>Data Acquisition Requests (DARS) must be submitted to request an image acquisition for a specific area of interest (http://eo1.usgs.gov/dar/instructions). EO-1 does not acquire data continuously and its sensors are only activated to collect specific scenes upon request. Although the ALI and Hyperion instruments continues to collect data for the extended mission, recently acquired scenes may not align directly with the WRS-2 path and row due to the degradation of the EO-1 orbit as the satellite draws closer to end of mission.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-180</westbc>
            <eastbc>180</eastbc>
            <northbc>83.1</northbc>
            <southbc>-83.9</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>NASA</themekey>
            <themekey>Landsat</themekey>
            <themekey>Imagery</themekey>
            <themekey>EO-1</themekey>
            <themekey>LDCM</themekey>
            <themekey>Land Surface</themekey>
            <themekey>Advanced Land Imager</themekey>
            <themekey>USGS</themekey>
            <themekey>Radiance</themekey>
            <themekey>Photography</themekey>
            <themekey>Earth Science</themekey>
            <themekey>Landforms</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>Any downloading and use of these data signifies a user's agreement to comprehension and compliance of the USGS Standard Disclaimer.  Insure all portions of metadata are read and clearly understood before using these data in order to protect both user and USGS interests.</accconst>
      <useconst> There is no guarantee of warranty concerning the accuracy of these data.  Users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since the data was collected and that some parts of these data may no longer represent actual surface conditions.  Users should not use these data for critical applications without a full awareness of their limitations.  Acknowledgement of the originating agencies would be appreciated in products derived from these data.  Any user who modifies the data set is obligated to describe the types of modifications they perform.  User specifically agrees not to misrepresent the data set, nor to imply that changes made were approved or endorsed by the U.S. Geological Survey.  Please refer to http://www.usgs.gov/privacy.html for the USGS disclaimer. </useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <secinfo>
         <secsys>none</secsys>
         <secclass>unclassified</secclass>
         <sechandl>none</sechandl>
      </secinfo>
      <native>Oracle</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>The identification of features is provided by the distinct electromagnetic energy it emits, reflects, or otherwise transmits.  This is called the spectral signature.  Other signatures such as tone (lightness or darkness), texture (surface roughness or smoothness), pattern, shadow, shape, and size are as important. 
</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Unknown</logic>
      <complete>See  Data Dictionary at: http://eo1.usgs.gov/</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Information about process levels are available at https://lta.cr.usgs.gov/ALI</procdesc>
            <procdate>20150421</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
                     <city>Sioux Falls</city>
                     <state>SD</state>
                     <postal>57198-0001</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
                  <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
      <cloud>Unknown</cloud>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
   </spdoinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the USGS, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the USGS regarding the use of the data on any other system, nor does the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. </distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Geographic Tagged Image File Format (GeoTIFF) or JPEG</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov and http://glovis.usgs.gov</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Tagged Image File Format (GeoTIFF) or JPEG</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov and http://glovis.usgs.gov</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>Typically, all data available from USGS/EROS are downloadable at no cost to the user.  There are some cases when a service fee is required to convert the analog film record to a digital file.</fees>
         <ordering>A Data Acquisition Request (DAR) must be submitted to collect an image for a specific area of interest (http://eo1.usgs.gov/dar/form).</ordering>
         <turnarnd>A majority of the data are available for immediate downloading. Specific data processing may take 24 to 48 hours and film scanning service requests involving payment to the USGS can required 3 to 4 weeks upon successful payment of the request.</turnarnd>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>_</custom>
      <techpreq>Adequate computer capability is the only technical prerequisite for viewing data in digital form.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150423</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
