<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) Earth Resources Observation and Science  (EROS) Center</origin>
            <pubdate>20150415</pubdate>
            <title>AVHRR-1K Global Land 10-Day Composites - 1992</title>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Sioux Falls, South Dakota, USA</pubplace>
               <publish>U. S. Geological Survey (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center 
</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov
http://glovis.usgs.gov</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The global land 1-km data set project represents an international effort to acquire, archive, process, and distribute 1-km AVHRR data of the entire global land surface in order to meet the needs of the international science community. A network of 29 high resolution picture transmission (HRPT) stations, along with data recorded by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), acquired daily global land coverage from 1 April, 1992 through  September 30, 1993, with the project subsequently extended through 1996.  The six major participants (NOAA, ESA, USGS, NASA, CSIRO, and SMC) coordinate HRPT receiving stations to acquire and compile the data set. NOAA coordinates two HRPT receiving stations, Gilmore Creek, Alaska and Wallops Island, Virginia, and schedules the satellite's recorders to obtain local area coverage (LAC) AVHRR 1-km data over areas not covered by the other HRPT receiving stations. 

This collection of over 40,000 AVHRR images has been archived and made available for distribution by the United States Geological Survey, EROS Center and the European Space Agency. 
 </abstract>
         <purpose>To acquire new images of the Earth</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>Completed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-180</westbc>
            <eastbc>180</eastbc>
            <northbc>90</northbc>
            <southbc>-90</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>Global</themekey>
            <themekey>NOAA POES</themekey>
            <themekey>HRPT</themekey>
            <themekey>LAC</themekey>
            <themekey>imagery</themekey>
            <themekey>Level 1B</themekey>
            <themekey>AVHRR</themekey>
            <themekey>USGS</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>imageryBaseMapsEarthCover</themekey>
            <themekey>010</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>Any downloading and use of these data signifies a user's agreement to comprehension and compliance of the USGS Standard Disclaimer.  Insure all portions of metadata are read and clearly understood before using these data in order to protect both user and USGS interests.</accconst>
      <useconst>There is no guarantee of warranty concerning the accuracy of the data.  Users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since this data set was collected and that some parts of this data may no longer represent actual surface conditions.  Users should not use this data for critical applications without a full awareness of its limitations.  Acknowledgement of the originating agencies would be appreciated in products derived from these data.  Any user who modifies the data is obligated to describe the types of modifications they perform.  User specifically agrees not to misrepresent the data, nor to imply that changes made were approved or endorsed by the U.S. Geological Survey.  Please refer to http://www.usgs.gov/privacy.html for the USGS disclaimer.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <secinfo>
         <secsys>none</secsys>
         <secclass>unclassified</secclass>
         <sechandl>none</sechandl>
      </secinfo>
      <native>Oracle</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>The identification of features is provided by the distinct electromagnetic energy it emits, reflects, or otherwise transmits.  This is called the spectral signature.  Other signatures such as tone (lightness or darkness), texture (surface roughness or smoothness), pattern, shadow, shape, and size are as important. </attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>None</logic>
      <complete>None</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The objective of this collection effort is to provide opportunities for studying and monitoring vegetation conditions in ecosystems including forests, tundra and grasslands with applications that include agricultural assessment, land cover mapping and production of large-area image maps.</procdesc>
            <procdate>19960521</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
                     <city>Sioux Falls</city>
                     <state>SD</state>
                     <postal>57198-0001</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
                  <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
      <cloud>Unknown</cloud>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
   </spdoinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty,  expressed or implied, is made by the USGS regarding the use of the data on any other system, nor does the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  </distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>TIFF and BIL</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://glovis.usgs.gov</networkr>
                        <networkr>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>Typically, all data available from USGS/EROS are downloadable at no cost to the user. There are some cases when a service fee is required to convert the analog film record to a digital file.</fees>
         <ordering>Consult the data sets product page for specific information.</ordering>
         <turnarnd>A majority of the data are available for immediate downloading.  Specific data processing may take 24 to 48 hours and film scanning service requests involving payment to USGS can require 3 - 4 weeks upon successful payment of the request.</turnarnd>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>_</custom>
      <techpreq>Adequate computer capability is the only technical prerequisite for viewing data in digital form.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150415</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998, Version 2</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
