<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>USGS Earth Resources Observation &amp; Science (EROS) Center</origin>
            <pubdate>20150415</pubdate>
            <title>Declassified Satellite Imagery - 2 (2002)</title>
            <geoform>Photograph and/or Digital Image</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Sioux Falls, South Dakota, USA</pubplace>
               <publish>USGS Earth Resources Observation &amp; Science (EROS) Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>Keyhole (KH) satellite systems KH-7 and KH-9 acquired photographs of the Earth's surface with a telescopic camera system and transported the exposed film through the use of recovery capsules. The capsules or buckets were de-orbited and retrieved by aircraft while the capsules parachuted to earth. The exposed film was developed and the images were analyzed for a range of military applications.

The KH-7 surveillance system was a high resolution imaging system that was operational from July 1963 to June 1967. Approximately 18,000 black-and-white images and 230 color images are available from the 38 missions flown during this program. Key features for this program were larger area of coverage and improved ground resolution. The cameras acquired imagery in continuous lengthwise sweeps of the terrain. KH-7 images are 9 inches wide, vary in length from 4 inches to 500 feet long, and have a resolution of 2 to 4 feet.

The KH-9 mapping program was operational from March 1973 to October 1980 and was designed to support mapping requirements and exact positioning of geographical points for the military. This was accomplished by using image overlap for stereo coverage and by using a camera system with a reseau grid to correct image distortion. The KH-9 framing cameras produced 9 x 18 inch imagery at a resolution of 20-30 feet. Approximately 29,000 mapping images were acquired from 12 missions.

The images have variable scales and quality.  Cloud cover is common.  The digital products are produced from a duplicate negative film source.  More than 40 percent of the imagery contains significant cloud cover.  The use of browse imagery gives the user the opportunity to review a reduced resolution image to determine if the area of interest is covered and to check for cloud cover.  The original film sources are maintained by the (http://www.nara.gov) National Archives and Records Administration (NARA).  </abstract>
         <purpose>Declassified satellite images provide an important worldwide record of land-surface change. With the success of the first release of classified satellite photography in 1995, images from U.S. military intelligence satellites KH-7 and KH-9 were declassified in accordance with Executive Order 12951 in 2002. The data were originally used for cartographic information and reconnaissance for U.S. intelligence agencies. Since the images could be of historical value for global change research and were no longer critical to national security, the collection was made available to the public.

</purpose>
         <supplinf>Corner coordinate data is a critical component of the index information. Accuracy in locating corner coordinates varies according to how coordinates were derived and according to the accuracy of information used for the derivation. As a general rule, metadata corner points have errors less than 10 miles from their actual ground positions.  After a search of the metadata, the user should inspect the browse image and its immediate neighbors in the image series for the point of interest before placing an order. The use of browse imagery allows the user to review a reduced resolution image to determine if a specific site is contained in the selected frame.  Visit the following site for further information:  http://www.nro.gov/.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-180</westbc>
            <eastbc>180</eastbc>
            <northbc>84.2</northbc>
            <southbc>-84.6</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>GCMD Parameter Keywords</themekt>
            <themekey>USGS</themekey>
            <themekey>PHOTOGRAPHS</themekey>
            <themekey>PANORAMIC CAMERA</themekey>
            <themekey>CARTOGRAPHIC CAMERA</themekey>
            <themekey>EARTH SCIENCE &gt; RADIANCE OR IMAGERY &gt; Visible Wavelengths &gt; Visible Imagery</themekey>
            <themekey>PHOTO-RECONNAISSANCE</themekey>
            <themekey>EROS</themekey>
            <themekey>SATELLITE</themekey>
            <themekey>DECLASSIFIED</themekey>
            <themekey>ENVIRONMENTAL</themekey>
            <themekey>IMAGERY</themekey>
            <themekey>EARTH SCIENCE &gt; RADIANCE OR IMAGERY &gt; Infrared Wavelengths &gt; Infrared Imagery</themekey>
            <themekey>PHOTOGRAPHY</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>Any downloading and use of these data signifies a user's agreement to comprehension and compliance of the USGS Standard Disclaimer.  Insure all portions of metadata are read and clearly understood before using these data in order to protect both user and USGS interests.</accconst>
      <useconst>There is no guarantee of warranty concerning the accuracy of these data.  Users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since the data was collected and that some parts of these data may no longer represent actual surface conditions.  Users should not use these data for critical applications without a full awareness of their limitations.  Acknowledgement of the originating agencies would be appreciated in products derived from these data.  Any user who modifies the data set is obligated to describe the types of modifications they perform.  User specifically agrees not to misrepresent the data set, nor to imply that changes made were proved or endorsed by the U.S. Geological Survey.  Please refer to http://www.usgs.gov/privacy.html for the USGS disclaimer.
</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <secinfo>
         <secsys>none</secsys>
         <secclass>unclassified</secclass>
         <sechandl>none</sechandl>
      </secinfo>
      <native>Oracle</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>The identification of features is provided by the distinct electromagnetic energy it emits, reflects, or otherwise transmits.  This is called the spectral signature.  Other signatures such as tone (lightness or darkness), texture (surface roughness or smoothness), pattern, shadow, shape, and size are as important.  Thus, through the use of remote sensing technologies, such elements as water features, soils, and vegetation can be identified and distinguished from each other</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Not available</logic>
      <complete>These photographs were retrieved under rigid quality control
and product specifications.</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>This image collection was produced under strict military guidelines and  initially used to produce maps and charts, providing stereo-optical coverage of selected areas, for the U.S. Department of Defense. </procdesc>
            <procdate>19801013</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
                     <city>Sioux Falls</city>
                     <state>SD</state>
                     <postal>57198-0001</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
                  <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
      <cloud>Unknown</cloud>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
   </spdoinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the USGS, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the USGS regarding the use of the data on any other system, nor does the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. </distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>TIFF</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov </networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>Typically, all data available from USGS/EROS are downloadable at no cost to the user. There are some cases when a service fee is required to convert the analog film record to a digital file. This non-refundable fee is $30 per scene/frame.</fees>
         <ordering>Consult the data sets product page for specific information.</ordering>
         <turnarnd>A majority of the data are available for immediate downloading.  Specific data processing may take 24 to 48 hours and film scanning service requests involving payment to USGS can require 3 - 4 weeks upon successful payment of the request.</turnarnd>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>_</custom>
      <techpreq>Adequate computer capability is the only technical prerequisite for viewing data in digital form.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150415</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
