<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>USGS Earth Resources Observation &amp; Science (EROS) Center</origin>
            <pubdate>20150415</pubdate>
            <title>National Aerial Photography Program (1987-present)</title>
            <geoform>Photograph and/or High Resolution Scanned Image</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Sioux Falls, SD</pubplace>
               <publish>USGS Earth Resources Observations &amp; Science (EROS) Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The National Aerial Photography Program (NAPP) was coordinated by the USGS as an interagency project to acquire cloud-free aerial photographs at an altitude of 20,000 feet above mean terrain elevation. The photographs were taken with a 6-inch focal length lens and are at a scale of 1:40,000. Coverage over the conterminous United States includes both black-and-white (BW) and color infrared (CIR) aerial photographs. Film type and extent of coverage were determined by available funds and operational requirements. The NAPP program, which was operational from 1987 to 2007, consists of more than 1.3 million images. Photographs were acquired on 9-inch film and were centered over quarters of USGS 7.5-minute quadrangles.

Photographs are available as medium resolution digital images in Tagged Image File Format (TIFF). Medium resolution digital products were created with a digital single-lens reflex camera at a resolution of 63 microns, or 400 dots per inch (dpi).
</abstract>
         <purpose>The NAPP program was established in 1987 to provide the USGS with accurate, cloud-free photographs to create and revise US topographic maps.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-124.8</westbc>
            <eastbc>0.1</eastbc>
            <northbc>49.4</northbc>
            <southbc>23.9</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>GCMD Parameter Keywords</themekt>
            <themekey>Imagery</themekey>
            <themekey>USGS</themekey>
            <themekey>EROS</themekey>
            <themekey>Photography</themekey>
            <themekey>EARTH SCIENCE &gt; RADIANCE OR IMAGERY &gt; Visible Wavelengths &gt; Visible Imagery</themekey>
            <themekey>Photographs</themekey>
            <themekey>NAPP</themekey>
            <themekey>Aerial Photography</themekey>
            <themekey>EARTH SCIENCE &gt; LAND SURFACE &gt; Surface Radiative Properties &gt; Reflectance</themekey>
            <themekey>EARTH SCIENCE &gt; RADIANCE OR IMAGERY &gt; Infrared Wavelengths &gt; Infrared Imagery</themekey>
            <themekey>EDC</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>Any downloading and use of these data signifies a user's agreement to comprehension and compliance of the USGS Standard Disclaimer.  Insure all portions of metadata are read and clearly understood before using these data in order to protect both user and USGS interests.</accconst>
      <useconst>There is no guarantee of warranty concerning the accuracy of these data.  Users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since the data was collected and that some parts of these data may no longer represent actual surface conditions.  Users should not use these data for critical applications without a full awareness of their limitations.  Acknowledgement of the originating agencies would be appreciated in products derived from these data.  Any user who modifies the data set is obligated to describe the types of modifications they perform.  User specifically agrees not to misrepresent the data set, nor to imply that changes made were approved or endorsed by the U.S. Geological Survey.  Please refer to http://www.usgs.gov/privacy.html for the USGS disclaimer.
</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <secinfo>
         <secsys>none</secsys>
         <secclass>unclassified</secclass>
         <sechandl>none</sechandl>
      </secinfo>
      <native>Oracle</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>Radiometry is verified by visual inspection of the photo image. Slight systematic radiometric differences may exist between adjacent files; these are due primarily to differences in source image capture dates and sun angles along flight lines. These differences can be observed in an image's general lightness or darkness when it is compared to adjacent file coverages. Tonal balancing may be performed over a group of images during a mosaicing process which may serve to lighten or darken adjacent images to improve their tone.
</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>None</logic>
      <complete>None</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>NAPP photographs are obtained on 9-inch film from an altitude of 20,000 feet above mean terrain elevation, and are centered on quarters of 7.5-minute quadrangles.  Strict specifications regarding sun angle, cloud cover, minimal haze, stereoscopic coverage, and image inspection were followed.</procdesc>
            <procdate>20070211</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
                     <city>Sioux Falls</city>
                     <state>SD</state>
                     <postal>57198-0001</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
                  <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
      <cloud>Unknown</cloud>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
   </spdoinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the USGS, no warranty, expressed or implied, is made by the USGS regarding the use of the data on any other system, nor does the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>High Resolution Scanned Image or Medium ResolutionDigitized Image</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov </networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>Typically, all data available from USGS/EROS are downloadable at no cost to the user. There are some cases when a service fee is required to convert the analog film record to a digital file. This non-refundable fee is $30 per scene/frame.</fees>
         <ordering>Consult the data sets product page for specific information.
	
	
	</ordering>
         <turnarnd>A majority of the data are available for immediate downloading.  Specific  data processing may take 24 to 48 hours and film scanning service requests  involving payment to USGS can require 3 - 4 weeks upon successful payment  of the request.</turnarnd>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>_</custom>
      <techpreq>Adequate computer capability is the only technical prerequisite for viewing data in digital form.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150415</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998, Version 2.0</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
