<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)</origin>
            <pubdate>20150415</pubdate>
            <title>Shuttle Radar Topography Mission 1 Arc and 3 Arc Second Digital Terrain Elevation Data - Void Filled - National Geospatial Data Asset (NGDA)</title>
            <geoform> Elevation data in raster format</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Sioux Falls, South Dakota</pubplace>
               <publish>USGS Earth Resources Observations and Science Center (EROS)</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The Shuttle Radar Topography Mission (SRTM) was a partnership between NASA and the National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency (NGA). Flown aboard the NASA Space Shuttle Endeavour (11-22 February 2000), SRTM fulfilled its mission to map the world in three dimensions. The USGS is under agreement with NGA and NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory to distribute SRTM elevation products derived from the C-band radar data.  SRTM utilized interferomic C-band Spaceborne Imaging Radar to generate elevation data over 80 percent of the Earth's land surface. 

The SRTM collection was edited to delineate and flatten water bodies, better define coastlines, remove spikes and wells, and fill small voids.  Since some areas of missing data or voids were still present in the SRTM collection, the NGA  filled the voids using interpolation algorithms in conjunction with other sources of elevation data. The SRTM Void Filled data set are the result of this additional processing. </abstract>
         <purpose>SRTM elevation data of the Earth's land surface are available with data points spaced at 1 arc second for the United States and at 3 arc seconds for global coverage. </purpose>
         <supplinf>Available Products:

SRTM data at 1 arc second (~30 meter) are currently available for the United States, its territories and possessions. SRTM data at 3 arc-seconds (~90 meters) are currently available for global coverage between 60 degrees North and 56 degrees South latitude.
  Raster size is 1 degree tiles.   The data are expressed in geographic coordinates (latitude/longitude) and is horizontally referenced to WGS84 and vertically referenced to the EGM96 Geoid.
Formats:
1. DTED - Digital Terrain Elevation Data is a standard mapping format designed by the NGA. Each file or cell contains a matrix of vertical elevation values spaced at regular horizontal intervals measured in geographic latitude and longitude units. DTED is a trademark of NGA.

2. BIL  - Band interleaved by line is a simple binary raster format with accompanying ASCII descriptor files. The BIL integer format is recommended for software packages that do not support floating-point data. 

3. GeoTIFF - Georeferenced Tagged Image File Format is a TIFF file with embedded geographic information. This is standard image format for GIS applications.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>In work</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-180</westbc>
            <eastbc>180</eastbc>
            <northbc>60</northbc>
            <southbc>-56</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>SRTM</themekey>
            <themekey>Mapping</themekey>
            <themekey>Topography</themekey>
            <themekey>Imaging Radar</themekey>
            <themekey>DTED</themekey>
            <themekey>NASA</themekey>
            <themekey>NGA</themekey>
            <themekey>Shuttle Radar Topography Mission</themekey>
            <themekey>C-band</themekey>
            <themekey>Elevation</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>NGDA Portfolio Themes</themekt>
            <themekey>NGDA</themekey>
            <themekey>National Geospatial Data Asset</themekey>
            <themekey>Elevation Theme</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>Any downloading and use of these data signifies a user's agreement to comprehension and compliance of the USGS Standard Disclaimer.  Insure all portions of metadata are read and clearly understood before using these data in order to protect both user and USGS interests.</accconst>
      <useconst>There is no guarantee of warranty concerning the accuracy of these data.  Users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since the data was collected and that some parts of these data may no longer represent actual surface conditions.  Users should not use these data for critical applications without a full awareness of their limitations.  Acknowledgement of NASA, NGA and the USGS would be appreciated in products derived from these data.  Any user who modifies the data set is obligated to describe the types of modifications they perform.  User specifically agrees not to misrepresent the data set, nor to imply that changes made were approved or endorsed by the originating agencies.  Please refer to http://www.usgs.gov/privacy.html for the USGS disclaimer.
</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <secinfo>
         <secsys>none</secsys>
         <secclass>unclassified</secclass>
         <sechandl>none</sechandl>
      </secinfo>
      <native>Oracle</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>The SRTM data meet the absolute horizontal and vertical accuracies of 20 meters (circular error at 90% confidence) and 16 meters (linear error at 90% confidence), respectively, as specified for the mission.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>None</logic>
      <complete>Unknown</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>This  image collection was produced under strict military guidelines and initially used to produce maps and charts, providing stereo-optical coverage of selected areas, for the U.S. Department of Defense. </procdesc>
            <procdate>20000211</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
                     <city>Sioux Falls</city>
                     <state>SD</state>
                     <postal>57198-0001</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
                  <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
      <cloud>Unknown</cloud>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
   </spdoinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the USGS regarding the use of the data on any other system, nor does the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  </distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>DTED, BIL, or GeoTIFF</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>SRTM data are available from USGS EROS at no cost to the user. </fees>
         <ordering>SRTM products are available via download through EarthExplorer (http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov).</ordering>
         <turnarnd>The data are available for immediate download.</turnarnd>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>_</custom>
      <techpreq>SRTM data are intended for scientific use with Geographic Information System (GIS) or other special application software that is compatible with the DTED, BIL, or GeoTIFF format.
</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150415</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998, Version 2</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
