<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), Earth Resources Observation System (EROS) Center</origin>
            <pubdate>20150415</pubdate>
            <title>Advanced Very High Resolution Radiometer Orbital Segments</title>
            <geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Sioux Falls, SD USA</pubplace>
               <publish>USGS Earth Resources Observation &amp; Science (EROS) Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The Advanced Very High Resolution Radiometer (AVHRR) data set is comprised of data collected by the AVHRR sensor and held in the archives of the USGS Earth Resources Observation and Science [EROS) Center. Carried aboard the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Polar Orbiting Environmental Satellite series, the AVHRR sensor is a broad-band, 4- or 5- channel scanning radiometer sensing in the visible, near-infared, and thermal infrared portions of the electromagnetic spectrum.

EROS houses AVHRR High Resolution Picture Transmission (HRPT) data and Local Area Coverage (LAC) data. The HRPT data are full resolution image data transmitted to a ground station as they are collected, while LAC data (also full resolution data) are recorded with an onboard tape recorder for subsequent transmission during a station overpass.</abstract>
         <purpose>The objective of the AVHRR instrument is to provide radiance data for investigation of clouds, land-water boundaries, snow and ice extent, ice or snow melt inception, day and night cloud distribution, temperatures of radiation surfaces, and sea surface temperature. The AVHRR data collection effort also provides opportunities for studying and monitoring vegetation conditions in ecosystems, including forests, tundra, cloud mask, quality control bands, and grasslands with applications that include agricultural assessment, land cover mapping, production of large-area image maps (e.g., country maps, continental maps, world maps), and evaluation of regional and continental snow cover.</purpose>
         <supplinf>The average instantaneous field-of-view (IFOV) of 1.4 milliradians yields a LAC/HRPT ground resolution of approximately 1.1 km at the satellite nadir from the nominal orbit altitude of 833 km (517 mi).

Additional data sets include the Alaska twice-monthly AVHRR and the U.S. Conterminous bi-weekly composites. These comprehensive time series data sets are calibrated, georegistered daily observations and twice-monthly NDVI composites for each annual growing season.

Global Experimental Bi-Weekly Normalized Difference data, computed from Global Vegetation Index (GVI) data, are analyzed to monitor global vegetation as a potential tool in global climatic studies.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>In work</progress>
         <update>daily</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-180</westbc>
            <eastbc>180</eastbc>
            <northbc>85.8</northbc>
            <southbc>-85.1</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>EARTH SCIENCE --&gt; RADIANCE OR IMAGERY --&gt; Visible Wavelengths --&gt; Visible Imagery</themekey>
            <themekey>EDC</themekey>
            <themekey>USGS</themekey>
            <themekey>NOAA POES &gt; NOAA Polar Orbiting Environmental Satellites</themekey>
            <themekey>AVHRR &gt; Advanced Very High Resolution Radiometer</themekey>
            <themekey>RASTER</themekey>
            <themekey>AVHRR</themekey>
            <themekey>LEVEL 1B</themekey>
            <themekey>EROS</themekey>
            <themekey>SATELLITE</themekey>
            <themekey>HRPT</themekey>
            <themekey>RADIANCE</themekey>
            <themekey>IMAGERY</themekey>
            <themekey>LAC</themekey>
            <themekey>EARTH SCIENCE --&gt; RADIANCE OR IMAGERY --&gt; Infrared Wavelengths --&gt; Infrared Imagery</themekey>
            <themekey>DIGITAL IMAGE</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>Any downloading and use of these data signifies a user's agreement to comprehension and compliance of the USGS Standard Disclaimer.  Insure all portions of metadata are read and clearly understood before using these data in order to protect both user and USGS interests.

</accconst>
      <useconst>There is no guarantee of warranty concerning the accuracy of these data.  Users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since the data was collected and that some parts of these data may no longer represent actual surface conditions.  Users should not use these data for critical applications without a full awareness of their limitations.  Acknowledgement of the originating agencies would be appreciated in products derived from these data.  Any user who modifies the data set is obligated to describe the types of modifications they perform.  User specifically agrees not to misrepresent the data set, nor to imply that changes made were approved or endorsed by the U.S. Geological Survey.  Please refer to http://www.usgs.gov/privacy.html for the USGS disclaimer.
</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <secinfo>
         <secsys>none</secsys>
         <secclass>unclassified</secclass>
         <sechandl>none</sechandl>
      </secinfo>
      <native>Oracle</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>The identification of features is provided by the distinct electromagnetic energy it emits, reflects, or otherwise transmits.  This is called the spectral signature.  Other signatures such as tone (lightness or darkness), texture (surface roughness or smoothness), pattern, shadow, shape, and size are as important. </attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>The AVHRR sensor was designed to view cold space and one or more internal warm blackbodies for each scan sequence while in orbit. In general, radiometric calibration involves exposing a radiometer to sources of radiation that have been calibrated against primary or secondary standards and determining a relationship between the output of the radiometer and the intensity of the incident radiation (radiance).
All of the radiometers flown on the NOAA/TIROS satellites undergo extensive prelaunch testing and calibration by their manufacturers to characterize their performance. The NESDIS independently analyzes the data from the prelaunch tests to determine the operating characteristics of the instruments, such as their signal-to-noise ratios, stability, linearity of response, and sensitivity. However, characteristics cannot be expected to be the same in orbit as they were before the launch. One reason is that the thermal environment varies with position in the orbit, causing sensitivities to vary orbitally. Also, instrument components age in the several years that usually elapse between the time of the prelaunch tests and launch, and the aging process continues during the two or more years the instrument typically operates in orbit. Therefore, the NOAA/TIROS radiometers have been designed to view cold space and one or more internal warm blackbodies as part of their normal scan sequences in orbit.</logic>
      <complete>As the spacecraft moves through its orbit, the expected angular distance between the nadir of adjacent LAC/HRPT scans is approximately 0.0296 degrees of arc, or 3.2914 kilometers, as measured from the center of the Earth. The actual value of the average angular distance can vary by up to about 0.1712 kilometers due to variations in satellite height, scan angle, and other factors.
The instantaneous field-of-view (IFOV) for all channels is specified to be 1.3 +/- 0.1 milliradians.</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The USGS Center for Earth Resources Observation &amp; Science (EROS) Center ADAPS flow for acquisitions and archiving begins with direct HRPT reception. Initial ingest of the data reformatting includes archive, and creation of browse quick looks and cartridge tapes.

The NOAA AVHRR processing flow begins with sensor data receipt by the CDA stations (Wallops Island, Virginia; Gilmore Creek, Alaska; Monterey, California (ftp); Prince Albert, Canada (ftp); and Australia(tape) where the data are re-broadcast via communications satellites to NOAA/NESDIS in Suitland, Maryland. 

The EROS ADAPS systematic georegistration process references AVHRR data to the Earth's surface. Through modeling, the position and attitude of the TIROS satellite platforms and the canning geometry of the AVHRR sensor, geometric distortions can be minimized. The position of the satellite is determined by an orbital model updated by ephemeris data received daily from NAVY Space Surveillance. The AVHRR sensor model characterizes the non-linear scanning of the sensor mirror. A refinement to the sensor model accounts for the displacement in longitude due to the rotation of the Earth under the satellite. All modeling is referenced to the time of acquisition. As the satellite clock time drifts, a delta time adjustment is applied. Collectively, these models comprise the geometric correction model in ADAPS. The positional accuracy of a systematic georegistration is approximately 5,000 meter, root-mean-square-error (RMSE). 
</procdesc>
            <procdate>19990930</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
                     <city>Sioux Falls</city>
                     <state>SD</state>
                     <postal>57198-0001</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
                  <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
      <cloud>Unknown</cloud>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Pixel</rasttype>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the USGS, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the USGS regarding the use of the data on any other system, nor does the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  </distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ASCII</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov </networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>Typically, all data available from USGS/EROS are downloadable at no cost to the user. There are some cases when a service fee is required to convert the analog film record to a digital file. </fees>
         <ordering>Consult the data sets product page for specific information.</ordering>
         <turnarnd>A majority of the data are available for immediate downloading.  Specific data processing may take 24 to 48 hours and film scanning service requests involving payment to USGS can require 3 - 4 weeks upon successful payment of the request.</turnarnd>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>_</custom>
      <techpreq>Adequate computer capability is the only technical prerequisite for viewing data in digital form.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150415</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998, Version 2</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
