<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>USGS Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</origin>
            <pubdate>20150415</pubdate>
            <title>Global Land Survey 1990; Landsat 4-5 TM (1987-1997)</title>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Sioux Falls, South Dakota USA</pubplace>
               <publish>USGS  Earth Resources Observation and Science Center (EROS</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>Originally, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) was responsible for operating the Landsat satellites through the early 1980s.  In January 1983 operations of the Landsat system were transferred to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration  (NOAA).  In October 1985 the Landsat system was commercialized.  After that date, all Landsat commercial rights became the property of Space Imaging, with exclusive sales rights to all U.S. thematic mapper (TM) data.  Throughout these changes, the USGS retained primary responsibility as the Government's long-term archive of Landsat data.  As of July 1, 2001, Space Imaging relinquished their commercial right to Landsat  data.  The Land Remote Sensing Policy Act of 1992  (Public Law 102-555) officially authorized the government and assigned responsibility to the Department of Interior delegated down to the USGS.
</othercit>
            <onlink>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov
http://glovis.usgs.gov</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The Global Land Survey (GLS) datasets are a collection of orthorectified, cloud-minimized Landsat-type satellite images, providing near complete coverage of the global land area decadally since the early 1970s. The global mosaics are centered on 1975, 1990, 2000, 2005, and 2010, and consist of data acquired from four sensors: Enhanced Thematic Mapper Plus, Thematic Mapper, Multispectral Scanner, and Advanced Land Imager. The GLS datasets have been widely used in land-cover and land-use change studies at local, regional, and global scales. This study evaluates the GLS datasets with respect to their spatial coverage, temporal consistency, geodetic accuracy, radiometric calibration consistency, image completeness, extent of cloud contamination, and residual gaps. In general, the three latest GLS datasets are of a better quality than the GLS-1990 and GLS-1975 datasets, with most of the imagery (85%) having cloud cover of less than 10%, the acquisition years clustered much more tightly around their target years, better co-registration relative to GLS-2000, and better radiometric absolute calibration. Probably, the most significant impediment to scientific use of the datasets is the variability of image phenology (i.e., acquisition day of year). This paper provides end-users with an assessment of the quality of the GLS datasets for specific applications, and where possible, suggestions for mitigating their deficiencies.</abstract>
         <purpose>The USGS Earth Resources Observation and Science Center (EROS) has managed the Landsat data archive since the launch of Landsat 1. This archive provides a rich collection of information about the Earth's land surface. Major characteristics and changes to the surface of the planet can be detected, measured, and analyzed using Landsat data.  The effects of desertification, deforestation, pollution, cataclysmic volcanic activity, and other natural and anthropogenic events can be examined using data acquired from the Landsat series of Earth-observing satellites. The information obtainable from the historical and current Landsat data play a key role in studying changes to the Earth's surface.  Landsat data have been used by government, commercial, industrial, civilian, and educational communities in the US and worldwide. They are being used to support a wide range of applications in such areas as global change research, agriculture, forestry, geology, resources management, geography, mapping, water quality, and oceanography.  The types of changes that can be identified include agricultural development, deforestation, natural disaster, urbanization, and the development and degradation of water resources.</purpose>
         <supplinf>GLS 1990 Landsat data is available from the USGS.  In addition to its Landsat data management responsibility, the USGS investigates new methods of characterizing and studying changes on the land surface with Landsat data.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>In work</progress>
         <update>Continually</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-169.5</westbc>
            <eastbc>179.6</eastbc>
            <northbc>79.3</northbc>
            <southbc>-56.8</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>Land</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>Any downloading and use of these data signifies a user's agreement to comprehension and compliance of the USGS Standard Disclaimer.  Insure all portions of metadata are read and clearly understood before using these data in order to protect both user and USGS interests.</accconst>
      <useconst> There is no guarantee of warranty concerning the accuracy of these data.  Users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since the data was collected and that some parts of these data may no longer represent actual surface conditions.  Users should not use these data for critical applications without a full awareness of their limitations.  Acknowledgement of the originating agencies would be appreciated in products derived from these data.  Any user who modifies the data set is obligated to describe the types of modifications they perform.  User specifically agrees not to misrepresent the data set, nor to imply that changes made were approved or endorsed by the U.S. Geological Survey.  Please refer to http://www.usgs.gov/privacy.html for the USGS disclaimer.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <secinfo>
         <secsys>none</secsys>
         <secclass>unclassified</secclass>
         <sechandl>none</sechandl>
      </secinfo>
      <native>Oracle</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>The identification of features is provided by the distinct electromagnetic energy it emits, reflects, or otherwise transmits.  This is called the spectral signature.  Other signatures such as tone (lightness or darkness), texture (surface roughness or smoothness), pattern, shadow, shape, and size are as important. </attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Not Available</logic>
      <complete>The Landsat platforms operate from a sun-synchronous, near-polar orbit imaging the same 185 km (115 miles) ground swath every 16 days.  The landsat system provides for global data between 81 degrees north latitude and 81 degrees south latitude.</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>This  image collection was produced under strict military guidelines and initially used to produce maps and charts, providing stereo-optical coverage of selected areas, for the U.S. Department of Defense. </procdesc>
            <procdate>19971102</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
                     <city>Sioux Falls</city>
                     <state>SD</state>
                     <postal>57198-0001</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
                  <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
      <cloud>Unknown</cloud>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Pixel</rasttype>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the USGS regarding the use of the data on any other system, nor does the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  </distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Geographcal-Tagged Image File Format (GeoTIFF, NLAPS Data Format (NDF). For additional information see
http://landsat.usgs.gov/Landsat_Processing_Details.php</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr> http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov and http://glovis.usgs.gov</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>Typically, all data available from USGS/EROS are downloadable at no cost to the user. there are some cases when a service fee is required to convert the analog film record to a digital file. This non-refundable fee is $30 per scene/frame.</fees>
         <ordering>Consult the data sets product page for specific information. </ordering>
         <turnarnd>A majority of the data are available for immediate downloading.  Specific data processing may take 24 to 48 hours and film scanning service requests involving payment to USGS can require 3 - 4 weeks upon successful payment of the request. </turnarnd>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>Limited from data set to data set. Please consult the data sets product page for specific information. </custom>
      <techpreq>Adequate computer capability is the only technical prerequisite for viewing data in digital form.
</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150415</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998, Version 2</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
