<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Kerry Weber</origin>
            <origin>Todd Severson</origin>
            <origin>James Luoma</origin>
            <pubdate>20150409</pubdate>
            <title>AEH-12-PSEUDO-04 Zebra Mussel Survival on Artificial Substrate -- All Exposures Survival Assessment</title>
            <geoform>Tabular Digital Data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>2015-1050</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Kerry Weber</origin>
                  <origin>Todd Severson</origin>
                  <origin>James Luoma</origin>
                  <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
                  <title>Efficacy of Pseudomonas fluorescens (Pf-CL145A) Spray Dried Powder for Controlling Zebra Mussels Adhering to Test Substrates</title>
                  <geoform>Publication (Journal)</geoform>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
                     <issue>2015-1050</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
                     <publish>USGS</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ofr20151050</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>A mobile bioassay trailer was used to assess the efficacy of Pseudomonas fluorescens (Pf-CL145A) spray dried powder (SDP) formulation for controlling zebra mussels (Dreissena polymorpha) from two midwestern lakes: Lake Carlos (Alexandria, Minnesota) and Shawano Lake (Shawano, Wisconsin). The effects of SDP exposure concentration and exposure duration on zebra mussel survival were evaluated along with comparing a benthic injection application technique to a whole water column (WWC) application. 
Groups of zebra mussels were collected from each lake and allowed to adhere to test substrates for at least 15 days before exposure to SDP. Two independent trials were completed at each lake: (1) a WWC application trial was used to evaluate the effects of SDP exposure concentration and exposure duration on zebra mussel survival; and (2) a benthic injection (BI) application trial in which the SDP was injected into the test tanks to determine the efficacy of a benthic injection application technique. Three exposure durations (6, 9, and 12 hours) were evaluated in the WWC trials and a 12-hour exposure duration was evaluated in the BI trials. All trials contained zebra mussels which were removed at the completion of each exposure duration, consolidated into wire mesh cages, and held in the lake for approximately 30 days before being assessed for survival.
For all trials, treatment was assigned to each test tank according to a randomized block design (n = 3 test tanks per treatment). The treatment groups included (1) an untreated control group, (2) a group that received an application of 50 milligrams of SDP per liter (mg SDP/L), and (3) a group that received an application of 100 mg SDP/L. During the BI trials, SDP was administered to achieve the desired exposure concentration in the bottom 50 percent (175 L) of the test tank. All exposure concentrations are reported as active ingredient. 
Approximately 30 days after exposure, zebra mussels were sorted into live and dead, and enumerated. Mean survival of zebra mussels in control treatments exceeded 95 percent. Mean survival of zebra mussels in the Lake Carlos WWC SDP-treated groups ranged from 0.5 to 2.1 percent and when compared at the same exposure duration, no difference was detected in survival between the 50 and 100 milligrams per liter (mg/L) treatment groups. Similarly, mean survival of zebra mussels in the Shawano Lake WWC SDP-treated groups ranged from 2.0 to 12.6 percent and when compared at the same exposure duration, no difference was detected in survival between the 50- and 100-mg/L treatment groups. Mean survival of zebra mussels in the Lake Carlos BI trial SDP-treated groups did not differ (p = 0.93) and was 18.1 and 18.0 percent in the 50- and 100-mg/L treatment groups, respectively. Mean survival of zebra mussels in the Shawano Lake BI trial SDP-treated groups differed (p &lt; 0.01) and was 2.9 and 0.9 percent in the 50- and 100-mg/L treatment groups, respectively. Survival of zebra mussels assigned to the SDP-treated groups in the Lake Carlos WWC trial (12-hour exposure duration) differed from the survival of zebra mussels assigned to the SDP-treated groups in the Lake Carlos BI trial; however, after modification of the BI application technique, no difference (p = 0.22) was detected between the survival of zebra mussel in the Shawano Lake WWC (12-hour exposure duration) and BI trials.</abstract>
         <purpose>Freshwater mussels native to North America (order Unionoida) are considered the most diverse in the world, consisting of approximately 297 recognized taxa, but they have been declining at an alarming rate due to anthropogenic activities such as pollution, habitat alteration, and over harvest (Williams and others, 1993; Neves and others, 1997). A survey completed by the Nature Conservancy revealed 55 percent of North America’s mussels are either extinct or imperiled (Master, 1990). The North American mussel extinction rate is predicted to be 6.4 percent per decade, which equates to the extinction of 127 species in the next 100 years (Ricciardi and Rasmussen, 1999). This prediction may be conservative, as it did not account for the invasion of North American waterways by dreissenid mussels (zebra mussel, Dreissena polymorpha and quagga mussel, Dreissena bugensis).
Dreissenid mussels are ideal invaders due to their high fecundity and their planktonic larvae, which are capable of dispersal over vast areas (Birnbaum, 2011). Dreissenid mussels pose a serious ecological threat and negatively affect many native aquatic species, particularly freshwater mussels. Dreissenid mussels can quickly inundate freshwater mussels and cause obstruction of valve movement as well as inhibition of feeding and respiration (Burlakova and others, 2000) resulting in an increased cost of metabolism, decreased fitness, and ultimately death (Baker and Hornbach, 1997).
Natural resource managers lack readily available, environmentally safe, and effective tools for controlling dreissenid mussels in open-water environments. One potential tool for limited open-water control of dreissenid mussels is a commercially formulated spray dried powder (SDP) formulation of Pseudomonas fluorescens (Zequanox®), produced by Marrone Bio Innovations, Inc. (MBI; Davis, California), which contains nonviable cells of a specific strain (CL145A) of the common soil bacterium Pseudomonas fluorescens. The SDP formulation was developed by MBI and registered by the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency for control non-native dreissenid (zebra and quagga) mussels in raw water conduit systems (that is, industrial cooling and irrigation systems, and so forth) and it has recently been approved for use in limited open-water environments.
The objectives of this study were (1) to evaluate the potential use of Pseudomonas fluorescens spray dried powder (SDP) formulation for controlling zebra mussels (Dreissena polymorpha) in limited open-water environments; and (2) to evaluate the use of a benthic injection (BI) application technique to reduce the amount of SDP required to induce zebra mussel mortality.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>20111001</begdate>
               <enddate>20131130</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>observed</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>Zequanox</themekey>
            <themekey>Pseudomonas fluorescens</themekey>
            <themekey>Zebra mussels</themekey>
            <themekey>Dreissena polymorpha</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>None</placekt>
            <placekey>Minnesota</placekey>
            <placekey>Wisconsin</placekey>
            <placekey>Douglas County</placekey>
            <placekey>Shwano County</placekey>
            <placekey>Lake Carlos</placekey>
            <placekey>Shawano Lake</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The USGS or the U.S. Government shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</accconst>
      <useconst>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The USGS or the U.S. Government shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Midwest Region</cntorg>
               <cntper>James A Luoma</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Research Fish Biologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>2630 Fanta Reed Road</address>
               <city>La Crosse</city>
               <state>WI</state>
               <postal>54603</postal>
               <country>US</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>608-781-6391</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>608-783-6066</cntfax>
            <cntemail>jluoma@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>New York State Museum's Field Research Laboratory; Minnesota Department of Natural Resources; Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources; Shawano County; Lake Carlos State Park</datacred>
      <native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; ESRI ArcCatalog 10.2 (Build 3552) Service Pack [N/A] (Build [N/A])</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Instruments were calibrated daily. All data points within the spreadsheets were checked against the original datasheets prior to analysis.</logic>
      <complete>Water samples were not collected at 6 and 9 h from the exposure tanks for un-ionized ammonia analysis for Lake Shawano whole water application.
Temperature readings from the first and last days of recorder deployment were omitted from data analysis. The temperature recorders may have sampled ambient air temperature during these time points. These entire days will be omitted as diurnal temperature fluctuation skew the mean daily temperature.
All lengths were reported except for those from mussels with broken shells or those &lt; 6 mm.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>N/A</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
         <vertacc>
            <vertaccr>N/A</vertaccr>
         </vertacc>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The four separate field trials with activities were conducted from October 2011 to November 2013. Applications were completed on August 15 and 17, 2012 at Lake Carlos and on September 6 and 8, 2012 at Shawano Lake.  Temperate data logger data was collected using a data SONDE.  Spectrophotometric, water chemistry, and survival data were collected at field sites.</procdesc>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Length Data: After survival analysis, one tray from each treatment level (0, 50 and 100 mg/L) from the 12 h exposure termination time point was retained for mussel length analysis. All animals were measured for length. All lengths were reported except for those from mussels with broken shells or those &lt; 6 mm.</procdesc>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Water Chemistry: Conductivity, hardness, and alkalinity were measured prior to dosing. Samples were collected from both headboxes used to fill individual tanks. Samples were analyzed in triplicate. Temperature, pH and dissolved oxygen levels were measured prior to dosing. Measurements were observed in each exposure tank. Water chemistry measurements (dissolved oxygen, pH and temperature) were observed for all test tanks at 0, 3, 6, 9 and 12 h after dosing.</procdesc>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Ammonia Samples: Water samples were collected at 12 h from each exposure tank. Samples were 0.45 µm filtered, acidified with sulfuric acid, and analyzed by the 4500-NH3 G. Automated Phenate Method (Standard Methods for the Examination of Water and Wastewater, 21st Edition, 2005) on a Technicon Autoanalyzer II by the UMESC water quality laboratory. The un-ionized ammonia fractions were calculated using the sample pH and temperature according to the formula in Emerson et al. (1975).</procdesc>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Temperature Data Loggers: Upon exposure termination, four wire mesh cages containing test animals were placed into each lake for a post-exposure holding period. Each cage was fitted with a HOBO temperature logger programmed to record water temperature every six hours (four times per day). Mean daily temperature (°C) and standard deviation were calculated from all daily measurements.</procdesc>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Survival Data: Each tank replicate contained 9 perforated aluminum trays (~15.2 cm x 15.2 cm with 2.5 cm sides) with attached zebra mussels enclosed in a mesh containment bag (~20.3 x 25.4 x 5.1 cm; 0.31 x 0.31 cm openings). Each substrate contained a minimum of 50 adhering zebra mussels prior to treatment. Aluminum trays were coded with tags according to treatment type (W = whole water body, B = bottom injection; tank number 1-9, row letter A, B, C; position number 1-3). Example code of W 1A3 = whole water body (tank) treatment, Tank 1, Row A, position 3. The tanks are numbered 1-9; the rows are in order from the front of the tank (isle) to the rear of the tank (wall) (A = isle; B = middle; C = wall); the position is from left to right in order (1 = left; 2 = center; 3 = right). Three trays were removed after 6, 9 and 12 h of exposure. The substrates were consolidated into wire mesh holding cages with 1 sampling time period per cage and the treatment levels indiscriminately distributed. The wire mesh holding cages were held in the lake until survival assessments were completed.</procdesc>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Spectrophotometric Analysis: The absorbance of triplicate samples of 25, 50, 100, and 200 mg/L dilutions of a 2,000 mg/L active ingredient (A.I.) stock were measured to prepare a standard curve. Standard checks were performed at 6, 9, and/or 12 hours by comparing the 25, 50, 100, and 200 mg/L (A.I.) dilutions to the linear curve. A linear regression was completed in SAS using the absorbance values obtained from the spectrophotometer of 3 replicate dilutions of 25, 50, 100 and 200 mg/L Zequanox. Standard checks and treatment sample concentrations were predicted in SAS by comparing the observed absorbances with the linear regression. Standard checks and treatment sample concentrations were predicted in SAS by comparing the observed absorbances with the linear regression.</procdesc>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Ammonia analysis was completed by UMESC LTRMP Branch.  Ammonia data was analyzed  using the automated Phenate Method (Standard Methods for the Examination of Water and Wastewater, 21st Edition, 2005). The un-ionized ammonia fractions were calculated using the sample pH and temperature according to the formula in Emerson et al. (1975).</procdesc>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Data analyses for water chemistry parameters were limited to simple summary statistics; comparative statistics were not generated. Exposure concentration means were determined using SAS® software version 9.3 (SAS Institute, Inc., Cary, N.C.). The SAS® software Proc Means procedure was used to determine the mean exposure concentration by individual test tank, treatment group, and exposure duration (appendix 7, items 2–4, 6–8, 10–12, 14–16). Because of observations of SDP settling and non-detectable levels of SDP in the suspended water samples, the bottom water sample exposure concentrations for the Lake Carlos BI trial are reported. The suspended water exposure concentrations for Shawano Lake BI trials are reported due to negligible (≤ 3mg/L) SDP exposure concentrations measured in the surface water samples.
Statistical comparisons of zebra mussel survival were completed using SAS® software version 9.3. Significance was declared at α ≤ 0.05. A generalized linear mixed model was used to analyze the survival of zebra mussels in each treatment group (appendix 9, items 1–3). The proportion of mortalities (number of dead zebra mussels compared to the total number of zebra mussels in the sample) was modeled using the SAS® software Proc GLIMMIX procedure with a binomial distribution and a logit link function. A scale parameter was added to the model using the SAS® software random_residual_ statement. Zebra mussel survival in each treatment group was individually compared to the zebra mussel survival in the untreated control group using a two-sided means comparison test.</procdesc>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>•	Data were entered into Excel spreadsheet (October 2013 to February 2014)
•	Summaries completed in Excel (if final format; 2014)
•	Data were proofed against original datasheets (2014)
•	Data imported into SAS (2014)
•	Data analyzed in SAS (2014)
•	Results reported in final report (March 2015)</procdesc>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed Name="All Exposures Survival Assessment">
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd>
            <enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>loc</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Location</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>LC</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Lake Carlos</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>SL</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Shawano Lake</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>trt_typ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Treatment Group</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>BI</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Bottom Injection</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>WT</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Whole Tank</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>conc</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Concentration</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>100</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>time</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Exposure Duration</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>6</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>12</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>tnk</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Exposure Tank ID</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>1</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>9</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>tray</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Substrate ID - the rows are in order from the front of the tank (isle) to the rear of the tank (wall) (A = isle; B = middle; C = wall); the position is from left to right in order (1 = left; 2 = center; 3 = right)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>B2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>A1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Isle Left</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>A2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Isle Center</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>A3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Isle Right</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>B1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Middle Left</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>B2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>B3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Middle Right</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Wall Left</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Wall Middle</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Wall Right</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>tot</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Total Number of Zebra Mussels</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>51</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>510</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>number of mussels</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>dead</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of Zebra Mussel Mortalities</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>453</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>number of dead mussels</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <overview>
         <eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes the tabular data associated with the data set. Please review the detailed descriptions that are provided (the individual attribute descriptions) for information on the values that appear as fields/table entries of the data set.</eaover>
         <eadetcit>The entity and attribute information was generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Please review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Midwest Region</cntorg>
               <cntper>James A Luoma</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Research Fish Biologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>2630 Fanta Reed Road</address>
               <city>La Crosse</city>
               <state>WI</state>
               <postal>54603</postal>
               <country>US</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>608-781-6391</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>608-783-6066</cntfax>
            <cntemail>jluoma@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The USGS or the U.S. Government shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Tabular Digital Data</formname>
            </digtinfo>
         </digform>
         <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150410</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>John C Nelson</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Midwest Region</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Biologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>2630 Fanta Reed Road</address>
               <city>La Crosse</city>
               <state>WI</state>
               <postal>54603</postal>
               <country>US</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>608-781-6370</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>608-783-6066</cntfax>
            <cntemail>jcnelson@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
