<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Gulf Coast Aerial Mapping Co., Inc.</origin>
            <pubdate>Unpublished material</pubdate>
            <title>Digital Orthoimagery for Mapping the Natchez Trace Parkway 2004</title>
            <geoform>raster digital data</geoform>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Amina Rangoonwala (Five Rivers Services, LLC at U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                  <origin>Terri Bannister (Five Rivers Services, LLC at U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                  <origin>Elijah W. Ramsey III, Ph.D (U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                  <pubdate>2011</pubdate>
                  <title>Mapping the Natchez Trace Parkway</title>
                  <geoform>report</geoform>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
                     <issue>2011-1276</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Lafayette, LA</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2011/1276/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This dataset represents aerial photography of the Natchez Trace Parkway that was taken in late September and early October of 2004.  Images were acquired during leaf-on conditions as required by the National Park Service (NPS) to accomplish their ground-based vegetation classification. Nearly 400 aerial photography frames were scanned and orthorectified to generate digital orthophoto quarter quads (DOQQs).  These were cut to match existing DOQQs creating a total of 235 DOQQs for the entire 715 km long Parkway.  For ease of use, the DOQQs were grouped into 11 mosaics, each covering a section of the Parkway. At the request of the NPS, each mosaic was divided into ten tiles to allow for efficient loading on less robust computers.</abstract>
         <purpose>The purpose of this dataset is to provide a data source for landcover mapping of the Natchez Trace Parkway for the USGS-NPS Vegetation Characterization Program.  The USGS-NPS Vegetation Characterization Program is a cooperative effort by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and the National Park Service (NPS) to classify, describe, and map vegetation communities in more than 280 national park units across the United States. This landmark program is both the first to provide national-scale descriptions of vegetation for a Federal agency and the first to create national vegetation standards for its data products.
 
The vegetation mapping program is an important part of the NPS Inventory and Monitoring Program, a long-term effort to develop baseline data for all national park units that have a natural resource component. For more information visit the Vegetation Inventory Program (VIP) website at: http://science.nature.nps.gov/im/inventory/veg/index.cfm.</purpose>
         <supplinf>The following is a list of the digital orthophoto quarter quadrangles (DOQQs) for each mosaic: 

Mosaic 1 (Mississippi - Zone 15) - Natchez (NE, SE), Washington (NE, NW, SE, SW), Pine Ridge (SE), Cranfield (NW), Church Hill (NE, NW, SE, SW), Rodney (SE, SW), Lorman (NE, NW, SW), Red Lick (NW), Widows Creek (NE, SE), Port Gibson (NE, NW, SW), Willows (SE, SW), and Hermanville (NW). 

Mosaic 2 (Mississippi - Zone 15; this mosaic has been divided into Mosaic 2 South and Mosaic 2 North) - Carlisle (NE, NW, SE, SW), Utica West (NW), Big Black (SE), Cayuga (SE, NE, SW), Learned (NE, NW, SW), Edwards (SE), Terry NW (NW), Raymond (NE, SE, SW), Clinton (NE, NW, SW), Pocahontas (SE, SW), Jackson (NW), Ridgeland (NE, NW, SE, SW), Madison (NE, NW, SE, SW), and Canton (SE). 

Mosaic 3 South (Mississippi - Zone 16) - Goshen Springs (NW), Shoccoe (NE, NW, SE, SW), Sharon SE (NE, NW, SW), Farmhaven (NE, SE, SW), Ofahoma (NE, NW, SE, SW), Thomastown (NE, NW, SE, SW), Conway (NW), Joseph (NE, SE), Singleton (NW, SW), Kosciusko (NE, NW, SE, SW), McAdams (SE), Ethel North (NE, NW, SE,SW), Ethel South (NW), and Kosciusko NE (SE). 

Mosaic 3 North (Mississippi - Zone 16) - French Camp (NE, SE, SW), Weir (NE, NW, SW), Tomnolen (NE, SE, SW), Reform (NE, NW, SW), Sapa (NE, SE, SW), Maben (NE, NW, SW), Mantee (NE, NW, SE, SW), Montpelier (NW), Woodland (NE, SE), and Sparta (NE, NW, SW). 

Mosaic 4 South (Mississippi - Zone 16) - Houston East (NE, NW, SE, SW), Troy (NE, SE), Troy SE (NE, NW, SW), Bissell (NE, NW, SE, SW), Verona (NW), Sherman (NE, SE), and Tupelo (NE, NW, SW). 

Mosaic 4 North (Mississippi - Zone 16) - Tupelo (NE, NW, SW), Guntown (NE, SE, SW), Ratliff (NE, NW, SE, SW), Kirkville (NE, NW, SW), Marietta (SE), Fulton NE (NE, NW), Paden SE (NE, SE, SW), Belmont (NE, NW, SW), and Tishomingo (SE, SW). 

Mosaic 5 South (Alabama - Zone 16) - Bishop (NE, NW, SE, SW), Margerum (NE, SE), Barton (NW), Cherokee (NE, NW, SE, SW), Wright (SE), Sinking Creek (NW), Threet (NE, NW, SE, SW), and Pleasant Site (NW). 

Mosaic 5 North (Tennessee - Zone 16) - Cypress Inn (NE, NW, SE, SW), Westpoint (NW), Whitten (NW), Three Churches (NE, SE), Collinwood (NE, NW, SW), Waynesboro East (SE, SW), and Ovilla (NE, NW, SE, SW). 

Mosaic 6 (Tennessee - Zone 16) - Riverside (NE, SE, SW), Henryville (NE, NW, SW), Gordonsburg (NE, NW, SE, SW), Sunrise (SE), Mount Joy (NW), Greensfield Bend (NE, NW, SE, SW), and Williamsport (NE, NW, SW). 

Mosaic 7 (Tennessee - Zone 16) - Primm Springs (NE, NW, SE, SW), Theta (NE, NW, SE, SW), Fairview (NE, SE, SW), Leipers Fork (NW), Kingston Springs (SE), and Bellevue (SW).</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <mdattim>
               <sngdate>
                  <caldate>20040929</caldate>
               </sngdate>
               <sngdate>
                  <caldate>20040930</caldate>
               </sngdate>
               <sngdate>
                  <caldate>20041006</caldate>
               </sngdate>
               <sngdate>
                  <caldate>20041015</caldate>
               </sngdate>
            </mdattim>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-91.370359</westbc>
            <eastbc>-86.964290</eastbc>
            <northbc>36.176145</northbc>
            <southbc>31.430989</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>color infrared</themekey>
            <themekey>CIR</themekey>
            <themekey>aerial photography</themekey>
            <themekey>leaf-on conditions</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>imageryBaseMapsEarthCover</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>None</placekt>
            <placekey>Natchez Trace</placekey>
            <placekey>Natchez Trace Parkway</placekey>
            <placekey>Mississippi</placekey>
            <placekey>Tennessee</placekey>
            <placekey>Alabama</placekey>
            <placekey>Southeast US</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
            <placekey>State of Mississippi</placekey>
            <placekey>State of Louisiana</placekey>
            <placekey>State of Alabama</placekey>
            <placekey>State of Tennessee</placekey>
            <placekey>Adams County</placekey>
            <placekey>Tishomingo County</placekey>
            <placekey>Jefferson County</placekey>
            <placekey>Claiborne County</placekey>
            <placekey>Hinds County</placekey>
            <placekey>Madison County</placekey>
            <placekey>Leake County</placekey>
            <placekey>Attala County</placekey>
            <placekey>Choctaw County</placekey>
            <placekey>Webster County</placekey>
            <placekey>Chickasaw County</placekey>
            <placekey>Pontotoc County</placekey>
            <placekey>Lee County</placekey>
            <placekey>Itawamba County</placekey>
            <placekey>Prentiss County</placekey>
            <placekey>Colbert County</placekey>
            <placekey>Lauderdale County</placekey>
            <placekey>Wayne County</placekey>
            <placekey>Lawrence County</placekey>
            <placekey>Lewis County</placekey>
            <placekey>Natchez Trace Parkway</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from the U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center and not indirectly through other sources which may have been changed in some way. The distributor makes no claim as to the data's suitability for other purposes.</accconst>
      <useconst>Acknowledgement of the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), National Wetlands Research Center (NWRC) as a data source would be appreciated in products developed from these data.  Such acknowledgement as is standard for citation and legal practices for data sources is expected by users of these data. Sharing new data layers developed directly from these data would be appreciated by the USGS NWRC staff. Users should be aware that comparison with other datasets for the same area from other time periods may be inaccurate because of inconsistencies resulting from changes in mapping conventions, data collection procedures, and computer processes over time. The distributor shall not be liable for improper or incorrect use of these data, based on the description of appropriate/inappropriate uses described in this metadata document. These data are not legal documents and are not to be used as such.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</cntorg>
               <cntper>Elijah W. Ramsey III, Ph.D</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Principal Investigator</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>700 Cajundome Blvd</address>
               <city>Lafayette</city>
               <state>LA</state>
               <postal>70506-3152</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>337-266-8500</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>337-266-8841</cntfax>
            <cntemail>elijah_ramsey@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <cntinst>Additional contact: Information Services, Voice 337-266-8692, Email nwrclibrary@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), National Wetlands Research Center (NWRC) would like to thank Paul Conzelman and Martha Segura of the National Park Service for allowing us the opportunity to contribute to the landcover mapping of the Nation's resources and Kurt Foote of the National Park Service for his guidance and vital help in our field reconnaissance. Partial funding for this work was provided through the U.S. National Park Service Agreement Number 14431A53200000. We are grateful to Steve Hartley (USGS) for his development of critical geographic information system (GIS) procedures and help in GIS processing.

The USGS NWRC would also like to acknowledge Gulf Coast Aerial Mapping Co., Inc. for the generation of the aerial photography.</datacred>
      <native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.3000</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>Not applicable; data are not attributed</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Not applicable</logic>
      <complete>The flight path was designed to cover the 715 km length of the Natchez Trace Parkway. Data are complete as possible.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>The DOQQs are compliant with the digital orthophoto standard as defined by the U.S. Geological Survey Rocky Mountain Mapping Center.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Color infrared (CIR) aerial photography was acquired during leaf-on conditions. The flights occurred on September 29-30 and October 6 and 15, 2004. The resulting aerial film rolls were then scanned at 25 microns by using a true color, true optics scanner to generate a 1,000-dot per inch (dpi) product and converted to DOQQs. The effects of tilt and relief were removed from the aerial photos by orthorectification. The transformation of the photographic frames to DOQQ representation provided uniform scale. Uniform scale allowed the direct measure of true distance and direction.  The tiles were then cut to match existing DOQQs in the UTM projection zones.  

The 235 DOQQs created from the 386 aerial frames were mosaiced to create full coverage of the Parkway. For ease of use, the DOQQs were grouped into 11 mosaics, each covering a section of the Parkway. At the request of the NPS, each mosaic was divided into ten tiles to allow for efficient loading on less robust computers.

For more detailed information, see Appendix 2 of 'Mapping the Natchez Trace Parkway.'</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Pixel</rasttype>
         <rowcount>5170</rowcount>
         <colcount>47698</colcount>
         <vrtcount>1</vrtcount>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <gridsys>
               <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
               <utm>
                  <utmzone>15</utmzone>
                  <transmer>
                     <sfctrmer>0.999600</sfctrmer>
                     <longcm>-93.000000</longcm>
                     <latprjo>0.000000</latprjo>
                     <feast>500000.000000</feast>
                     <fnorth>0.000000</fnorth>
                  </transmer>
               </utm>
            </gridsys>
            <planci>
               <plance>row and column</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>1</absres>
                  <ordres>1</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>meters</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>D_WGS_1984</horizdn>
            <ellips>WGS_1984</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.257224</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</cntorg>
               <cntper>Elijah W. Ramsey III, Ph.D</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Principal Investigator</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>700 Cajundome Blvd.</address>
               <city>Lafayette</city>
               <state>LA</state>
               <postal>70506-3152</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>337-266-8500</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>337-266-8841</cntfax>
            <cntemail>elijah_ramsey@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <cntinst>Additional contact: Information Services, Voice 337-266-8692, Email nwrclibrary@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>110 files are named by mosaic and tile number using the following convention: mosaic1_CIR_1.tif (Mosaic 1, Tile 1), mosaic1_CIR_2.tif (Mosaic 1, Tile 2), etc.</resdesc>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from the U.S. Geological Survey server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata associated with this data. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
      <custom>For data requests, contact the U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center directly.</custom>
      <techpreq>Adequate computer capability is the only technical prerequisite for viewing data in digital form.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20120125</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Metadata Coordinator</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>700 Cajundome Blvd</address>
               <city>Lafayette</city>
               <state>LA</state>
               <postal>70506</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>337-266-8500</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>337-266-8841</cntfax>
            <cntinst>Additional contact: Information Services, Voice 337-266-8692, Email nwrclibrary@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <metac>There are no access limitations on acquiring the metadata document. Metadata can be accessed through the U.S. Geological Survey Metadata Clearinghouse.</metac>
      <metuc>Acknowledgement of the U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center as the metadata source would be appreciated. Please cite the original metadata when using portions of the record to create a similar record for slightly altered data for reprojection or subsetting.

Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
