<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Amina Rangoonwala (Five Rivers Services, LLC at U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
            <origin>Terri Bannister (Five Rivers Services, LLC at U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
            <origin>Elijah W. Ramsey III, Ph.D (U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
            <pubdate>2011</pubdate>
            <title>Mapping Landcover of the Natchez Trace Parkway 2004-2005</title>
            <geoform>raster digital data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>2011-1276</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Lafayette, LA</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2011/1276/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This dataset consists of a map depicting the landcover of the Natchez Trace Parkway. The mapping output was created using mosaiced color infrared aerial photography of the Parkway. The map shows the distribution of 18 landcover classes based on the National Vegetation Classification Standard.  Ground-based vegetation classification was provided by the National Park Service (NPS). The mapping output delineates grasses, road-developed areas, scrub-shrub, shrubland, plantation, water bodies, areas of white oak, oak, pine-oak, pine-cedar, pine-sweetgum, sweetgum (including sweetgum-oak), scattered trees, swamp forest, irregular classes, aquatic vegetation, invasive species, canopy gaps, and clouds.

Total mapped area includes a 100 m buffer outside the park boundary. 235 digital orthophoto quarter quadrangles (DOQQs) were required to cover the entire 715 km long Parkway. For ease of use, the DOQQs were grouped into 11 mosaics, each covering a section of the Parkway. At the request of the NPS, each mosaic was divided into ten tiles to allow for efficient loading on less robust computers.</abstract>
         <purpose>The purpose of this dataset is to provide an accurate depiction of the Natchez Trace Parkway landscape using the National Vegetation Classification Standard. This map is part of the USGS-NPS Vegetation Characterization Program, a cooperative effort by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and the National Park Service (NPS), to classify, describe, and map vegetation communities in more than 280 national park units across the United States. This landmark program is both the first to provide national-scale descriptions of vegetation for a Federal agency and the first to create national vegetation standards for its data products. The vegetation mapping program is an important part of the NPS Inventory and Monitoring Program, a long-term effort to develop baseline data for all national park units that have a natural resource component. For more information visit the Vegetation Inventory Program (VIP) website at: http://science.nature.nps.gov/im/inventory/veg/index.cfm.</purpose>
         <supplinf>The following is a list of the digital orthophoto quarter quadrangles (DOQQs) for each mosaic: 

Mosaic 1 (Mississippi - Zone 15) - Natchez (NE, SE), Washington (NE, NW, SE, SW), Pine Ridge (SE), Cranfield (NW), Church Hill (NE, NW, SE, SW), Rodney (SE, SW), Lorman (NE, NW, SW), Red Lick (NW), Widows Creek (NE, SE), Port Gibson (NE, NW, SW), Willows (SE, SW), and Hermanville (NW). 

Mosaic 2 (Mississippi - Zone 15; this mosaic has been divided into Mosaic 2 South and Mosaic 2 North) - Carlisle (NE, NW, SE, SW), Utica West (NW), Big Black (SE), Cayuga (SE, NE, SW), Learned (NE, NW, SW), Edwards (SE), Terry NW (NW), Raymond (NE, SE, SW), Clinton (NE, NW, SW), Pocahontas (SE, SW), Jackson (NW), Ridgeland (NE, NW, SE, SW), Madison (NE, NW, SE, SW), and Canton (SE). 

Mosaic 3 South (Mississippi - Zone 16) - Goshen Springs (NW), Shoccoe (NE, NW, SE, SW), Sharon SE (NE, NW, SW), Farmhaven (NE, SE, SW), Ofahoma (NE, NW, SE, SW), Thomastown (NE, NW, SE, SW), Conway (NW), Joseph (NE, SE), Singleton (NW, SW), Kosciusko (NE, NW, SE, SW), McAdams (SE), Ethel North (NE, NW, SE,SW), Ethel South (NW), and Kosciusko NE (SE). 

Mosaic 3 North (Mississippi - Zone 16) - French Camp (NE, SE, SW), Weir (NE, NW, SW), Tomnolen (NE, SE, SW), Reform (NE, NW, SW), Sapa (NE, SE, SW), Maben (NE, NW, SW), Mantee (NE, NW, SE, SW), Montpelier (NW), Woodland (NE, SE), and Sparta (NE, NW, SW). 

Mosaic 4 South (Mississippi - Zone 16) - Houston East (NE, NW, SE, SW), Troy (NE, SE), Troy SE (NE, NW, SW), Bissell (NE, NW, SE, SW), Verona (NW), Sherman (NE, SE), and Tupelo (NE, NW, SW). 

Mosaic 4 North (Mississippi - Zone 16) - Tupelo (NE, NW, SW), Guntown (NE, SE, SW), Ratliff (NE, NW, SE, SW), Kirkville (NE, NW, SW), Marietta (SE), Fulton NE (NE, NW), Paden SE (NE, SE, SW), Belmont (NE, NW, SW), and Tishomingo (SE, SW). 

Mosaic 5 South (Alabama - Zone 16) - Bishop (NE, NW, SE, SW), Margerum (NE, SE), Barton (NW), Cherokee (NE, NW, SE, SW), Wright (SE), Sinking Creek (NW), Threet (NE, NW, SE, SW), and Pleasant Site (NW). 

Mosaic 5 North (Tennessee - Zone 16) - Cypress Inn (NE, NW, SE, SW), Westpoint (NW), Whitten (NW), Three Churches (NE, SE), Collinwood (NE, NW, SW), Waynesboro East (SE, SW), and Ovilla (NE, NW, SE, SW). 

Mosaic 6 (Tennessee - Zone 16) - Riverside (NE, SE, SW), Henryville (NE, NW, SW), Gordonsburg (NE, NW, SE, SW), Sunrise (SE), Mount Joy (NW), Greensfield Bend (NE, NW, SE, SW), and Williamsport (NE, NW, SW). 

Mosaic 7 (Tennessee - Zone 16) - Primm Springs (NE, NW, SE, SW), Theta (NE, NW, SE, SW), Fairview (NE, SE, SW), Leipers Fork (NW), Kingston Springs (SE), and Bellevue (SW).</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>2011</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-91.370359</westbc>
            <eastbc>-86.964290</eastbc>
            <northbc>36.176145</northbc>
            <southbc>31.430989</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>imagery</themekey>
            <themekey>raster data</themekey>
            <themekey>landcover</themekey>
            <themekey>National Vegetation Classification Standard</themekey>
            <themekey>land use</themekey>
            <themekey>NVCS</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>imageryBaseMapsEarthCover</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>None</placekt>
            <placekey>Mississippi</placekey>
            <placekey>Southeast US</placekey>
            <placekey>Natchez Trace</placekey>
            <placekey>Natchez Trace Parkway</placekey>
            <placekey>Alabama</placekey>
            <placekey>Tennessee</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
            <placekey>State of Mississippi</placekey>
            <placekey>State of Louisiana</placekey>
            <placekey>State of Alabama</placekey>
            <placekey>State of Tennessee</placekey>
            <placekey>Adams County</placekey>
            <placekey>Tishomingo County</placekey>
            <placekey>Jefferson County</placekey>
            <placekey>Claiborne County</placekey>
            <placekey>Hinds County</placekey>
            <placekey>Madison County</placekey>
            <placekey>Leake County</placekey>
            <placekey>Attala County</placekey>
            <placekey>Choctaw County</placekey>
            <placekey>Webster County</placekey>
            <placekey>Chickasaw County</placekey>
            <placekey>Pontotoc County</placekey>
            <placekey>Lee County</placekey>
            <placekey>Itawamba County</placekey>
            <placekey>Prentiss County</placekey>
            <placekey>Colbert County</placekey>
            <placekey>Lauderdale County</placekey>
            <placekey>Wayne County</placekey>
            <placekey>Lawrence County</placekey>
            <placekey>Lewis County</placekey>
            <placekey>Natchez Trace Parkway</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from the U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center and not indirectly through other sources which may have been changed in some way. The distributor makes no claim as to the data's suitability for other purposes.</accconst>
      <useconst>Acknowledgement of the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), National Wetlands Research Center (NWRC) as a data source would be appreciated in products developed from these data. Such acknowledgement as is standard for citation and legal practices for data sources is expected by users of these data. Sharing new data layers developed directly from these data would be appreciated by the USGS NWRC staff. Users should be aware that comparison with other datasets for the same area from other time periods may be inaccurate because of inconsistencies resulting from changes in mapping conventions, data collection procedures, and computer processes over time. The distributor shall not be liable for improper or incorrect use of these data, based on the description of appropriate/inappropriate uses described in this metadata document. These data are not legal documents and are not to be used as such.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</cntorg>
               <cntper>Elijah W. Ramsey III, Ph.D</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Principal Investigator</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>700 Cajundome Blvd</address>
               <city>Lafayette</city>
               <state>LA</state>
               <postal>70506-3152</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>337-266-8500</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>337-266-8841</cntfax>
            <cntemail>elijah_ramsey@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <cntinst>Additional contact: Information Services, Voice 337-266-8692, Email nwrclibrary@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.3000</native>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Gulf Coast Aerial Mapping Co., Inc.</origin>
            <pubdate>Unpublished material</pubdate>
            <title>Digital Orthoimagery for Mapping the Natchez Trace Parkway 2004</title>
            <geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Amina Rangoonwala (Five Rivers Services, LLC at U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                  <origin>Terri Bannister (Five Rivers Services, LLC at U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                  <origin>Elijah W. Ramsey III, Ph.D (U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                  <pubdate>2011</pubdate>
                  <title>Mapping the Natchez Trace Parkway</title>
                  <geoform>report</geoform>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
                     <issue>2011-1276</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Lafayette, LA</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2011/1276/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>National Vegetation Classification data compiled by the National Park Service (NPS) at ground sites throughout the Natchez Trace Parkway were used to assign the class descriptors in the landcover classifications.  A minimum of 30 independent accuracy assessment points per landcover was desired; however, this was not reached for all landcover classes.  Further, ground sites were often sparse in regions of the Parkway.  The lack of an adequate number of sites per class and the sparseness of the sites prevented the creation of two assessment sets; one for assigning class and one for accuracy assessment.  Because of this, classification accuracy assessments used the same NPS data to assign class descriptors.  The overall accuracy of the landcover classes was estimated to be 74%.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Not applicable</logic>
      <complete>Data are complete as possible</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>The accuracy of the horizontal positions meets the U.S. Geological Survey National Mapping standard.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Gulf Coast Aerial Mapping Co., Inc.</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unpublished material</pubdate>
                  <title>Digital Orthoimagery for Mapping the Natchez Trace Parkway 2004</title>
                  <geoform>raster digital data</geoform>
                  <lworkcit>
                     <citeinfo>
                        <origin>Amina Rangoonwala (Five Rivers Services, LLC at U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                        <origin>Terri Bannister (Five Rivers Services, LLC at U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                        <origin>Elijah W. Ramsey III, Ph.D (U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                        <pubdate>2011</pubdate>
                        <title>Mapping the Natchez Trace Parkway</title>
                        <geoform>report</geoform>
                        <serinfo>
                           <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
                           <issue>2011-1276</issue>
                        </serinfo>
                        <pubinfo>
                           <pubplace>Lafayette, LA</pubplace>
                           <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</publish>
                        </pubinfo>
                        <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2011/1276/</onlink>
                     </citeinfo>
                  </lworkcit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>digital database file</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <mdattim>
                     <sngdate>
                        <caldate>20040929</caldate>
                     </sngdate>
                     <sngdate>
                        <caldate>20040930</caldate>
                     </sngdate>
                     <sngdate>
                        <caldate>20041006</caldate>
                     </sngdate>
                     <sngdate>
                        <caldate>20041015</caldate>
                     </sngdate>
                  </mdattim>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>DOQQs</srccitea>
            <srccontr>The primary data source for the mosaiced imagery</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>National Park Service</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unpublished material</pubdate>
                  <title>Field Site Catalog</title>
                  <geoform>tabular digital data</geoform>
                  <lworkcit>
                     <citeinfo>
                        <origin>Amina Rangoonwala (Five Rivers Services, LLC at U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                        <origin>Terri Bannister (Five Rivers Services, LLC at U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                        <origin>Elijah W. Ramsey III, Ph.D (U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                        <pubdate>2011</pubdate>
                        <title>Mapping the Natchez Trace Parkway</title>
                        <geoform>report</geoform>
                        <serinfo>
                           <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
                           <issue>2011-1276</issue>
                        </serinfo>
                        <pubinfo>
                           <pubplace>Lafayette, LA</pubplace>
                           <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</publish>
                        </pubinfo>
                        <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2011/1276/</onlink>
                     </citeinfo>
                  </lworkcit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>CD-ROM</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <mdattim>
                     <sngdate>
                        <caldate>200409</caldate>
                     </sngdate>
                     <sngdate>
                        <caldate>200509</caldate>
                     </sngdate>
                  </mdattim>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>NPS field sites</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Provided the source for landcover classification</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unpublished material</pubdate>
                  <title>Filtered Digital Orthoimagery for Mapping the Natchez Trace Parkway 2004</title>
                  <geoform>raster digital data</geoform>
                  <lworkcit>
                     <citeinfo>
                        <origin>Amina Rangoonwala (Five Rivers Services, LLC at U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                        <origin>Terri Bannister (Five Rivers Services, LLC at U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                        <origin>Elijah W. Ramsey III, Ph.D (U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                        <pubdate>2011</pubdate>
                        <title>Mapping the Natchez Trace Parkway</title>
                        <geoform>report</geoform>
                        <serinfo>
                           <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
                           <issue>2011-1276</issue>
                        </serinfo>
                        <pubinfo>
                           <pubplace>Lafayette, LA</pubplace>
                           <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</publish>
                        </pubinfo>
                        <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2011/1276/</onlink>
                     </citeinfo>
                  </lworkcit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>digital database file</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <mdattim>
                     <sngdate>
                        <caldate>20040929</caldate>
                     </sngdate>
                     <sngdate>
                        <caldate>20040930</caldate>
                     </sngdate>
                     <sngdate>
                        <caldate>20041006</caldate>
                     </sngdate>
                     <sngdate>
                        <caldate>20041015</caldate>
                     </sngdate>
                  </mdattim>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Filtered DOQQs</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Filtered DOQQs used to minimize unwanted variability when classifying landcover</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unpublished material</pubdate>
                  <title>Machine-based Landcover Mapping of the Natchez Trace Parkway 2004-2005</title>
                  <geoform>raster digital data</geoform>
                  <lworkcit>
                     <citeinfo>
                        <origin>Amina Rangoonwala (Five Rivers Services, LLC at U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                        <origin>Terri Bannister (Five Rivers Services, LLC at U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                        <origin>Elijah W. Ramsey III, Ph.D (U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center)</origin>
                        <pubdate>2011</pubdate>
                        <title>Mapping the Natchez Trace Parkway</title>
                        <geoform>report</geoform>
                        <serinfo>
                           <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
                           <issue>2011-1276</issue>
                        </serinfo>
                        <pubinfo>
                           <pubplace>Lafayette, LA</pubplace>
                           <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</publish>
                        </pubinfo>
                        <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2011/1276/</onlink>
                     </citeinfo>
                  </lworkcit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>digital database file</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <rngdates>
                     <begdate>2005</begdate>
                     <enddate>2010</enddate>
                  </rngdates>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>observed</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Unsupervised classification</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Preliminary landcover classification</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>An 11 m by 25 m (average) spectral filter was applied to the DOQQs to produce a scale comparable to the 20 m by 50 m ground-plot size used by the National Park Service. This filter was applied to each of the 11 mosaic sections of the Parkway imagery. The filter minimized unwanted canopy variability (irregularly illuminated tree crowns and canopy gaps and associated shadowing) and maximized forest-stand identification.</procdesc>
            <srcused>DOQQs</srcused>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
            <srcprod>Filtered DOQQs</srcprod>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>An unsupervised classification (accomplished numerically and impartially with little human input) was performed on the eleven mosaic sections of the Parkway. This process involved aggregating the pixels into spectral groupings, or clusters, based solely on the spectral distribution present in the image. The analyst then determined the landcover identity of these spectral groups by associating the classified image data with ground reference data from the National Park Service classification and notes from field reconnaissance missions.

For more details, see the methods section in 'Mapping the Natchez Trace Parkway.'</procdesc>
            <srcused>Filtered DOQQs</srcused>
            <srcused>NPS Field Sites</srcused>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
            <srcprod>Unsupervised classification</srcprod>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The final mapping of the Parkway involved both machine processes (unsupervised classification) and human analysis (supervised classification).  As a first step, shadows, edge and gap, were isolated and replaced on the map. Steps were taken to minimize the abrupt changes that occur between mosaiced orthophotos. Cutlines were compensated for by creating masks at the borders between orthophotos and applying classification algorithms only in the masked areas. 

The modified data were classified using an unsupervised classification algorithm. Progressive clustering techniques were used to separate and group clusters with mixed identities until all possible groups had been identified.  The leftover clusters were labeled irregular classes on the map legend.  Once all possible spectrally distinct classes had been identified, the final set of classes was migrated to the next adjacent mosaic section. A single signature migration was not applied from one end of the Parkway to the other; however, a mixture of progressive mapping classifications and signature migrations were applied throughout the Parkway.

In a continued effort to generate a map product conforming to requests by the National Park Service, different filters were applied to the mapping output in order to reduce mapping artifacts, such as isolated pixel groups and ribbons. As a final step, an assessment of mapping accuracy was completed to provide an overall estimate of mapping performance. Field site observations were compared to the generated landcover map and the accuracy reported in contingency tables. Lastly, mapping outputs were then divided into 10 tiles per mosaic section at the request of the National Park Service.

For more details see the Final Mapping Classification section in 'Mapping the Natchez Trace Parkway.'</procdesc>
            <srcused>Unsupervised classification</srcused>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <indspref>Natchez Trace Parkway</indspref>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <gridsys>
               <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
               <utm>
                  <utmzone>15</utmzone>
                  <transmer>
                     <sfctrmer>0.999600</sfctrmer>
                     <longcm>-93.000000</longcm>
                     <latprjo>0.000000</latprjo>
                     <feast>500000.000000</feast>
                     <fnorth>0.000000</fnorth>
                  </transmer>
               </utm>
            </gridsys>
            <planci>
               <plance>row and column</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>1</absres>
                  <ordres>1</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>meters</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>D_WGS_1984</horizdn>
            <ellips>WGS_1984</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.257224</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>Mapped landcover</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Attributes of the mapped landcover</enttypd>
            <enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>ObjectID</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Sequential unique numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Value</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Landscape classes</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>0</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Not classified; beyond the boundary of the Parkway</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Grasslands</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Road-developed</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Scrub-shrub</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>4</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Shrubland</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>5</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Plantation</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>6</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Water</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>7</edomv>
                  <edomvd>White oak</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>8</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Oak</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>9</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Sweetgum</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>10</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Pine-oak</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>11</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Pine-cedar</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>12</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Pine-sweetgum</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>13</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Scattered trees</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>14</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Swamp forest</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>15</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Irregular classes</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>16</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Aquatic vegetation</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>17</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Invasive species</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>18</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Gaps</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>19</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Clouds</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>20-255 are default values not used in the classification</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Red</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Intensity of red light</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Intensity of red light from 0 (none) to 1 (most intense) with fractional values in between</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Green</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Intensity of green light</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Intensity of green light from 0 (none) to 1 (most intense) with fractional values in between</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Blue</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Intensity of blue light</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Intensity of blue light from 0 (none) to 1 (most intense) with fractional values in between</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</cntorg>
               <cntper>Elijah W. Ramsey III, Ph.D</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Principal Investigator</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>700 Cajundome Blvd.</address>
               <city>Lafayette</city>
               <state>LA</state>
               <postal>70506-3152</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>337-266-8500</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>337-266-8841</cntfax>
            <cntemail>elijah_ramsey@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <cntinst>Additional contact: Information Services, Voice 337-266-8692, Email nwrclibrary@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>110 files are named by mosaic and tile number using the following convention: mosaic1_CLF_1.tif (Mosaic 1, Tile 1), mosaic1_CLF_2.tif (Mosaic 1, Tile 2), etc.</resdesc>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from the U.S. Geological Survey server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata associated with this data. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
      <custom>For data requests, contact the U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center directly.</custom>
      <techpreq>Adequate computer capability is the only technical prerequisite for viewing data in digital form.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20120125</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Metadata Coordinator</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>700 Cajundome Blvd.</address>
               <city>Lafayette</city>
               <state>LA</state>
               <postal>70506-3152</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>337-266-8500</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>337-266-8841</cntfax>
            <cntemail>nwrclibrary@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <cntinst>Additional contact: Information Services, Voice 337-266-8692, Email nwrclibrary@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <metac>There are no access limitations on acquiring the metadata document. Metadata can be accessed through the U.S. Geological Survey Metadata Clearinghouse.</metac>
      <metuc>Acknowledgement of the U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center as the metadata source would be appreciated. Please cite the original metadata when using portions of the record to create a similar record for slightly altered data for reprojection or subsetting.

Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
