<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Rexstad, Eric and Kenneth Burnham</origin>
            <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
            <title>CAPTURE- computes estimates of capture probability and population size for ''closed'' population capture-recapture data</title>
            <geoform>tools software</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Laurel, Maryland</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software.html</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The CAPTURE Program computes estimates of capture probability and population size for ''closed'' population capture-recapture data. Estimation of abundance produces an estimate of the number of individuals in the population at risk of capture.  Point estimates along with 95% confidence intervals are produced.</abstract>
         <purpose>The program CAPTURE consists of two executable components: an analytical component that performs abundance and density estimation from information provided by the user, and a new component allowing easy data entry.</purpose>
         <supplinf>Information for this metadata was taken from http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software/doc/capture/captframe.html.  (previous geoform was 'software')</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>Unknown</update>
      </status>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>abundance estimation</themekey>
            <themekey>density estimation</themekey>
            <themekey>simulation</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <taxonomy>
         <keywtax>
            <taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
            <taxonkey>animal</taxonkey>
         </keywtax>
         <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Animal</taxonrv>
         </taxoncl>
      </taxonomy>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Eric Rexstad</cntper>
               <cntorg>Institute of Arctic Biology and Department of Biology and Wildlife</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>211 Irving Building</address>
               <city>Fairbanks</city>
               <state>Alaska</state>
               <postal>99775-0180</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>907-474-7159</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>ffear@uaf.edu</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>Funding for this work was provided by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service Region 6 Enhancement Program through the Rocky Mountain Arsenal. Thanks to Gary White and David Anderson for advice and comments on computer coding and this users guide.</datacred>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Eric Rexstad and Kenneth Burnham, Colorado Cooperative Fish &amp; Wildlife Research Unit, Colorado State University, Fort Collins, Colorado.</origin>
            <pubdate>1991</pubdate>
            <title>User's Guide for Interactive Program CAPTURE</title>
            <geoform>online publication</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Fort Collins, Colorado</pubplace>
               <publish>Colorado State University</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software/doc/capture/captframe.html</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>White, G.C., K.P. Burnham, D.L. Otis, and D.R. Anderson</origin>
            <pubdate>1978</pubdate>
            <title>User's Manual for Program CAPTURE</title>
            <geoform>Book</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Logan, Utah</pubplace>
               <publish>Utah State University Press</publish>
            </pubinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>Problems have been known to exist with the confidence interval estimation of N.  Confidence interval calculations for all estimators have been revamped to attempt to remedy some of these problems.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>not applicable</logic>
      <complete>Revisions were made to the original version of CAPTURE and discussed in the User's Guide for Interactive Program CAPTURE.</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>At http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software/doc/capture/capture.htm there is an in depth discussion of revisions to Capture including new confidence interval estimators.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>James E. Hines</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>11510 American Holly Dr. #201</address>
               <city>Laurel</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20708-4017</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5661</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>Jim_Hines@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>The distribution disk contains the following files: File-Description, 2CAPTURE.EXE - Interactive front-end data entry program, CAPTURE.EXE-Abundance and density estimation program. LIST.COM-Shareware file scanner, HELPT.TXT-Narrative for interactive help (Can be modified by user with ASCII word processor), EXAMPLES- Input file contain examples from Otis et al. (1978), EDWARD.CAP - Input file used in this guide.</resdesc>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a U.S. Geological Survey server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data.  The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ZIP</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software.html</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None if available online.</fees>
         <ordering>The FTP server is located at ftp://pwrcftpr.er.usgs.gov/research. This should have no effect on downloading files. If you have trouble, please let the distributor know. The programs are stored as "zip" archives. Most of the zip files contain both the source code (usually FORTRAN) and IBM-PC compatible executable files. If you need an unzipping program, you can download a free Windows unzipper [PowerArc] or a free MSDOS unzipper [unzip.exe].</ordering>
      </stdorder>
      <techpreq>These programs are designed to run on any IBM-PC compatible computers. Monochrome and color displays are supported. To speed execution, CAPTURE has been compiled (using the Ryan-McFarland FORTRAN compiler) using the capability of a numeric coprocessor (Intel 80x87 chip). If this chip is not present in the user's computer, CAPTURE will generate an Error 4001 message. Another requirement of the user's computer is adequate memory availability. After loading all memory-resident programs (TSRs, network BIOS, etc.), the user's computer must have approximately 540Kb of available memory to be able to use 2CAPTURE in concert with CAPTURE. Both programs must be resident in memory simultaneously and CAPTURE is approximately 430Kb in size. and 2CAPTURE is 110Kb in size.  The maximum size of analysis problem that can be handled by CAPTURE in this release is 18 capture occasions, 8 nested grids for density estimation, and 1000 animals in simulation experiments. If the user wishes to exceed any of these limitations, CAPTURE must be recompiled after making the requisite modifications to the file PARMTR.INC. Increasing any of these limits will increase the size of the program, necessitating even greater memory requirements.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20020329</metd>
      <metfrd>20030329</metfrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
               <cntorg>Science Systems and Applications, Inc.</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Metadata specialist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>10210 Greenbelt Road, Suite 500</address>
               <city>Lanham</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20706</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 867-2080</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301-867-2149.</cntfax>
            <cntemail>solomon@gcmd.nasa.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
      <metac>none</metac>
      <metuc>none</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
