<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Brownie, Cavell, North Carolina State University; David R. Anderson, Colorado Cooperative Fish and Wildlife Research Unit, Colorado State University; Kenneth P. Burnham, Department of Statistics, North Carolina State University; Douglas S. Robson, Biometrics Unit, Cornell University</origin>
            <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
            <title>BROWNIE- program to estimate survival and recovery rates for two age classes from band-recovery data</title>
            <geoform>tools software</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Laurel, Maryland</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software.html</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The calculation of the various point estimates and their associated standard errors and covariances and tests of hypotheses is a laborious task, even for small sets of banding and recovery data.  The computational requirements are large when the Maximum Likelihood equations must be solved numerically.  Rounding errors can become significant and mathematical errors are nearly unavoidable if the calculations are performed by hand.  To alleviate these problems, two comprehensive computer programs were developed to allow estimation and testing to be done inexpensively, accurately, and quickly. These are extremely powerful computer programs allowing the more sophisticated user to make ML estimates and efficient tests based on more complex models. Program BROWNIE is an old FORTRAN program to estimate survival and recovery rates for two age classes from band-recovery data. A more modern, flexible program for this type of analysis is program MARK (a Windows program written by Gary White) which is available at the following web site: http://www.cnr.colostate.edu/~gwhite/mark/mark.htm.</abstract>
         <purpose>Use of the output from these programs allows the biologist to concentrate on the interpretation of the results, rather than on the tedious and often complex calculations involved.</purpose>
         <supplinf>Information for this metadata was taken from http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software/doc/brownie.html and from http://www.cnr.colostate.edu/class_info/fw663/Brownie1985/chapter6.pdf  (previous geoform was 'software program')</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>age-specific models</themekey>
            <themekey>goodness of fit tests</themekey>
            <themekey>recovery rates</themekey>
            <themekey>survival rates</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <taxonomy>
         <keywtax>
            <taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
            <taxonkey>birds</taxonkey>
         </keywtax>
         <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
            <taxoncl>
               <taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
               <taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
               <taxoncl>
                  <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
                  <taxonrv>Birds</taxonrv>
               </taxoncl>
            </taxoncl>
         </taxoncl>
      </taxonomy>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Brownie, Cavell</cntper>
               <cntorg>North Carolina University, Department of Statistics</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <city>Raleigh</city>
               <state>North Carolina</state>
               <postal>27695-8203</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(919) 515-1935</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(919) 515-1169</cntfax>
            <cntemail>brownie@stat.ncsu.edu</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Brownie, Cavell, David R. Anderson, Kenneth P. Burnham, Douglas S. Robson</origin>
            <pubdate>1985</pubdate>
            <title>Statistical Inference from Band Recovery Data - A Handbook</title>
            <edition>Second Edition</edition>
            <geoform>Book chapter</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Resource Publication</sername>
               <issue>No. 156</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Washington, D.C.</pubplace>
               <publish>United States Department of the Interior, Fish and Wildlife Service</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.cnr.colostate.edu/class_info/fw663/Brownie1985/BrownieList.html</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>A more modern Windows95 program, MARK (written by G. White) is recommended instead of BROWNIE.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>not applicable</logic>
      <complete>to be added to</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Brownie allows estimation under the various age-specific models.  Goodness of fit tests and tests between these models are also computed by Brownie.  In addition, a chi-square test for differences between adult male and female recovery and survival rates is provided as an option.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>James E. Hines</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>11510 American Holly Dr. #201</address>
               <city>Laurel</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20708-4017</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5661</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>Jim_Hines@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a U.S. Geological Survey server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data.  The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ZIP</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software.html</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None, if available online</fees>
         <ordering>The FTP server is located at ftp://pwrcftpr.er.usgs.gov/research. This should have no effect on downloading files. If you have trouble, please let the distributor know. The programs are stored as "zip" archives. Most of the zip files contain both the source code (usually FORTRAN) and IBM-PC compatible executable files. If you need an unzipping program, you can download a free Windows unzipper [PowerArc] or a free MSDOS unzipper [unzip.exe].</ordering>
      </stdorder>
      <techpreq>The Brownie Computer program is written in Fortran 77 and designed to be run on nearly any modern computer.  Brownie requires a machine with 256k bytes of memory and a FORTRAN 77 compiler.  All mainframe computers satisfy these requirements.  Within the past year or two, many desktop microcomputers have achieved these capabilities (e.g. The IBM PC class and various compatible machines).</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20020331</metd>
      <metfrd>20030331</metfrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
               <cntorg>Science Systems and Applications, Inc.</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Metadata specialist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>10210 Greenbelt Road, Suite 500</address>
               <city>Lanham</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20706</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 867-2080</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301-867-2149.</cntfax>
            <cntemail>solomon@gcmd.nasa.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
      <metac>none</metac>
      <metuc>none</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
