<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Gary White, Colorado State University</origin>
            <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
            <title>MARK- provides parameter estimates from marked animals when they are re-encountered at a later time</title>
            <geoform>tools software</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Fort Collins, Colorado</pubplace>
               <publish>Colorado State University</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.cnr.colostate.edu/~gwhite/mark/mark.htm</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>Program MARK provides parameter estimates from marked animals when they are re-encountered at a later time.  Re- encounters can be from dead recoveries (e.g., the animal is harvested), live recaptures (e.g. the animal is re-trapped or re-sighted), radio tracking, or from some combination of these sources of re-encounters.  The time intervals between re-encounters do not have to be equal, but are assumed to be 1 time unit if not specified.  More than one attribute group of animals can be modeled, e.g., treatment and control animals, and covariates specific to the group or the individual animal can be used.  The basic input to program MARK is the encounter history for each animal.  MARK can also provide estimates of population size for closed populations. Capture (p) and re-capture (c) probabilities for closed models can be modeled by attribute groups, and as a function of time, but not as a function of individual-specific covariates. The database is viewed and manipulated in a Results Browser window.  Summaries available from the Results Browser window include viewing and printing model output (estimates, standard errors, and goodness-of-fit tests), deviance residuals from the model (including graphics and point and click capability to view the encounter history responsible for a particular residual), likelihood ratio and analysis of deviance (ANODEV) between models, and adjustments for over dispersion. Models can also be retrieved and modified to create additional models. These capabilities are implemented in a Microsoft Windows 95 interface.  Context-sensitive help screens are available with Help click buttons and the F1 key. The Shift-F1 key can also be used to investigate the function of a particular control or menu item. Help screens include hypertext links to other help screens, with the intent to provide all the necessary program documentation on-line with the Help System.  The theory and methods used in Program MARK are described in more detail in an ''electronic book''.  Sixteen different parameterizations of encounter data are provided in Program MARK.</abstract>
         <purpose>Program MARK is a Windows-based software application developed by Gary White (Colorado State University) for the  analysis of data from marked individuals. The motivation for developing Program MARK was to bring a common interface to the problem of parameter estimation. Marked animals can be re-encountered as either alive or dead, in a variety of experimental frameworks. Prior to MARK, no program combined the estimation of survival from both live and dead  re-encounters.</purpose>
         <supplinf>The information for this metadata was taken from http://www.cnr.colostate.edu/~gwhite/mark/mark.htm.  (previous geoform was 'software')</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>analysis of data from marked individuals</themekey>
            <themekey>parameter estimates</themekey>
            <themekey>program</themekey>
            <themekey>dead recoveries</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <taxonomy>
         <keywtax>
            <taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
            <taxonkey>animals</taxonkey>
         </keywtax>
         <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Animal</taxonrv>
         </taxoncl>
      </taxonomy>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Gary White</cntper>
               <cntorg>Colorado State University</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
               <address>Colorado State University</address>
               <city>Fort Collins</city>
               <state>CO</state>
               <postal>80521</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(970) 491-6678</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(970) 491-5091</cntfax>
            <cntemail>gwhite@cnr.colostate.edu</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Evan Cooch and Gary White</origin>
            <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
            <title>Program Mark, A Gentle Introduction</title>
            <geoform>Online Document</geoform>
            <onlink>http://www.phidot.org/software/mark/docs/book/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>The Mark program is a modern flexible program to estimate survival and recovery rates from band-recovery data.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>not applicable</logic>
      <complete>unknown</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Parameters can be constrained to be the same across re-encounter occasions, or by age, or by group, using the parameter index matrix (PIM). A set of common models for screening data initially are provided, with time effects, group effects, time*group effects, and a null model of none of the above provided for each parameter. Besides the logit function to link the design matrix to the parameters of the model, other link functions include the log-log, complimentary log-log, sine, log, and identity.  Program MARK computes the estimates of model parameters via numerical maximum likelihood techniques. The FORTRAN program that does this computation also determines numerically the number of parameters that are estimable in the model, and reports its guess of one parameter that is not estimable if one or more parameters are not estimable.  The number of estimable parameters is used to compute the quasi-likelihood AIC value (QAICc) for the model. Outputs for various models that the user has built (fit) are stored in a database, known as the Results Database. The input data are also stored in this database, making it a complete description of the model building process.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>James E. Hines</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>11510 American Holly Dr. #201</address>
               <city>Laurel</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20708-4017</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5661</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>Jim_Hines@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a U.S. Geological Survey server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data.  The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ZIP</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software.html</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None if available online.</fees>
         <ordering>The FTP server is located at ftp://pwrcftpr.er.usgs.gov/research. This should have no effect on downloading files. If you have trouble, please let the distributor know. The programs are stored as "zip" archives. Most of the zip files contain both the source code (usually FORTRAN) and IBM-PC compatible executable files. If you need an unzipping program, you can download a free Windows unzipper [PowerArc] or a free MSDOS unzipper [unzip.exe].</ordering>
      </stdorder>
      <techpreq>Mark is a Windows 95, 98, or NT program.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20020329</metd>
      <metfrd>20030329</metfrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
               <cntorg>Science Systems and Applications, Inc.</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Metadata specialist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>10210 Greenbelt Road, Suite 500</address>
               <city>Lanham</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20706</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 867-2080</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301-867-2149.</cntfax>
            <cntemail>solomon@gcmd.nasa.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
      <metac>none</metac>
      <metuc>none</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
