<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>James E. Hines</origin>
            <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
            <title>RDSURVIV- computes parameter estimates of survival and capture
probability and temporary emigration using models described in ''Estimating Temporary Emigration using Capture-recapture Data with Pollock's Robust''</title>
            <geoform>tools software</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Laurel, Maryland</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division, Patuxent Wildlife Research Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>
Program RDSURVIV (Robust-Design-SURVIVal analysis) computes parameter estimates of survival and capture
probability and temporary emigration using models described in ''Estimating Temporary Emigration using Capture-recapture Data with Pollock's Robust'' (Kendall et. al., 1997). Actually, RDSURVIV is a specially modified version of Dr. G. White's program SURVIV (White, 1983) which incorporates the robust-design models. With this program and it's companion program, CNVRDSRV, users are able to get parameter estimates for these complex models from capture-history data without having to specify the cell probabilities. This program/method should be used in cases where a significant portion of the sampled population is unavailable for capture during some of the sampling periods. Ignoring the situation by using standard open model Jolly-Seber analysis will result in biased estimates of population size and capture probability. For example, if the trapping area only allows the capture of breeders, then the animals which are non-breeders in a particular sample are ''temporary emigrants'' for that sample since their probability of capture is zero.
</abstract>
         <purpose>RDSURVIV is intended to be used in a situation where the sampling experiment consists of a combination of both closed" and "open" model design. Under the "closed" part of the design, animals are captured, tagged and released repeatedly over a short period of time. It is called "closed" because it is assumed that the samples are taken over such a short period of time that the population is "closed" to any type of additions or deletions to the population (ie., the population size is fixed). Under the "open" part of the design, the "closed" type samples are repeated after a period of time long enough to allow additions and deletions to the population. In the program and documentation, samples taken during the "open" part of the experiment are called "primary" or "major" sampling periods. Sampling occasions within the primary periods where the population is assumed closed are called "secondary" or "minor" sampling periods. An example of this design is one where small mammals are captured on the first five days of each month for ten months. Each day would be a secondary period, and each group of five days of the month would be considered a primary period. We would expect that there would be almost no change in the population over the five days of the secondary periods, but there would be changes between months (primary periods).</purpose>
         <supplinf>The information for this metadata was taken from http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software/doc/rdsurv.html.  (previous geoform was 'software')</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>capture probability</themekey>
            <themekey>survival probability</themekey>
            <themekey>temporary emigration</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <taxonomy>
         <keywtax>
            <taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
            <taxonkey>animal</taxonkey>
         </keywtax>
         <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Animal</taxonrv>
         </taxoncl>
      </taxonomy>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Gary White</cntper>
               <cntorg>Colorado State University</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
               <address>Colorado State University</address>
               <city>Fort Collins</city>
               <state>CO</state>
               <postal>80521</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(970) 491-6678</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(970) 491-5091</cntfax>
            <cntemail>gwhite@cnr.colostate.edu</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Kendall, W.L., J.D. Nichols, and J.E. Hines.</origin>
            <pubdate>1997</pubdate>
            <title>Estimating Temporary Emigration and Breeding Porportions using Capture-Recapture data with Pollock's Robust Design</title>
            <geoform>Journal article</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Ecology</sername>
               <issue>78</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <othercit>pp. 563-578</othercit>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Lindberg, M. S., W. L. Kendall, J. E. Hines, and M. G. Anderson</origin>
            <pubdate>2001</pubdate>
            <title>Combining band recovery data and Pollock's robust design to model temporary and permanent emigration.</title>
            <geoform>Journal article</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Biometrics</sername>
               <issue>57:273-281.</issue>
            </serinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>not applicable</logic>
      <complete>RDSURVIV is intended to be used in a situation where the sampling experiment consists of a combination of both "closed" and "open" model design.</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Output from RDSURVIV includes survival probability estimates, capture probability estimates, estimates of the proportion of temporary emigrants, goodness-of-fit tests, and likelihood-ratio tests. Estimates may be computed under the "Markovian temporary emigration" models or the "Random temporary emigration" models. The Markovian models assume that probability of an animal temporarily emigrating depends on weather the animal was a temporary emigrant in the previous sampling occasion. "Random emigration models assume that the probability of an animal temporarily emigrating does not depend on weather the animal was a temporary emigrant in the previous sampling occasion.  By default, several models are generated. The names of the models are combinations of the names used by program CAPTURE for closed models, and a commonly used scheme for open models used by programs MARK and SURGE.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>James E. Hines</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>11510 American Holly Dr. #201</address>
               <city>Laurel</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20708-4017</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5661</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>Jim_Hines@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a U.S. Geological Survey server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data.  The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ZIP</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software.html</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None if available online.</fees>
         <ordering>The FTP server is located at ftp://pwrcftpr.er.usgs.gov/research. This should have no effect on downloading files. If you have trouble, please let the distributor know. The programs are stored as """"zip"""" archives. Most of the zip files contain both the source code (usually FORTRAN) and IBM-PC compatible executable files. If you need an unzipping program, you can download a free Windows unzipper [PowerArc] or a free MSDOS unzipper [unzip.exe].</ordering>
      </stdorder>
      <techpreq>RDSURVIV is available for IBM-compatible PC's running Windows 3.1, 95 or NT, DOS, or OS/2. The source code for RDSURVIV is available for anyone using another operating system (unix, Macintosh).</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20020329</metd>
      <metfrd>20030329</metfrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
               <cntorg>Science Systems and Applications, Inc.</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Metadata specialist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>10210 Greenbelt Road, Suite 500</address>
               <city>Lanham</city>
               <state>Maryland</state>
               <postal>20706</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 867-2080</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301-867-2149.</cntfax>
            <cntemail>solomon@gcmd.nasa.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
      <metac>none</metac>
      <metuc>none</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
