<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>James Lowe Association of Field Ornithologists</origin>
            <pubdate>1997</pubdate>
            <title>Breeding Bird Census (BBC)</title>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Journal of Field Ornithology</sername>
               <issue>unknown</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <othercit>
This metadata file can be found at:
ftp://cameron.cr.usgs.gov/pub/nbii_metadata/brdpwrc0007.txt
(text format)
and
ftp://cameron.cr.usgs.gov/pub/nbii_metadata/brdpwrc0007.html
(HTML format)
and
ftp://cameron.cr.usgs.gov/pub/nbii_metadata/brdpwrc0007.sgml
(SGML format).
</othercit>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>
Recognizing the importance of long-term studies for improving our
understanding of changes in distribution and abundance patterns of
avian communities, the former U.S. Bureau of Biological Survey
initiated the concept of a Breeding Bird Census (BBC) in 1914. These
censuses were initially administered by the Biological Survey into the
1920s. Between 1937- 1984, the National Audubon Society sponsored the
program and published the annual results in American Birds and its
predecessor publications. Between 1985-1993, the program was administered
by the Cornell Laboritory of Ornithology. Since 1993, the BBC has been
administered by the Association of Field Ornithologists.  The results
were not published for several years during the 1980s, but have appeared
as a supplement to the Journal of Field Ornithology during the 1990s.
</abstract>
         <purpose>
The Breeding Bird Census program is based on individual study plots
established within a single habitat type. Standardized methods are
followed to collect data on the avian and vegetative communities. Over
a period of years, these data provide insight into the changes
occurring in the breeding avifaunas within these communities.
An under-utilized database, the full potential of the BBC remains to
be explored. Only a relatively small number of studies have been
published using BBC data, and most of these studies have shown
long-term trends of species at individual plots or at a selected group
of plots (see bibliography below for some examples). These analyses
have generally required consistent data collection over a period of
years or decades, although some studies have examined population
changes from a small number of censuses separated by 30-40+
years. While the BBC provides habitat-specific data on the composition
of bird communities, aspects of bird-habitat relationships have not
been examined using this data set.
</purpose>
         <supplinf>
BBC RESULTS The BBC results are provided as the total number of
territories for each species present in each plot during each
year. These results are also standardized as the number of territories
per 40 hectares for species with 3 or more territories on a plot. The
numbers of nests and fledglings recorded during the censuses are also
provided for each species. A list of species considered to be
"visitors" is provided separately from the list of breeding
species. In the published accounts, a remarks section provides brief
comments concerning the importance of the year-to-year changes and
long-term trends for species on the plots, as well as other
information relevant to the censuses. Portions of the BBC database
have been computerized and can be accessed via ftp.
ftp://ftp.mp1-pwrc.usgs.gov/pub/data/bbc/
1937-1983 National Audubon Society gathered breeding bird census data
1984-1987 four year hiatus
1988-1997 Association of Field Ornithologists took over
1997 Discussions about whether the Patuxent Wildlife Research Center might take
over Breeding Birds Censusx
</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>1914</begdate>
               <enddate>1997</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>
From Breeding Bird Census metadata on Bird Monitoring in America
Inventory &amp; Monitoring Pages
</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>In work</progress>
         <update>annually</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <descgeog>North America, Canada</descgeog>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>170</westbc>
            <eastbc>-50</eastbc>
            <northbc>70</northbc>
            <southbc>10</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>breeding bird census</themekey>
            <themekey>National Audubon Society</themekey>
            <themekey>Cornell Laboratory of Ornithology</themekey>
            <themekey>breeding birds</themekey>
            <themekey>territories</themekey>
            <themekey>density</themekey>
            <themekey>breeding</themekey>
            <themekey>habitats</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>North America</placekey>
            <placekey>Canada</placekey>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>Mexico</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <taxonomy>
         <taxonkey>birds</taxonkey>
         <taxoncov>
            <taxoninf>
               <kingdom>Animal</kingdom>
               <phylum>Chordata</phylum>
               <class>Aves</class>
            </taxoninf>
            <taxongen>aves, birds</taxongen>
         </taxoncov>
      </taxonomy>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Association of Field Ornithologists</cntorg>
               <cntper>James D. Lowe</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>159 Sapsucker Woods Road</address>
               <city>Ithaca</city>
               <state>New York</state>
               <postal>14850</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>607 254-2413</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>607 254-2415</cntfax>
            <cntemail>jdl6@cornell.edu</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>
National Audubon Society
Cornell Laboratory of Ornithology
</datacred>
      <native>unknown</native>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Robbins, C.S.</origin>
            <pubdate>1970</pubdate>
            <title>
Recommendations for an international standard for a
mapping method in bird census work
</title>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Aud. Field Notes</sername>
               <issue>24</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <othercit>pp. 723-726</othercit>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Williams, A.B.</origin>
            <pubdate>1936</pubdate>
            <title>The composition and dynamics of a beech-maple climax community.</title>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Ecol. Monogr.</sername>
               <issue>6</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <othercit>pp. 317-408</othercit>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>
Data is collected by volunteers of various abilities, so no
warranty is expressed or implied regarding the accuracy or
utility of the data on any system or for general or scientific
purposes.
</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>not applicable</logic>
      <complete>
The original data was collected when computer space was limited and
expensive.  Therefore from 1937-mid 1970s, only information on the top
12 species in each plot was kept. Later, other species were added back
in for the northeast region.
A number of factors could potentially limit some of the uses of BBC
data. At larger geographic scales, the most important question
concerns how representative are the BBC plots of the habitats and
avian communities in an area? Whether or not the temporal changes in
the bird communities are representative of the trends of the entire
area is also questionable. The factors used to select each site are
largely unknown, but may include ease of access, proximity to the
observer's residence, or the fact that the sites are known to be "good
birding areas". Hence, using BBC data to draw conclusions beyond the
boundaries of the individual plots may be rather tenuous.
Other factors complicate the ability to compare data from individual
plots. Minor differences in the sizes of the plots, geography, and
structure and composition of the plant communities may not be apparent
in the descriptions of the plots, yet could potentially be responsible
for major changes in the composition and trends of the bird
communities. Additionally, changes to the surrounding habitats could
also have an important influence on the trends of bird populations,
but changes to surrounding habitats are seldom described for the
individual plots.
Additional factors need to be considered when examining the data from individual
plots (Johnson 1990).
These factors may limit the utility of these data, and include:
the aperiodicity of the data from some plots
annual variation in census effort
inadequate vegetation-site description during the first census
biased estimates of population density, such as the assumption
that a singing male truly represents
a breeding pair, or under-estimating the population density if
some males were not singing regularly
failure to describe any changes occurring within or immediately
adjacent to the plots
variation in observer competency, and changes in observer
competency over time
variation in the interpretation of the census data when
preparing the spot maps
</complete>
      <lineage>
         <method>
            <methtype>field/bird counts</methtype>
            <methdesc>
The exact location of each BBC plot and the habitat studied within the
plot are at the discretion of the individual cooperator(s), although
they must meet certain requirements established by the program. No
random selection process is involved in the establishment of their
locations. Most plots are located at sites that are relatively free
from disturbance, such as parks, nature preserves, and wildlife
refuges, although a number have also been established on private
property. The continental distribution of these plots reflects
the distribution of people willing to conduct these censuses. No detailed
analysis of their geographic placement has ever been
conducted. Preliminary studies indicate that the BBC plots tend to be
grouped within a relatively small number of states and provinces
primarily in eastern North America, while there are large areas where
few censuses have ever been conducted.
The exact size and dimensions of the study plot are also at the
discretion of the cooperator(s), and may be influenced by the amount
of effort required to obtain complete censuses. However, minimal plot
sizes are recommended by the BBC of 10 hectares in closed habitats and
40 hectares in open habitats, although some plots may be smaller than
these recommendations. Most woodland plots are smaller than 30
hectares in size, while plots in open habitats may be as large as 100
hectares.
A summary of the habitats censused by the BBC has never been
prepared. However, the vast majority of BBC plots have been
established in forested communities. At the initiation of each study
plot, quantitative data are collected to describe the species
composition and vegetative structure of the community. Standard
methodologies are followed so the data are comparable between plots
(James and Shugart 1970).  Subsequent changes in the structure and
composition of the vegetative community are frequently described in
subjective narratives, although some plots will repeat the
quantitative surveys at periodic intervals.
The BBC employs the spot-mapping methodology to estimate population
densities for each species present in the study plots (Robbins
1970). This methodology has only been slightly modified since it was
initially described in detail by Williams (1936), allowing for between
plot comparisons. This methodology maps the locations of all singing
males and pairs present in the plot on different days during the
breeding season.  When these locations are combined for the entire
season, each territory can be identified with reasonable
accuracy. Assuming that each territory is occupied by a pair of that
species, the number of territories can be translated into the number
of breeding pairs on a plot during each year. A minimum of 8 visits
are normally required each breeding season to accurately map the
territories of all species. These visits should be spaced throughout
the season, including censuses during spring for species breeding
early in the year. Rules for interpreting these spot-maps are also
defined in this methodology, although these rules do not completely
eliminate all of the individual interpretation of the data.
</methdesc>
            <methcite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Robbins, C.S.</origin>
                  <pubdate>1970</pubdate>
                  <title>
Recommendations for an international standard for a
mapping method in bird census work
</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>Aud. Field Notes</sername>
                     <issue>24</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <othercit>pp. 723-726</othercit>
               </citeinfo>
            </methcite>
            <methcite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Williams, A.B.</origin>
                  <pubdate>1936</pubdate>
                  <title>The composition and dynamics of a beech-maple climax community.</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>Ecol. Monogr.</sername>
                     <issue>6</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <othercit>pp. 317-408</othercit>
               </citeinfo>
            </methcite>
         </method>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>With plot size, count all birds and derive density</procdesc>
            <procdate>Not Complete</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <indspref>Based on local reference names</indspref>
   </spdoinfo>
   <eainfo>
      <overview>
         <eaover>
Entity - birds
Associated Attributes - breeding density
</eaover>
         <eadetcit>unknown</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>
Patuxent Wildlife Research Center,
Inventory and Monitoring ,
Biological Resource Division ,
U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)
</cntorg>
               <cntper>Brett Hoover</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>12100 Beech Forest Road</address>
               <city>Laurel</city>
               <state>MD</state>
               <postal>20708-4038</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5819</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301 497-5784</cntfax>
            <cntemail>brett_hoover@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>
No warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or
utility of the data on any system or for general or scientific
purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such
warranty.  This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data
and aggregate use with other data.  It is strongly recommended that
these data are directly acquired from the Biological Resources Division (BRD)
U.S. Geological Survey and not indirectly though other sources which may have
changed the data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended that
careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file
associated with these data.  Neither the BRD nor the NASA
Global Change Master Directory shall be held liable for improper or
incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.
</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>unknown</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.mp1-pwrc.usgs.gov/birds/bbc.html</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
               <offoptn>
                  <offmedia>unknown</offmedia>
                  <recfmt>unknown</recfmt>
               </offoptn>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>unknown</fees>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>Please contact Brett Hoover in section 6.1</custom>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>1996</metd>
      <metrd>19970415</metrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Hughes STX</cntorg>
               <cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>7701 Greenbelt Rd</address>
               <city>Greenbelt</city>
               <state>MD</state>
               <postal>20770</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 441-4249</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301 441-9486</cntfax>
            <cntemail>solomon@gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>
DRAFT Content Standard for National Biological Information
Infrastructure Metadata.
</metstdn>
      <metstdv>December 1995</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
