<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Patuxent Wildlife Research Center,
Biological Resources Division,
U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)
</origin>
            <pubdate>1997</pubdate>
            <title>North American Breeding Bird Survey (BBS)</title>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Laurel, MD</pubplace>
               <publish>
Patuxent Wildlife Research Center,
Biological Resources Division,
U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)
</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>
This metadata file can be found at:
http://www1.usgs.gov/metadata/mdata/USGS_PWRC/brdpwrc0004.xml (XML format).
</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.pwrc.usgs.gov/bbs/RawData/Choose-Method.cfm</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>
The North American Breeding Bird Survey (BBS), which is coordinated by
the Biological Resources Division and Canadian Wildlife Service, is a
primary source of population trend and distribution information for
most species of North American birds. The BBS was initiated during
1966 by Chan Robbins and his associates at the Patuxent Wildlife
Research Center to monitor the populations of all breeding bird species
across the continental U.S., Canada, and Alaska.
Approximately 2200 skilled observers participate in the survey each
year.  The BBS has accumulated 30 years of data on the abundance, distribution,
and trends for more than 400 species of birds.  These
data are widely used by researchers, various federal and state
agencies, non-governmental organizations, and the general public.
Analyses of BBS data by PWRC statisticians have been instrumental in
the development of innovative approaches for analyzing trends of
wildlife populations.
</abstract>
         <purpose>
In the 1960s, chlorinated hydrocarbon pesticides and similar poisons
were widely used to control insect populations.  Pesticide spraying
not only killed insects but also killed birds, raising serious
concerns over its effects on bird population trends.  Unfortunately,
no long-term regional or continental population data were available
for most bird species, making it difficult for birders to demonstrate
declines in bird populations.
The Bird Breeding Survey has proven to be a valuable source of
information on bird population trends.  Robbins et al. (1986) provided
the first continental relative abundance maps for various songbirds
based on BBS data. When viewed at continental or regional scales,
these maps provide a reasonably good indication of the relative
abundance of species that are well sampled by the BBS.
In addition, the BBS is a good source of information on temporal
patterns in trends.  Populations of permanent resident and
short-distance migrant (birds wintering primarily in the U.S. and
Canada) species may be adversely affected by episodes of unseasonal
weather.  The extent of any declines in a particular bird population is
known after the data is analyzed.
The BBS is also a good source of geographic patterns in trends.  Few species
have consistent trends across their entire ranges, so geographic
patterns in trends are of considerable interest to anyone
concerned with the status of the continent's birds.  With the use of
a Geographic Information System, route-specific trends are smoothed to
produce geographic patterns that are not based on political boundaries
or physiographic strata.  These analyses allow identification of
regions of increase and decline.  Once these regions have been
pinpointed, researchers can undertake studies that will allow them to
identify the factors responsible for the population trends.
</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>1966</begdate>
               <enddate>Present</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>
From Breeding Bird Survey literature.
The first BBS publication was an annual summary produced in 1967.
</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>complete</progress>
         <update>updated annually and as needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <descgeog>
Continental U.S., Canada, &amp; Alaska, with spotty coverage in Alaska
and northern half of Canada.  A few routes have been recently
established in northern Mexico.
</descgeog>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-165</westbc>
            <eastbc>-50</eastbc>
            <northbc>75</northbc>
            <southbc>20</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>GCMD parameter keywords</themekt>
            <themekey>EARTH SCIENCE &gt; BIOSPHERE &gt; ZOOLOGY &gt; BIRDS</themekey>
            <themekey>EARTH SCIENCE &gt; BIOSPHERE &gt; ECOLOGICAL DYNAMICS &gt; POPULATION DYNAMICS</themekey>
            <themekey>EARTH SCIENCE &gt; BIOSPHERE &gt; ECOLOGICAL DYNAMICS &gt; ABUNDANCE &gt;</themekey>
            <themekey>Relative Abundance</themekey>
            <themekey>EARTH SCIENCE &gt; BIOSPHERE &gt; ECOLOGICAL DYNAMICS &gt; ABUNDANCE &gt;</themekey>
            <themekey>Species Abundance</themekey>
            <themekey>EARTH SCIENCE &gt; BIOSPHERE &gt; ECOLOGICAL DYNAMICS &gt; ABUNDANCE &gt;</themekey>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>Population Change</themekey>
            <themekey>abundance</themekey>
            <themekey>breeding birds</themekey>
            <themekey>breeding bird survey</themekey>
            <themekey>counts</themekey>
            <themekey>distribution</themekey>
            <themekey>estimating equation</themekey>
            <themekey>population change</themekey>
            <themekey>population trend</themekey>
            <themekey>relative abundance</themekey>
            <themekey>route-regression</themekey>
            <themekey>surveys</themekey>
            <themekey>trends</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>North America</placekey>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>Alaska</placekey>
            <placekey>Canada</placekey>
            <placekey>Mexico</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <taxonomy>
         <taxonkey>birds</taxonkey>
         <taxonkey>breeding birds</taxonkey>
         <taxoncov>
            <taxoninf>
               <kingdom>Animalia</kingdom>
               <phylum>Chordata</phylum>
               <class>Aves</class>
            </taxoninf>
            <taxongen>North American breeding birds</taxongen>
         </taxoncov>
      </taxonomy>
      <accconst>
Contact Bruce Peterjohn of the Patuxent Wildlife Research Center
Breeding Bird Office to acquire raw data.  All of the trend information
can be retrieved from BBS web site:
http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/bbs/bbs.html
</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>
Patuxent Wildlife Research Center,
Biological Resources Division,
U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)
</cntorg>
               <cntper>Bruce Peterjohn and Keith Pardieck</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>12100 Beech Forest Road</address>
               <city>Laurel</city>
               <state>MD</state>
               <postal>20708</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5841,</cntvoice>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5843</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301 497-5784</cntfax>
            <cntemail>bruce_peterjohn@usgs.gov,</cntemail>
            <cntemail>keith_pardieck@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/bbs/bbs.html</browsen>
         <browsed>North American breeding bird page</browsed>
         <browset>Internet site</browset>
      </browse>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service
U.S. Department of the Interior
</origin>
            <pubdate>1966-1990</pubdate>
            <title>North American Breeding Bird Survey Annual Summary</title>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Washington, D.C.</pubplace>
               <publish>Fish and Wildlife Service, U.S. Department of the Interior</publish>
            </pubinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Fish and Wildlife Service
U.S. Department of the Interior
</origin>
            <pubdate>1986</pubdate>
            <title>The Breeding Bird Survey: Its First Fifteen Years 1965-1979</title>
            <edition>Resource Publication 157</edition>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Washington, D.C.</pubplace>
               <publish>
Fish and Wildlife Service,
U.S. Department of the Interior
</publish>
            </pubinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Patuxent Environmental Science Center
National Biological Service
Department of the Interior
</origin>
            <pubdate>199412</pubdate>
            <title>The North American Breeding Bird Survey</title>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Journal of the American Birding Association</sername>
               <issue>26:6</issue>
            </serinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
National Biological Service
Patuxent Wildlife Research Center
</origin>
            <pubdate>1994</pubdate>
            <title>Estimating equations estimates of trends.</title>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Bird Populations</sername>
               <issue>2:23-32</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Laurel, MD</pubplace>
               <publish>Patuxent Wildlife Research Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>
In the early years, the data set had 500-600 routes.  There are now more
than 3000 routes.   These routes are checked manually and computer
edits performed.  However, when there were only 500 routes, this was
easier to accomplish.  The computer performs edits for computational
errors, species range errors.  Print outs are sent back to original
observer to verify.
</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>not applicable</logic>
      <complete>
After experimental surveys were conducted in Maryland and
Delaware in 1965, the BBS has expanded to cover the continental
United States and southern Canada.    The survey was initiated in
different years in different parts of its range.  BBS routes were
run only on routes in the United States east of the Mississippi
River and in Quebec and the maritime provinces of Canada in 1966.
In 1967, the BBS extended to the Central United States, with a few
routes in Ontario and Manitoba.  By 1968, all of the continental
United States was covered, and routes were run across southern
Canada. Routes in Alaska, Yukon, and Northwest Territories were
added during the early 1980s.
Many patterns occur in geographic coverage of the BBS.  Some
patterns occur as a consequence of logistics.  BBS routes near
human population centers tend to be consistently surveyed but
remote routes are not surveyed every year, which causes regional
variation in the efficiency of the survey (Robbins et al. 1986).
Although all States and Provinces vary in coverage over time, some
consistent regional patterns occur in BBS coverage.  Coverage in
the Northeastern United States (excluding ME) is most extensive,
with the highest density of BBS routes (up to 16 per degree block
of latitude and longitude) occurring in MD, DE, and NJ (See also
Table 1).  Routes are much less densely distributed elsewhere with
maxima of 4-5 routes / degree block in a number of states while NV
and portions of some Canadian Provinces have a minimum of 1 route
degree block. Route densities are less than 1 route / degree
block only in arctic and boreal regions. In Canada, the BBS is
largely restricted to the south, and our summary maps truncate the
range of each species to indicate the region with sufficient BBS
data.
Superimposed on the regional variation in route densities
is temporal variation in the number of routes run in many states. Most
states show a general pattern of increasing routes over time.  In
some cases, this pattern is extreme, with states such as ME having
few routes until the early 1970's, when numbers started to
increase.  Some states (e.g., UT) have had consistently low numbers
of routes over most of the survey period, while other states (VT,
SC, SD) have had periods when the number of routes decreased.
For some States and Provinces (e.g., Alaska, Yukon, PEI and NFD),
the few years routes were run clearly invalidates any trend
analyses from the data.
Efficiency of the BBS Sample
Overall sampling efficiency of the BBS for each
bird species by examining sampling attributes over the entire range
of the BBS, and categorized them as (1) not sampled by the BBS, (2)
small sample-size, (3) highly variable, or (4) low relative
abundance.   Possession of one of these attributes does not
necessarily eliminate the species from trend analyses.  These species
can be well surveyed by the BBS within portions of their
breeding range or during certain time periods.  However, long-term
regional or survey-wide trend estimates for these species should be
used with caution.  Numbers presented below were taken from an
unpublished manuscript by Sauer and Droege, and use trend
data from 1966 - 1990.
The Species not sampled by the BBS-North American bird species
that were seen on no more than 1 BBS route fall into broad
categories of northern breeders (note that Alaskan BBS routes are
not included in standard BBS analyses), tropical or Mexican
resident species, pelagic or coastal species, accidental species,
and exotics.
Small sample-size species-These species have trend estimates
with fewer than 14 degrees of freedom, which means that ([number of
routes] - [number of strata within states in which the species
occurred] &lt; 14).  The 99 species seen on few routes of the BBS fall
into several general categories, most of which are related to
breeding ranges or habitats of the species. Many northern-breeding species
and coastal colonial species are seen on some BBS routes,
but must be considered accidental occurrences on the BBS.  Many
tropical and Mexican species are seen on routes in southern Florida
and near the Mexican border.  Several species of owls and species
with northern ranges are only infrequently recorded on BBS routes.
Although some species listed by or under review for
Endangered Species status are occasionally detected on BBS routes, the BBS
provides little information of use for evaluating their population
status.  None of the BBS guilds contain a high proportion of species
with extremely low sample sizes, and overall, 20% of all species seen
on BBS routes are sampled with &lt; 14 degrees of freedom.
Highly variable species-Eighty-four species had trends with
large variances.   Several heron species, many duck species,
waterbirds, a few species with northern breeding ranges, several
warblers, some sparrow species, and some blackbirds occur in this
list, among other species.  These species can be characterized as
birds with specialized habitats or limited distributions in the BBS
range, spruce-budworm species, or colonial nesting species.
Overall, 22% of the species in the survey were in this category,
with hunted species, coniferous forest nesting species, waterfowl,
and wetland nesting species guilds having &gt; 22% of their species
with high variances.
Low relative abundance species - Ninety-five species had
rangewide average counts of &lt; 0.5 birds/route in the BBS.  This
list has similar species categories as the highly variable and low
sample size lists, including the widely distributed nocturnal
birds, rails, hawks, ducks, and species whose breeding ranges only
partially overlap with regions surveyed by the BBS.  Several species
that are widely distributed but sampled at low numbers on
the BBS occur in this list, such as Wood Ducks, American Woodcock,
and Great Horned Owl.  Overall, 20 % of the species contained in
the BBS data had low relative abundances, and the only guilds with
20 % of species in this category were the hunted and primary
cavity nesting guilds.
Overall, 204 (41%) of the 504 species we analyzed for 25-year
trends were in at least one of the categories.  The guild with the
lowest proportion of species in the lists was urban species (8%),
while hunted, wetland nesting, and waterfowl guilds had &gt; 41% of
their species in 1 of the 3 categories.
Biases in BBS analyses
Other potential biases in the BBS cannot be documented from
analysis of the survey.  These biases were discussed in the publication
(Bystrak 1981, Droege 1990), and we will only mention them
here to remind BBS users of the potential problems.  They include:
Proportion of range in the survey area-All BBS analyses
incorporate data only from BBS routes.  Analysis of survey data
cannot tell us the proportion of the individuals in a species that
breed outside the range of the survey.  Species that are recorded
only on the margins of the surveyed area are often of low sample
size or variable, but many species (e.g., Canada Goose) may have
substantial populations within the survey area.  Trends are always
specific to the areas surveyed.
Roadside biases-The BBS is a roadside survey, and a major
criticism of the survey has been that habitat changes along
roadsides may not be representative of regional habitat changes.
Trends from the BBS may therefore reflect only populations along
roads rather than regional bird population changes.
Habitat biases-Within the range of the BBS, many habitats are
not well covered, and species that specialize in those habitats are
poorly sampled.  Wetland birds and species occupying alpine tundra
habitats are examples of groups thought to be poorly represented in
the survey.
Even with all of the sampling and other biases discussed
above, the BBS represents a unique attempt at a survey of breeding
populations of birds in North America.  Enormous amounts of data
have been collected that provide the only information on regional
population trends and breeding distributions of birds.  The
challenge for the future is to maintain and augment survey effort,
and to identify and minimize deficiencies in the survey.
</complete>
      <lineage>
         <method>
            <methtype>field procedures</methtype>
            <methdesc>
The field procedures are the same as those shown in
the first Breeding Bird Survey report (Robbins and Van Velzen
1967). New scannable data forms were developed in 1997 which
replaced the old data forms.  Each observer is sent a packet
containing instructions, the route map,  scannable data forms
and a return envelope.
Each route consists of 50 3-minute stops 0.5 mile (0.8 km) apart,
and is run one morning each year, at the height of the breeding
season, starting at 0.5 h before sunrise.  In most of the United
States coverage is restricted to the month of June, but late May is
permissible in the southern States, as is early July in Canada. At
each stop the observer stands near his car and records, on prepared
forms, the total number of each bird species heard, as well as those
seen within 0.25 mile (400 m).  Sky condition, wind speed, and
temperature are recorded at the beginning and end of each route.  Each
route is confined to a single degree block and to a single State or
Province and, in most instances, to a single major physiographic region.
</methdesc>
         </method>
         <method>
            <methtype>data processing and analysis</methtype>
            <methdesc>
For each route, the observer submits the five scannable data
sheets, a comment page, and a cover page with pre-printed address
information.  The observer provides any updated address information
and the appropriate weather data on the cover page.
</methdesc>
            <methcite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Robbins and Van Velzen</origin>
                  <pubdate>1967</pubdate>
                  <title>The Breeding Bird Survey</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>Spec. Sci. Rep.-Wildlife</sername>
                     <issue>102</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>unknown</pubplace>
                     <publish>Bureau of Sport Fish and Wildlife</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </methcite>
         </method>
         <method>
            <methtype>trend analysis</methtype>
            <methdesc>
Many analyses of data from large-scale surveys such as the North
American Breeding Bird Survey have used an analytical approach called
route regression analysis.  In this analysis, trends are estimated on
individual survey routes and a composite regional trend estimate is
derived from a weighted average of the route specific trends.  This
approach has several advantages: it allows for variation in trends
among routes, it allows for the easy accommodation of route-specific
covariates in estimating these trends, and it differentially weights
route-specific trend estimates in accordance with their precision.
At the very heart of the route-regression procedure is the analytical
procedure used to estimate the trends for individual routes.
</methdesc>
            <methcite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Link, W. A. and J. R. Sauer</origin>
                  <pubdate>1994</pubdate>
                  <title>Estimating equations estimates of trends</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>Bird Populations</sername>
                     <issue>2:23-32</issue>
                  </serinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </methcite>
         </method>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
route regression analysis
Analysis of 2-year population change follows the route-regression
analysis described by Link and Sauer (1994) Route-specific change
is estimated as the ratio of counts on survey routes that were
consistently surveyed over two years.  Regional change is estimated as
a weighted average of these route estimates, with weights of relative abundance
and area of strata-within states.  The area weight is used to adjust
for regional differences in sample intensity.  Variances are estimated
through bootstrapping route estimates, and z-tests are used to assess
significance of the null hypothesis of no population change for the interval.
</procdesc>
            <srcused>Link and Sauer (1994)</srcused>
            <procdate>1990</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <indspref>Based on local reference names</indspref>
   </spdoinfo>
   <eainfo>
      <overview>
         <eaover>
Primary Entity - breeding birds and bird counts
Associated Attributes - abundance, relative abundance, counts
</eaover>
         <eadetcit>none</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>
Patuxent Wildlife Research Center,
Biological Resources Division,
U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)
</cntorg>
               <cntper>Bruce Peterjohn and Keith Pardieck</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>12100 Beech Forest Road</address>
               <city>Laurel</city>
               <state>MD</state>
               <postal>20708</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 497-5841, 497-5843</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301 497-5784</cntfax>
            <cntemail>bruce_peterjohn@usgs.gov, keith_pardieck@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>
No warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or
utility of the data on any system or for general or scientific
purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such
warranty.  This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data
and aggregate use with other data.  It is strongly recommended that
these data are directly acquired from the Biological Resources Division (BRD)
U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and not indirectly though other sources which may have
changed the data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended that
careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file
associated with these data.  Neither the BRD nor the NASA
Global Change Master Directory shall be held liable for improper or
incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.
</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>unknown</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>
To obtain trend analysis: 
http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/bbs/bbs.html
</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>
Contact Bruce Peterjohn, Keith Pardieck
Patuxent Research Center
Can be provided as text files or hard copy
</custom>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>19961021</metd>
      <metrd>199611</metrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Hughes STX</cntorg>
               <cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>7701 Greenbelt Rd</address>
               <city>Greenbelt</city>
               <state>MD</state>
               <postal>20770</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301 441-4249</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>301 441-9486</cntfax>
            <cntemail>solomon@gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>
DRAFT Content Standard for National Biological Information
Infrastructure Metadata.
</metstdn>
      <metstdv>December 1995</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
