<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Michael B. Robblee

Clinton Hittle;
Joan Browder;
Maria Criales;
John Wang
</origin>
            <pubdate>Unpublished Material</pubdate>
            <title>Empirical Studies in Support of Florida Bay and Adjacent Marine Ecosystems Restoration</title>
            <geoform>none</geoform>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/projects/index.php?project_url=emp_flbay</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The Principal Investigator participated in the Comprehensive Everglades Restoration Plan (CERP) as member of the Florida Bay Program Management Committee, as a member of the Florida Bay Florida Keys Feasibility Study team, and as a member of the RECOVER South Estuaries Sub Team</abstract>
         <purpose>
Florida Bay lies downstream of the Everglades ecosystem.  Perceived deterioration of the Everglades over the last century - and Florida Bay since the mid-1980&#x92;s - is generally viewed as linked to changes in freshwater flow and water quality associated with water management in South Florida.

The objectives of these project are broadly: 1) to develop and implement (with other agency members) a program of research to support the restoration of Florida Bay; 2) with other PDT members to develop and evaluate restoration alternatives for Florida Bay and 3) with other committee members to develop performance measures and assess restoration alternatives affecting Florida Bay, Biscayne Bay, Barnes Sound and Manatee Bay and the lower southwest coast mangrove estuaries.
</purpose>
         <supplinf>This project is no longer funded by the USGS Greater Everglades Priority Ecosystems Science Program.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>20021001</begdate>
               <enddate>20030930</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>Unknown</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-81.25</westbc>
            <eastbc>-80.125</eastbc>
            <northbc>25.33</northbc>
            <southbc>24.75</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>biota</themekey>
            <themekey>environment</themekey>
            <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
            <themekey>002</themekey>
            <themekey>007</themekey>
            <themekey>012</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>biology</themekey>
            <themekey>hydrology</themekey>
            <themekey>model</themekey>
            <themekey>pink shrimp</themekey>
            <themekey>mangroves</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1995, Countries, Dependencies, Areas of Special Sovereignty, and Their Principal Administrative Divisions,  Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS) 10-4, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>US</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>U.S. Department of Commerce, 1987, Codes for the identification of the States, the District of Columbia and the outlying areas of the United States, and associated areas (Federal Information Processing Standard 5-2): Washington, DC, NIST</placekt>
            <placekey>Florida</placekey>
            <placekey>FL</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1990, Counties and Equivalent Entities of the United States, Its Possessions, and Associated Areas, FIPS 6-3, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>Monroe County</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>USGS Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
            <placekey>Florida Bay</placekey>
            <placekey>Barnes Sound</placekey>
            <placekey>Manatee Bay</placekey>
            <placekey>Biscayne Bay</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Florida Keys</placekey>
            <placekey>Johnson Key Basin</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Michael Robblee</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>
c/o South Florida Natural Resources Center, Everglades National Park

40001 State Road 9336
</address>
               <city>Homestead</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33034</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>305 242-7832</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>305 242-7836</cntfax>
            <cntemail>mike_robblee@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>Project personnel include Andre Daniels, David Moore, Leslie James, David Kieckbusch, and Vin Difrenna</datacred>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Fourqurean, J. W.

Robblee, M. B.
</origin>
            <pubdate>1999</pubdate>
            <title>Florida Bay: a history of recent ecological changes</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Estuaries</sername>
               <issue>v. 22, n.2B</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>New York</pubplace>
               <publish>Springer New York</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.springerlink.com/content/vh24236250573557/fulltext.pdf</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Browder, J. A.</origin>
            <pubdate>1985</pubdate>
            <title>Relationship between pink shrimp production on the Tortugas and water flow patterns in the Florida Everglades</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Bulletin of Marine Science</sername>
               <issue>37</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Coral Gables, FL</pubplace>
               <publish>University of Florida Press</publish>
            </pubinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Browder, J. A.

Restrepo, V. R.;
Rice, J. K.;
Robblee, M. B.;
Zein-Eldin, A.
</origin>
            <pubdate>1999</pubdate>
            <title>Environmental influences on potential recruitment of pink shrimp, Farfantepenaeus duoraram, from Florida Bay nursery grounds</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Estuaries</sername>
               <issue>v. 22, n. 2B</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>New York, New York</pubplace>
               <publish>Springer New York</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.springerlink.com/content/j16867808145740n/fulltext.pdf</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Browder, J. A.

Moore, D.
</origin>
            <pubdate>1981</pubdate>
            <title>A new approach to determining the quantative relationship between fishery production and the flow of fresh water to estuaries</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Proceedings, National Symposium on Freshwater Inflow to Estuaries</sername>
               <issue>Vol. 1, FWS/OBS-81/04</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Washington, DC</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>R. Cross and D. Williams, editors</othercit>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Browder, J. A.</origin>
            <pubdate>1991</pubdate>
            <title>Watershed management and the importance of freshwater flow to estuaries</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Proceedings, Tampa Bay Area Scientific Information Symposium</sername>
               <issue>none</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Tampa, FL</pubplace>
               <publish>unknown</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>S. F. Treat and P. A. Clark, editors</othercit>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>not applicable</logic>
      <complete>not available</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
The research objectives can be summarized as:

1) to document long-term responses of the seagrass associated shrimp and fish community in Johnson Key Basin to environmental conditions (e.g. salinity) and changes in seagrass habitat;

2) to develop performance measures relating the fish and crustacean communities of southern Biscayne Bay to salinity and habitat and

3) to evaluate postlarval immigration (seasonal timing and abundance) to and into Florida Bay in relation to environmental conditions and habitat. The pink shrimp is a species of special interest in each of the above studies because it has been chosen as an indicator species for use in restoration of south Florida estuaries. Empirical and experimental data developed in these studies will be used to support the development of a pink shrimp landscape simulation model and restoration performance measures.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Michael Robblee</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
                     <address>
c/o South Florida Natural Resources Center, Everglades National Park

40001 State Road 9336
</address>
                     <city>Homestead</city>
                     <state>FL</state>
                     <postal>33034</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>305 242-7832</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>305 242-7836</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>mike_robblee@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
In October of 2001, a study began to determine the volume transport at each of the six stations where postlarvae are being sampled.  Acoustic Doppler technology has been installed at the four defined channels connecting Florida Bay with the Gulf of Mexico (Sandy, Middle Ground) and the Atlantic Ocean (Whale Harbor, Indian Key) and the two interior channels Conchie, Panhandle) that connect to Florida Bay interior sub basins where monthly postlarval sampling occurs.  These estimates of volume transport facilitate the direct comparison of the six stations being sampled for postlarvae and are essential to an assessment of the relative importance of the two known pathways of larval immigration into Florida Bay - west from the Gulf of Mexico and from the Atlantic Ocean through passages in the Florida Keys.  These continuous measurements are also essential in developing a larval transport module for the pink shrimp simulation model.  A significant additional benefit of the data being collected is that it will be very useful in the development of a Florida Bay circulation model, a high priority of CERP.   Specific objectives include:

1. Estimate volume transport in the six channels being sampled for postlarvae.
2. Construct rating curves at each station under a variety of tidal flow conditions in order to improve volume transport estimates.
3. Compare volume transport among the six stations in a comparison of postlarval immigration into Florida Bay.
4. Participate in the development of a transport module for the pink shrimp simulation model.

Measurements of flow, stage, and salinity will continue in FY 2003 in the six channels being sampled for post larvae.  In collaboration with Dr. Joan Browder of NOAA these data will be applied to the construction of the larval transport module for the pink shrimp simulation module.  Methods developed to date and in other studies will continue to be employed.  Acoustic Doppler Velocity Meters (ADVM) have been installed at the instrumented sites and are used to measure continuous (15- minute) water velocity.  A boat-mounted Acoustic Doppler Current Profiler (ADCP) is used to calculate total discharge along a transect of the channels during inspections.  The ADCP also measures water depth, boat speed, and direction of boat movement using acoustic reflections from the streambed.  Discharge and flow direction are both calculated from data collected with the ADCP.  The mean velocity for the creek section is calculated by dividing the total discharge measured with the ADCP by the cross-sectional area corresponding to the water level at the time of the discharge measurement.  The cross-sectional area is computed by using site-specific stage-area ratings.  A velocity rating between the mean ADCP velocity and the in situ ADVM velocity is calculated by regression analysis.  This rating equation is then used to calculate continous discharge using the velocity data.  Stage measurements are made acoustically and through water pressure in the ADVM and Salinity instrumentation respectively.  Stage is used to define the cross-sectional area over which flow measurements are made, and are used in the regression analysis between flow and stage.  Salinity measured near the surface and bottom of each channel to quantify the vertical stratification present at each site, which could be detrimental to acoustic signals.  Additionally, temperature is measured to monitor possible vertical temperature gradients that could be detrimental to acoustic signals and as a necessary parameter to calculate salinity from conductivity.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>2004</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Mark Zucker</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>3110 SW 9th Ave.</address>
                     <city>Ft. Lauderdale</city>
                     <state>FL</state>
                     <postal>33315</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>954 377-5952</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>954 377-5901</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>mzucker@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Work planned for FY 2004

1. The CESI sponsored long-term study entitled 'Temporal and spatial variation in seagrass associated fish and invertebrates in Johnson Key Basin, western Florida Bay, with emphasis on the pink shrimp, Farfantepenaeus duorarum' will document long-term responses of the seagrass associated shrimp and fish community in Johnson Key Basin to environmental conditions (e.g. salinity) and changes in seagrass habitat

2. with Joan Browder the SFWMD sponsored study entitled 'Biscayne Bay Coastal and Nearshore Community Baseline Study to Develop Biological Performance Measures'  will develop performance measures relating the fish and crustacean communities of southern Biscayne Bay to salinity and habitat

3  with Joan Browder, Maria Criales and Clinton Hittle the NOAA sponsored study entitled 'Immigration pathways of pink shrimp postlarvae into and within Florida Bay' will evaluate postlarval immigration (seasonal timing and abundance) to and into Florida Bay in relation to environmental conditions and habitat. The pink shrimp is a species of special interest in each of the above studies because it has been chosen as an indicator species for use in restoration of south Florida estuaries.  Empirical and experimental data developed in these studies will be used to support the development of a pink shrimp landscape simulation model and restoration performance measures.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Michael Robblee</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
                     <address>
c/o South Florida Natural Resources Center, Everglades National Park

40001 State Road 9336
</address>
                     <city>Homestead</city>
                     <state>FL</state>
                     <postal>33034</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>305 242-7832</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>305 242-7836</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>mike_robblee@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <indspref>Florida Bay</indspref>
   </spdoinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Heather Henkel</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth Street South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727 803-8747 ext 3028</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727 803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>sofia-metadata@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>Hydrology Data</resdesc>
      <distliab>The data have no explicit or implied guarantees.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ASCII</formname>
               <formvern>unknown</formvern>
               <formcont>Data for each collection site are available by data type</formcont>
               <transize>3</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://sofia.usgs.gov/exchange/hydro_pinkshrimp/index.html</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>The files may be downloaded from the SOFIA website</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20090511</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Heather Henkel</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth Street South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727 803-8747 ext 3028</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727 803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>sofia-metadata@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <metac>none</metac>
      <metuc>This metadata record may have been copied from the SOFIA website and may not be the most recent version.  Please check http://sofia.usgs.gov/metadata to be sure you have the most recent version.</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
