<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata xmlns="http://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/csdgm"
          xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/metadata/usgswrd/fgdc-std-001-1998.xsd">
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Michael Wieczorek, USGS</origin>
            <pubdate>2004</pubdate>
            <title>Subsurface Drains on Agricultural Land in the Conterminous United States, 1992: National Resource Inventory Conservation Practice 606</title>
            <edition>Version 1.1, February 19, 2002</edition>
            <geoform>raster digital data</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://water.usgs.gov/lookup/getspatial?nri92_cp606</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This data set represents the estimated percentage of the 1-km grid cell that is covered by or subject to the agricultural conservation practice (CP606), Subsurface Drains (SD) on agricultural land by county.  Subsurface Drains are described as "a conduit, such as corrugated plastic tubing, tile, or pipe, installed beneath the ground surface to collect and/or convey drainage." (U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1995)  This data set was created with geographic information systems (GIS) and database management tools. The acres on which SD's are applied were totaled at the county level in the tabular NRI database and then apportioned to a raster coverage of agricultural land within the county based on the Enhanced National Land Cover Dataset (NLCDe) 1-kilometer resolution land cover grids (Nakagaki, 2003). Federal land is not considered in this analysis because NRI does not record information on those lands.</abstract>
         <purpose>This dataset was created for two main purposes; (1) summarize and provide refined spatial detail to attributes of agricultural practices from the 1992 NRI dataset; and (2) to support hydrologic modeling.  The U. S. Geological Survey's (USGS) National Water-Quality Assessment (NAWQA) program is using the spatially refined SD dataset to produce ancillary information for characterizing surface and ground-water sampling sites. Calculation of percentages of NAWQA study areas treated by Subsurface Drains is one example of the type of use of this data set. The 1992 NRI data was used because it was created in the same early to mid-1990s time frame as the NLCD. NAWQA plans on processing the NRI in this fashion every 5 years as new NRI and NLCDE data are published.</purpose>
         <supplinf>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) initiated the National Water-Quality Assessment (NAWQA) Program in 1991 to accomplish two primary objectives. The first objective was to assess the status and trends in the quality of the Nation's ground-water and surface-water resources, and the second objective was to link the status and trends with an understanding of the natural and human factors that affect water quality (Gilliom and others, 1995).
"The National Resources Inventory is a statistically based sample of land-use and natural resource conditions and trends on U.S. nonfederal lands. It is the most comprehensive database of its kind ever attempted anywhere in the world. The Natural Resources Conservation Service's program for NRI serves as the Federal Government's principal source of information on the status, condition, and trends of soil, water, and related resources in the United States. The assessment of a nation's natural resources and environmental condition provided by the NRI requires a nationally consistent database that allows for manipulation of various parameters in order to make accurate assessments. For these manipulations and subsequent analyses to be useful for public policy considerations, the NRI database has a high degree of reliability, looks at the natural resources over a period of time, and permits analyses at national, regional, and local levels. The NRI is unique because it provides a nationally consistent database for all nonfederal lands, it features data gathered and monitored in 1982, 1987, 1992, and 1997 by thousands of technical and natural resource data collection experts, and it has a direct correlation with soils data, which permits analysis of resources in relation to the capability of the land and in terms of soil resources and conditions.  Informed and valid decisions are best made when based upon scientifically derived data. The NRI has been developed to supply this type of information. The NRI database is powerful, credible, and scientifically constructed. The present NRI is the result of many decades of development." (U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1995)

Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes
only and does not imply endorsement by the
U.S. Government.

Although this Federal Geographic Data Committee-compliant metadata
file is intended to document the dataset in nonproprietary form,
as well as in ArcInfo format, this metadata file may include some
ArcInfo-specific terminology.

Cited references

Gilliom, R.G., Alley, W.M., and Gurtz, M.E., 1995, Design of the National Water-Quality Assessment Program--occurrence and distribution of water-quality conditions: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 1112, 33 p.

U.S. Department of Agriculture.  May 1995 (Reissued).  1992 National Resources Inventory, Natural Resources Conservation Service, Washington, DC, and Statistical Laboratory, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa, CD-ROM.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>1992</caldate>
               <time>unknown</time>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-127.887748</westbc>
            <eastbc>-65.346810</eastbc>
            <northbc>51.608770</northbc>
            <southbc>22.860749</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>Subsurface Drains</themekey>
            <themekey>Agricultural Practices</themekey>
            <themekey>National Resources Inventory</themekey>
            <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Conterminous United States</placekey>
         </place>
         <temporal>
            <tempkt/>
            <tempkey>1992</tempkey>
         </temporal>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>The NRI dataset is tabulated at the county level only and deemed accurate for this analysis (Nusser and Goebel, 1997). The spatial distribution of this data also assumes the NLCDe has an acceptable accuracy for this analysis (Nakagaki, 2003). Therefore this data set does not provide specific locations of a particular NRI code but the percent of county agricultural land that practices NRI code 607 over the total agricultural land in a particular county.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Michael Wieczorek</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Geographer</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>8987 Yellow Brick Road</address>
               <city>Baltimore</city>
               <state>MD</state>
               <postal>21237</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(410) 238-4250</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(410) 238-4210</cntfax>
            <cntemail>mewieczo@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/browse/cp606.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Illustration of data set</browsed>
         <browset>jpg</browset>
      </browse>
      <datacred>Prepared as part of the National Water-Quality Assessment Program.
Kerie J. Hitt, USGS, supplied the 1992 NRI database and Naomi Nakagaki, USGS, supplied an updated version of the National Land Cover Dataset processed at 1-kilometer resolution.</datacred>
      <native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 1; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.0.0.535</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>Nusser, S. M., and J. J. Goebel, 1997, The National Resources Inventory: A Long-Term Multi-Resource Monitoring Programme, Environmental and Ecological Statistics, 4(3):181- 204.</attraccr>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>PCT</attraccv>
            <attracce>Represents the percentage of a cell of agricultural land which Subsurface Drains (SD) are practiced.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Environmental Systems Research Institute, Inc. (ESRI) ARC 8.3 software was used to test the data for consistency against the original NRI tabular data, 12/04/03. Several NRI codes in random counties were selected in both the derived GIS dataset and the original tabular file. The total sum of area was compared and found to be the same.</logic>
      <complete/>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Naomi Nakagaki</origin>
                  <pubdate>200311</pubdate>
                  <pubtime>Unknown</pubtime>
                  <title>NLCD 1-kilometer resolution percent land-use/land cover grids with modifications made for orchards and vineyards</title>
                  <edition>Version 2, November 2003</edition>
                  <geoform>map</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Sacramento, CA USA</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>ftp://ftpdcascr.wr.usgs.gov/nsp/natsyngis/NLCDe1km.tgz</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1992</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>NLCDE</srccitea>
            <srccontr>VALUE (land cover code)</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Department of Agriculture</origin>
                  <pubdate>19950101</pubdate>
                  <pubtime>Unknown</pubtime>
                  <title>1992 National Resource Inventory</title>
                  <geoform>tabular digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Fort Worth, TX</pubplace>
                     <publish>SCS National Cartography &amp; GIS Center</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>U.S. Department of Agriculture, May 1995 (Reissued).  1992 National Resources Inventory, Natural Resources Conservation Service, Washington, DC, and Statistical Laboratory, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa, CD-ROM.</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://gis.esri.com/library/userconf/proc95/to200/p1682.html</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>CD-ROM</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Unknown</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>NRI</srccitea>
            <srccontr>PCT is percentage of cell that is Agricultural land treated with CPIS01 conservation practice.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin/>
                  <pubdate/>
                  <title/>
                  <onlink>http://www.nhq.nrcs.uWISa.gov/NRI/1997/)</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc/>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Unknown</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea/>
            <srccontr/>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The reasons for creating this dataset were to (1) summarize and provide refined spatial detail to conservation practices attributes from the 1992 NRI dataset; and (2) to support hydrologic modeling. This dataset was derived by summarizing NRI attributes at the county level and then apportioning these county values to the NLCDe 1-km grid cells identified as agriculture within the appropriate counties. The value of each grid cell represents the estimated percentage of the 1-km grid cell that is covered by or subject to the agricultural conservation practice (CP606 ), Subsurface Drains on agricultural land by county.  Kerie J. Hitt, USGS, supplied a copy of the 1992 NRI database.  Naomi Nakagaki, USGS, supplied the 1-kilometer updated orchards National Land Cover Dataset  (NLCDe) that was used to apportion the county areally weighted Waste Management System values onto agricultural land located within each county.  The cell value for this NLCDe grid is the percentage of 30-meter resolution grid cells in the 1 by 1 kilometer area with agricultural land cover classification.

All percentages are expressed as integer values. Please note that NRI does not include data for federal lands. Therefore, federal lands were excluded from the apportionment calculations and the percentages were based on land areas and county areas of nonfederal lands only.
The process for summarizing and distributing NRI attributes involved the following steps:</procdesc>
            <procdate/>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
            <srcused>C:\DOCUME~1\mewieczo\LOCALS~1\Temp\xml668.tmp</srcused>
            <procdate/>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Grid Cell</rasttype>
         <rowcount>2905</rowcount>
         <colcount>4614</colcount>
         <vrtcount>1</vrtcount>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <mapproj>
               <mapprojn>Albers Conical Equal Area</mapprojn>
               <albers>
                  <stdparll>29.500000</stdparll>
                  <stdparll>45.500000</stdparll>
                  <longcm>-96.000000</longcm>
                  <latprjo>23.000000</latprjo>
                  <feast>0.000000</feast>
                  <fnorth>0.000000</fnorth>
               </albers>
            </mapproj>
            <planci>
               <plance>row and column</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>1000.000000</absres>
                  <ordres>1000.000000</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>meters</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
            <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.257222</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>
ofr041189606</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Internal feature number</enttypd>
            <enttypds>ESRI</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>ObjectID</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Value</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Conservation practice percentage treated x 100</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Wieczorek</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>1</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>9866</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrmfrq>None planned</attrmfrq>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Count</attrlabl>
            <attrdef/>
            <attrdefs>Wieczorek</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>31</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>6388670</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Pct</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Percentage of cell land treated with conservation practice CP606 .</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Wieczorek</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>.01</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>98.66</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>
Value</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Percent of NRI prctice per cell * 100</enttypd>
            <enttypds>Wieczorek</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Value</attrlabl>
            <attrdef/>
            <attrdefs/>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>1</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>9866</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>
Count</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Number of cells with unique percent</enttypd>
            <enttypds>Wieczorek</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl/>
            <attrdef/>
            <attrdefs/>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>1</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>7735715</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>
PCT</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Percent of cell that practices NRI code on Ag land</enttypd>
            <enttypds>Wieczorek</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl/>
            <attrdef/>
            <attrdefs/>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>.01</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>98.66</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <overview>
         <eaover>The cell attributes represents the estimated percentage of the 1-km grid cell that is covered by or subject to the agricultural conservation practice (CP606), Subsurface Drains on agricultural land by county.  Cells with a zero value or NODATA for PCT either have no agricultural land, or NRI reported no usage of conservation practice CP606, or were in counties not included in the NRI survey, or have predominantly federal lands or no land area in their cell.</eaover>
         <eadetcit>Wieczorek, NRCS</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Ask USGS -- Water Webserver Team</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>445 National Center</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747 (1-888-ASK-USGS)</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>http://answers.usgs.gov/cgi-bin/gsanswers?pemail=h2oteam&amp;subject=GIS+Dataset+nri92_cp606</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been used by the U.S. Geological Survey, U.S. Department of the Interior, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the U.S. Geological Survey as to the accuracy of the data.  The act of distribution shall not constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumed by the U.S. Geological Survey in the use of these data, software, or related materials.
The use of firm, trade, or brand names in this report is for identification purposes only and does not constitute endorsement by the U.S. Geological Survey.  The names mentioned in this document may be trademarks or registered trademarks of their respective trademark owners.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname/>
               <formcont/>
               <filedec>Tar and zip</filedec>
               <transize/>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/dsdl/nri_cp606.tgz</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None.  This dataset is provided by USGS as a public service.</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20050211</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Ask USGS -- Water Webserver Team</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>445 National Center</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747 (1-888-ASK-USGS)</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>http://answers.usgs.gov/cgi-bin/gsanswers?pemail=h2oteam&amp;subject=GIS+Dataset+nri92_cp606</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
