<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Gene Shinn (retired)

Chris Reich;
Don Hickey;
Ann Tihansky
</origin>
            <pubdate>2005</pubdate>
            <title>Groundwater Flow Rates at the Oceanside Well Cluster study site</title>
            <geoform>spreadsheets</geoform>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/exchange/shinn</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The dataset contains the values for the dyes from the tracer study on the oceanside of Key Largo</abstract>
         <purpose>
Treated sewage is injected into the limestone under the Florida Keys via on-site disposal systems (OSDs).  There are 25,000 septic tank systems, approximately 5,000 cesspools, and approximately 1000 class 5 injection wells.  Depths of injection wells ranges from 10 to 30 meters.  Excessive algal growth, coral diseases and both marine grass and sponge mortality is perceived by the local population, NOAA, and EPA to be caused by sewage nutrients leaking from groundwater on both sides of the Florida Keys.  Determining the rate and direction of saline groundwater movement beneath the Key, and the Florida Bay was considered critical to understanding the fate and effects of subsurface waste water disposal n the Florida Keys.

The objective of this research was to determine the rate, direction of flow, and contamination levels of saline groundwater in the Florida Keys and Florida Bay.  Contamination studies are necessary to determine if nutrient and other contaminant levels are rising and to provide a baseline of data for future decision making.
</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>19960618</begdate>
               <enddate>19970417</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-80.466</westbc>
            <eastbc>-80.466</eastbc>
            <northbc>25.067</northbc>
            <southbc>25.067</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>chemistry</themekey>
            <themekey>hydrology</themekey>
            <themekey>seepage</themekey>
            <themekey>sewage</themekey>
            <themekey>groundwater</themekey>
            <themekey>flow</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>environment</themekey>
            <themekey>007</themekey>
            <themekey>014</themekey>
            <themekey>oceans</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1995, Countries, Dependencies, Areas of Special Sovereignty, and Their Principal Administrative Divisions,  Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS) 10-4, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>US</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>U.S. Department of Commerce, 1987, Codes for the identification of the States, the District of Columbia and the outlying areas of the United States, and associated areas (Federal Information Processing Standard 5-2): Washington, DC, NIST</placekt>
            <placekey>Florida</placekey>
            <placekey>FL</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1990, Counties and Equivalent Entities of the United States, Its Possessions, and Associated Areas, FIPS 6-3, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>Monroe County</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>USGS Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
            <placekey>Florida Bay</placekey>
            <placekey>Key Largo</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Florida Keys</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Chris Reich</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth St. South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727 803-8747 ext 3032</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727 803-2032</cntfax>
            <cntemail>creich@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://sofia.usgs.gov/publications/posters/hydro_flkeys/clflasatx.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>satellite image of southern Florida showing study site</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://sofia.usgs.gov/publications/posters/hydro_flkeys/ccircle1x.gif</browsen>
         <browsed>graphic showing flow and direction of flourescein injected in the central well of the Oceanside Well Cluster</browsed>
         <browset>GIF</browset>
      </browse>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://sofia.usgs.gov/publications/posters/hydro_flkeys/ccircle2x.gif</browsen>
         <browsed>graphic showing flow and direction of rhodamine injected in the central well of the Oceanside Well Cluster</browsed>
         <browset>GIF</browset>
      </browse>
      <native>MS Excel</native>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Shinn, E. A.

Reese, R. S.;
Reich, C. D.
</origin>
            <pubdate>1994</pubdate>
            <title>Fate and pathways of injection-well effluent in the Florida Keys</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>USGS Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>94-276</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Florida</pubplace>
               <publish>U. S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/publications/ofr/94-276</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Reich, C. D.</origin>
            <pubdate>1996</pubdate>
            <title>Diver-operated manometer: a simple device for measuring hydraulic head in underwater wells</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Journal of Sedimentary Rresearch</sername>
               <issue>v. 66 n. 5</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Tulsa, OK</pubplace>
               <publish>S E P M Society for Sedimentary Research</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>Journal of Sedimentary Research table of contents and abstracts are open access.  Full text articles are available to non-member subscribers or pay-per-view at two websites accessed from the JSR website (http://www.sepm.org/jsr/jsr_home.html)</othercit>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Halley, R. B.

Vacher, H. L.;
Shinn, E. A.
</origin>
            <pubdate>1997</pubdate>
            <title>Geology and Hydrogeology of the Florida Keys</title>
            <geoform>book chapter</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Developments in Sedimentology</sername>
               <issue>Geology and hydrogeology of carbonate islands</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Doorwerth, The Netherlands</pubplace>
               <publish>Elsevier Science B. V.</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>This chapter was originally published in Geology and Hydrology of Carbonate Islands, Developments in Sedimentology 54, edited by H. L. Vacher and T. Quinn</othercit>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/publications/papers/keys_geohydro/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Paul, J. H.

Rose, J. B.;
Brown, J.;
Shinn, E. A.;
Miller, S.;
Farrah, S. R.
</origin>
            <pubdate>1995</pubdate>
            <title>Viral tracer studies indicate contamination of marine waters by sewage disposal practices in Key Largo, Florida</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</sername>
               <issue>v. 61, n. 6</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Washington, DC</pubplace>
               <publish>American Society for Microbiology</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>The full article may be downloaded from the AEM website</othercit>
            <onlink>http://aem.asm.org/cgi/reprint/61/6/2230</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Paul, J. H.

Rose, J. B.;
Jiang, S.;
Kellogg, C.;
Shinn, E. A.
</origin>
            <pubdate>1995</pubdate>
            <title>Occurrence of fecal indicator bacteria in surface waters and the subsurface aquifer in Key Largo, Florida</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</sername>
               <issue>v. 61, n. 6</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Washington, DC</pubplace>
               <publish>American Society for Microbiology</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>The full article may be downloaded from the AEM website</othercit>
            <onlink>http://aem.asm.org/cgi/reprint/61/6/2235</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>The same tests were run on all samples from the satellite wells</logic>
      <complete>The central wells were not sampled due to the contained/retained high concentrations of dye.  Samples from all satellite wells were analyzed.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>Benchmarks were installed onshore on both sides of Key Largo and position and elevation determined using GPS_Military P-code enabled.  Two wells at each cluster were later leveled in using the benchmarks as a reference point.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Twenty wells were installed to form two (200 ft diameter) circular clusters, each with an injection well in the center. The clusters, located on opposite sides of Key Largo, were designed to determine groundwater flow direction and rate. Each was screened at two depths, (-20 and -45 ft). The following tests were  conducted using the well clusters: 1) three separate dye tracer tests using fluorescein and Rhodamine, 2) one test using a colaphage (done in conjunction with University of South Florida) and 3) a single test with Sulfur Hexafluoride (SF6) as the tracer. The first two sets of tests determined flow direction and provided sufficient information to "zero-in" on the actual flow rate. An additional well (100 ft from cluster) was added to each cluster once the direction of movement was determined. The third test (using a combination of dyes and SF6) provided accurate flow-rate estimates. These data facilitated the design of future rate and direction experiments.  All wells were continuously cored and cores reside at the St. Petersburg Coastal Center.

The well clusters were completed so that all of the piezometers were 100 ft (30.3 m) away from the central well.  The central well became the location for the injection of dye to trace the natural gradient of groundwater flow.  Fluorescein was injected in the shallow, central piezometer and Rhodamine WT was injected in the deep, central piezometer.  The central well for the oceanside cluster is approximately 100 m offshore.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>1997</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Perform a tracer experiment in existing well clusters.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1998</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Field work included a dye-tracer study using the newly completed transect of wells across Key Largo.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1999</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Chris Reich</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>600 Fourth St. South</address>
                     <city>St. Petersburg</city>
                     <state>FL</state>
                     <postal>33701</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>727 803-8747 ext 3032</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>727 803-2032</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>creich@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <indspref>Oceanside Well Cluster</indspref>
      <direct>Point</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>9</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <latres>0.001</latres>
            <longres>0.001</longres>
            <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
         </geograph>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>WGS84</horizdn>
            <ellips>WGS84</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <overview>
         <eaover>
The Groundwater Flow Rates at the Oceanside Well Cluster study site contains the results of the injection of two fluorescent dyes in the center wells in the well cluster on the oceanside of Key Largo.

Values for the dyes are ppb.
</eaover>
         <eadetcit>USGS</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Heather S.Henkel</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth St. South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727 803-8747 ext 3028</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727 803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>hhenkel@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>Groundwater Flow Rates at the Oceanside Well Cluster study site</resdesc>
      <distliab>No warrantees are implied or explicit for the data</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>MS Excel</formname>
               <formvern>unknown</formvern>
               <formcont>contains the results of the injection of two tracer dyes in the center wells of the oceanside well cluster</formcont>
               <transize>0.033</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://sofia.usgs.gov/exchange/shinn/</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>Data may be downloaded from the SOFIA website</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20080111</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Heather Henkel</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth Street South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727 803-8747 ext 3028</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727 803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>sofia-metadata@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
