<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Eric Swain

Melinda Wolfert
</origin>
            <pubdate>2003</pubdate>
            <title>TIME and SICS modeling of surface water and interactions with ground water</title>
            <geoform>computer model</geoform>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/projects/coupling/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>
This project focuses on the implementation, verification, and validation of a system of coupling numerical models to represent the interaction between the ground-water and surface-water systems in the SICS and TIME areas.

In this investigation, multidimensional coupled surface-water/ ground-water models have been developed for the southern Florida wetlands and offshore area.  The initial surface-water model, the SICS model, represents the southeast coastal region with the two-dimensional dynamic wave model SWIFT2D. The coupling with the SEAWAT three-dimensional ground-water model allows leakage to be represented with salinity transfer included.  In order to represent regional restoration scenarios, the SICS model is to be linked via boundary water levels to the regional South Florida Water Management Model.  Uses of this modeling system will include nutrient transport simulations for determining the fate of phosphorous and nitrogen in the coastal wetland system.  The same modeling system is in the process of being expanded to the west and north to form the TIME domain.  This encompasses more of the structural controls in the area and allows for the representation of Shark Slough flows.
</abstract>
         <purpose>
The results of the numerical modeling and scenario testing provide essential information and insight into the flow system and how it responds to the variations in hydrologic input.  The computed flows and salinity exchange at the coast are to be used as boundary conditions for circulation models of Florida Bay, which are to be used to assess the effects of systemic changes on biota in the bay.  The computed flows also are used to calibrate the regional water management model&#x92;s boundary.  The nutrient transport simulations will yield information on the effects of various scenarios on nutrient levels in the wetlands and offshore

The objectives of this project are to integrate field process studies, represent relevant factors affecting flow in the coastal Everglades, and test restoration alternatives.  Field process studies develop all the major factors that affect flow and transport: evapotranspiration, frictional resistance, topography and more.  These are used to construct and test the initial surface-water model.  Construction of the ground-water model is also dependent on data collected for aquifer parameters and boundaries.  This incremental model development is continued by linkage to regional model output for scenario evaluation and the expansion of the SICS model area to create the TIME domain.
</purpose>
         <supplinf>This project is now part of the SICS and TIME model linkages and development in support of Everglades Restoration</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>200010</begdate>
               <enddate>200609</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-81.555039</westbc>
            <eastbc>-80.304809</eastbc>
            <northbc>25.976713</northbc>
            <southbc>25.026572</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>hydrology</themekey>
            <themekey>Tides and Inflows in the Mangrove Ecotone</themekey>
            <themekey>groundwater</themekey>
            <themekey>surface water</themekey>
            <themekey>TIME</themekey>
            <themekey>SICS</themekey>
            <themekey>Southern Inland and Coastal Systems</themekey>
            <themekey>flow</themekey>
            <themekey>model</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>environment</themekey>
            <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
            <themekey>007</themekey>
            <themekey>012</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1995, Countries, Dependencies, Areas of Special Sovereignty, and Their Principal Administrative Divisions,  Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS) 10-4, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>US</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>U.S. Department of Commerce, 1987, Codes for the identification of the States, the District of Columbia and the outlying areas of the United States, and associated areas (Federal Information Processing Standard 5-2): Washington, DC, NIST</placekt>
            <placekey>Florida</placekey>
            <placekey>FL</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1990, Counties and Equivalent Entities of the United States, Its Possessions, and Associated Areas, FIPS 6-3, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>Collier County</placekey>
            <placekey>Miami-Dade County</placekey>
            <placekey>Monroe County</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>USGS Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
            <placekey>Everglades National Park</placekey>
            <placekey>Florida Bay</placekey>
            <placekey>Taylor Slough</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Central Everglades</placekey>
            <placekey>SW Big Cypress</placekey>
            <placekey>South East Coast</placekey>
            <placekey>Florida Keys</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Eric D. Swain</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>3110 SW 9th Avenue</address>
               <city>Ft. Lauderdale</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33315</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>954 377-5925</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>954 377-5901</cntfax>
            <cntemail>edswain@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://pubs.usgs.gov/fs/2004/3130</browsen>
         <browsed>map of southern Florida showing the active model domains of SICS and TIME and the SFWMM grid</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <datacred>Project personnel include Chris Langevin</datacred>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Swain. E. D</origin>
            <pubdate>1999</pubdate>
            <title>Numerical Representation of Dynamic Flow and Transport at the Everglades/Florida Bay Interface</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Proceedings of the Third International Symposium on Ecohydraulics</sername>
               <issue>none</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Salt Lake City, UT</pubplace>
               <publish>International Association for Hydraulic Research</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/publications/papers/numeric/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Swain, E. D.

Wolfert, M.
</origin>
            <pubdate>2002</pubdate>
            <title>Cooperative linking of numerical models for coastal wetland planning</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Proceedings</sername>
               <issue>Spring Specialty Conference on Coastal Water Resources</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>New Orleans, LA</pubplace>
               <publish>American Water Resources Association</publish>
            </pubinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Swain, E. D.</origin>
            <pubdate>1996</pubdate>
            <title>Modeling the interaction between a dynamic surface and ground-water system</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>EOS Transactions</sername>
               <issue>v. 77, no. 46</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Washington, DC</pubplace>
               <publish>American Geophysical Union</publish>
            </pubinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Swain, E. D.

Howie, Barbara;
Dixon, Joann
</origin>
            <pubdate>1996</pubdate>
            <title>Description and field analysis of a coupled ground-water/surface-water flow model (MODFLOW/BRANCH) with modifications for structures and wetlands in southern Dade County, Florida</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Water Resources Investigations Report</sername>
               <issue>96-4118</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/usgspubs/wri/wri964118</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Swain, Eric D.

Wolfert, Melinda A.;
Bales, Jerad D.;
Goodwin, Carl R.
</origin>
            <pubdate>2003</pubdate>
            <title>Two-dimensional hydrodynamic simulation of surface-water flow and transport to Florida Bay through the Southern Inland and Coastal Systems (SICS)</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>USGS Water-Resources Investigations Report</sername>
               <issue>03-4287</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Tallahassee, FL</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/publications/wri/03-4287</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>
Langevin, C. D.

Swain, E.D.;
Wolfert, M. A.
</origin>
            <pubdate>2004</pubdate>
            <title>Simulaton of integrated surface-water/ground-water flow and salinity for a coastal wetland and adjacent estuary</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>USGS Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>2004-1097</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Tallahassee, FL</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2004/1097</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>not applicable</logic>
      <complete>not available</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The 2-dimensional dynamic wave model SWIFT2D was implemented with modifications to account for evapotranspiration and recharge.  Field studies supplied land elevation, vegetative frictional resistance, evapotranspiration parameters, ground-water leakage estimates, and flows for comparison.  The model was applied to the SICS area to represent surface-water flow and salinity transport.  A more complete representation of the ground water and the ground-water interactions was developed next by adding the SEAWAT code for three-dimensional ground-water flow and salinity transport.  The coupling of the two codes was accomplished by making them subroutines of FTLOADDS, a main routine that passed the necessary data between the two models to compute leakage and salinity flux.  This resulted in improved SICS model capabilities, especially in representing surface-water salinity.  Both the SWIFT2D and the SEAWAT input data for the TIME domain are under separate development.  These models will then be coupled using the FTLOADDS code which has been refined for the SICS domain.  A linkage of the SICS model which allows the use of boundary conditions generated by the South Florida Water Management Model (SFWMM) is in the process of being created.  This linkage allows the examination of various restoration schemes represented in the SFWMM on the SICS area.</procdesc>
            <procdate>2002</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Fiscal year 2003 will focus primarily on data collection. Scheduled sampling will start with a bimonthly sampling with approximately 50 samples taken per trip around the Taylor Slough area. The schedule will be monthly in the middle of the wet season. The samples will be tested using low-level protocols for: total phosphorus, phosphorous as PO4, total nitrogen, nitrogen as NH3, nitrogen as NO2, and nitrogen as NO2 +NO3. Access to the sites will either be by helicopter, supplied by CERP, or by airboat</procdesc>
            <procdate>2003</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The last half of FY 2003 will involve an evaluation of the existing SWIFT2D transport of reactive constituents. The nutrient interactions and cycling determined from Everglades studies will be used to develop modifications to the reactive transport algorithm.</procdesc>
            <procdate>2003</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Production of  a users manual on the current version of the SWIFT2D code, including all modifications made for the SICS application, and a journal article on the surface-water/ground-water coupling procedure and application is planned for completion during the first half of FY 2003.   In order to present results to the wider scientific community, an article and presentation will be developed for the GEER conference in April 2003.  Work on the users manual will continue throughout FY 2003, with a first draft completed by the end of the fiscal year.</procdesc>
            <procdate>2003</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The previously constructed SWIFT2D surface-water model of the TIME domain and the SEAWAT ground-water model will be used in the coupled model scheme with leakage and salinity transfer. The coupled model will be calibrated using available data (topography, flow, and ground-water data will not be available until later) and the simulation period extended to one year. The objective is to produce a prototype larger domain model that encompasses more of the operational structures and allows for a wider analysis of hydroperiods and flows.  Work on the surface-water model of the TIME domain is external to this task and will not be completed until the middle of FY 2003. During the latter half of FY 2003, work begins on coupling this preliminary surface-water model, through the code developed in the SICS area, to the TIME domain ground-water model.</procdesc>
            <procdate>2004</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The calibration of the leakage interaction and simulation period extension will be initiated in FY 2004.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Work planned for FY 2004:

Nutrient tracking in the TIME/SICS area to develop a data set useful in transport model development.  Field sampling of nutrients in Taylor Slough will be carried out to collect data for development of boundary and calibration data in the SICS model.

The documentation of the coupled model will include a Water Resource Investigations Report (WRIR), a journal article describing the FTLOADDS model coupling, a Users Manual for the SWIFT2D model coupling, and an Open-File Report describing the linkage of SICS/TIME with the SWIFT2D 2x2 model.

The linked model will be implemented with a number of restoration scenario outputs from the 2x2 model to represent the effects on water level, flows, and salinity of restoration alterations to the hydrologic system.
</procdesc>
            <procdate>Not complete</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Eric D. Swain</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
                     <address>3110 SW 9th Avenue</address>
                     <city>Ft. Lauderdale</city>
                     <state>FL</state>
                     <postal>33315</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>954 377-5925</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>954 377-5901</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>edswain@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <indspref>SICS and TIME areas</indspref>
   </spdoinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Eric D. Swain</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>3110 SW 9th Avenue</address>
               <city>Ft. Lauderdale</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33315</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>954 377-5925</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>954 377-5901</cntfax>
            <cntemail>edswain@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>SICS and TIME coupled models</resdesc>
      <distliab>There are no explicit or implicit warrantees for the data.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <nondig>computer model</nondig>
         <fees>none</fees>
         <ordering>Contact Eric Swain for more information regarding data and the models from this project.</ordering>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20070403</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Heather Henkel</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth Street South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727 803-8747 ext 3028</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727 803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>sofia-metadata@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
