<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Roy Sonenshein</origin>
            <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
            <title>Approximate Eastern Limit of the Gray Limestone Aquifer in Broward County, USGS WRIR 87-4034, figure 36</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/exchange/gis/data/glime_limit_brwd_east_arc.htm</onlink>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Fish, J. E.</origin>
                  <pubdate>1988</pubdate>
                  <title>Hydrogeology, Aquifer Characteristics, and Ground-Water Flow of the Surficial Aquifer System Broward County, Florida</title>
                  <geoform>report</geoform>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>USGS Water Resources Investigations Report</sername>
                     <issue>87-4034</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Tallahassee, FL</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>prepared in cooperation with the South Florida Water Management District</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://sofia.usgs.gov/publications/wri/87-4034/index.html</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>
An investigation of the surficial aquifer system in Broward County, begun in 1981, is part of a regional study of the aquifer system in southeast Florida.  Test drilling for lithologic samples, flow measurements taken during drilling, aquifer testing, and analyses of previously available data permitted delineation of the permeability  framework (on geologic sections), the aquifers in the system and the generalized transmissivity distribution, and interpretation of the ground-water flow system.

In addition to the Biscayne aquifer, a previously undefined aquifer, composed of gray (in places, greenish-gray or tan) limestone of the lower part and locally the middle part of the Tamiami Formation, was found at depth in west Broward County. Although it is less permeable than the Biscayne aquifer, the gray limestone is nevertheless a significant aquifer and a potential source of water. The aquifer is informally and locally named as the gray limestone aquifer. It is defined as that part of the limestone beds (usually gray) and contiguous coarse clastic beds of the lower to middle part of the Tamiami Formation that are highly permeable (having a hydraulic conductivity of about 100 ft/d or more) and at least 10 feet thick. Above and below the gray limestone aquifer in west Broward County and separating it from the Biscayne aquifer and the base of the surficial aquifer system are sediments having relatively low permeability, such as mixtures of sand, clay, silt, shell, and lime mud, and some sediments of moderate to low permeability, such as limestone, sandstone, and claystone.

Subsequent drilling has traced the gray limestone aquifer into southwest Palm Beach County where the water contains high dissolved solids and into northwest Dade County where the water generally has low dissolved solids. The aquifer probably extend westward into Collier County, and it likely is the source of water for irrigation and drinking on the Seminole Indian Reservation and sugar cane fields of southeast Hendry County.

The map shows the approximate eastern limit of the gray limestone aquifer in Broward County.
</abstract>
         <purpose>
Most previous work in southeast Florida had been concentrated in the populated coastal area.  Drilling and monitoring activities were commonly restricted to zones used for water supply or overlying zones.  Hence, information concerning the characteristics of the western or deeper parts of the Biscayne aquifer and of sediments below the Biscayne aquifer in the surficial aquifer system were insufficient for present needs.  Because of persistent increases in demand from the surficial aquifer system in the highly populated and growing coastal area of southeast Florida and because of attendant concerns for the protection and management of the water supply, the U.S. Geological Survey, in cooperation with the South Florida Water management District, began an investigation to define the extent of the surficial aquifer system and its characteristics on a regional scale.

The overall objectives of the regional study are to determine the hydrogeologic framework, the extent and thickness of the surficial aquifer system and the aquifers within it, the areal and vertical water-quality distribution and factors that affect the water quality, the hydraulic characteristics of the components of the surficial aquifer system, and to describe ground-water flow in the aquifer system.
</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>1981</begdate>
               <enddate>1984</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-80.462533</westbc>
            <eastbc>-80.249039</eastbc>
            <northbc>26.360125</northbc>
            <southbc>25.958789</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>hydrogeology</themekey>
            <themekey>hydrology</themekey>
            <themekey>geology</themekey>
            <themekey>surficial aquifer system</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>environment</themekey>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
            <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
            <themekey>007</themekey>
            <themekey>008</themekey>
            <themekey>012</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1995, Countries, Dependencies, Areas of Special Sovereignty, and Their Principal Administrative Divisions,  Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS) 10-4, Washington, D.C., National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>US</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>U.S. Department of Commerce, 1987, Codes for the identification of the States, the District of Columbia and the outlying areas of the United States, and associated areas (Federal Information Processing Standard 5-2): Washington, D. C., NIST</placekt>
            <placekey>Florida</placekey>
            <placekey>FL</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Department of Commerce, 1990, Counties and Equivalent Entities of the United States, Its Possessions, and Associated Areas, FIPS 6-3, Washington, DC, National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
            <placekey>Broward County</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>South East Coast</placekey>
         </place>
         <stratum>
            <stratkt>none</stratkt>
            <stratkey>Gray limestone aquifer</stratkey>
         </stratum>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>None</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Roy Sonenshein</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>3110 SW 9th Avenue</address>
               <city>Ft. Lauderdale</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33315</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>954 377-5924</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>sunshine@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://sofia.usgs.gov/exchange/gis/browsegraphics/glime_limit_brwd_east_arc.gif</browsen>
         <browsed>Approximate Eastern Limit of the Gray Limestone Aquifer in Broward County, WRIR 87-4034, figure 36</browsed>
         <browset>GIF</browset>
      </browse>
      <native>ESRI ArcCatalog 8.3.0.800 shapefile</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>The data set was checked for topological consistency using the Arc/INFO command BUILD and CLEAN. No other checks for logical consistency were performed on this data set.</logic>
      <complete>This data set contains data for Broward County, FL</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>unknown</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Base maps were scanned at 300 dpi and stored in tiff file format.  Ground control points were ascertained from base map.  Base map was imported into ESRI's Arcmap and rectified using a first order polynomial transformation.  Heads up digitizing was performed on georeferenced base map to produce vector layer.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Roy Sonenshein</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>3110 SW 9th Avenue</address>
                     <city>Ft. Lauderdale</city>
                     <state>FL</state>
                     <postal>33315</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>954 377-5924</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>sunshine@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Vector</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm Name="glime_limit_brwd_east_arc">
            <sdtstype>String</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>2</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <latres>0.000003</latres>
            <longres>0.000003</longres>
            <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
         </geograph>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1927</horizdn>
            <ellips>Clarke 1866</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378206.4</semiaxis>
            <denflat>294.978698</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
      <vertdef>
         <altsys>
            <altdatum>National Geodetic Vertical Datum of 1929</altdatum>
            <altres>1.000000</altres>
            <altunits>feet</altunits>
            <altenc>Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc>
         </altsys>
      </vertdef>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed Name="glime_limit_brwd_east_arc">
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>arc</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Approximate eastern limit of the gray limestone aquifer in Broward County</enttypd>
            <enttypds>USGS</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl Sync="TRUE">FNODE_</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl Sync="TRUE">TNODE_</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl Sync="TRUE">LPOLY_</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl Sync="TRUE">RPOLY_</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl Sync="TRUE">LENGTH</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl Sync="TRUE">FID</attrlabl>
            <attrdef Sync="TRUE">Internal feature number.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs Sync="TRUE">ESRI</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom Sync="TRUE">Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>LINETYPE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Dashed lines are approximately located, solid lines are inferred from data</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>linetype</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl Sync="TRUE">FIG36BND_</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl Sync="TRUE">SHAPE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef Sync="TRUE">Feature geometry.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs Sync="TRUE">ESRI</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom Sync="TRUE">Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl Sync="TRUE">Shape</attrlabl>
            <attrdef Sync="TRUE">Feature geometry.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs Sync="TRUE">ESRI</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom Sync="TRUE">Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl Sync="TRUE">FIG36BND_I</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl Sync="TRUE">SHAPE_Leng</attrlabl>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Heather S.Henkel</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth St. South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>FL</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727 803-8747 ext 3028</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727 803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>hhenkel@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>glime_limit_brwd_east_arc</resdesc>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the U.S. Geological Survey regarding the utility of the data on any other system, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. No responsibility is assumed by the U.S. Geological Survey in the use of these data. These data are not constituted legal documents and are not intended to be used as such.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>zipped files</formname>
               <formvern>unknown</formvern>
               <formcont>Each zipped file contains an Arc GIS shapefile and its associated files</formcont>
               <transize>0.008</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://sofia.usgs.gov/exchange/gis/shapefiles/glime_limit_brwd_east_arc.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>Log onto the SOFIA website at http://sofia.usgs.gov</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20060712</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Heather Henkel</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>600 Fourth Street South</address>
               <city>St. Petersburg</city>
               <state>Fl</state>
               <postal>33701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>727 803-8747 ext 3028</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>727 803-2030</cntfax>
            <cntemail>sofia-metadata@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <mettc Sync="TRUE">local time</mettc>
      <metextns>
         <onlink Sync="TRUE">http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink>
         <metprof Sync="TRUE">ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof>
      </metextns>
   </metainfo>
   <lineage/>
</metadata>
