<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata xmlns="http://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/csdgm"
          xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/metadata/usgswrd/fgdc-std-001-1998.xsd">
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Price, Curtis</origin>
            <origin>Clawges, Rick</origin>
            <pubdate>1999</pubdate>
            <title>Digital data sets describing population density in the conterminous US</title>
            <edition>1.0</edition>
            <geoform>map</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>99-78</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://water.usgs.gov/lookup/getspatial?ofr99-78_popdeng</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>Grid of population density in the conterminous United States at a
resolution of one kilometer. The grid was converted from an
ASCII file obtained from the Consortium for International
Earth Science Information Network (CIESIN).
			</abstract>
         <purpose>Large scale representation of population distribution in the
conterminous United  States.  This data set was converted for
use in the analysis of ground-water quality data on volatile
organic compounds (VOCs) by the U.S. Geological Survey
(USGS) National Water-Quality Assessment Program (NAWQA) VOC
National Synthesis Team.
			</purpose>
         <supplinf>PROCEDURES USED

The data from which the population density grid was created
was retrieved in ASCII format from data released by the
Consortium for International Earth Science Information Network
(CIESIN) (1995) and a FORTRAN program was used to convert it
into a format that could be read into an ARC/INFO grid data
set. The data was then projected from its original projection
to an Albers projection using nearest-neighbor
resampling. Detailed processing steps are included in this
metadata file.
The following documentation file also was released
by CIESIN and is included here.

&gt;
&gt;
&gt;******************** BEGIN CIESIN README FILE ********************

&gt;
&gt; The Socioeconomic Data and Applications Center (SEDAC)
&gt;
&gt;         INTEGRATED DATASETS FOR THE USA
&gt;                 June 27 1995
&gt;
&gt;---------------------------------------------------------
GENERAL

The primary mission of The Socioeconomic Data and Applications Center
(SEDAC), at the Consortium for International Earth Science Information
Network (CIESIN), is to develop new policy oriented applications and
information products that synthesize earth science and socioeconomic
data. The SEDAC policy applications development effort is the primary
means by which the Earth Observing System Data and Information System
(EOSDIS) program helps to ensure that the scientific investment embodied
in NASA's Mission to Planet Earth (MTPE) program leads to tangible
benefits.

Within this framework, the "Population, Land Use and Emissions" Task
(PLUE) embarked on integrating data from different sources.
Specifically, data from the US decennial census (1990) and recent
satelite data were integrated. In the initial attempt, the focus is on
transforming census vector based data to satelite pixel based data.
&gt;From the US census data Total Persons and Total Housing Unit Structures
were the selected data items (from the blockgroup geography) to be
merged with the Land Cover Characteristics database (square kilometer
resolution) for the conterminous United States from the EROS Data
Center.  This land cover was derived from Advanced Very High Resolution
Radiometer (AVHRR) 1990 multitemporal satelite data.

LOCATION

The US census blockgroup boundary information are present on a publicly
accessible FTP archive: The Archive of Census Related Products. To
access this Archive connect to

&gt;    ftp ftp.ciesin.org &lt;160.39.8.201&gt;
&gt;      user &lt;log in as anonymous or ftp&gt;
&gt;      password &lt;enter email address&gt;
&gt;      cd /pub/census

Please read the file "archive.ann" and "archive2.ann" for a detailed
description of this Archive which contains 11,000+ densely compressed
boundary and demographic data files. The census blockgroup boundary
files are located, by state, in /pub/census/usa/tiger.

The Archive may also be reached via WWW at the URL

http://www.ciesin.org/datasets/us-demog/us-demog-home.html

The integrated data products are posted as generic compressed ascii files
in the location in

ftp://ftp.ciesin.org/pub/census/usa/grid

The data files, their structure and creation, are described in further
detail below. A series of graphic (GIF) files provide for a quick
glance at the data products. In the near future, this information will
be accessible via The Interactive System for Analysis Services (ISAS), a
suite of query engines for WWW browsers.

LAYOUT

For each state, US census data and EROS Land Cover data have been
integrated, meaning both datasets are reported at the square kilometer
resolution for the conterminous USA. Support files include:

&gt;      gridlgd.txt    legend  &amp; variable/file descriptions
&gt;      griddoc.txt    [this file]
&gt;      gridbox.txt    bounding boxes for the states
&gt;     gridcomb.sas    file for data processing and image creation

CREATION

The integrated data were created using in-house developed algorithms written
in C. A proportional allocation algorithm was applied. The individual steps
of data processing are described next.

a) The census blockgroups, derived from the US Bureau of the Census
Topologically Integrated Geographic Encoding and Referencing database
(TIGER/Line 1992), were first projected from their latitude-longitude
source to the projection used in the Land Cover Charateristics database.
This coordinate system is the oblique Lamberts Azimuthal Equal Area
LAZEA) projection with an origin of -100 longitude and +45 latitude.
The exact equations applied to tranform TIGER92 to this projection were:

&gt;X=Rkcos(lat)sin(long-long_origin)
&gt;Y=Rk[cos(lat_origin)sin(lat)-sin(lat_origin)cos(lat)cos(long-long_origin)]
&gt;
&gt;k={2/[1+sin(lat_origin)sin(lat)+
&gt;  cos(lat_origin)cos(lat)cos(long-long_origin)]}**1/2

R is radius of sphere (by default 6,370,997 meters)

[from: Map Projections-A Working Manual by John P. Snyder, USGS 1987].

b) Once the boundaries are in LAZEA format, the selected data items from
the census were merged into these files and submitted to a suite of
programs.

c) Proportional allocation. By state, each census blockgroup's bounding
box is first determined in the LAZEA X-Y system. Next the area of
overlap for each pixel (km2 grid) is determined. The sum of all
overlapping areas is assigned as the total area of the polygon. Next,
the data items, typically count type data (such as number of persons or
buildings), are distributed across the intersecting grids based on the
fraction of grid-overlapping-area over total-polygon-area. These steps
are repeated for all polygons within each state and the values are
accumulated in memory for each grid. (A check calculation is performed
by adding all grid values for the polygon in question and verifying that
the actual value does sum to the original total). In a final step, the
accumulated total within each LAZEA X-Y grid are divided by the area of
the grid itself to arrive at density measures (in our example, each grid
is 1 kilometer by 1 kilometer, but this value may be changed).

d) To make the data available in a generic way, the saved binary output
files, one for each state, are accessed and the data dumped out in a
generic image format. The structure of these files (the ??_int.zip files
in ftp://ftp.ciesin.org/pub/census/usa/grid/pall) is as follows:
&gt;
&gt;2781 3475 1862 2569          xmin xmax ymin ymax
&gt;1.000000 1.000000            xsize ysize
&gt;0.000000 0.000000 0          pdkm hdkm lckm
&gt;0.000000 0.000000 0          pdkm hdkm lckm
&gt;1.105958 4.150659 91         pdkm hdkm lckm
&gt;0.736277 3.411086 136        pdkm hdkm lckm
&gt;...                          ...

Records are shown for each grid inside the state's bounding box. The
size of the image (bounding box) is determined by the points (xmin,ymin)
for lower left and (xmax,ymax) for top right. The table size is
rows=ymax-ymin by cols=xmax-xmin. The grid size is, in kilometers,
reported on record 2. The sequence of the records reported from line 3
till end of file begin at (xmin,ymax) on row=1, col=1. Sequentially,
all grid values are reported for row=1 until the end of row=1 is
encountered (cols) before the row iterates and reporting starts at
(row=2,col=1).

These ascii files are then zipped with a CR-LF added to the end of each
record (unix users use the unzip -a option replacng CR-LF with a LF).
See the file "gridcomb.sas" for more detail.

The file "gridbox.txt" summarizes all the bounding boxes for all states.

e) When accessing multiple states, boundary conditions need to be
corrected.  For example, the state boundary line between two states
could split a single grid. So the grid in question will get data
allocated to it by both states . When splicing multiple states together
these duplicate records need to be collapsed into one record.

For the users this has been done for regions of the US (See the directory
/pub/census/usa/grid/pall/us). The abbreviations used are:

&gt;      Regional Area                States
&gt;      ------------------------     --------------------------
&gt;      NE    NorthEast              me nh vt ma ct ri ny pa nj
&gt;      SA    South Atlantic         dc de md wv va nc sc ga fl
&gt;      ESA   East South Atlantic    ky tn al ms
&gt;      WSA   West South Atlantic    ar la ok tx
&gt;      ENC   East North Central     mi wi il in oh
&gt;      WNC   West North Central     mn ia mo nd sd ne ks
&gt;      NWM   North West Mountain    mt wy id
&gt;      SWM   South West Mountain    ut az co nm
&gt;      PAC   Pacific                wa or ca nv

From these files a USgrid.asc file will be put together for the whole US.
More information on this file and a program to extract, based on any 2
points defining a rectangle, will be added into this file soon.

These &lt;REGION&gt;grid.asc files have yet another file structure simplifying
spatial retrievals based LAZEA X-Y. The layout looks like:

&gt;3556 1559 42.638058 16.016323 47   lazea-X lazea-Y pdkm hdkm lckm
&gt;3557 1559 5.12569 1.939586 47      lazea-X lazea-Y pdkm hdkm lckm
&gt;3336 1558 1.402889 0.5097 52       lazea-X lazea-Y pdkm hdkm lckm
&gt;...

The file "gridbox.txt" can be used in conjunctions with these X,Y
coordinates for spatial referencing. The "USgrid.asc" file
created solves the boundary problems between regions. Consult
the file "us/us-dist.txt" for simple stats on these files.

PROBLEMS

These files currently contain two problems which have been identified.
Future releases will correct for these errors or approach the problem
differently. In addition, in the future we will add more census and land
cover varibales as well as emissions data.

1. Water areas receiving data in allocation program. First, this is
explained by those grids on the shorelines. Part of the grid is water,
part of the grid is land. The proportional allocation algorithm thus
allocates census data to the grids for which there is partial water. The
definition of the grid being water or land should be incorporated into
the algorithm to fix this. The other problem in this area is those
census blockgroups who consists of a large portion of water area and a
tiny land area with significant population (see the Saginaw Bay area of
Lake Huron). To avoid this problem, census blocks should be used which
are either land or water, not a mixture of the two.

2. An oddity was discovered when examining the District of Columbia. In
this area certain pixels receive data values that absolutely have no
coverage with any of the polygons in the census blockgroup layer. We are
currently investigating this problem and its effect on the integrated
data layers.

3. A peculiarity. Certain areas of the census blockgroup coverage are
missing because we were unable to "chain" the particular polygon. In
other instances, large geographic areas might not contain persons in it.
In both cases the density values assinged to the grid are 0. When
integrating with the Land Cover grids, the with 0 density were missed
when integrating the grid data. There does exist a Land Cover
Characterization Code for these grids and their density values are zero.
A peculiarity we did not catch in time when processing.

4. One LCKM values in the Northwest was assigned a nonsense value over
the maximum possible of 159. Please delete this value.

NOTE: Please note that the term "land use" is used loosely. Land cover
is a better definition. The housing unit structures density is the only
measure of urban activity in these data so far. Similarly, emissions
data is at the current time lacking from the design.

&gt;---------------------------------------------------------------------------
Email comments/ideas/suggestions and bug reports to ciesin.info@ciesin.org

Phone them in at: 517.797.2727

&gt;********************* END CIESIN README FILE *********************
&gt;
&gt;

REVIEWS APPLIED TO DATA

This electronic report was subjected to the same review
standard that applies to all U.S. Geological Survey
reports. Reviewers were asked to check the topological
consistency, tolerances, attribute frequencies and statistics,
projection, and geographic extent. The reviewers checked the
metadata and a_readme.1st files for completeness and accuracy.
REFERENCES

Consortium for International Earth Science Information Network (CIESIN),
1995, Socioeconomic Data and Applications Center (SEDAC),
Archive of Census Related Products: CIESIN/SEDAC,
accessed July 21, 1998 at URL http://sedac.ciesin.org/plue/cenguide.html

Environmental Systems Research Institute, Inc. (ESRI), 1997,
ARC/INFO 7.1.1 Help, Redlands, Calif., [on-line documentation].

NOTES

Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive
purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the
U.S. Government.

Although this data set has been used by the U.S. Geological
Survey, U.S. Department of the Interior, no warranty expressed
or implied is made by the U.S. Geological Survey as to the
accuracy of the data and related materials.

The act of distribution shall not constitute any such
warranty, and no responsibility is assumed by the
U.S. Geological Survey in the use of this data, software, or
related materials.

Although this Federal Geographic Data Committee-compliant
metadata file is intended to document the data set in
nonproprietary form, as well as in ARC/INFO format, this
metadata file may include some ARC/INFO-specific terminology.
			</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>1990</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>The data is described by CIESIN in their online documentation as
derived from 1990 Census block-group level data.
			</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned.</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-129.49760931</westbc>
            <eastbc>-64.43380054</eastbc>
            <northbc>48.63644682</northbc>
            <southbc>21.80790306</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>census</themekey>
            <themekey>population</themekey>
            <themekey>density</themekey>
            <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>None</placekt>
            <placekey>Conterminous 48 United States</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>None</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Curtis V. Price</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Physical Scientist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>1608 Mountain View Rd</address>
               <city>Rapid City</city>
               <state>South Dakota</state>
               <postal>57702</postal>
               <country>United States of America</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(605) 355-4523</cntfax>
            <cntemail>cprice@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <cntinst>none</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>Compilation of the data sets was supported by the National
Water-Quality Assessment (NAWQA) Program of the U.S. Geological
Survey. The objectives of the NAWQA Program are to: (1) describe
current water-quality conditions for a large part of the
Nation's freshwater streams, rivers, and aquifers, (2) describe
how water quality is changing over time, and (3) improve the
understanding of the primary natural and anthropogenic factors
that affect water-quality conditions. National analysis of data,
based on aggregation of comparable information obtained from
across the United States, is a major component of the NAWQA
Program. These data sets were created in support of NAWQA
national data analysis activities.
		</datacred>
      <secinfo>
         <secsys>Public</secsys>
         <secclass>Unclassified</secclass>
         <sechandl>None</sechandl>
      </secinfo>
      <native>Operating System: UNIX, ARC/INFO version 7.1.1</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>Not applicable</logic>
      <complete>No changes were made (except for integer truncation) of the persons per
square mile grid and the reprojection to Albers coordinates.
		</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>Grid cell size is one kilometer; accuracy of edges (coastlines, etc.)
not tested.
				</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
         <vertacc>
            <vertaccr>Unknown</vertaccr>
         </vertacc>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Consortium for International Earth Science Information Network</origin>
                  <pubdate>19950627</pubdate>
                  <title>Archive of Census Related Products</title>
                  <geoform>map</geoform>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>NA</sername>
                     <issue>NA</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>NA</pubplace>
                     <publish>Information available online</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://water.usgs.gov/lookup/getspatial?ofr99-78_popdeng</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>2000000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>19900101</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>none</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Array of population density values.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The data from which the population density grid was created
was retrieved from URL

ftp://ftp.ciesin.org/pub/census/grid/us

The original data file was formatted like this:

&gt;16 1909 0.150968 0.145122 149
&gt;16 1910 0.384075 0.369201 149
&gt;16 1911 0.407049 0.391286 149
&gt;(... 245 MB of data)

The first three columns represent row, column,
and population density.

A FORTRAN program was used to reformat the file into
an input format used by the ARC ASCIIGRID command. The
cell size, corner coordinates, and projection came from the
documentation of the data files as posted on the CIESIN ftp site.
(This documentation file is included in this metadata file.)

The ASCIIGRID file was formatted like this:

&gt;ncols         4587
&gt;nrows         2889
&gt;xllcorner     -2050500
&gt;yllcorner     -2136500
&gt;cellsize      1000
&gt;NODATA_value  -9
&gt;4 5 3 5 3 4 5 5 3 3 3 2 2 1 1 1 1 ... (4587 values per row)
(data continues for a total of 2889 rows)

The ARC/INFO ASCIIGRID command was used to read this into a
grid, and the PROJECT command then was used to project the
grid from its original projection (Lambert Azimuthal) to the
Albers projection.  Nearest-neighbor resampling was done to
preserve the population density values through the
projection change.

This processing was performed by David Wolock, U.S. Geological
Survey, Lawrence, Kansas.
				</procdesc>
            <procdate>19950829</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Grid Cell</rasttype>
         <rowcount>2898</rowcount>
         <colcount>4521</colcount>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <mapproj>
               <mapprojn>Albers Conical Equal Area</mapprojn>
               <albers>
                  <stdparll>29.5</stdparll>
                  <stdparll>45.5</stdparll>
                  <longcm>-96</longcm>
                  <latprjo>23</latprjo>
                  <feast>0.00000</feast>
                  <fnorth>0.00000</fnorth>
               </albers>
            </mapproj>
            <planci>
               <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>1055.359799626</absres>
                  <ordres>1055.359799626</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>METERS</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1927</horizdn>
            <ellips>Clarke 1866</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378206.4</semiaxis>
            <denflat>294.98</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <overview>
         <eaover>There is a value attribute table associated with this data set,
as well as a file containing statistics about the grid.
&gt;
&gt;POPDENG.VAT:
&gt;
&gt;COLUMN   ITEM NAME        WIDTH OUTPUT  TYPE N.DEC  ALTERNATE NAME
&gt;    1  VALUE                  4    10     B      -
&gt;    5  COUNT                  4    10     B      -
&gt;
&gt;VALUE contains values of population density.
&gt;
&gt;COUNT is the number of grid cells with each particular VALUE.
&gt;
&gt;
&gt;POPDENG.STA:
&gt;
&gt;COLUMN   ITEM NAME        WIDTH OUTPUT  TYPE N.DEC  ALTERNATE NAME
&gt;    1  MIN                    8    15     F      3
&gt;    9  MAX                    8    15     F      3
&gt;   17  MEAN                   8    15     F      3
&gt;   25  STDV                   8    15     F      3
&gt;
&gt;MIN is minumum value.
&gt;
&gt;MAX is maximum value.
&gt;
&gt;MEAN is the arithmetic mean.
&gt;
&gt;STDV is the standard deviation.
			</eaover>
         <eadetcit>None</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Ask USGS - Water Webserver Team</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing</addrtype>
               <address>445 National Center</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747 (1-888-ASK-USGS)</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>http://water.usgs.gov/user_feedback_form.html</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although this data set has been used by the U.S. Geological
Survey, U.S. Department of the Interior, no warranty expressed or
implied is made by the U.S. Geological Survey as to the accuracy
of the data and related materials. The act of distribution shall not 
constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumed by 
the U.S. Geological Survey in the use of this data, software, or 
related materials.

Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive
purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S.
Government.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Export</formname>
               <formcont>Full coverage</formcont>
               <filedec>zipped</filedec>
               <transize>1</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/dsdl/ofr99-78_popdenge.gz</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Other</formname>
               <formcont>DEM Format</formcont>
               <filedec>zipped</filedec>
               <transize>1</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/dsdl/ofr99-78_popdengd.gz</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Grid</formname>
               <formcont>Full coverage</formcont>
               <filedec>zipped</filedec>
               <transize>1</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/dsdl/ofr99-78_popdenga.gz</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None. This dataset is provided by USGS as a public service.</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20041108</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Ask USGS -- Water Webserver Team</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing</addrtype>
               <address>445 National Center</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747 (1-888-ASK-USGS)</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>http://answers.usgs.gov/cgi-bin/gsanswers?pemail=h2oteam&amp;subject=GIS+Dataset+ofr99-78_popdeng</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
