<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata xmlns="http://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/csdgm"
          xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://igsaaahmvsw001/waterportal/fgdc-std-001-1998.xsd">
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Faunt, Claudia C.</origin>
            <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
            <title>Potential structural barriers to ground-water flow, Death Valley regional ground-water flow system, Nevada and California</title>
            <edition>Edition 2 which is an update from sir045205_hfbs_geo.xml</edition>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Digital geospatial data sets for the hydrogeologic framework and transient ground-water flow model, Death Valley regional ground-water flow system, Nevada and California</sername>
               <issue>hfbs_geo</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Reston, Virginia</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://water.usgs.gov/lookup/getspatial?pp1711_hfbs_geo</onlink>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Belcher, W.R. and Sweetkind, D.S. (editors)</origin>
                  <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
                  <title>Death Valley regional ground-water flow system, Nevada and California - Hydrogeologic framework and transient ground-water flow model</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper</sername>
                     <issue>1711</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Reston, Virginia</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>6 chapters, 2 appendices, 2 plates, 403 p.</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp1711</onlink>
                  <lworkcit>
                     <citeinfo>
                        <origin>Belcher, W.R. (editor)</origin>
                        <pubdate>2004</pubdate>
                        <title>Death Valley regional ground-water flow system, Nevada and California - Hydrogeologic framework and transient ground-water flow model</title>
                        <serinfo>
                           <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Report</sername>
                           <issue>2004-5205</issue>
                        </serinfo>
                        <pubinfo>
                           <pubplace>Reston, Virginia</pubplace>
                           <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                        </pubinfo>
                        <othercit>6 chapters, 2 appendices, 2 plates, 408 p.</othercit>
                        <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sir/2004/5205/</onlink>
                     </citeinfo>
                  </lworkcit>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This digital dataset defines the surface traces of regional geologic structures designated as potential ground-water flow barriers in an approximately 45,000 square-kilometer area of the Death Valley regional ground-water flow system (DVRFS) in southern Nevada and California. Most geologic structures representing potential flow barriers were faults that were identified on the basis of length, offset, type of slip, orientation with respect to predominate ground-water flow directions, the location of springs, abrupt water level offsets, and hydraulic characteristics (Sweetkind and others, 2004). A subset of the potential ground-water flow barriers was incorporated into a transient ground-water flow model of the DVRFS (Faunt and others, 2004). This model is the most recent in a number of regional-scale models developed by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) for the U.S. Department of Energy (DOE) to support investigations at the Nevada Test Site (NTS) and at Yucca Mountain, Nevada (see "Larger Work Citation", Chapter A, page 8).</abstract>
         <purpose>Structures representing potential ground-water flow barriers were used in the development of the transient ground-water flow model of the DVRFS.</purpose>
         <supplinf>The potential-flow barrier data set is one of many layers in a geospatial data base supporting the USGS DVRFS project. During this 5-year (1998-2004) project the USGS, in cooperation with DOE and other Federal, State, and local agencies, developed this geospatial data base for a regional-scale, 3D hydrogeologic framework model (HFM) and a ground-water flow model. The models are intended to address water-resource issues and the potential movement of radioactive material from the Nevada Test Site and the proposed high-level nuclear waste repository at Yucca Mountain, Nevada.

Data from two previous ground-water flow models of the greater Death Valley region (see "Larger Work Citation", Chapter A, p. 7) were the foundation of the DVRFS geospatial database. Those and other data were reexamined through a series of regional-scale hydrologic investigations to provide updated and spatially consistent interpretations for the DVRFS study. In some cases, new data were collected to augment the existing information. Data compiled from the studies include natural ground-water discharge occurring through evapotranspiration and spring flow; ground-water pumping for the period 1913-98; ground-water recharge simulated as net infiltration; ground-water inflow and outflow at lateral model boundaries; hydraulic conductivity and its relation to depth and other rock properties; and the estimation of water levels representative of prepumped and pumped conditions in the region. Digital elevation models, geologic maps, borehole information, cross sections, and other 3D models were used to develop the HFM which represents the geometry of 27 hydrogeologic units and structural features. The resulting geospatial data base supports characterization and conceptualization of the DVRFS, construction of 3D hydrogeologic framework and ground-water flow models, and visualization of analysis and model results.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>2004</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>
-117.999214</westbc>
            <eastbc>
-114.961993</eastbc>
            <northbc>
37.738519</northbc>
            <southbc>
35.501620</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>USGS Water Basics Glossary. Accessed May 3, 2005 at http://capp.water.usgs.gov/GIP/h2o_gloss/; American Geological Institute Glossary of Geology</themekt>
            <themekey>Death Valley regional ground-water flow system</themekey>
            <themekey>flow model</themekey>
            <themekey>ground water</themekey>
            <themekey>ground-water flow barrier</themekey>
            <themekey>horizontal flow barrier</themekey>
            <themekey>hydrogeologic framework model</themekey>
            <themekey>hydrogeology</themekey>
            <themekey>hydrology</themekey>
            <themekey>transient ground-water model</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>U.S. Board of Geographic Names (BGN) and Geographic Names Information System (GNIS)</placekt>
            <placekey>Amargosa Desert</placekey>
            <placekey>Ash Meadows</placekey>
            <placekey>California</placekey>
            <placekey>California Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Chicago Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>China Ranch</placekey>
            <placekey>Clark County</placekey>
            <placekey>Clayton Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Coal Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Death Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Esmeralda County</placekey>
            <placekey>Eureka Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Franklin Lake</placekey>
            <placekey>Franklin Well</placekey>
            <placekey>Garden Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Inyo County</placekey>
            <placekey>Kern County</placekey>
            <placekey>Las Vegas Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Lincoln County</placekey>
            <placekey>Mesquite Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Mineral County</placekey>
            <placekey>Mono County</placekey>
            <placekey>Nevada</placekey>
            <placekey>Nevada Test Site</placekey>
            <placekey>Nye County</placekey>
            <placekey>Oasis Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Owlshead Mountains</placekey>
            <placekey>Pahranagat Range</placekey>
            <placekey>Pahrump Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Panamint Range</placekey>
            <placekey>Penoyer Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Railroad Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Resting Spring</placekey>
            <placekey>Saline Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>San Bernadino County</placekey>
            <placekey>Sarcobatus Flat</placekey>
            <placekey>Sheep Range</placekey>
            <placekey>Shoshone</placekey>
            <placekey>Silurian Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>southern Nevada</placekey>
            <placekey>Spring Mountains</placekey>
            <placekey>Stewart Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Stone Cabin Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Tecopa</placekey>
            <placekey>Yucca Mountain</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>Data have been checked to ensure the accuracy of the data. If any errors are detected, please notify the originating office. The U.S. Geological Survey strongly recommends that careful attention be paid to the metadata file associated with these data. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and (or) contained herein.

Acknowledgement of the U.S. Geological Survey would be appreciated in products derived from these data.

Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.  Although this Federal Geographic Data Committee-compliant metadata file is intended to document the data set in nonproprietary form, as well as in ArcGIS format, this metadata file may include some ArcGIS-specific terminology.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
               <cntper>Claudia Faunt</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>California Water Science Center</address>
               <address>San Diego Projects Office</address>
               <address>4165 Spruance Road, Suite 200</address>
               <city>San Diego</city>
               <state>California</state>
               <postal>92101</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(619) 225-6142</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(619) 225-6101</cntfax>
            <cntemail>ccfaunt@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/browse/sir045205_hfbs_geo.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Illlustration of data set</browsed>
         <browset>jpg</browset>
      </browse>
      <datacred>Spatial data sets supporting the Death Valley regional ground-water flow system (DVRFS) project were developed in cooperation with the U.S. Department of Energy (DOE) National Nuclear Security Administration/Nevada Site Office (NNSA/NSO) Underground Test Area (UGTA) project of the Office of Environmental Management, the NNSA/NSO Hydrologic Resource Management Program (HRMP), the Office of Civilian Radioactive Waste Management (OCRWM) Yucca Mountain Project (YMP), the NNSA/NSO Maintenance of Test Capability (MTC) program, and the National Park Service (NPS).</datacred>
      <native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.1.0.722</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>Attributes added by the GIS and the data set author were checked by inspection using a GIS. In addition, attributes were checked and evaluated as part of the review process associated with the publication of the source report.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Line features in this dataset represent the plan view locations of geologic structures. Lines may overlap. No duplicate line features exist. All nodes are represented by a single coordinate pair which indicates the beginning or end of a line. All vertices that define the shape of the line are represented by a unique coordinate pair.</logic>
      <complete>Line features in this data set were selected by Sweetkind and others (2004) from a larger digital compilation of regional faults and structural zones for purposes of representing significant hydrostructural features in the DVRFS models. The data set is complete and is not anticipated to change.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>The accuracy of the compiled digital line features in the data set is based upon the accuracy of source maps and digital data sets which generally are compiled to meet National Map Accuracy Standards. Horizontal positional accuracy was tested by visually comparing these line features to source maps using a GIS and hardcopy plots.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Sweetkind, D.S.</origin>
                  <origin>Belcher, W.R.</origin>
                  <origin>Faunt, C.C.</origin>
                  <origin>Potter, C.J.</origin>
                  <pubdate>2004</pubdate>
                  <title>Geology and Hydrogeology</title>
                  <othercit>Chapter B</othercit>
                  <lworkcit>
                     <citeinfo>
                        <origin>Belcher, W.R. (ed.)</origin>
                        <pubdate>2004</pubdate>
                        <title>Death Valley regional ground-water flow system, Nevada and California--Hydrogeologic framework and transient ground-water flow model</title>
                        <geoform>document</geoform>
                        <serinfo>
                           <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Report</sername>
                           <issue>2004-5205</issue>
                        </serinfo>
                        <pubinfo>
                           <pubplace>Reston, Virginia</pubplace>
                           <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                        </pubinfo>
                        <onlink>http://water.usgs.gov/pubs/sir/2004/5205/</onlink>
                     </citeinfo>
                  </lworkcit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>250,000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2004</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Sweetkind and others (2004)</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Source data for models.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Faunt, C.C.</origin>
                  <origin>Sweetkind, D.S.</origin>
                  <origin>Belcher, W.R.</origin>
                  <pubdate>2004</pubdate>
                  <title>Three-Dimensional Hydrogeologic Framework Model</title>
                  <othercit>Chapter E</othercit>
                  <lworkcit>
                     <citeinfo>
                        <origin>Belcher, W.R. (ed.)</origin>
                        <pubdate>2004</pubdate>
                        <title>Death Valley regional ground-water flow system, Nevada and California--Hydrogeologic framework and transient ground-water flow model</title>
                        <geoform>document</geoform>
                        <serinfo>
                           <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Report</sername>
                           <issue>2004-5205</issue>
                        </serinfo>
                        <pubinfo>
                           <pubplace>Reston, Virginia</pubplace>
                           <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                        </pubinfo>
                        <onlink>http://water.usgs.gov/pubs/sir/2004/5205/</onlink>
                     </citeinfo>
                  </lworkcit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>250,000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2004</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Faunt and others (2004)</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Three-Dimensional Hydrogeologic Framework Model</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>A subset of mapped faults was selected from a digital compilation of principal faults and structural zones potentially influencing ground-water flow in the DVRFS region (Sweetkind and others, 2004). Faults were selected on the basis of length, offset, type of slip, orientation, and hydraulic characteristics. Using a GIS, Sweetkind and others (2004) analyzed the faults relative to a potentiometric surface of the DVRFS, a map of springs, and ground-water flow paths. This data set contains the resulting faults designated as potential flow barriers. These faults were source data for the development of hydrostructural features in the transient ground-water flow model of the DVRFS (Faunt and others, 2004).</procdesc>
            <srcused>Sweetkind and others (2004)</srcused>
            <srcused>Faunt and thers (2004)</srcused>
            <procdate>2003</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Vector</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>String</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>110</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <gridsys>
               <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
               <utm>
                  <utmzone>11</utmzone>
                  <transmer>
                     <sfctrmer>0.999600</sfctrmer>
                     <longcm>-117.000000</longcm>
                     <latprjo>0.000000</latprjo>
                     <feast>500000.000000</feast>
                     <fnorth>0.000000</fnorth>
                  </transmer>
               </utm>
            </gridsys>
            <planci>
               <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>0.000512</absres>
                  <ordres>0.000512</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>meters</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1927</horizdn>
            <ellips>Clarke 1866</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378206.400000</semiaxis>
            <denflat>294.978698</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>
Potential ground-water flow barrier</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Geologic structure which potentially retards ground-water flow</enttypd>
            <enttypds>Author (Metadata Contact Person)</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>FID</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Environmental Systems Research Institute, Inc. (ESRI)</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>NAME</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Abbreviated name of geologic structure</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Author (Point of Contact)</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Name of fault or lineament</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>FAULT_NO</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Fault identification number</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>"Larger Work" (Table B-8, Figure B-39)</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>32</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>STRUCTURE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Structure type</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Author (Point of Contact)</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Type description of structure.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>DESCRIP</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Structure or lineament name</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>"Larger Work Citation" (Table B-8)</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Name of structure used in "Larger Work Citation"</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <overview>
         <eaover>Each line feature has 6 attributes. Two attributes are automatically generated by the GIS (FID, Shape) for internal software purposes. The remaining attributes were assigned by the author (Point of Contact) for analysis and (or) model development.</eaover>
         <eadetcit>-</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
               <cntper>Ask USGS - Water Webserver Team</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>445 National Center</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>http://water.usgs.gov/user_feedback_form.html</cntemail>
            <cntinst>Contact via email or phone.</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>Digital geospatial data sets for the transient ground-water flow model and hydrogeologic framework model, Death Valley regional ground-water flow system, Nevada and California</resdesc>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. These data should be directly acquired from a U.S. Geological Survey server, and not indirectly through other sources that may have altered the data in some way.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Shapefile</formname>
               <formvern>1.0</formvern>
               <filedec>Unzip</filedec>
               <transize>67 Kilobytes</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/dsdl/hfbs_geo.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20070201</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>445 National Center</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>Virginia</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747 (1-888-ASK-USGS)</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>http://answers.usgs.gov/cgi-bin/gsanswers?pemail=h2oteam&amp;subject=GIS+Dataset+pp1711_hfbs_geo</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
