<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Greta J. Orris</origin>
            <origin>James D. Bliss</origin>
            <pubdate>2002</pubdate>
            <title>Mines and Mineral Occurrences of Afghanistan</title>
            <edition>First</edition>
            <geoform>Microsoft Excel 98 spreadsheet</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>02-110</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Menlo Park, CA</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/0110/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This dataset contains latitudes, longitudes, commodity, andlimited geologic data for metallic and nonmetallic mines,deposits, and mineral occurrences of Afghanistan.  The datain this compilation were derived from published literatureand data files of members of the USGS National IndustrialMinerals project.  This dataset consists of one table with17 fields and over 1000 sites.</abstract>
         <purpose>This dataset was compiled due to interest in Afghanistanand anticipated continuing interest as post-war aidand reconstruction begin.</purpose>
         <supplinf>This dataset consists of one Excel 98 spreadsheet file,OF02110.xls. Data fields include location, deposit, commodity,and geologic data for mineral deposits, mines and occurrences.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <current>Much of the data dates from the Russian occupation ofAfghanistan, although the published sources had more recent dates.</current>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>2002</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>No updates are planned.</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>60.45</westbc>
            <eastbc>75.0</eastbc>
            <northbc>38.5</northbc>
            <southbc>29.25</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>economic geology</themekey>
            <themekey>mineral resources</themekey>
            <themekey>geospatial datasets</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Afghanistan</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Augmented FIPS 10-4 and FIPS 6-4</placekt>
            <placekey>AF = Afghanistan</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None.</accconst>
      <useconst>This digital database is not meant to be used or displayed atany scale larger than 1:1,000,000.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Dr. Greta J. Orris</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
               <address>520 N. Park Ave.; Suite 355</address>
               <city>Tucson</city>
               <state>AZ</state>
               <postal>85719</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(520) 670-5583</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>greta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <native>Microsoft Excel 98</native>
      <datacred>G.J. Orris and J.D. Bliss compiled the data on Afghanistanmineral resources from previously published compilations,other published sources, and project files. Locations weretaken from published sources; no effort was made to determinethe correctness of these data beyond a preliminary review to besure they plot in the correct country and reconciliation ofduplicate and conflicting data where possible. Most of thelatitudes-longitudes are believed to be within 5 minutes oftheir true locations, but other locations may be highlyinaccurate.</datacred>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>The accuracy of file data attributes is highly variable,based on the compilers' evaluation of the source literature.The data tables were proofed against the original reports.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Point data is given in latitude and longitude decimal degrees.Location errors are a result of incorrect original data, errorcaused by multiple locations with the same name, and errorintroduced by data entry or location format conversion.</logic>
      <complete>This report is the most complete compilation of Afghanistanmines, deposits, and occurrences known.  However, it is highlylikely that there are additional sites that are not included.In addition, data for many of the sites are incomplete.Determination of latitudes and longitudes for some sites with nopublished location were impossible given the available data.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>Most locations are believed to be within 5 minutes of thecorrect location.  The latitudes and longitudes were largelytaken directly from the published literature. Theaccuracy of these locations varies with the detail ofthe original information.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Data were separated into various fields (categories) withinthe Excel spreadsheet.  Duplicates were removed where identifiedand inconsistencies reconciled or noted in the Comments field.</procdesc>
            <procdate>2002</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Creation of original metadata record</procdesc>
            <procdate>20020320</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Dr. Greta J. Orris</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
                     <address>520 N. Park Ave. Suite 355</address>
                     <city>Tucson</city>
                     <state>AZ</state>
                     <postal>85719</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>(520) 670-5583</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>greta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <indspref>Geographic coordinates are provided for each location,however it is important to consider the informationgiven in the comments field of each row to interpretthe geographic coordinates properly.</indspref>
   </spdoinfo>
   <eainfo>
      <overview>
         <eaover>The following attributes exist in the OF02XXX spreadsheet ofthe data.
1. Locality/Deposit Name
2. Synonyms and Other Names or Spellings
3. Deposit or District Name
4. Province
5. Latitude - degrees, minutes, seconds
6. Longitude - degrees, minutes, seconds
7. Commodity(s) - This field contains one or more standardsymbols for chemical elements along with abbreviations forminerals and other commodities as follows:
&gt; Abbrev  Commodity&gt;  Arag    aragonite&gt;  Asb     asbestos&gt;  Ba      barite&gt;  Bri     brine&gt;  COA     coal&gt;  COLL    collectibles&gt;  Ca      calcite&gt;  Cly     clay&gt;  Dol     dolomite&gt;  Epi     epidote&gt;  F       fluorite&gt;  Fld     feldspar&gt;  GEM     gemstones&gt;  GRF     graphite&gt;  Gar     garnet&gt;  Gyp     gypsum&gt;  Hal     halite&gt;  Lst     limestone&gt;  Mbl     marble&gt;  Mg      magnesium, magnesite&gt;  Mica    mica, muscovite&gt;  NaCO    Sodium carbonate&gt;  Oli     olivine&gt;  Peat    peat&gt;  Qtz     quartz&gt;  REE     rare earths&gt;  SDG     sand and gravel&gt;  Serp    serpentine&gt;  Shl     shale&gt;  Si      silica&gt;  Tlc     talc
8. Type of Deposit - brief deposit description
9. Status
10. Host Rock Age
11. Host Rock
12. Significant Minerals or Materials
13. Deposit Size and (or) Grade
14. Comments (explains location values)
15. References (these are in-text citations; the fullbibliographic references are given in the report)
16. Decimal Latitude
17. Decimal Longitude</eaover>
         <eadetcit>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/0110/of02-110.pdf</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Information Services Open-File Report Sales</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
               <address>Box 25286</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>CO</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(303)202-4700</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(303)202-4188</cntfax>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>USGS Open-File Report 02-110</resdesc>
      <distliab>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) provides these geographicdata "as is." The USGS makes no guarantee or warrantyconcerning the accuracy of information contained in thegeographic data. The USGS further makes no warranties, eitherexpressed or implied as to any other matter whatsoever, including,without limitation, the condition of the product, or its fitnessfor any particular purpose. The burden for determining fitness foruse lies entirely with the user. Although these data have beenprocessed successfully on computers at the USGS, no warranty,expressed or implied, is made by the USGS regarding the use ofthese data on any other system, nor does the fact ofdistribution constitute or imply any such warranty.In no event shall the USGS have any liability whatsoever forpayment of any consequential, incidental, indirect, special, ortort damages of any kind, including, but not limited to, anyloss of profits arising out of use of or reliance on thegeographic data or arising out of the delivery, installation,operation, or support by USGS.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>XLS</formname>
               <formcont>Latitudes, longitudes, commodity information, commodity,and geologic data for  mines, deposits, and occurrencesof Afghanistan</formcont>
               <transize>0.404</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2002/0110/of02-110.xls</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150204</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Peter N Schweitzer</cntper>
               <cntorg>USGS Midwest Area</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Collection manager, USGS Geoscience Data Clearinghouse, http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Mail Stop 95412201 Sunrise Valley Dr</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192-0002</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>703-648-6533</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>703-648-6252</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pschweitzer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
