<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Gibbs, Ann E.</origin>
            <pubdate>20001018</pubdate>
            <title>SWWA26_750UTM: Southwest Washington 750 meter, 1926 BathymetryGrid; UTM Projection</title>
            <edition>Version 1.0</edition>
            <geoform>raster digital data</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Menlo Park, CA</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Gibbs, A.E.</origin>
                  <origin>Buijsman, M.C.</origin>
                  <origin>Sherwood, C.R.</origin>
                  <pubdate>2000</pubdate>
                  <title>Non-navigational Gridded Bathymetry Data: The Washington-OregonCoast, 1926-1998; A data release and description of methods.</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
                     <issue>00-448</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2000/of00-448/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>SWWA26_750UTM is a digital bathymetric surface grid of the seafloor offthe coast of Southwest Washington and Northwest Oregon.Grid cell spacing is 750m and the projection is UTM Zone 10.The surface was produced by gridding National Ocean Service (NOS)Hydrographic Surveys collected between 1926 and 1928. This work includesthe most recent bathymetric data available on a regional scale over theinner to middle continental shelf off the coast of Washington. Theresults represent the best available estimate of the seafloor morphologyfor the time period circa 1926.</abstract>
         <purpose>This bathymetric surface grid is intended for use as an historicalbathymetric base map for scientific research. It is not intended fornavigational purposes.  The grid was originally intended for use in wavemodelling experiments as part of the Southwest Washington Coastal ErosionStudy (SWCES), a cooperative study by the US Geological Survey and theWashington State Department of Ecology.</purpose>
         <supplinf>The SWCES was initiated to examine coastal geology, processes, andnatural hazards within the Columbia River littoral cell.  The study isjointly directed by the U.S. Geological Survey Coastal and MarineGeology Program and the Washington State Department of EcologyShorelands and Environmental Assistance Program, withactive participation of local communities in Pacific and Grays Harborcounties. Related USGS work in the Southwest Washington Coastal ErosionStudy can be found online at:http://www.ecy.wa.gov/programs/sea/swce/
The grid described here is part of a data release of sixteen similarbathymetric grids.  These include: 1926 and 1926-1998 mergedOregon/Washington (ORWA) and Southwest Washington study area (SWWA)grids, each at 500m and 750m grid spacing, in UTM Zone 10 (meters)and Washington State Plane South Zone 5626 (meters) projections.The ORWA data set extends from Heceta Head, Oregon to Cape Johnson,Washington, from the shoreline to about 2000m water depth; the SWWA dataset extends from Tillamook Head Oregon to Pt. Grenville WA, from theshore to approximately 700m water depth.
The data used to create this bathymetric grid were collected between1926 and 1928. Most data were collected between 1926 and 1927.Refer to Gibbs and others, 2000 for details.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>1926</begdate>
               <enddate>1928</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-124.56053838</westbc>
            <eastbc>-123.91978744</eastbc>
            <northbc>47.35119221</northbc>
            <southbc>45.87359687</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>marine geology</themekey>
            <themekey>bathymetry</themekey>
            <themekey>sea-floor characteristics</themekey>
            <themekey>geospatial datasets</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>Coastal Geology</themekey>
            <themekey>Marine Geology</themekey>
            <themekey>Bathymetry</themekey>
            <themekey>Hydrographic Data</themekey>
            <themekey>Southwest Washington Coastal Erosion Study</themekey>
            <themekey>Columbia River Littoral Cell</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Southwest Washington</placekey>
            <placekey>Northwest Oregon</placekey>
            <placekey>Washington</placekey>
            <placekey>Oregon</placekey>
            <placekey>Grays Harbor</placekey>
            <placekey>Willapa Bay</placekey>
            <placekey>Columbia River</placekey>
            <placekey>Pacific Ocean</placekey>
            <placekey>Pacific Northwest</placekey>
            <placekey>USA</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Augmented FIPS 10-4 and FIPS 6-4</placekt>
            <placekey>41007 = Clatsop</placekey>
            <placekey>53031 = Jefferson</placekey>
            <placekey>53027 = Grays Harbor</placekey>
            <placekey>53049 = Pacific</placekey>
            <placekey>OC41 = Northeast Pacific</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>Please recognize the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) as the source ofthis information.
Although these data have been used by the U.S. Geological Survey,U.S. Department of the Interior, no warranty expressed or impliedis made by the U.S. Geological Survey as to the accuracy of thedata. The act of distribution shall not constitute any such warranty, andno responsibility is assumed by the U.S. Geological Survey in theuse of this data, software, or related materials.
This information is not intended for navigational purposes.
Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptivepurposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S.Government.
Feel free to use the data but please cite this publication:Gibbs, A.E., Buijsman, M.C., and Sherwood, C.R., 2000,Non-navigational Gridded Bathymetry Data : The Washington-OregonCoast, 1926-1998; A data release and description of methods.USGS Open-File-Report OF 00-448.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>United States Geological Survey (USGS),Coastal and Marine Geology (CMG)</cntorg>
               <cntper>Ann E. Gibbs</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Geologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>USGS, MailStop 999, 345 Middlefield Road</address>
               <city>Menlo Park</city>
               <state>CA</state>
               <postal>94025-3561</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(650) 329-5060</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(650) 329-5190</cntfax>
            <cntemail>agibbs@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>This Program is jointly funded by the Washington State Department ofEcology and the US Geological Survey, Coastal &amp; Marine Geology Program.</datacred>
      <native>SunOS UNIX, ARC/INFO version 7.2.1, SURFER V.6</native>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Ann E. Gibbs and Guy Gelfenbaum</origin>
            <pubdate>1999</pubdate>
            <title>Bathymetric change off the Washington/Oregon Coast</title>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Coastal Sediments '99</sername>
               <issue>Proceedings of the 4th International Symposiumon Coastal Engineering and Scienceof Coastal Sediment Processes</issue>
            </serinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>The data have been thoroughly analyzed for for gross inaccuracies.A discussion of errors and accuracies associated with the originaldata collection methodologies can be found in Gibbs and Gelfenbaum(1999).</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Only NOS sounding data with an original cartographic code of 711are included.  The data set was rigorously editedof obviously erroneous points.</logic>
      <complete>Gaps in the hydrographic survey point data exists west of Willapa Bayfrom approximately -124.034 to -124.363 degrees longitude and46.573 to 46.738 degrees latitude and northwest of Tillamook Bayfrom approximately -123.834 to -124.120 longitude and45.472 to 45.626 latitude. The remaining data are considered complete.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>Horizontal accuracies for NOS surveys vary by water depth anddistance from shore (see Gibbs and Gelfenbaum, 1999).</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
         <vertacc>
            <vertaccr>Vertical accuracies for NOS surveys vary by water depth anddistance from shore (see Gibbs and Gelfenbaum, 1999).</vertaccr>
         </vertacc>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>National Geophysical Data Center</origin>
                  <pubdate>1998</pubdate>
                  <title>National Ocean Service Hydrographic Survey Data:US Coastal Waters. CD-ROM Set, Version 4.0.</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>NOAA Data Announcement</sername>
                     <issue>98-MGG-03</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <publish>World Data Center for Marine Geology &amp; Geophysics</publish>
                     <pubplace>Boulder CO</pubplace>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>CD-ROM</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <rngdates>
                     <begdate>1926</begdate>
                     <enddate>1974</enddate>
                  </rngdates>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>NOS_HSD</srccitea>
            <srccontr>All pre-1998 hydrographic data were obtained from this source.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Data were processed using both ARC/INFO (v. 7.1) and SURFER32 (v6.0). Original NOS point data were projected from geographic units(latitude/longitude, datum NAD27) to the Washington State PlaneSouth coordinate system (datum NAD83). Non-sounding data(cartographic code not equal to 711; rocks awash, pilings, etc.)and obviously erroneous or questionable data (based on contour*donuts*, trackline crossing inconsistencies, etc.) were editedout of the data set. USACE data for Grays Harbor and Willapa Baywere converted from Washington State Plane South (feet) and forthe Columbia River from Oregon State Plane (feet). SURFER was usedto generate preliminary grids of all the data. Data editing andfinal grid construction was completed using ARC/INFO.
Individual grids were processed using different data sets andgridding methodologies. Grid boundaries for the SWWA and ORWAgrids are listed in Tables 3 and 4, respectively.
The SWWA26 grid was created by gridding three subsets of editedNOS point data (midshore; nearshore; shoreface; Fig. 2) usingparameters that best fit the individual data set. Subsetboundaries were determined based on differences in the original1926 survey scale, sounding distribution, and data precision (seeGibbs and Gelfenbaum, 1999 for a more detailed description). Eachsubset was gridded separately in SURFER, using the processingsteps outlined in Table 5, then imported into ARC/INFO, clipped toits specific boundary, and merged with the other sub-grids tocreate the final SWWA26 surface.
The SWWA98 grid is the SWWA26 grid with a subset of merged andgridded 1926/1998 point data nested within it. The merged1926/1998 point data set includes both the 1998 USACE hydrographicdata from the approaches to and ebb-tidal deltas of Grays Harbor,Willapa Bay, and the Columbia River, and portions of the 1926 NOShydrographic data set. Because of large changes that have occurredin the location and morphology of these ebb-tidal deltas since1926, the merged data have, in places, abrupt and irregularboundaries. In order to obtain a smooth transition across thesurvey boundaries, data was edited, modified, and, wherenecessary, point data added, based on inferred shoreface andebb-tidal delta morphology. This modified and merged 1926/1998data set was then gridded, clipped to the modified 1998 surveyboundaries, and mosaicked with SWWA26 to produce the final SWWA98surface. Specific techniques used to create the merged 1926/1998point data set are discussed in the following section GeneratingThe Modern 1998 Hydrographic Data Set. Specific grid processingparameters used to create SWWA98 are shown in Table 6.
The ORWA grids include gridded raw, unedited NOS hydrographic datawith the more rigorously edited and processed SWWA grids nestedwithin them. The NOS point data were gridded using a linearkriging algorithm, matrix smoothed, and mosaicked with either theSWWA26 or SWWA98 grid to create the final ORWA26 and ORWA98surfaces, respectively. Specific processing parameters are shownin Table 7.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1999</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>US Geological Survey, CMG</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unpublished material</pubdate>
                  <title>Point coverage SWWA26PTS_UTM</title>
                  <edition>Version 1.0</edition>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <rngdates>
                     <begdate>1926</begdate>
                     <enddate>1928</enddate>
                  </rngdates>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>SWWA26PTS_UTM</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Edited NOS hydrographic data points used for gridding.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>NOS_HSD data projected from Lat/Long NAD27 to WASP SouthZone 5626, edited of erroneous points, and converted to UTM10.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1999</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Creation of original metadata record</procdesc>
            <procdate>20001018</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntorgp>
                     <cntorg>United States Geological Survey (USGS),Coastal and Marine Geology (CMG)</cntorg>
                     <cntper>Ann E. Gibbs</cntper>
                  </cntorgp>
                  <cntpos>Geologist</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
                     <address>USGS, MailStop 999, 345 Middlefield Road</address>
                     <city>Menlo Park</city>
                     <state>CA</state>
                     <postal>94025-3561</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>(650) 329-5060</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>(650) 329-5190</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>agibbs@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Grid Cell</rasttype>
         <rowcount>218</rowcount>
         <colcount>62</colcount>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <gridsys>
               <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
               <utm>
                  <utmzone>10</utmzone>
                  <transmer>
                     <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
                     <longcm>-123.</longcm>
                     <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
                     <feast>500000</feast>
                     <fnorth>0</fnorth>
                  </transmer>
               </utm>
            </gridsys>
            <planci>
               <plance>row and column</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>750</absres>
                  <ordres>750</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>Meters</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
            <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378206.4</semiaxis>
            <denflat>294.98</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
      <vertdef>
         <depthsys>
            <depthdn>Mean lower low water</depthdn>
            <depthres>1.0</depthres>
            <depthdu>meters</depthdu>
            <depthem>Explicit depth coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</depthem>
         </depthsys>
      </vertdef>
   </spref>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>United States Geological Survey (USGS),Coastal and Marine Geology (CMG)</cntorg>
               <cntper>Ann E. Gibbs</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Geologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>USGS, MailStop 999, 345 Middlefield Road</address>
               <city>Menlo Park</city>
               <state>CA</state>
               <postal>94025-3561</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(650) 329-5060</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(650) 329-5190</cntfax>
            <cntemail>agibbs@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>USGS Open-File Report 00-448</resdesc>
      <distliab>Please recognize the US Geological Survey andSouthwest Washington Coastal Erosion Studyas the source of this information
Although these data have been used by the U.S.Geological Survey, U.S. Department of the Interior,no warranty expressed or implied is made by the U.S.Geological Survey as to the accuracy of the data.
The act of distribution shall not constitute any suchwarranty, and no responsibility is assumed by theU.S. Geological Survey in the use of this data,software, or related materials.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ARCE</formname>
               <formvern>7.1</formvern>
               <formcont>Gridded bathymetry, georegistered</formcont>
               <filedec>gzip -d</filedec>
               <transize>0.04</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2000/of00-448/utm/grids/swwa26_750utm.e00.gz</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Arc/Info ASCII grid</formname>
               <formvern>7.1</formvern>
               <formcont>Gridded bathymetry, georegistered</formcont>
               <filedec>gzip -d</filedec>
               <transize>0.04</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2000/of00-448/utm/grids/swwa26_750utm.asc.gz</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Surfer ASCII grid</formname>
               <formvern>Surfer32 6.0</formvern>
               <formcont>Gridded bathymetry, georegistered</formcont>
               <filedec>gzip -d</filedec>
               <transize>0.04</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2000/of00-448/utm/grids/swwa26_750utm.grd.gz</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Columnar text</formname>
               <formspec>Points are specified one per line, x and y are integer, z is floating point with depth negative.</formspec>
               <formcont>Gridded bathymetry, georegistered</formcont>
               <filedec>gzip -d</filedec>
               <transize>0.08</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2000/of00-448/utm/grids/swwa26_750utm.dat.gz</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150204</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Peter N Schweitzer</cntper>
               <cntorg>USGS Midwest Area</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Collection manager, USGS Geoscience Data Clearinghouse, http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Mail Stop 95412201 Sunrise Valley Dr</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192-0002</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>703-648-6533</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>703-648-6252</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pschweitzer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
