<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Pamela D. Derkey</origin>
            <origin>Bruce R. Johnson</origin>
            <origin>Beatrice B. Lackaff</origin>
            <origin>Robert E. Derkey</origin>
            <pubdate>1998</pubdate>
            <title>Digital geologic map of the Rosalia 1:100,000 quadrangle,Washington and Idaho: a digital database for the 1990S.Z. Waggoner map</title>
            <edition>version 1.0</edition>
            <geoform>map</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>98-357</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Spokane WA</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/1998/of98-357/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The geology of the Rosalia 1:100,000 quadrangle, Washington and Idahowas compiled and published as a paper product by the WashingtonDivision of Geology and Earth Resources (Waggoner, 1990).  The U.S.Geological Survey converted the geologic data to a digital geographicinformation system (GIS) format as part of a larger effort to createregional digital geology for the Pacific Northwest. The digitalgeologic map database can be queried in many ways to produce a varietyof derivative geologic maps.</abstract>
         <purpose>This dataset was developed to provide geologic map GIS of theRosalia 1:100,000 quadrangle for use in future spatial analysisby a variety of users.
This database is not meant to be used or displayed at any scalelarger than 1:100,000 (e.g., 1:62,500 or 1:24,000).</purpose>
         <supplinf>This GIS consists of two major Arc/Info datasets: one line andpolygon file (ros100k) containing geologic contacts and structures(lines) and geologic map rock units (polygons), and one point file(rospnt) containing structural data.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>1998</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>In progress</progress>
         <update>Will update with new geologic map datamodel, perhaps in 1999.</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-118.0</westbc>
            <eastbc>-117.0</eastbc>
            <northbc>47.50</northbc>
            <southbc>47.00</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>geology</themekey>
            <themekey>geologic maps</themekey>
            <themekey>bedrock geologic units</themekey>
            <themekey>geologic structure</themekey>
            <themekey>geospatial datasets</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Idaho</placekey>
            <placekey>Washington</placekey>
            <placekey>Rosalia</placekey>
            <placekey>Adams County</placekey>
            <placekey>Lincoln County</placekey>
            <placekey>Spokane County</placekey>
            <placekey>Whitman County</placekey>
            <placekey>Pacific Northwest</placekey>
            <placekey>USA</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Augmented FIPS 10-4 and FIPS 6-4</placekt>
            <placekey>53001 = Adams</placekey>
            <placekey>53043 = Lincoln</placekey>
            <placekey>53063 = Spokane</placekey>
            <placekey>53075 = Whitman</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst/>
      <useconst>This digital database is not meant to be used or displayed atany scale larger than 1:100,000 (e.g., 1:62,500 or 1:24,00).
Any hardcopies utilizing these data sets shall clearly indicatetheir source.  If the user has modified the data in any waythey are obligated to describe the types of modifications theyhave performed on the hardcopy map.  User specifically agreesnot to misrepresent these data sets, nor to imply that changes theymade were approved by the U.S. Geological Survey.</useconst>
      <datacred>Stephanie Z. Waggoner (1990) compiled the geology ontostable-base material;
A contractor (PacifiCad Inc., Spokane, WA) scanned theoriginal stable-base geologic map (provided by theWashington Division of Geology and Earth Resources) andprovided the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) with anuncompressed TIFF file (reverse image, scanned at 600dots per inch);
Bruce R. Johnson (USGS) converted the image to a vectorgeographic information system (GIS);
Pamela D. Derkey (USGS) and Beatrice B. Lackaff editedthe vector data;
Pamela D. Derkey generated a GIS file for the point data,attached and attributed an interim geologic map datamodel (database).
Robert E. Derkey (WA DGER) digitized the point data andprovided it in an Arc/Info GENERATE format file.</datacred>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Pamela D Derkey</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, GEO-WRG-MRS</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>W 904 Riverside Avenue</address>
               <city>Spokane</city>
               <state>WA</state>
               <postal>99201</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>509-368-3114</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>509-368-3199</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pderkey@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <native>SunOS, 5.5.1, sun4u UNIXARC/INFO version 7.1.1</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>Attribute accuracy was verified by manual comparisonof the source with hard copy printouts and plots.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Polygon and chain-node topology present.Polygons intersecting the neatline are closed along the border.Segments making up the outer and inner boundaries of a poygontie end-to-end to completely enclose the area.  Line segments area set of sequentially numbered coordinate pairs.  No duplicatefeatures exist nor duplicate points in a data string.  Intersectinglines are separated into individual line segments at the point ofintersection.  Point data are represented by two sets of coordinatepairs, each with the same coordinate values.  All nodes arerepresented by a single coordinate pair which indicates the beginningor end of a line segment.  The neatline was generated bymathematically  generating the four sides of the quadrangle,densifying the lines of latitude and projecting the file to UTMzone 11 (with a y-shift).</logic>
      <complete>This digital dataset was produced from a previouslypublished report (Waggoner, 1990), and is consideredto be the best geologic map available for the areaat a scale of 1:100,000.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>The horizontal positional accuracy for the digital data may be nobetter than +/- 70 meters. It was tested by visual comparison ofthe source with hard copy plots.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Waggoner, S.Z.</origin>
                  <pubdate>1990</pubdate>
                  <title>Geologic map of the Rosalia 1:100,000 quadrangle,Washington-Idaho</title>
                  <geoform>map</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Olympia, WA</pubplace>
                     <publish>Washington Division of Geology and Earth Resources</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>100,000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>stable-base film positive</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1990</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Waggoner, 1990</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Waggoner (1990) is the sole source of geologic datain this digital geographic information system (GIS).</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
                  <pubdate>1993</pubdate>
                  <title>1:100,000-scale digital line graph (DLG) data -hydrography and transportation, Area 13 --Northwestern states</title>
                  <geoform>digital line graph (DLG) data</geoform>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Digital Line Graph</sername>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>100,000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>CD-ROM</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1993</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>USGS, 1993</srccitea>
            <srccontr>This source provided hydrography in a digital format.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Stable-base geologic map was scanned at 600 dots per inchby a contractor (PacifiCad, Inc., Spokane, WA) and providedto the U.S. Geological Survey as reverse TIFF-format image.The image was registered to a UTM grid and rectified inArc/Info. Then it was converted to a vector GIS layer usingthe GRIDLINE vectorization tool included in the Arc/Info GRIDextension. Subsequent clean-up of the vector layer was done inPC Arc/Info. Linework for water bodies that obscured geologiccontacts was converted from digital line graph (DLG) formatfiles (USGS, 1993) to PC Arc/Info so as to delineate discretegeologic unit boundaries.  The resulting geologic map wasattributed, converted to Arc/Info, and then plotted andcompared to the original.
Point data were digitized from the original stable-base mapinto GSMAP, ver. 9 (Selner and Taylor, 1993) as points in a UTMzone 11 map projection (with a y-shift of -5,000,000 meters).These point data ewre output to Arc/Info GENERATE-formatfiles using the GSMGIS utility (G.I. Selner, written commun.,1994).  An Arc/Info point location map was then generated,attributed and annotated.</procdesc>
            <procdate>1996-97</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Creation of original metadata record</procdesc>
            <procdate>19980720</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Pamela D Derkey</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, GEO-WRG-MRS</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
                     <address>W 904 Riverside Avenue</address>
                     <city>Spokane</city>
                     <state>WA</state>
                     <postal>99201</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>509-368-3114</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>509-368-3199</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>pderkey@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Vector</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>630</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>String</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>1973</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>GT-polygon composed of chains</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>631</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <gridsys>
               <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
               <utm>
                  <utmzone>11</utmzone>
                  <transmer>
                     <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
                     <longcm>-117</longcm>
                     <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
                     <feast>500000</feast>
                     <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
                  </transmer>
               </utm>
            </gridsys>
            <planci>
               <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>not determined</absres>
                  <ordres>not determined</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>METERS</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1927</horizdn>
            <ellips>Clarke 1866</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378206.4</semiaxis>
            <denflat>294.98</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <overview>
         <eaover>The 'Digital geologic map of the Rosalia 1:100,000quadrangle...' Open-File Report 98-357 contains a detaileddescription of each attribute code and a reference to theassociated map symbols on the map source materials.The GIS includes a geologic linework arc attribute table,ros100k.aat, that relates to the ros100k.con (contact look-uptable), ros100k.str (structure look-up table), ros100k.lgu(linear geologic unit look-up table) and ros100k.ref (sourcereference look-up table) files; a rock unit polygonattribute table, ros100k.pat, that relates to the ros100k.ru(rock unit look-up table) and ros100k.ref (source referencelook-up table) files; and a geologic map symbol pointattribute table, rospnt.pat, that relates to the rospnt.sym(structural point data look-up tables) and rospnt.ref (sourcereference look-up table) files.</eaover>
         <eadetcit>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/1998/of98-357/of98-357.pdf</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Information Services</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Open-File Reports, Box 25286</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>CO</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-303-202-4200</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>1-303-202-4693</cntfax>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) provides these geographic data "as is."The USGS makes no guarantee or warranty concerning the accuracy ofinformation contained in the geographic data.  The USGS further makes nowarranties, either expressed or implied as to any other matter whatsoever,including, without limitation, the condition of the product, or itsfitness for any particular purpose. The burden for determining fitness foruse lies entirely with the user.  Although these data have been processedsuccessfully on computers at the USGS, no warranty, expressed or implied,is made by the USGS regarding the use of these data on any other system,nor does the fact of distribution constitute or imply any such warranty.
In no event shall the USGS have any liability whatsoever for paymentof any consequential, incidental, indirect, special, or tort damagesof any kind, including, but not limited to, any loss of profitsarising out of use of or reliance on the geographic data or arisingout of the delivery, installation, operation, or support by USGS.
This digital geologic map GIS of the Rosalia 1:100,000 quadrangle,Idaho, is not meant to be used or displayed at any scale larger than1:100,000 (e.g., 1:62,500 or 1:24,000).</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ARCE</formname>
               <formvern>7.x</formvern>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/1998/of98-357/covers.tar.Z</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150202</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Peter N Schweitzer</cntper>
               <cntorg>USGS Midwest Area</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Collection manager, USGS Geoscience Data Clearinghouse, http://geo-nsdi.er.usgs.gov/</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Mail Stop 95412201 Sunrise Valley Dr</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192-0002</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>703-648-6533</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>703-648-6252</cntfax>
            <cntemail>pschweitzer@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <metac>none</metac>
      <metuc>none</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
