<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Roger Sayre</origin>
            <origin>Patrick Comer</origin>
            <origin>Jill Cress</origin>
            <origin>Harumi Warner</origin>
            <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
            <title>Terrestrial Ecosystems of the Conterminous United States</title>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Map</sername>
               <issue>3106</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>
scale 1:5,000,000
1 sheet
</othercit>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3106/</onlink>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3106/pdf/SIM3106.pdf</onlink>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/pp/1768</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>
The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) modeled the distribution of terrestrial ecosystems for the contiguous United States using a standardized, deductive approach to associate unique physical environments with ecological systems characterized in NatureServe's Ecological Systems of the United States classification (Comer et al., 2003). This approach was first developed for South America (Sayre et al., 2008) and is now being implemented globally (Sayre et al., 2007).

Unique physical environments were delineated from a massive biophysical stratification of the nation into the major structural components of ecosystems: biogeographic regions (Cress et al., 2008c), land surface forms (Cress et al., 2008a), surficial lithology (Cress et al., 2008d), and topographic moisture potential (Cress et al., 2008b). Each of these structural components was mapped for the contiguous United States and then spatially combined to produce ecosystem structural footprints which represented unique abiotic (physical) environments. Among 49,168 unique structural footprint classes, 13,482 classes which met a minimum pixel count threshold (20,000 pixels) were aggregated into 419 NatureServe ecosystems through semi-automated labeling process using rule set formulations for attribution of each ecosystem.
</abstract>
         <purpose>This dataset delineates the distribution of deductively-modeled NatureServe terrestrial ecosystems for the contiguous United States.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>2010</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-128.006694</westbc>
            <eastbc>-65.230305</eastbc>
            <northbc>51.670907</northbc>
            <southbc>22.696740</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>NGDA Portfolio Themes</themekt>
            <themekey>National Geospatial Data Asset</themekey>
            <themekey>NGDA</themekey>
            <themekey>Biota Theme</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>ecosystem</themekey>
            <themekey>Group on Earth Observations</themekey>
            <themekey>GEO</themekey>
            <themekey>Global Earth Observation System of Systems</themekey>
            <themekey>GEOSS</themekey>
            <themekey>biophysical stratification</themekey>
            <themekey>bioclimate</themekey>
            <themekey>biogeography</themekey>
            <themekey>lithology</themekey>
            <themekey>landforms</themekey>
            <themekey>surface moisture</themekey>
            <themekey>land cover</themekey>
            <themekey>mesoscale</themekey>
            <themekey>United States Geological Survey</themekey>
            <themekey>USGS</themekey>
            <themekey>Geological Survey</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>United States of America</placekey>
            <placekey>conterminous United States</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>
We make every effort to provide and maintain accurate, complete, usable, and timely information on our Web sites. However, some U. S. Geological Survey data and information accessed through these pages may, of necessity, be preliminary in nature and presented prior to final review and approval by the Director of the U. S. Geological Survey. These data and information are provided with the understanding that they are not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Users are cautioned to consider carefully the provisional nature of these data and information before using them for decisions that concern personal or public safety or the conduct of business that involves substantial monetary or operational consequences. Conclusions drawn from, or actions undertaken on the basis of, such data and information are the sole responsibility of the user.

Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.

Any use of trade, product or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U. S. Government.
</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Jill Cress, Computer Scientist</cntper>
               <cntorg>US Geological Survey, Geosciences and Environmental Change Science Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing</addrtype>
               <address>US Geological Survey, Geosciences and Environmental Change Science Center, Box 25046, DFC, MS 980</address>
               <city>Lakewood</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>303-236-1248</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>jjcress@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>
This effort to map standardized, meso-scale ecosystems for both the conterminous United States and Africa is the first of its kind, and represents a biophysical stratification. The data developed for this mapping process were not all of the same quality or spatial resolution, but each dataset obtained and used for the mapping was considered to be "best available data" for that theme at a National extent. The primary goal for the first round of this mapping effort was to utilize the best source data currently available to generate a first iteration of ecosystems as quickly as possible. This goal was framed on the logic that reasonably robust and satisfactory results could be obtained from this method without a multi-year, million-plus dollar investment, and the methodology would therefore prove suitable for application in the global ecosystems mapping project under GEOSS.

As such, these data should be considered as first generation, first iteration products assembled specifically for the purpose of delineating ecosystems in a standardized manner. The input layers that represent interim products in the geospatial delineation of ecosystems should not be construed, in and of themselves, as "definitive" products. All these products could be improved in terms of strength of concept, quality of source data, and spatial resolution. These data should therefore be considered as representative of a first iteration attempt to use best available data to model standardized ecosystems, and improvements in the data input layers and final products all have the potential to be improved over time, in subsequent iterations.

Based on the nature of this first iteration of products, the following potential issues were already identified for two of the ecosystems data layers generated for the conterminous United States:
Data artifact transfer from CTI source data to Topographic Moisture Potential

1) Topographic Moisture Potential - This dataset was derived from the Compound Topographic Index (CTI) dataset, which was itself a derivative product of the National Elevation Dataset (NED), created by the Elevation Derivatives for National Applications (EDNA) project. Therefore any data artifacts found in either the CTI dataset or NED were inherited in the Topographic Moisture Potential dataset. These artifacts appear as grid patterns in the Topographic Moisture Potential and can be found in areas of flatter terrain. The Topographic Moisture Potential dataset also includes small occurrences of No Data areas, with a pixel value of zero, based on No Data areas in the CTI dataset. No attempt was made to eliminate these artifacts or No Data pixels from the derived dataset; however, additional efforts are planned to research the effects of these issues.

2) Land Surface Forms - This dataset was derived from the NED based on various neighborhood analysis using a 1-km2 analysis window. However, it was determined that the NED did not include sufficient elevation data on Canadian side of the northwestern U.S.–Canada border. As a result, in the areas within approximately 600-meters to the south of this border, neighborhood analysis were run with insufficient input data therefore land surface form classes in this area are expected to have lower accuracy.
</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>see the attribute accuracy report</logic>
      <complete>See the attribute accuracy report</complete>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Cress, J., R. Sayre, P. Comer, and H. Warner</origin>
                  <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
                  <title>Terrestrial Ecosystems—Land Surface Forms of the Conterminous United States</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Map</sername>
                     <issue>3085</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>1 sheet</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://rmgsc.cr.usgs.gov/outgoing/ecosystems/USdata/land_surface_forms_30m.zip</onlink>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3085</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>5000000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>online digital data and/or digital map</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2009</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Cress and others, 2009b</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Used as one of the layers combined to generate Structural Footprints which were then aggregated into 419 NatureServe ecosystems.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>
J. Cress
D. Soller
R. Sayre
P. Comer
H. Warner
</origin>
                  <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
                  <title>Terrestrial Ecosystems—Surficial Lithology of the Conterminous United States</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Map</sername>
                     <issue>3126</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>
1 sheet.
Data Used: Surficial Materials in the Conterminous United States (Soller, D.R., and Reheis, M.C., compilers, 2004, Surficial materials in the conterminous United States: U.S. Geological Survey Open-file Report 03-275, scale 1:5,000,000.)  http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2003/of03-275/
</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://rmgsc.cr.usgs.gov/outgoing/ecosystems/USdata/lithology_1km.zip</onlink>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3126</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>5000000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>online digital data and/or digital map</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2010</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Cress and others, 2010</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Used as one of the layers combined to generate Structural Footprints which were then aggregated into 419 NatureServe ecosystems.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>
J. Cress
R. Sayre
P. Comer
H. Warner
</origin>
                  <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
                  <title>Terrestrial Ecosystems—Topographic Moisture Potential of the Conterminous United States</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Map</sername>
                     <issue>3086</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>Data Used: Compound Topographic Index (CTI), EDNA (Elevation Derivative for National Applications), US Geological Survey, http://edna.usgs.gov/edna/datalayers/cti.asp</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://rmgsc.cr.usgs.gov/outgoing/ecosystems/USdata/topo_moist_potential_30m.zip</onlink>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3086</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>5000000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>online digital data and/or digital map</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2009</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Cress and others, 2009c</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Used as one of the layers combined to generate Structural Footprints which were then aggregated into 419 NatureServe ecosystems.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>
J. Cress
R. Sayre
P. Comer
H. Warner
</origin>
                  <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
                  <title>Terrestrial Ecosystems—Isobioclimates of the Conterminous United States</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Map</sername>
                     <issue>3084</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>
1 sheet.
Data Used: Daymet (Daily Surface Weather and Climatological Summaries), The University of Montana, Numerical Terradynamic Simulation Group (NTSG), http://www.daymet.org/
</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://rmgsc.cr.usgs.gov/outgoing/ecosystems/USdata/isobioclimates_1km.zip</onlink>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/sim/3084</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>5000000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>online digital data and/or digital map</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2009</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Cress and others, 2009a</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Used as one of the layers combined to generate Structural Footprints which were then aggregated into 419 NatureServe ecosystems.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>
P. Comer
D. Faber-Langendoen
R. Evans
S. Gawler
C. Josse
G. Kittel
S. Menard
M. Pyne
M. Reid
K. Schulz
K. Snow
J. Teague
</origin>
                  <pubdate>2003</pubdate>
                  <title>Ecological Systems of the United States: A Working Classification of U.S. Terrestrial Systems</title>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Arlington, Virginia.</pubplace>
                     <publish>NatureServe</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://www.natureserve.org/library/usEcologicalsystems.pdf</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2003</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Comer and others, 2003</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Provided the  terrestrial ecosystems classification (developed by NatureServe) that was used as the final classification of the United States ecosystems mapping product.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>
Roger Sayre
Patrick Comer
Harumi Warner
Jill Cress
</origin>
                  <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
                  <title>A new map of standardized terrestrial ecosystems of the conterminous United States</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper</sername>
                     <issue>1768</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
                     <publish>U. S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>17 p.</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/pp/1768</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2009</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Sayre and others, 2009</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Provided the deductive, biophysical stratification approach to delineate ecosystems by their major structural elements.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Salvador Rivas-Martínez</origin>
                  <pubdate>2004</pubdate>
                  <title>Global Bioclimatics (Clasificación bioclimática de la Tierra): Version 27-08-04</title>
                  <edition>Version 27-08-04</edition>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Madrid, Spain</pubplace>
                     <publish>Phytosociological Research Center</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>Accessed January 5, 2009</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://www.globalbioclimatics.org/book/bioc/global_bioclimatics_2.htm#2</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2004</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Rivas-Martínez 2004</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Provided the methodology for the generation of isobioclimate classes for the conterminous United States.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>
Salvador Rivas-Martínez
Daniel Sánchez-Mata
Manuel Costa
</origin>
                  <pubdate>1999</pubdate>
                  <title>North American Boreal and Western Temperate Forest Vegetation (Syntaxonomical synopsis of the potential natural plant communities of North America, II)</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>Itinera Geobotanica</sername>
                     <issue>12:5-316</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Madrid, Spain</pubplace>
                     <publish>Phytosociological Research Center</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>Accessed January 5, 2009</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://www.globalbioclimatics.org/book/namerica2/namerica.htm</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1999</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Rivas-Martínez and others, 1999</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Provided the concept of establishing a quantifiable classification system which would closely relate the distribution of vegetation to climatic parameters and indices</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>
Salvador Rivas-Martínez
Daniel Sánchez-Mata
Manuel Costa
</origin>
                  <pubdate>2004</pubdate>
                  <title>Synoptical Worldwide Bioclimatic Classification System</title>
                  <othercit>Accessed January 5, 2009</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://www.globalbioclimatics.org/book/bioc/tabla3.htm</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2004</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Rivas-Martínez and others, 2004</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Contributed to the method for establishing bioclimatic indices and applying sets of decision rules to identify the climate classes.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>University of Montana, Numerical Terradynamic Simulation Group (NTSG)</origin>
                  <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
                  <title>Daymet-Daily surface weather and climatological summaries</title>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Missoula, Montana</pubplace>
                     <publish>University of Montana</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>Last accessed January, 2006</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://www.daymet.org/dataSelection.jsp</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <rngdates>
                     <begdate>1980</begdate>
                     <enddate>1997</enddate>
                  </rngdates>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>from documentation</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Daymet</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Provided the temperature and precipitation data for establishing bioclimatic indices.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>P. E. Thornton</origin>
                  <pubdate>1997</pubdate>
                  <title>Daymet: Climatological summaries for the conterminous United States, 1980–1997</title>
                  <othercit>User's Guide available online at http://www.daymet.org/daymetus_userguide.pdf</othercit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1997</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Thornton, 1997</srccitea>
            <srccontr>User's guide for the Daymet data</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>E. H. Hammond</origin>
                  <pubdate>1964</pubdate>
                  <title>Analysis of Properties in Land Form Geography—An Application to Broad-Scale Land Form Mapping</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>Annals of the Association of American Geographers</sername>
                     <issue>v. 54, no. 1, p. 11–19.</issue>
                  </serinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>paper journal publication</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1964</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Hammond 1964a</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Original land surface form classification which was modified by the Missouri Resource Assessment Partnership (MoRAP).</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>E. H. Hammond</origin>
                  <pubdate>1964</pubdate>
                  <title>Classes of land surface form in the forty-eight states</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S.A. Annals of the Association of American Geographers</sername>
                     <issue>54(1): map supplement no. 4</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <othercit>1: 5,000,000</othercit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>map supplement to a paper publication in a journal</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1964</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Hammond, 1964b</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Original land surface form classification which was modified by the Missouri Resource Assessment Partnership (MoRAP).</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Diane True</origin>
                  <pubdate>2002</pubdate>
                  <title>Landforms of the Lower Mid-West</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>MoRAP Map Series</sername>
                     <issue>MS-2002-01</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Columbia, Missouri</pubplace>
                     <publish>Missouri Resource Assessment Partnership</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>scale 1:1,500,000</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://www.cerc.usgs.gov/morap/Maps.aspx?MapId=7</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2002</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>True, 2002</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Contributed to the neighborhood analysis used to generate the Land Surface Forms (Cress and others, 2009b)</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>
D. True
T. Gordon
D. Diamond
</origin>
                  <pubdate>2000</pubdate>
                  <title>How the size of a sliding Window impacts the generation of landforms</title>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Columbia, Missouri</pubplace>
                     <publish>Missouri Resource Assessment Partnership</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://www.cerc.usgs.gov/morap/Content/UploadedFiles/Projects/landform_model/landforms2001_files/frame.htm</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2000</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>True and others, 2000</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Contributed to the neighborhood analysis used to generate the Land Surface Forms (Cress and others, 2009b)</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
                  <pubdate>2004</pubdate>
                  <title>National Elevation Dataset (NED)</title>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Reston, Virginia</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>Last accessed January, 2006</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://seamless.usgs.gov/index.php</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2004</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>USGS 30-meter National Elevation Dataset (NED)</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Provided 30 elevation data as part of the development of Land Surface Forms (Cress and others, 2009b).</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Andrew Weiss</origin>
                  <pubdate>2001</pubdate>
                  <title>Topographic position and landforms analysis—Poster presentation</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>Environmental Sciences Research Institute User Conference</sername>
                     <issue>July 2001, San Diego, Calif.</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>San Diego, California</pubplace>
                     <publish>Environmental Sciences Research Institute</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Poster presentation</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2001</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Weiss, 2001</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Contributed to defining the slope position classes representing areas positioned lower than the surrounding areas, valley and lower slope, as a step in the Land Surface Forms (Cress and others, 2009b) generation.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Jeff Jenness</origin>
                  <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
                  <title>Topographic Position Index (TPI) extension for ArcView 3.x</title>
                  <edition>v. 1.2</edition>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Flagstaff, Arizona</pubplace>
                     <publish>Jenness Enterprises</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>Accessed June 2006</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://jennessent.com/arcview/arcview_extensions.htm</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Provided tools for defining topographic positions.</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2006</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Jenness, 2006</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Contributed to defining the slope position classes representing areas positioned lower than the surrounding areas, valley and lower slope, as a step in the Land Surface Forms (Cress and others, 2009b) generation.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
                  <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                  <title>National Wetlands Inventory (NWI)</title>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Arlington, Virginia</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>Last accessed February 24, 2009</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://www.fws.gov/wetlands/Data/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2008</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>National Wetlands Inventory</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Provided wetland boundaries as a step in the process of creating Topographic Moisture Potential (Cress and others, 2009c).</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
                  <pubdate>2003</pubdate>
                  <title>Elevation Derivatives for National Applications (EDNA)—Compound Topographic Index (CTI)</title>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>Accessed February 24, 2009</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://edna.usgs.gov/Edna/datalayers/cti.asp</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2003</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>National Compound Topographic Index</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Provided a quantification of the position of a site in the local landscape as a step in the process of generating Topographic Moisture Potential (Cress and others, 2009c).</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>
D. r. Soller
M. C. Reheis
</origin>
                  <pubdate>2004</pubdate>
                  <title>Surficial materials in the conterminous United States</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>U.S. Geological Survey. Open-file Report</sername>
                     <issue>03–275</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>scale 1:5,000,000</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2003/of03-275/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2004</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Soller and Reheis, 2004</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Provided the input data for deriving Surficial Lithology (Cress and others, 2010).</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>A. Kruckeberg</origin>
                  <pubdate>2002</pubdate>
                  <title>Geology and plant life</title>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Seattle, Washington</pubplace>
                     <publish>University of Washington Press.</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>paper</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2002</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Kruckeberg, 2002</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Contributed to the reclassification of the Surficial Materials (Soller and Reheis, 2004) into the 18 lithologies that typically control or influence the distribution of vegetation types.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>
R. Sayre
J. Bow
C. Josse
L. Sotomayor
J. Touval
</origin>
                  <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                  <title>Terrestrial Ecosystems of South America</title>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
                     <publish>Association of American Geographers</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <lworkcit>
                     <citeinfo>
                        <origin>
J. C. Campbell
K. Bruce Jones
J.H. Smith (eds.)
</origin>
                        <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                        <title>North America Land Cover Summit—A Special Issue of the Association of American Geographers.</title>
                        <edition>A Special Issue of the Association of American Geographers.</edition>
                        <pubinfo>
                           <pubplace>Washington, D.C.</pubplace>
                           <publish>Association of American Geographers</publish>
                        </pubinfo>
                     </citeinfo>
                  </lworkcit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2008</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Sayre and others, 2008</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Provides the biophysical stratification approach being implemented globally as a step in the process of creating the terrestrial ecosystems for the conterminous United States (Sayre and others, 2009).</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>
Roger Sayre
Alberto Yanosky
Doug Muchoney
</origin>
                  <pubdate>2007</pubdate>
                  <title>Mapping global ecosystems-The GEOSS approach</title>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>London, U.K.</pubplace>
                     <publish>Tudor Rose</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>Group on Earth Observations, ed.</othercit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2007</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Sayre and others, 2007</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Describes the global implementation of the biophysical stratification for generating the 419 terrestrial ecosystems for the conterminous United States (Sayre and others, 2009).</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
The U.S. Geological Survey, Rocky Mountain Geographic Science Center (now Geosciences and Environmental Change Science Center) modeled the distribution of terrestrial ecosystems for the conterminous United States using the geospatial mapping methodology that was developed from a deductive, biophysical stratification approach to delineate ecosystems by their major structural elements (Sayre and others, 2009). Each major structural component of ecosystems (land surface forms, surficial lithology, bioclimates, topographic moisture potential, and so forth) was modeled for the Nation and then spatially combined to produce a new map of biophysical settings for the Nation, termed ecosystem structural footprints. Each structural footprint represents a unique combination based on the union of the input layers, and results in a massive biophysical stratification of the Nation into a set of unique physical environments. These ecosystem structure units characterize the abiotic (physical) potential of the environment. As the final step in this process, the unique structural footprints are aggregated into the terrestrial ecosystems classification that was developed by NatureServe (Comer and others, 2003).

These are some of the specific data layers that were generated:
Isobioclimates,
Land Surface Forms,
Topographic Moisture Potential,
Surficial Lithology,
Structural Footprints, and
Labeled Ecosystems.
Each of these data layers were generated at the highest possible resolution.
</procdesc>
            <srcused>Sayre and others, 2009</srcused>
            <srcused>Comer and others, 2003</srcused>
            <procdate>2008</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Bioclimate information for the ecosystems model was provided by the generation of isobioclimate classes for the conterminous United States (Cress and others, 2009a) using the Rivas-Martínez methodology (Rivas-Martínez 2004). This methodology is based on the concept of establishing a quantifiable classification system which would closely relate the distribution of vegetation to climatic parameters and indices (Rivas-Martínez and others, 1999). This method first establishes bioclimatic indices calculated from various ranges of temperature and precipitation data, compares these indices to defined thresholds, and finally applies sets of decision rules to identify the climate classes. The complete climate classification is done in four levels: macrobioclimates, bioclimates, thermotypes, and ombrotypes. Thermotypes, which represent thermoclimatic belts, are identified using the positive annual temperature (Tp) thresholds or the compensated thermicity index (Itc) thresholds (Rivas-Martínez 2004, Rivas-Martínez and others, 1999, 2004). Ombrotypes, which represent ombroclimatic belts, are based on the ombrothermic index (Io) which is calculated as a function of both the total positive precipitation and temperature (Rivas-Martínez 2004, Rivas-Martínez and others 1999, 2004). For this national implementation the source data used for establishing the bioclimatic indices was Daymet. Daymet temperature and precipitation data was developed from 18-years (1980-1997) of climatological records and is available at a spatial resolution of 1 kilometer (Thornton, 1997). This implementation of the Rivas-Martinez methodology resulted in the generation of four climate layers for the conterminous United States: macroclimates, bioclimates, thermotypes, and ombrotypes.

However, the biophysical stratification approach used for the ecosystems modeling effort required a single climate layer. Therefore, the final step in this implementation was the generation of a single isobioclimate based on some utilization of the four Rivas-Martinez climate classifications. Based on a series of investigations the decision was made that in order to achieve the required climate variations, especially in the upper mid-west and north-west, while still working with a manageable number of classifications, the best choice for this final isobioclimate dataset would be a combination of the thermotypes and ombrotypes. After this process was performed the final isobioclimates layer was generated that provides the required amount of climate variation, and contains 127 unique thermotype-ombrotype combinations.
</procdesc>
            <srcused>Cress and others, 2009a</srcused>
            <srcused>Rivas-Martínez 2004</srcused>
            <srcused>Rivas-Martínez and others, 1999</srcused>
            <srcused>Rivas-Martínez and others, 2004</srcused>
            <srcused>Daymet</srcused>
            <procdate>2008</procdate>
            <srcprod>Cress and others, 2009a</srcprod>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
Land surface forms for the conterminous United States were also generated as part of the ecosystems modeling effort (Cress and others, 2009b). After extensive investigation into various land surface form methodologies, the decision was made to use the methodology developed by the Missouri Resource Assessment Partnership (MoRAP). MoRAP made modifications to Hammond's (1964a, 1964b) land surface form classification, which allowed the use of 30-meter source data and a 1-km2 window for analyzing the data cell and its surrounding cells (neighborhood analysis) (True, 2002; True and others, 2000). While Hammond's methodology was based on three topographic variables, slope, local relief, and profile type, MoRAP's methodology uses only slope and local relief (True, 2002). Using the MoRAP method, slope is classified as gently sloping when more than 50 percent of the area in a 1-km2 neighborhood has slope less than 8 percent, otherwise the area is not gently sloping, that is, steeply sloped. Local relief, which is the difference between the maximum and minimum elevation in a neighborhood, is classified into five groups: 0-15 m, 15-30 m, 30-90 m, 90-150 m, and &gt;150 m. The land surface form classes are derived by combining slope and local relief which creates eight landform classes: flat plains (gently sloping and local relief &lt;= 15 m), smooth plains (gently sloping and 15 m &lt; local relief &lt;= 30 m), irregular plains (gently sloping and 30 m &lt; local relief &lt;= 90 m), escarpments (gently sloping and local relief &gt; 90 m), low hills (not gently sloping and local relief &lt;= 30 m), hills (not gently sloping and 30 m &lt; local relief &lt;= 90 m), breaks/foothills (not gently sloping and 90 m &lt; local relief &lt;= 150 m), and low mountains (not gently sloping and local relief &gt; 150 m). However, in the U. S. Geological Survey (USGS) application of the MoRAP methodology, an additional local relief group was used (&gt; 400 m). As a result, low mountains were redefined as not gently sloping and 150 m &lt; local relief &lt; 400 m, and a new land surface from class, high mountains/deep canyons, was identified as not gently sloping and local relief &gt; 400 m. The final application of the MoRAP methodology was preformed using the USGS 30-meter National Elevation Dataset (NED), and an existing USGS slope dataset that had been derived by calculating the slope from the NED in Universal Transverse Mercator (UTM) coordinates in each UTM zone, and then combining all of the zones into a national dataset.

As a final step, an additional class called drainage channels was derived independently from the other land surface form classes and was used to identify wet and dry river channels, which were not specifically represented by any of the other classifications. This class was based on the two Andrew Weiss's slope position classes that represented areas positioned lower than the surrounding areas, valley and lower slope (Weiss, 2001; Jenness, 2006). The USGS applied Weiss's algorithm to the 30-meter NED data using a 1-km2 neighborhood analysis window and then the resultant drainage channel class was added to the land surface forms dataset. Thus, the final land surface forms dataset contains ten classes: flat plains, smooth plains, irregular plains, escarpments, low hills, hills, breaks/foothills, low mountains, high mountains/deep canyons, and drainage channels.
</procdesc>
            <srcused>Hammond, 1964a</srcused>
            <srcused>Hammond, 1964b</srcused>
            <srcused>True, 2002</srcused>
            <srcused>True and others, 2000</srcused>
            <srcused>USGS 30-meter National Elevation Dataset (NED)</srcused>
            <srcused>Weiss, 2001</srcused>
            <srcused>Jenness, 2006</srcused>
            <procdate>2008</procdate>
            <srcprod>Cress and others, 2009b</srcprod>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The topographic moisture potential for the conterminous United States was derived to help contribute substrate moisture regimes into the ecosystems model (Cress and others, 2009c). The method used to produce these topographic moisture potential classes was based on the derivation of ground moisture potential using a combination of computed topographic characteristics (CTI, slope, and aspect) and mapped National Wetland Inventory boundaries. This method does not use climate or soil attributes to calculate relative topographic moisture potential since these characteristics are incorporated into the ecosystem model though other input layers. All of the topographic data used for this assessment was derived from the USGS 30-meter NED including the National Compound Topographic Index. The CTI index is a topographically derived measure of slope for a raster cell and the contributing area from upstream raster cells, and thus expresses potential for water flow to a point. In other words CTI data are "a quantification of the position of a site in the local landscape", where the lowest values indicate ridges and the highest values indicate stream channels, lakes and ponds (USGS, 2003). These CTI values were compared to independent estimates of water accumulation by obtaining geospatial data from a number of sample locations representing two types of NWI boundaries, Freshwater Emergent Wetlands and Freshwater Forested/Shrub Wetlands. Where these shorelines (the interface between the NWI wetlands and adjacent land) occurred, the CTI values were extracted and a histogram of their statistical distributions was calculated. Based on an evaluation of these histograms, CTI thresholds were developed to separate periodically saturated or flooded land, mesic uplands (moderately moist), and uplands. After the range of CTI values for these three different substrate moisture regimes was determined, the CTI values were grouped into three initial topographic moisture potential classes. As a final step in the generation of this national data layer, the uplands classification was further broken down into either very dry uplands or dry uplands. Very dry uplands were defined as uplands with relatively steep, south-facing slopes, and identification of this class was based on the slope and aspect datasets derived from the USGS NED. The remaining uplands that did not meet these additional criteria were simply re-classified as dry uplands. The final National Topographic Moisture Potential dataset for the conterminous United States contains four classes: periodically saturated or flooded land (CTI &gt;= 18.5), mesic uplands (12 &lt;= CTI &lt; 18.5), dry uplands (CTI &lt; 12), and very dry uplands (CTI &lt; 12, Slope &gt; 24 degrees and 91 degrees &lt;= Aspect &lt;= 314 degrees).</procdesc>
            <srcused>National Wetlands Inventory</srcused>
            <srcused>USGS 30-meter National Elevation Dataset (NED)</srcused>
            <srcused>National Compound Topographic Index</srcused>
            <procdate>2008</procdate>
            <srcprod>Cress and others, 2009c</srcprod>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The surficial lithology classes for the conterminous United States (Cress and others, 2010) were derived from the USGS map "Surficial Materials in the conterminous United States", which was based on texture, internal structure, thickness, and environment of deposition or formation of materials (Soller and Reheis, 2004). This original map was produced from a compilation of regional surficial and bedrock geology source maps using broadly defined common map units for the purpose of providing an overview of the existing data and knowledge. For the terrestrial ecosystem effort, the 28 lithology classes of Soller and Reheis (2004) were generalized and then reclassified (http://rmgsc.cr.usgs.gov/ecosystems/docs/litho_crosswalk.pdf) into a set of 18 lithologies that typically control or influence the distribution of vegetation types (Kruckeberg, 2002).</procdesc>
            <srcused>Soller and Reheis, 2004</srcused>
            <srcused>Kruckeberg, 2002</srcused>
            <procdate>2008</procdate>
            <srcprod>Cress and others, 2010</srcprod>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
The structural footprints for the conterminous United States were produced by spatially combining each of the major structural components of ecosystems described in previous process steps. These ecosystem structure units characterize the abiotic (physical) potential of the environment, and represent distinct facets of the landscape with respect to biogeography, bioclimate, landform, lithology, and surface moisture potential.

This layer was developed from a spatial combination of each of the layers described above, and an Ecological Divisions of the United States data layer (Comer and others, 2003). NatureServe's North American Ecological Divisions, twelve biogeographic regions for the conterminous United States, was used to represent sub-continental landscapes reflecting both climate and biogeographic history (Comer and others, 2003). The final set of ecosystem structural footprints was generated from a spatial combination of all of the base layers, and then to minimize artifacts, the final footprints dataset was aggregated to a minimum mapping unit of approximately two acres, resulting in 49,168 unique structural footprints.
</procdesc>
            <srcused>Cress and others, 2009a</srcused>
            <srcused>Cress and others, 2009b</srcused>
            <srcused>Cress and others, 2009c</srcused>
            <srcused>Cress and others, 2010</srcused>
            <srcused>Comer and others, 2003</srcused>
            <procdate>2008</procdate>
            <srcprod>Structural Footprints</srcprod>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>
The U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), with support from NatureServe, has modeled the potential distribution of 419 terrestrial ecosystems for the conterminous United States (Sayre and others, 2009) using a classification developed by NatureServe (Comer and others, 2003). A biophysical stratification approach, developed for South America (Sayre and others, 2008) and now being implemented globally (Sayre and others, 2007), was used to model these terrestrial ecosystem distributions. This biophysical stratification approach is based on mapping the major structural components of ecosystems (landform, surface moisture potential, surficial lithology, bioclimate and biogeographic region) and then spatially combining them to produce a set of unique biophysical environments.

Terrestrial ecosystems for the conterminous United States were mapped by delineating physically distinct areas as the fundamental structural units ("building blocks") of ecosystems, and subsequently aggregating and labeling these structural footprints into the NatureServe classification. These structural footprints were developed from the union of several base layers including: biogeographic regions, isobioclimates (Cress and others, 2009a), land surface forms (Cress and others, 2009b), topographic moisture potential (Cress and others, 2009c), and surficial lithology (Cress and others, 2009d). Among the 49,168 unique structural footprint classes that resulted from the union, 13,482 classes met a minimum pixel count threshold (20,000 pixels), and were aggregated into 419 NatureServe ecosystems using a semi-automated labeling process based on rule-set formulations for attribution of each ecosystem.

The resulting ecosystems are those that are expected to occur based on the combination of the bioclimate, biogeography, and geomorphology. Where land use by humans has not altered land cover, natural vegetation assemblages are expected to occur, and these are described in the ecosystems classification. The map does not show the distribution of urban and agricultural areas — these will be masked out in subsequent analyses to depict the current land cover in addition to the potential distribution of natural ecosystems.
</procdesc>
            <srcused>Sayre and others, 2009</srcused>
            <srcused>Comer and others, 2003</srcused>
            <srcused>Sayre and others, 2008</srcused>
            <srcused>Sayre and others, 2007</srcused>
            <srcused>Structural Footprints</srcused>
            <procdate>2009</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Pixel</rasttype>
         <rowcount>104307</rowcount>
         <colcount>225995</colcount>
         <vrtcount>1</vrtcount>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <latres>0.000278</latres>
            <longres>0.000278</longres>
            <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
         </geograph>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
            <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.257222</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
               <cntper>Jill Cress</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
               <address>US Geological Survey, Geosciences and Environmental Change Science Center, Box 25046, DFC, MS 980</address>
               <city>Lakewood</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>303-236-1248</cntvoice>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>zipped "ERDAS" .img files</formname>
               <formverd>20090504</formverd>
               <transize>1300</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://rmgsc.cr.usgs.gov/outgoing/ecosystems/USdata/labeled_ecosystems_30m.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Global Ecosystems Data Viewer</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://rmgsc.cr.usgs.gov/ecosystems/dataviewer.shtml</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150127</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Roger Sayre</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Land Change Science Program</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Senior Scientist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>physical address</addrtype>
               <address>519 National Center</address>
               <city>Reston</city>
               <state>VA</state>
               <postal>20192</postal>
               <country>U.S.A.</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(703) 648-4529</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>rsayre@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>"FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata"</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <metac>None</metac>
      <metuc>None</metuc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
