<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Upekala C. Wijayratne</origin>
            <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
            <title>Root elongation rates for Wyoming big sagebrush (Artemisia tridentata subsp. wyomingensis) seedlings for Paired Rootbox Experiment, Spring 2010.</title>
            <geoform>Maps and Data</geoform>
            <onlink>http://srfs.wr.usgs.gov/Fresc_ScienceData/FRE00650.zip</onlink>
            <onlink>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/53f79879e4b05ec1f246ef1e</onlink>
            <onlink>http://fresc.usgs.gov/products/dataset/sagebrush/FRE00650.zip</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The semi-arid sagebrush steppe ecosystem is one of the largest biomes in
 North America. The steppe provides critical habitat and forage for wildlife and is
 economically important to recreation and livestock industries. However, the ecosystem
 is threatened primarily due to several negative effects associated with expansion of the
 exotic annual grass Bromus tectorum (cheatgrass). Because of these changes
 rehabilitation of the habitat is extremely difficult and energy intensive. Restoration of
 one of the foundation species, Artemisia tridentata (big sagebrush), is a function of
 seed availability, seed germination, seedling establishment and mature plant survival.
 Many studies have addressed various aspects of A. tridentata seed germination and
 mature plant ecophysiology, but gaps in our knowledge include seed bank dynamics
 and biotic interactions that may hinder seedling survival.
 The prevalence of large fires in B. tectorum-invaded habitat limits availability
 of dispersed seeds in the interior of burned areas, leaving pre-existing viable seeds in
 the soil seed bank as the primary natural seed source. I investigated seed longevity of
 two A. tridentata subspecies over a 2-year period by retrieving seed bags that were
 placed at varying depths and sampling soil and litter fractions of the existing seed
 bank across six locations in the Great Basin. Artemisia tridentata ssp. wyomingensis
 and A. t. ssp. vaseyana exhibited patterns of a steadily decreasing abundance of viable
 seeds on the surface and beneath litter, with 100% loss of surface seed viability in 24
 months. However, 29-36% (A. t. ssp. wyomingensis) and 30-40% (A. t. ssp. vaseyana)
 of buried seeds remained viable throughout the duration of the experiment. Abundance
 of naturally occurring seeds varied considerably among locations and between years
 across the Great Basin for both subspecies. Loss of viable seeds from the existing seed
 bank between post-dispersal and pre-dispersal the following season was higher in
 magnitude for A. t. ssp. wyomingensis soil fractions compared to litter fractions, and
 higher overall than for A. t. ssp. vaseyana.
 Access to resources is critical during early spring when resources are plentiful,
 and this access affects the probability of survival through the summer drought period.
 Artemisia tridentata resource acquisition may be adversely affected during this time
 via root interaction mechanisms that are not mediated through resources (interference
 competition). I examined whether and how root interactions affected growth of A. t.
 ssp. wyomingensis by forcing its roots to interact with roots of conspecifics, B.
 tectorum, Elymus wawawaiensis (Snake River wheatgrass), and Agropyron xhybrid
 (cultivar 'Hycrest'). Activated carbon was used to counteract any potentially negative
 effects of root exudates. Artemisia tridentata above- and belowground biomass was
 not affected when grown with E. wawawaiensis or A. xhybrid compared to control
 seedlings, but root growth rate and branching density decreased when grown with B.
 tectorum (root growth: p &lt; 0.01; branching density: p = 0.07). These effects did not
 occur in potting media amended with activated carbon but may have been the result of
 unintentional fertilization. Roots of A. tridentata seedlings changed direction or
 stopped growing altogether more often when grown into roots of conspecific seedlings
 than when contacting roots of other species (p = 0.08). The odds of this occurring
 decreased when seedlings were grown in activated carbon-amended potting medium.
 These results suggest that A. tridentata may have a chemical signaling mechanism to
 avoid roots of conspecifics.
 I also assessed whether root and shoot competition (resource-mediated or
 exploitative competition) of the three grass species affected A. t. ssp. wyomingensis
 seedling growth and survival, and whether root and shoot competition interacted to
 affect growth. Size-asymmetric competition takes place when a resource is preempted
 by a larger individual over a smaller individual, and the larger individual receives a
 disproportionately larger share of the resource for its relative size. Following wildfires,
 B. tectorum cover can increase significantly more than that of other species,
 potentially promoting asymmetric aboveground competition between it and A.
 tridentata seedlings. Root and shoot competition from B. tectorum lowered A.
 tridentata biomass dramatically compared to that of control seedlings, with shoot
 competition alone decreasing growth by over 80%. Only full competition from E.
 wawawaiensis tended to decrease A. tridentata growth compared to control seedlings,
 while A. xhybrid had no significant effect at all seedling growth. Bromus tectorum had
 an average of 92% cover and may explain why shoot competition from this species
 had such a substantial effect, whereas cover of E. wawawaiensis and A. xhybrid was
 71% and 43%, respectively. Root and shoot competition did not interact for any of the
 grasses, indicating that there was no mechanism for positive or negative feedbacks
 between one form of competition and the other. Competition from shoots is likely not
 severe enough for asymmetric light competition to occur.
 The first study provides land managers with a bet-hedging application while
 the others offer insight into why the seedling life history stage, already vulnerable, has
 become more so with B. tectorum invasion. Reseeding techniques promoting burial of
 some A. tridentata seeds in the soil seed bank may increase restoration success by
 hedging against the potential for failure of establishment in the initial year of seeding.
 Selective thinning or removal of potential competitors may be required to benefit
 resource status of A. tridentata seedlings before the summer drought period
 commences. This is especially important in areas that are dominated by B. tectorum as
 competition from the annual reduces A. tridentata root growth substantially and may
 impact its ability to take up soil resources.</abstract>
         <purpose>The data are results of a study undertaken in the spring of 2010 to assess how Wyoming big sagebrush root growth is affected by the presence of neighbor roots.  </purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>201004</begdate>
               <enddate>201006</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>observed</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <descgeog>Data were collected at the greenhouse facility at the EPA's Willamette Research Station in Corvallis, Oregon</descgeog>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-123</westbc>
            <eastbc>-123</eastbc>
            <northbc>45</northbc>
            <southbc>45</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>roots</themekey>
            <themekey>root competition</themekey>
            <themekey>root communication</themekey>
            <themekey>sagebrush steppe</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>None</placekt>
            <placekey>Great Basin</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <taxonomy>
         <keywtax>
            <taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
            <taxonkey>multiple species</taxonkey>
            <taxonkey>plants</taxonkey>
            <taxonkey>vegetation</taxonkey>
         </keywtax>
         <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
            <taxoncl>
               <taxonrn>Division</taxonrn>
               <taxonrv>Magnoliophyta</taxonrv>
               <taxoncl>
                  <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
                  <taxonrv>Liliopsida</taxonrv>
                  <taxoncl>
                     <taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
                     <taxonrv>Cyperales</taxonrv>
                     <taxoncl>
                        <taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
                        <taxonrv>Poaceae</taxonrv>
                        <taxoncl>
                           <taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
                           <taxonrv>Agropyron</taxonrv>
                           <taxoncl>
                              <taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
                              <taxonrv>Agropyron desertorum</taxonrv>
                              <common>clustered wheat grass, desert wheatgrass</common>
                           </taxoncl>
                        </taxoncl>
                        <taxoncl>
                           <taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
                           <taxonrv>Bromus</taxonrv>
                           <taxoncl>
                              <taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
                              <taxonrv>Bromus tectorum</taxonrv>
                              <common>cheatgrass</common>
                           </taxoncl>
                        </taxoncl>
                        <taxoncl>
                           <taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
                           <taxonrv>Elymus</taxonrv>
                           <taxoncl>
                              <taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
                              <taxonrv>Elymus wawawaiensis</taxonrv>
                           </taxoncl>
                        </taxoncl>
                     </taxoncl>
                  </taxoncl>
               </taxoncl>
               <taxoncl>
                  <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
                  <taxonrv>Magnoliopsida</taxonrv>
                  <taxoncl>
                     <taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
                     <taxonrv>Asterales</taxonrv>
                     <taxoncl>
                        <taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
                        <taxonrv>Asteraceae</taxonrv>
                        <taxoncl>
                           <taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
                           <taxonrv>Artemisia</taxonrv>
                           <taxoncl>
                              <taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
                              <taxonrv>Artemisia tridentata</taxonrv>
                              <taxoncl>
                                 <taxonrn>Subspecies</taxonrn>
                                 <taxonrv>Artemisia tridentata ssp. wyomingensis</taxonrv>
                                 <common>big sagebrush, Wyoming big sagebrush</common>
                              </taxoncl>
                           </taxoncl>
                        </taxoncl>
                     </taxoncl>
                  </taxoncl>
               </taxoncl>
            </taxoncl>
         </taxoncl>
      </taxonomy>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>Acknowledge the originator when using this data set as a source</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Communications and Information Program</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>777 NW 9th Street, Suite 400</address>
               <city>Corvallis</city>
               <state>Oregon</state>
               <postal>97330</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>541-750-1030</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <native>Microsoft Excel spreadsheet</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>No tests for attribute accuracy were conducted</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Not available</logic>
      <complete>Not available</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>No process steps have been described for this data set</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>root lengths</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Unknown</enttypd>
            <enttypds>U. Wijayratne</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Box</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Pre-assigned, unique ID for each rootbox</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unique values consisting of strings of integers or letters</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Carbon</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>No carbon/carbon treatment</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C, NC</edomv>
                  <edomvd>C: Carbon treatment; NC: No carbon treatment</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>U. Wijayratne</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Testsp</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Neighbor species Treatment</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>ARTR, BRTE, PSSP, AGDE</edomv>
                  <edomvd>ARTR=(A. tridentata);
BRTE=(B. tectorum);
PSSP=(E. wawawaiensis);
AGDE=(A. desertorum)</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>U. Wijayratne</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Contact</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Designates whether root segment contacted neighbor root</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>1, 0</edomv>
                  <edomvd>1=contact; 0=no contact</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>U. Wijayratne</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>ConDay</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Julian day of contact</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>91</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>181</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>-16:12 (# days before/after contact)</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of days before and after contact and corresponding root segment lengths</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>unknown</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>millimeters</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>time</enttypl>
            <enttypd>?</enttypd>
            <enttypds>U. Wijayratne</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Box</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Pre-assigned, unique ID for each rootbox</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unique values consisting of strings of integers or letters</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Carbon</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>No carbon/carbon treatment</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C, NC</edomv>
                  <edomvd>C: Carbon treatment; NC: No carbon treatment</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>U. Wijayratne</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Testsp</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Neighbor species Treatment</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>ARTR, BRTE, PSSP, AGDE</edomv>
                  <edomvd>ARTR (A. tridentata)
              BRTE (B. tectorum)
              PSSP (E. wawawaiensis)
              AGDE (A. desertorum)</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>U. Wijayratne</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Contact</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Designates whether root segment contacted neighbor root</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>1, 0</edomv>
                  <edomvd>1=contact; 0=no contact</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>U. Wijayratne</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>ConDay</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Julian day of contact</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>91</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>181</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>-16:12</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of days before and after contact and corresponding time that each root segment was recorded</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>24</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>hours</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>growth rate</enttypl>
            <enttypd>?</enttypd>
            <enttypds>U. Wijayratne</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Box</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Pre-assigned, unique ID for each rootbox</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unique values consisting of strings of integers or letters</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Carbon</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>No carbon/carbon treatment</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C, NC</edomv>
                  <edomvd>C: Carbon treatment; NC: No carbon treatment</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>U. Wijayratne</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Testsp</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Neighbor species Treatment</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>ARTR, BRTE, PSSP, AGDE</edomv>
                  <edomvd>ARTR (A. tridentata)
              BRTE (B. tectorum)
              PSSP (E. wawawaiensis)
              AGDE (A. desertorum)</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>U. Wijayratne</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Contact</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Designates whether root segment contacted neighbor root</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>1, 0</edomv>
                  <edomvd>1=contact; 0=no contact</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>U. Wijayratne</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>ConDay</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Julian day of contact</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>91</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>181</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>-16:12 (# days before/after contact)</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of days before and after contact and corresponding root segment growth rate</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>unknown</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>millimeters per hour</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Derail</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Designates whether root deviated from or stopped downward progress</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U. Wijayratne</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>1, 0</edomv>
                  <edomvd>1=deviated/stopped; 0=continued</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>U. Wijayratne</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <overview>
         <eaover>Data are in a MS Excel spreadsheet with three sheets. Sheet 1 contains daily lengths of root segments. Sheet 2 contains the time each root segment was recorded. Sheet 3 contains average growth rate.</eaover>
         <eadetcit>U. Wijayratne</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Communications and Information Program</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>777 NW 9th Street, Suite 400</address>
               <city>Corvallis</city>
               <state>Oregon</state>
               <postal>97330</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>541-750-1030</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a U.S. Geological Survey server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20111207</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Communications and Information Program</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>777 NW 9th Street, Suite 400</address>
               <city>Corvallis</city>
               <state>Oregon</state>
               <postal>97330</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>777 NW 9th Street, Suite 400</address>
               <city>Corvallis</city>
               <state>Oregon</state>
               <postal>97330</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>541-750-1030</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
