<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>VeeAnn A. Cross</origin>
            <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
            <title>RESGPSLNS_JD249.SHP: Ship Trackline along which Continuous Resistivity Profile Data was Collected in the Potomac River/Chesapeake Bay on Sept., 6, 2006 on USGS Cruise 06018</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>2009-1151</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Woods Hole Coastal and Marine Science Center, Woods Hole, MA</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Coastal and Marine Geology Program</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2009/1151/data/navigation/resistivity/resgpslns_jd249.zip</onlink>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2009/1151/html/catalog.html</onlink>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>VeeAnn A. Cross</origin>
                  <origin>David S. Foster</origin>
                  <origin>John F. Bratton</origin>
                  <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
                  <title>Continuous Resistivity Profiling and Seismic-Reflection Data Collected in 2006 from the Potomac River Estuary, Virginia and Maryland</title>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>Open-File Report</sername>
                     <issue>2009-1151</issue>
                  </serinfo>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Woods Hole Coastal and Marine Science Center, Woods Hole, MA</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Coastal and Marine Geology Program</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2009/1151/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>In order to test hypotheses about groundwater flow under and into Chesapeake Bay, geophysical surveys were conducted by U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) scientists on Chesapeake Bay and the Potomac River Estuary in September 2006. Chesapeake Bay resource managers are concerned about nutrients that are entering the estuary via submarine groundwater discharge, which are contributing to eutrophication. The USGS has performed many related studies in recent years to provide managers with information necessary to make informed decisions about this issue. The research carried out as part of the study described here was designed to help refine nutrient budgets for Chesapeake Bay by characterizing submarine groundwater flow and discharge of groundwater beneath part of the mainstem and a major tributary, the Potomac River Estuary.</abstract>
         <purpose>The purpose of this polyline shapefile is to indicate the ship's position during the continuous resistivity profile survey. These lines can also be used to hyperlink to JPEG images of the corresponding resistivity profile enabling the resistivity data to be placed in spatial context with other GIS data.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>20060906</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-76.454833</westbc>
            <eastbc>-76.310367</eastbc>
            <northbc>38.295767</northbc>
            <southbc>37.946450</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>General</themekt>
            <themekey>U.S. Geological Survey</themekey>
            <themekey>USGS</themekey>
            <themekey>Coastal and Marine Geology Program</themekey>
            <themekey>CMGP</themekey>
            <themekey>Woods Hole Coastal and Marine Science Center</themekey>
            <themekey>WHCMSC</themekey>
            <themekey>Field Activity Serial Number 06018</themekey>
            <themekey>navigation</themekey>
            <themekey>polyline</themekey>
            <themekey>shapefile</themekey>
            <themekey>Continuous Resistivity Profiling</themekey>
            <themekey>CRP</themekey>
            <themekey>R/V Kerhin</themekey>
            <themekey>Lowrance GPS</themekey>
            <themekey>Info Bank ID K-1-06-CH</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
            <themekey>location</themekey>
            <themekey>oceans</themekey>
            <themekey>oceans and estuaries</themekey>
            <themekey>oceans and coastal</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>General</placekt>
            <placekey>North America</placekey>
            <placekey>North Atlantic</placekey>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
            <placekey>Virginia</placekey>
            <placekey>Maryland</placekey>
            <placekey>Potomac River Estuary</placekey>
            <placekey>Chesapeake Bay</placekey>
            <placekey>Dennis Point Marina</placekey>
            <placekey>Solomons, Maryland</placekey>
            <placekey>Patuxent River</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None.</accconst>
      <useconst>The public domain data from the U.S. Government are freely redistributable with proper metadata and source attribution. Please recognize the U.S. Geological Survey as the originator of the dataset.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>John F. Bratton</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Woods Hole Coastal and Marine Science Center</address>
               <address>384 Woods Hole Rd.</address>
               <city>Woods Hole</city>
               <state>MA</state>
               <postal>02543-1598</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(508) 548-8700  x2254</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(508) 457-2310</cntfax>
            <cntemail>jbratton@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <browse>
         <browsen>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2009/1151/data/navigation/resistivity/resgpslns_jd249.gif</browsen>
         <browsed>Thumbnail image showing the location of resistivity tracklines collected Sept. 6, 2006. The coastline is included for spatial reference.</browsed>
         <browset>GIF</browset>
      </browse>
      <native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.2.6.1500</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>Each line was generated in the same manner.</logic>
      <complete>All the points in the input shapefile were used to generate these polylines. These lines represent all the survey lines from this day.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>The primary navigation system used was a Lowrance 480M with an LGC-2000 Global Positioning System (GPS) antenna. The antenna was located 7.9 meters forward of the anchor point for the resistivity streamer, and approximately 3 meters forward of the fathometer transducer. These offsets were not entered into the GPS system. Additionally, because of navigation and fathometers issues, periodically the ship's navigation system was used to supplement these data. The ship had a Differential GPS (DGPS) system with the antenna placed in the same location as the Lowrance antenna. The fathometer was located (hull-mounted) roughly directly below the antenna, so no horizontal offset. Because of the mixture of systems, the accuracy is on the order of 20 meters.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
         <vertacc>
            <vertaccr>All the bathymetric values from this day were collected by the ship's fathometer. This fathometer was hull mounted approximately midship, relatively close to the navigation antenna. The values are assumed to be accurate to within 1 meter.</vertaccr>
         </vertacc>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccontr>
The continuous resistivity profile (CRP) system used on this cruise was an AGI SuperSting marine system described at the website: www.agiusa.com/marinesystem.shtml.  The particular system used for this acquisition was a 100-m streamer with an 11 electrode array with electrodes spaced 10 meters apart. The source electrodes are graphite, while the receiver electrodes are stainless steel. A dipole-dipole configuration was used for the data collection in which two fixed current electrodes are assigned with the measurement of voltage potential between electrode pairs in the remaining electrodes.  Each line of data acquisition records several files. The two files necessary for processing are the *.stg and the *.gps file.  The STG file contains the resistivity data, while the GPS file contains the navigation information.  The navigation system used in concert with the CRP system is a Lowrance LMS-480M with an LGC-2000 GPS antenna and a 200 kHz fathometer transducer.  The transducer also contains a temperature sensor which was not working on Julian Day 249.  Lowrance indicates the speed of sound used by the system is 4800 feet/second.  On the first day of data collection (Julian Day 249, Sept. 6, 2006) the Lowrance transducer was side-mounted mid-ship on the port side of the boat. The remainder of the cruise the transducer was side-mounted mid-ship of the starboard side of the boat.
The CRP system images the subsurface electrical properties of an estuarine, riverine or lacustrine environment. Resistivity differences can be attributed to subsurface geology (conductive vs less conductive layers) and hydrogeologic conditions with fresh water exhibiting high resistivity and saline conditions showing low resistivity.
</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>In ArcMap 9.2 an ArcMap extension written in Woods Hole (VACExtras, v2.05) was used to convert the individual navigation points to lines. The "Points to Line v2" tool within the extension was used. The user selects an attribute to be the unique identifier used to group the points into a line; in this case, the attribute "linename" was used. The script assumes the order of the points in the point shapefile is the order they need to be added to the line, and the projection of the output shapefile is the same as the input point shapefile. The user can also select additional attributes to be carried over to the output polyline shapefile. The value written out is the first occurrence of the attribute on the unique "line".  The additional attributes carried over were gpstime, gpsdate, and depth_m.</procdesc>
            <srcused>resgpspnts_jd249.shp</srcused>
            <procdate>2009</procdate>
            <srcprod>resgpslns_jd249.shp</srcprod>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>VeeAnn A. Cross</cntper>
                     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntpos>Marine Geologist</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>Woods Hole Coastal and Marine Science Center</address>
                     <address>384 Woods Hole Rd.</address>
                     <city>Woods Hole</city>
                     <state>MA</state>
                     <postal>02543-1598</postal>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>(508) 548-8700  x2251</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>(508) 457-2310</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>vatnipp@usgs.gov</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Two text attributes were added to the attribute table in ArcMap 9.2.  The attribute "hotlink" will allow the user to hyperlink to the MATLAB JPEG images of the CRP line from within ArcMap.  The attribute "hlink2" will allow the user to hyperlink to the EarthImager JPEG image of the long version of the CRP line from within ArcMap.  See the entity and attribute overview for instructions on how to implement this feature.</procdesc>
            <srcused>resgpslns_jd249.shp</srcused>
            <procdate>2009</procdate>
            <srcprod>resgpslns_jd249.shp</srcprod>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Vector</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>String</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>6</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <latres>0.000001</latres>
            <longres>0.000001</longres>
            <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
         </geograph>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
            <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.257222</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
      <vertdef>
         <depthsys>
            <depthdn>Local surface</depthdn>
            <depthres>0.1</depthres>
            <depthdu>meters</depthdu>
            <depthem>Implicit coordinate</depthem>
         </depthsys>
      </vertdef>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>resgpslns_jd249</enttypl>
            <enttypd>ESRI polyline shapefile</enttypd>
            <enttypds>ESRI</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>FID</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Id</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>An automatically generated numeric value.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>VACExtras v2.05</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>0</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>linename</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The alphanumeric name corresponding to the prefix of the GPS filename. This name reflects the name assigned to the line of data acquisition and incorporates modifiers to reflect modification of the GPS file.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Character set.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>gpstime</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>GPS time of the start of the line in the format HH:MM:SS. GPS time is recorded in UTC which is +4 hours compared to local time during the survey (daylight savings time - DST).</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Character set.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>gpsdate</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The date recorded in the GPS navigation corresponding to the first point of the line in the format DDMMYY. Because of the 4 hour time difference between UTC and DST, this date could actually be different than the local acquisition date.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Character set.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>depth_m</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Depth of the water below the fathometer of the first point in the line, units are meters.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>2.8</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>9.8</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>meters</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>hotlink</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Text field which provides the partial path and full filename of the MATLAB JPEG image of the CRP line associated with the trackline.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Data processor.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Character set.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>hlink2</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Text field which provides the partial path and full filename of the long JPEG image of the CRP line associated with the trackline.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Data processor.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Character set.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <overview>
         <eaover>In order to effectively utilize the "hotlink" or "hlink2" attribute in ArcGIS, the user must follow a couple of steps.  First, the user must open the Layer Properties of the shapefile within ArcMap - select the Display tab - and click on the check box next to "Support Hyperlinks using field:" and the field selected from the dropdown menu needs to be "hotlink" or "hlink2". The hyperlink is set to a document.  Additionally, a hyperlink base must be supplied in the ArcMap document (mxd) to complete the full path to the images. This is accomplished from File - Document Properties.  On the Summary tab there is a section for "Hyperlink base".  The text supplied here needs to be the disk information preceding "data" in the full path to the image.  If the data are being read from a DVD, this would be the drive letter such as F:\.</eaover>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>John F. Bratton</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Woods Hole Coastal and Marine Science Center</address>
               <address>384 Woods Hole Rd.</address>
               <city>Woods Hole</city>
               <state>MA</state>
               <postal>02543-1598</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(508) 548-8700  x2254</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(508) 457-2310</cntfax>
            <cntemail>jbratton@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
      <distliab>Neither the U.S. government, the Department of the Interior, nor the USGS, nor any of their employees, contractors, or subcontractors, make any warranty, express or implied, nor assume any legal liability or responsibility for the accuracy, completeness, or usefulness of any information, apparatus, product, or process disclosed, nor represent that its use would not infringe on privately owned rights. The act of distribution shall not constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumed by the USGS in the use of these data or related materials. Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>WinZip</formname>
               <formvern>9.0</formvern>
               <formcont>This WinZip file contains the polyline shapefile as well as the associated metadata files.</formcont>
               <transize>0.075 MB</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2009/1151/data/navigation/resistivity/resgpslns_jd249.zip</networkr>
                        <networkr>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2009/1151/html/catalog.html</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
               <offoptn>
                  <offmedia>DVD-ROM</offmedia>
                  <reccap>
                     <recden>4.75</recden>
                     <recdenu>GBytes</recdenu>
                  </reccap>
                  <recfmt>UDF</recfmt>
               </offoptn>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None.</fees>
      </stdorder>
      <techpreq>This WinZip file contains data available in ESRI polyline shapefile format. The user must have software capable of uncompressing the WinZip file and reading/displaying the shapefile.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20100325</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>VeeAnn A. Cross</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Marine Geologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Woods Hole Coastal and Marine Science Center</address>
               <address>384 Woods Hole Rd.</address>
               <city>Woods Hole</city>
               <state>MA</state>
               <postal>02543-1598</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(508) 548-8700  x2251</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(508) 457-2310</cntfax>
            <cntemail>vatnipp@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
      <metextns>
         <onlink>http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink>
         <metprof>ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof>
      </metextns>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
