<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Taft, Oriane W., and Susan M. Haig</origin>
            <pubdate>2004</pubdate>
            <title>January 2000 classified RADARSAT image depicting winter shorebird habitat in the Willamette Valley, OR</title>
            <geoform>raster digital data</geoform>
            <onlink>http://srfs.wr.usgs.gov/Fresc_ScienceData/wetlands_jan.zip</onlink>
            <onlink>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/53f78d17e4b05ec1f246eef1</onlink>
            <onlink>http://fresc.usgs.gov/ArcIMS/WEbsite/radar</onlink>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Taft, O.W., S.M. Haig and C. Kiilsgaard</origin>
                  <pubdate>2004</pubdate>
                  <title>Use of radar remote sensing (RADARSAT) to map winter wetland habitat for shorebirds in an agricultural landscape</title>
                  <geoform>Journal article</geoform>
                  <serinfo>
                     <sername>Environmental Management</sername>
                     <issue>33: 750-763</issue>
                  </serinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This dataset is one of a collection of three land cover maps of the Willamette Valley of Oregon, USA, depicting 4 habitat classes: wet with &lt;= 50% vegetation cover (class 1), wet with &gt;50% vegetation (class 2), dry with &lt;= 50% vegetation (class 3), dry with &gt;50% vegetation (class 4).  Land cover maps were derived by classifying signatures from C-band (5.6 cm wavelength), HH-polarized radar remote sensing (RADARSAT) data collected at a 38 degree  incidence angle (8-m resolution).  The data are in the form of an ERDAS Imagine image.</abstract>
         <purpose>Data were collected to map the distribution of winter shorebird habitat on agricultural lands in the Willamette Valley of western Oregon.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>20020128</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Date of satellite data collection</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-123.536316</westbc>
            <eastbc>-122.408327</eastbc>
            <northbc>45.541194</northbc>
            <southbc>43.933582</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO19139 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>imageryBaseMapsEarthCover</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>Biocomplexity Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>Agricultural land</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>RADARSAT</themekey>
            <themekey>agricultural landscape</themekey>
            <themekey>shorebirds</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>None</placekt>
            <placekey>Willamette Valley</placekey>
            <placekey>Oregon</placekey>
            <placekey>OR</placekey>
         </place>
         <temporal>
            <tempkt>None</tempkt>
            <tempkey>winter</tempkey>
         </temporal>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>No legal or policy restrictions to data access</accconst>
      <useconst>Data set originators must be cited if these data are used for analysis or display.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Communications and Information Program</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>777 NW 9th Street, Suite 400</address>
               <city>Corvallis</city>
               <state>Oregon</state>
               <postal>97330</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>777 NW 9th Street, Suite 400</address>
               <city>Corvallis</city>
               <state>Oregon</state>
               <postal>97330</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>541-750-1030</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <datacred>Funding was provided by Oregon Watershed Enhancement Board and U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service.  Analysis was conducted by Northwest Habitat Institute, Corvallis, OR.</datacred>
      <native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.0.0.535</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>We assessed accuracy of final maps using the remaining ground reference sites not used for training (see  methods); this resulted in 274 verification sites for December, 283 for January, and 284 for March.  For each site, we compared its predicted class from final maps to the site?s true class and constructed an error matrix of these comparisons for each date.  The error assessment characterized the accuracy of each map, with commission error or "user?s accuracy" (proportion of sites assigned to a class that are correctly assigned) and omission error or "producer?s accuracy" (the proportion of sites of a certain class that are correctly assigned) included.  For each map, we calculated overall accuracy as the number of correctly classified sites divided by the total number of testing sites.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Not applicable</logic>
      <complete>In mapping shorebird habitat on agricultural lands, we focused on identifying flooded fields with exposed soil (less than 50% cover); these conditions are preferred by Dunlin and ecological allies (species in the family Scolopacidae).  We designed a classification scheme of four classes based on presence of water and vegetation: 1) wet (either impounded water or shallowly flooded) with &lt;= 50% vegetation, 2) wet with &gt;50% vegetation, 3) dry (without visible standing water) with &lt;= 50% vegetation, 4) dry with &gt;50% vegetation.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>Before rectifying scenes, we used Sigma and Lee filters to reduce speckle noise (Rio et al. 2000).  Among nine scenes, we were able to reduce coefficients of variation for noise from 0.387-0.399 at raw imagery to 0.213-0.223 at the second pass.  We then rectified all December scenes to a 1996 Landsat Thematic Mapper reference image of the Valley.  Among the three December scenes, we selected between 18 and 34 ground control points (GCPs) to calculate third-order polynomial transformations used to geo-register input images to the reference scene. Among the three scenes, registration was achieved with an error of 22-28 meters, approximately the size of a Landsat TM pixel (30 m).  Scenes for January (using 41-52 GCPs) and March (38-45 GCPs) were geo-registered to the rectified December scenes, also using third-order polynomial transformations.  Registration errors were lower among these six scenes, ranging from 4.8-16.7 meters.  We used a cubic convolution resampling procedure to assign new coordinate grids to scenes.  After geo-registration, the three scenes for each date were mosaicked into composite images used in the classification effort.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Pater, D.E., S. Bryce, T.D. Thorson, J. Kagan, C. Chappell, J. Omernik, S. Azevedo and A. J. Woods</origin>
                  <pubdate>1997</pubdate>
                  <title>Ecoregions of western Washington and Oregon</title>
                  <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Corvallis, Oregon</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <srcscale>100000</srcscale>
            <typesrc>electronic file</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1997</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>ecoregions</srccitea>
            <srccontr>The Willamette Valley Foothills ecoregion was selected and rasterized and used to mask this area from the radar imagery.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Kiilsgaard, C.</origin>
                  <pubdate>1999</pubdate>
                  <title>Oregon vegetation: mapping and classification of landscape-level cover types</title>
                  <geoform>report</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Moscow, Idaho</pubplace>
                     <publish>USGS</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>Final report, USGS-BRD GAP Analysis Program</othercit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>computer program</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>1999</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>GAP data</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Each of the final classified mosaicked images was overlaid with urban, forest, and permanent open water (reservoirs, rivers, etc.) land cover from this data set.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Radarsat, International</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
                  <title>RADARSAT Imagery</title>
                  <geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
                  <othercit>8 meter pixel size</othercit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>photographic print</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <mdattim>
                     <sngdate>
                        <caldate>19991210</caldate>
                     </sngdate>
                     <sngdate>
                        <caldate>20000128</caldate>
                     </sngdate>
                     <sngdate>
                        <caldate>20000315</caldate>
                     </sngdate>
                  </mdattim>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>date of satellite data collection</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>radar image</srccitea>
            <srccontr>We acquired imagery on three selected days when the Canadian RADARSAT satellite passed over the Valley study area: 10 December 1999, 27 January 2000, and 15 March 2000.  With these dates we aimed to capture the extent of shorebird wetland habitat at three different time periods: at the onset of early winter rainfall (early December), at the peak of the mid-winter rainy season (January), and during waning rain activity in late winter/early spring (March).</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>We acquired imagery on three selected days when the Canadian RADARSAT satellite passed over the Valley study area: 10 December 1999, 27 January 2000, and 15 March 2000.  With these dates we aimed to capture the extent of shorebird wetland habitat at three different time periods: at the onset of early winter rainfall (early December), at the peak of the mid-winter rainy season (January), and during waning rain activity in late winter/early spring (March).

The RADARSAT satellite carries a C-band (5.6 cm wavelength) synthetic aperture radar (SAR) with HH (horizontally transmitted/horizontally received) wavelength polarization.  All scenes were taken in fine 1 far (F1F) beam mode (8-meter pixel resolution; 38.78o incidence angle) on descending orbits at 14:18 hours.  Scenes at F1F are approximately 50 x 50 km, thus it took three scenes to cover our focal study area (central and southern Valley) on each acquisition date.  These images were aligned and acquired north-south so that each final map, once mosaicked, would continuously cover an area roughly 50 x 150 km (4500 km2), encompassing Valley lowlands from Eugene to Newberg, Oregon.  We used ecoregions to mask the Valley Foothills subecoregion from radar imagery acquired in the 50 x 150 km swath.  The size of the study area portrayed by final maps was 4209 km2.</procdesc>
            <srcused>ecoregions</srcused>
            <srcused>radar image</srcused>
            <procdate>2000</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Kiilsgaard, Chris</cntper>
                     <cntorg>Northwest Habitat Institute</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
                     <address>PO Box 855</address>
                     <city>Corvallis</city>
                     <state>OR</state>
                     <postal>97339</postal>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>541-757-3118</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>541-753-2440</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>chris@nwhi.org</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>We used both supervised and unsupervised classification techniques to associate spectral signature with habitat classes.  Using our field data, we were able to distinguish a specific signature to supervise the classification of class 1 habitat only; we used unsupervised training to produce signatures for the remaining classes.  For supervised classification of habitat in class 1, we delineated polygons around pixel clusters of homogeneous spectral returns within class 1 reference sites, and calculated mean, standard deviation, minimum and maximum digital values for all pixels within each polygon.  We then used a maximum likelihood classification algorithm to delineate class 1 habitat within mosaicked scenes.  To classify habitat in classes 2-4, we separated returns remaining in the class 1-masked scene into 50 distinct spectral clusters.  We chose the number 50 to accommodate the variability of signatures we expected from the myriad of permutations of wet and dry soils with varying amount of vegetation.  Using roughly half of our ground reference dataset (415 sites from December, 448 sites from January, and 308 sites from March) as training sites (randomly chosen), we then visually determined which of the three categories each of the 50 return clusters represented and recoded the 50 clusters into three remaining habitat classes.  Finally, we overlaid each of the final classified mosaicked images with urban, forest, and permanent open water (reservoirs, rivers, etc.) land cover using an ancillary map developed from 1996 Landsat TM imagery (Kiilsgaard 1999).</procdesc>
            <srcused>GAP data</srcused>
            <srcused>radar image</srcused>
            <procdate>2000</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>Kiilsgaard, Chris</cntper>
                     <cntorg>Northwest Habitat Institute</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
                     <address>PO Box 855</address>
                     <city>Corvallis</city>
                     <state>OR</state>
                     <postal>97339</postal>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>541-757-3118</cntvoice>
                  <cntfax>541-753-2440</cntfax>
                  <cntemail>chris@nwhi.org</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Pixel</rasttype>
         <rowcount>22302</rowcount>
         <colcount>11008</colcount>
         <vrtcount>1</vrtcount>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <mapproj>
               <mapprojn>Transverse Mercator</mapprojn>
               <transmer>
                  <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
                  <longcm>-123</longcm>
                  <latprjo>0</latprjo>
                  <feast>500000</feast>
                  <fnorth>0</fnorth>
               </transmer>
            </mapproj>
            <planci>
               <plance>Coordinate Pair</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>8</absres>
                  <ordres>8</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>meters</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>D_GRS_1980</horizdn>
            <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.257222</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>jan 28 2000.img</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Erdas Imagine file</enttypd>
            <enttypds>ERDAS</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Blue</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>meter number of blue in the RGB color model</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>RGB color model</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>1</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Class_names</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Name of habitat class</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Dataset developer</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>0</edomv>
                  <edomvd>unclassified area</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>user-defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Wet, unvegetated (&lt;50%)</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>user-defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Wet, vegetated (&gt;50%)</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>user-defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Dry, unvegetated (&lt;50%)</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>user-defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>4</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Dry, vegetated (&gt;50%)</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>user-defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>5</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Urban Area</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>user-defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>6</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Open water</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>user-defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>7</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Forest</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>user-defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Count</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels in class</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>ERDAS</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>Unknown Maximum</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Green</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>meter number for the amount of green in RBG color model</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>RGB color model</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>1</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>ObjectID</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Opacity</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Code identifying a pixel as a class set or part of background</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Dataset developer</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>0</edomv>
                  <edomvd>background</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>user-defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>class set</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>user-defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Red</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>meter number for the amount of red in RGB color model</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>RGB color model</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>1</rdommax>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystems Science Center (FRESC)
Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center (FRESC)</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Communications and Information Program</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing and Physical Address</addrtype>
               <address>777 NW 9th Street, Suite 400</address>
               <city>Corvallis</city>
               <state>Oregon</state>
               <postal>97330</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>541-750-1030</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>s:\projects\gis\workspace\taft\</resdesc>
      <distliab>The USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center and its research partners make every effort to provide and maintain accurate, complete, usable, and timely information. However, some USGS data and information may, of necessity, be preliminary in nature. These data and information are provided with the understanding that they are not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Users are cautioned to consider carefully the provisional nature of these data and information before using them for decisions that concern personal or public safety or the conduct of business that involves substantial monetary or operational consequences. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data and information. Conclusions drawn from, or actions undertaken on the basis of, such data and information are the sole responsibility of the user.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Winzip</formname>
               <formcont>Raster digital data as an ERDAS Imagine image (.img) and metadata.</formcont>
               <filedec>Use Winzip or PKUnzip for decompression</filedec>
               <transize>46.745</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://fresc.usgs.gov/products/dataset/radarsat/wetlands_jan.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>Downloadable data</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None</fees>
         <ordering>Download from FRESC Website: http://fresc.usgs.gov/products/dataset/radarsat/wetlands_jan.zip or ArcIMS website http://fresc.usgs.gov/ArcIMS/Website/radar</ordering>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20040830</metd>
      <metrd>20040903</metrd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystems Science Center (FRESC)
Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center (FRESC)</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Communications and Information Program</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing and Physical Address</addrtype>
               <address>777 NW 9th Street, Suite 400</address>
               <city>Corvallis</city>
               <state>Oregon</state>
               <postal>97330</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>541-750-1030</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
