<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>2001</pubdate>
            <title>Geochemistry of unconsolidated sediments in the US
from the RASS database</title>
            <geoform>map</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://mrdata.usgs.gov/rass/sediment/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This dataset contains geochemical data for unconsolidated
sediments (stream sediments, lake sediments, etc.) collected by
U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) personnel and analyzed in the
analytical laboratories of the Geologic Division of the USGS.
These data represent analyses of sediment samples collected in
support of various USGS programs.  The data were originally
entered into the in-house Rock Analysis Storage System (RASS)
database which was used by the Geologic Division from the early-
1970's through the late-1980's to archive geochemical data. An
unpublished CD-ROM was developed in 1996 that contains the RASS
data in GSSEARCH format.  That CD was used to generate this data
set.</abstract>
         <purpose>These data may be useful for mineral resource evaluation and for
defining geochemical baseline values and statistics.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>1965</begdate>
               <enddate>1988</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Sample collection and analysis period</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>The RASS database is currently the focus of an error-
identification and correction process that has, to this point in
time (January 2001), concentrated on data from Alaska. Upgraded
data files for Alaska from the RASS database are being placed on
the following web site as they become available:
http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/1999/of99-433/
The upgrades are primarly related to 1) additional information on
the exact sample medium analyzed, 2) adding location coordinates
where there were none, and 3) correcting location coordinates
known to be inaccurate.</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-175.908</westbc>
            <eastbc>0</eastbc>
            <northbc>77.64</northbc>
            <southbc>1</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>sediment</themekey>
            <themekey>geochemistry</themekey>
            <themekey>geochemical data</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>NGDA Portfolio Themes</themekt>
            <themekey>Geology</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>None</placekt>
            <placekey>United States of America</placekey>
         </place>
         <temporal>
            <tempkt>None</tempkt>
            <tempkey>2001</tempkey>
         </temporal>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>None</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Smith, David B.</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Box25046, MS 973
Denver Federal Center</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>United States of America</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-303-236-1849</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>1-303-236-3200</cntfax>
            <cntemail>&lt;dsmith@usgs.gov&gt;</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Elizabeth A. Bailey</origin>
            <origin>David B. Smith</origin>
            <origin>Carl C. Abston</origin>
            <origin>Matthew Granitto</origin>
            <origin>Kuuipo A. Burleigh</origin>
            <title>National Geochemical Database: U.S. Geological Survey RASS
(Rock Analysis Storage System) geochemical data for Alaska</title>
            <pubdate>2000</pubdate>
            <edition>2.0</edition>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report</sername>
               <issue>99-433</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/1999/of99-433/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>The samples in this dataset were chemically analyzed by a variety
of techniques over a period of time from the early 1960's to the
late 1980's.  The accuracy of the data varies with the analytical
methodology and with the concentration of the element being
analyzed.  A qualifier such as "N" (less than the detection limit
of the analytical method) or "G" (greater than the upper
determination limit of the analytical method) accompanies some
analytical data values. These qualifiers are defined as follows:
L = the element was detected by the technique but at a level
below the lower limit of determination for the method.  The value
of the lower limit of determination is given in the adjacent data
field.
G = the element was measured at a concentration greater than the
upper determination limit for the method. The upper limit of
determination is given in the adjacent data field.
N = the element was not detected at concentrations above the
lower limit of determination for the method. The value of the
lower limit of determination is given in the adjacent data field.
B = the element was requested for analysis by the sample
submitter, but for some reason the laboratories did not analyze
for this element.
When appropriate, these qualifying values appear in this dataset
as a separate field preceding each element. The attribute, or
field name, for the qualifier field is always denoted by the
letter "Q".  For example, "N" in the "S_ASQ" field preceding an
analytical data field labelled "S_AS" would indicate the actual
concentration of arsenic (AS) is less than the data value listed,
which is the lower limit of determination for the method.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>This data set contains a variety of sample media prepared from
unconsolidated sediments.  For example, there are samples of
unconsolidated sediments that have simply been sieved to specific
size fractions before analysis.  Unfortunately, the original RASS
database had no field for identifying this size fraction.  As we
upgrade the database, we are adding this information when possible;
however, the data set for which this metadata is written does not
contain information on the sieve size. There are also samples of
various types of heavy mineral concentrates within the data set
When these types of samples were properly identified within the
RASS database, they were separated into another data set and not
included in this data set.  However, if the concentrates were not
properly identified, they could not be located for exclusion.  The
upgrading of the RASS data will include identification of the
currently unidentified heavy-mineral-concentrate samples.</logic>
      <complete>This dataset provides chemical data for Fe, Mg, Ca, Na, K, Ti, Mn,
Ag, As, Au, B, Ba, Be, Bi, Cd, Co, Cr, Cu, La, Mo, Nb, Ni, Pb, Sb,
Sc, Sn, Sr, U, V, W, Y, Zn, Zr, Th, Tl, F, Hg, Pt, and Pd.  In
addition, the dataset provides location and descriptive information
for each sample.  Not all the descriptive fields contain
information for a particular sample because not all sample
submitters completed all the fields. The analytical methods used
were selected by the sample submitter based on the goals of the
project and will vary throughout the data set.  The predominant
analytical methods used for samples in this dataset are:
Emission Spectrography: Grimes and Marranzino, 1968; Fe, Mg, Ca,
Ti, Mn, Ag, As, Au, B, Ba, Be, Bi, Cd, Co, Cr, Cu, La, Mo, Nb, Ni,
Pb, Sb, Sc, Sn, Sr, V, W, Y, Zn, Zr, Th, Ga, Ge, Pd, and Pt.
Atomic Absorption, partial extraction: O'Leary and Meier, 1986; O'
Leary and Viets, 1986; Viets, 1978; Viets, Clark, and Campbell,
1984; Viets, O'Leary, and Clark, 1984; Ward and others, 1969: Ag,
Bi, Cd, Cu, Mo, Pb, Sb, and Zn.
The complete references for all analytical methods used are given below:
Adrian, B.A. and Carlson, R.R., personal communication, Platinum-group elements and gold by nickel-sulfide fire assay separation and optical emission spectroscopy
Alminas, H. and Mosier, E.L., 1976, Oxalic-acid leaching of rock, soil, and stream-sediment samples as an anomaly-accentuation technique: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 76-275. 26 p.
Chao, T.T., Sanzolone, R.F., and Hubert, A.E., 1978, Flame and flameless atomic absorption determination of tellurium in geologic materials: Analytica Chimica Acta, v. 96, p. 251-257.
Church, S.E., 1981, Multi-element analysis of fifty-four geochemical reference samples using inductively coupled plasma-atomic emission spectrometry: Geostandards Newsletter, v. 5, p. 133-160.
Cooley, E.F., Curry, K.J., and Carlson, R.R., 1976, Analysis for the platinum-group metals and gold by fire-assay emission spectroscopy: Applied Spectroscopy, v. 30. P. 52-56.
Fishman, M.J., and Pyen, G., 1979, Determination of selected anions in water by ion chromatography: U.S. Geological Survey Water Resources Investigations 79-101, 30 p.
Grimes, D.J., and Marranzino, A.P., 1968, Direct-current arc and alternating-current spark emission spectrographic field methods for the semiquantitative analysis of geologic materials: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 591, 6 p.
Hubert, A.E., and Chao, T.T., 1985, Determination of gold, indium, tellurium and thallium in the same sample digest of geological materials by atomic-absorption spectroscopy and two-step solvent extraction: Talanta, v. 32, no. 7, p. 568-570.
McKown, D.M., and Knight, R.J., 1990, Determination of uranium and thorium in geologic materials by delayed neutron counting, in Arbogast, B.F., editor, Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 146-15
Mosier, E.L., 1972, A method for semiquantitative spectrographic analysis of plant ash for use in biogeochemical and environmental studies: Applied Spectroscopy, v. 26, no. 6, p. 636-641.
Mosier, E.L., 1975, Use of emission spectroscopy for the semiquantitative analysis of trace elements in silver and native gold, in Ward, F.N., editor, New and refined methods of trace analysis useful in geochemical exploration: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1408, p. 97-105.
Mosier, E.L., and Motooka, J.M., 1984, Induction coupled plasma-atomic emission spectrometry-Analysis of subsurface Cambrian carbonate rocks for major, minor, and trace elements, in Proceedings volume of international conference on Mississippi Valley-type lead-zinc deposits, Oct. 11-14: Rolla, MO, University of Missouri-Rolla, p. 155-165.
Myers, A.T., Havens, R.G., and Dunton, P.J., 1961, A spectrochemical method for the semiquantitative analysis of rocks, minerals, and ores: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1084-I, p. I207-I229.
O'Leary, R.M., 1990, Determination of sulfur in geologic materials by iodometric titration, in Arbogast, B.F., editor, Quality assurance manual for the Branch of Geochemistry, U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 90-668, p. 136-138.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration in 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948, 48 p.
O'Leary, R.M., and Meier, A.L., 1986, Bismuth, cadmium, copper, lead, silver, and zinc, organic extraction method, in Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration, 1984: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 948,p. 11-13.
O'Leary, R.M., and Viets, J.G., 1986, Determination of antimony, bismuth, cadmium, copper, lead, molybdenum, silver, and zinc in geologic materials by atomic absorption spectrometry using a hydrochloric acid-hydrogen peroxide digestion: Atomic Spectroscopy, v. 7, no. 1, p. 4-8.
Orion Research, Inc., 1975, Orion Research Analytical Methods Guide, 7th edition: Cambridge, MA, 20 p.
Perkin-Elmer Corporation, 1976, Analytical methods for atomic absorption spectrophotometry: Norwalk, CT, Perkin-Elmer Corp., 586 p.
Perkin-Elmer Corporation, 1977, Analytical methods for atomic absorption spectrophotometry, using the HGA graphite furnace: Norwalk, CT, Perkin-Elmer Corp., 286 p.
Sutley, S.J., and Mosier, E.L., personal communication, Rb, Cs, Li, Tl by modification of optical emission spectroscopy method of Grimes and Marranzino, 1968
Thompson, C.E., Nakagawa, H.M., and VanSickle, G.H., 1968, Rapid analysis for gold in geologic materials: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 600-B, p. B130-B132.
Vaughn, W.W., and McCarthy, J.H., Jr., 1964, An instrumental technique for the determination of submicrogram concentrations of mercury in soils, rocks, and gas: U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 501-D, p. D123-D127.
Viets, J.G., 1978, Determination of silver, bismuth, cadmium, copper, lead, and zinc in geologic materials by atomic absorption spectrometry with tricaprylyl methyl ammonium chloride: Analytical Chemistry, v. 50, no. 8, p. 1097-1101.
Viets, J.G., Clark, J.R., and Campbell, W.L., 1984, A rapid, partial leach and organic separation for the sensitive determination of Ag, Bi, Cd, Cu, Mo, Pb, Sb, and Zn in surface geologic materials by flame atomic absorption: Journal of Geochemical Exploration, v. 20, p. 355-366.
Viets, J.G., O'Leary, R.M., and Clark, J.R., 1984, Determination of arsenic, antimony, bismuth, cadmium, copper, lead, molybdenum, silver and zinc in geological materials by atomic-absorption spectrometry: The Analyst, v. 109, p. 1589-1592.
Ward, F.N., Lakin, H.W., Canney, F.C., and others, 1963, Analytical methods used in geochemical exploration by the U.S. Geological Survey: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1152, 100 p.
Ward, F.N., Nakagawa, H.M., VanSickle, G.H., and Harms, T.F., 1969, Atomic absorption methods useful in geochemical exploration: U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 1289, 45 p.
Watterson, J.R., 1976, Determination of tellurium and gold in rocks to 1 part per billion: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 76-531, 3 p.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>Sample locations were determined from USGS topographic maps of
various scales.  The accuracy is dependant on the scale of the
map from which the determination was made as well as the care
taken by the individual who made the determination.
Unfortnately, some location coordinates were not carefully
determined.  In other cases, the individual who collected the
samples only identified the location as a corner of the
quadrangle in which the samples were collected. When submitters
reported locations as degrees, minutes, and seconds of latitude
and longitude the accuracy should be within a few seconds.
When submitters only reported locations as degrees and minutes
the accuracy is only to the nearest minute.  The base maps,
from which latitude and longitude coordinates were determined,
use the 1927 North American Datum (NAD27) based on the Clarke
1866 ellipsoid.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The data were generated by the analytical laboratories of the
U.S. Geological Survey over several years, beginning in the
early 1960s and ending about 1987.  Upon completion of the
chemical analysis, the data were stored in the RASS database.
An unpublished CD-ROM was developed in 1996 that contains the
RASS data in GSSEARCH format.  This CD-ROM was used to
generated the data set in .dbf format. The RASS DBF file was
imported into ArcView 3.2 and an ArcView shapefile was
generated which contained 199,850 sample locations (5135
samples were eliminated due to location discrepancies).</procdesc>
            <procdate>200101</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>vector</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>199850</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <geogunit>decimal degrees</geogunit>
         </geograph>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>North American Datum of 1927</horizdn>
            <ellips>Clarke 1866</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378206.4</semiaxis>
            <denflat>294.98</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>sedimentsrass.dbf</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Geochemical sample submitted for analysis</enttypd>
            <enttypds>U.S. Geological Survey</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>SUBNAME</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Submitter's name, name of the individual who submitted the samples to the laboratory for analysis.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>TAGNUMBER</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Unique identification number assigned by the laboratory.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>FIELDNO</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Field number assigned by the submitter designated in the SUBNAME field.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>LATITUDE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Latitude of sample site reported in degrees, minutes, and seconds (ddmmss).</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>LATDIR</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Direction north (N) or south (S) of the equator.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>LONGITUD</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Longitude of the sample site reported in degrees, minutes, and seconds (ddmmss).</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>LONGDIR</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Direction east (E) or west (W) of the 0 meridian (Greenwich).</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>LATDD</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Latitude of sample site reported in Decimal Degress.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>LONGDD</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Longitude of sample site reported in Decimal Degress.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>SMPLTYPE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Sample type, nature of material collected for sample.</attrdef>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>B</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Unconsolidated sediment</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>METHCOLL</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Sample collection method, character of sample</attrdef>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>A</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Single (grab)</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>B</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Composite</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Channel</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>D</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Other</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>SMPLSRC</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Source of sample</attrdef>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>A</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Outcrop</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>B</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Mine</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>C</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Dump or prospect pit</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>D</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Float</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>E</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Drill hole, well</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Marine</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>G</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Other</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>H</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Stream</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>I</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Spring</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>J</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Lake</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>K</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Aquaduct, canal, irrigation ditch</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>L</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Atmosphere</edomvd>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_FE_</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Iron concentration (percent) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_MG_</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Magnesium concentration (percent) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_CA_</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Calcium concentration (percent) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_TI_</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Titanium concentration (percent) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_MN</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Manganese concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_AG</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Silver concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_AS</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Arsenic concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_AU</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Gold concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_B</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Boron concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_BA</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Barium concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_BE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Beryllium concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_BI</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Bismuth concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_CD</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Cadmium concenration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_CO</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Cobalt concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_CR</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Chromium concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_CU</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Copper concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_LA</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Lanthanum concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_MO</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Molybdenum concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_NB</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Niobium concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_NI</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Nickel concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_PB</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Lead concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_SB</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Antimony concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_SC</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Scandium concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_SN</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Tin concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_SR</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Strontium concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_V</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Vanadium concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_W</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Tungsten concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_Y</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Yttrium concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_ZN</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Zinc concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_ZR</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Zirconium concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_TH</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Thorium concentration (parts per million) as determined by semi-quantitative emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AA_AU_PQ</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AA_AU_P</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Gold concentration (parts per million) as determined by partial extraction of the sample followed by atomic absorption spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>INST_HGQ</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>INST_HG</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Mercury concentration (parts per million) as determined by an instrumental technique such as cold vapor atomic absorption spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AA_AS_PQ</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AA_AS_P</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Arsenic concentration (parts per million) as determined by partial extraction of the sample followed by atomic absorption spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AA_CD_PQ</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AA_CD_P</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Cadmium concentration (parts per million) as determined by partial extraction of the sample followed by atomic absorption spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AA_SB_PQ</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AA_SB_P</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Antimony concentration (parts per million) as determined by partial extraction of the sample followed by atomic absorption spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AA_ZN_PQ</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AA_ZN_P</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Zinc concentration (parts per million) as determined by partial extraction of the sample followed by atomic absorption spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AA_CU_PQ</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AA_CU_P</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Copper concentration (parts per million) as determined by partial extraction of the sample followed by atomic absorption spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AA_PB_PQ</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AA_PB_P</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Lead concentration (parts per million) as determined by partial extraction of the sampled followed by atomic absorption spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AA_AG_PQ</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AA_AG_P</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Silver concentration (parts per million) as determined by partial extraction of the sample followed by atomic absorption spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>SI_FQ</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>SI_F</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Fluorine concentration (parts per million) as determined by specific ion electrode.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>U_INSTQ</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>U_INST</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Uranium concentration (parts per million) as determined by an instrumental technique such as fluorimetry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AS_PTQ</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AS_PT</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Platinum concentration (parts per million) as determined by fire assay emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AS_PDQ</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>AS_PD</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Paladium concentration (parts per million) as determined by fire assay emission spectrometry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>CM_ASQ</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>CM_AS</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Arsenic concentration (parts per million) as determined by colorimetry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>CM_MOQ</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>CM_MO</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Molybdenum concentration (parts per million) as determined by colorimetry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>CM_WQ</attrlabl>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>CM_W</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Tungsten concentration (parts per million) as determined by colorimetry.</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>JOBNUMBER</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Arbitrary identifier for the analytical process</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_FE_Q</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for iron concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_MG_Q</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for magnesium concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_CA_Q</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for calcium concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_TI_Q</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for titanium concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_MNQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for manganese concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_AGQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for silver concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_ASQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for arsenic concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_AUQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for gold concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_BQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for boron concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_BAQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for barium concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_BEQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for beryllium concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_BIQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for bismuth concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_CDQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for cadmium concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_COQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for cobalt concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_CRQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for chromium concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_CUQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for copper concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_LAQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for lanthanum concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_MOQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for molybdenum concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_NBQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for niobium concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_NIQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for nickel concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_PBQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for lead concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_SBQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for antimony concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_SCQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for scandium concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_SNQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for tin concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_SRQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for strontium concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_VQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for vanadium concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_WQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for tungsten concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_YQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for yttrium concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_ZNQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for zinc concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_ZRQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for zirconium concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>S_THQ</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Quality indicator for thorium concentration</attrdef>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Smith, David B.</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Research Geologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Box 25046, Denver Federal Center, MS 973</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80025</postal>
               <country>United States</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-303-236-1849</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>1-303-236-3200</cntfax>
            <cntemail>dsmith@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>These data are released on the condition that neither the U.S.
Geological Survey (USGS) nor the United States Government may be
held liable for any damages resulting from authorized or
unauthorized use.  The USGS provides these data "as is" and makes
no guarantee or warranty concerning the accuracy of information
contained in the data.  The USGS further makes no warranties,
either expressed or implied as to any other matter, whatsoever,
including, without limitation, the condition of the product, or its
fitness for any particular purpose.  The burden for determining
fitness for use lies entirely with the user.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>shapefile</formname>
               <formvern>1.0</formvern>
               <formcont>Geochemical sample locations and analyses</formcont>
               <filedec>unzip</filedec>
               <transize>10.6</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://mrdata.usgs.gov/rass/sediment/rasssed.zip</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>none</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20141201</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Smith, David B.</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Research Geologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>Box 25046, Denver Federal Center, MS 973</address>
               <city>Denver</city>
               <state>Colorado</state>
               <postal>80225</postal>
               <country>United States</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-303-236-1849</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>1-303-236-3200</cntfax>
            <cntemail>dsmith@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
