<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing (CCRS), Earth Sciences Sector, Natural Resources
Canada</origin>
            <origin>Comisión Nacional para el Conocimiento y Uso de la Biodiversidad (CONABIO)</origin>
            <origin>Comisión Nacional Forestal (CONAFOR)</origin>
            <origin>Insituto Nacional de Estadística y Geografía (INEGI)</origin>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)</origin>
            <pubdate>2013</pubdate>
            <title>2005 Land Cover of North America at 250 meters - National Geospatial Data Asset (NGDA) Land Use Land Cover</title>
            <edition>2.0</edition>
            <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Montréal, Québec, Canada</pubplace>
               <publish>Commission for Environmental Cooperation</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.cec.org/naatlas/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This data set replaces the 2010 edition (Edition 1.0) of the 2005 Land Cover of
North America.  Following the release of the first 2005 land cover data, several
errors were identified in the data, including both errors in labeling and
misinterpretation of thematic classes.   To correct the labeling errors, each
country focused on its national territory and corrected the errors which it
considered most critical or misleading.  For the continental data sets (including
surrounding water fringe) 17440830 pixels (4.33% of the area) changed in the
update.   The following national counts exclude the water fringe: Canada, 10223412
pixels changed (6.44%); Mexico, 141142 pixels changed (0.45%), and U.S., 6878656
pixels changed (4.54%).
The countries worked together to produce a definitive list of land cover
classifications for the 2005 data; this document is available for download from the
same site as the data and is entitled: North American Land Cover Classifications
(2005).
Version 1 of the 2005 North American Land Cover data set was produced as part of
the North American Land Change Monitoring System (NALCMS), a trilateral effort
between the Canada Centre for Remote Sensing, the United States Geological Survey,
and three Mexican organizations including the National Institute of Statistics and
Geography (Instituto Nacional de Estadistica y Geografia), National Commission for
the Knowledge and Use of the Biodiversity (Comisión Nacional Para el Conocimiento y
Uso de la Biodiversidad) and the National Forestry Commission of Mexico (Comisión
Nacional Forestal).  The collaboration is facilitated by the Commission for
Environmental Cooperation, an international organization created by the Canada,
Mexico, and United States governments under the North American Agreement on
Environmental Cooperation to promote environmental collaboration between the three
countries.
The general objective of NALCMS is to devise, through collective effort, a
harmonized multi-scale land cover monitoring approach which ensures high accuracy
and consistency in monitoring land cover changes at the North American scale and
which meets each country&#x92;s specific requirements.  The data set of 2005 Land Cover
of North America at a resolution of 250 meters is the first step toward this goal.
The initial data set used to generate land cover information over North America was
produced by the Canada Centre for Remote Sensing from observations acquired by the
Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS/Terra).  All seven land
spectral bands were processed from Level 1 granules into top-of-atmosphere
reflectance covering North America at a 250-meter spatial and 10-day temporal
resolution.
In order to generate a seamless and consistent land cover map of North America,
national maps were generated for Canada by the CCRS; for Mexico by INEGI, CONABIO,
and CONAFOR; and for the United States by the USGS.  Each country used specific
training data and land cover mapping methodologies to create national data sets.
This North America data set was produced by combining the national land cover
data sets.</abstract>
         <purpose>Information on land cover across North America provided by this data set is
valuable for a range of audiences, including international organizations such as
the United Nations Environment Programme, nongovernmental conservation
organizations, land managers, and scientific researchers.  The continental scale
land cover data generated under NALCMS can be used to address issues such as
climate change, carbon sequestration, biodiversity loss, and changes in ecosystem
structure and function, by helping users to better understand the dynamics and
continental-scale patterns of North America&#x92;s changing environment.
The North American Atlas data are intended for geographic display and analysis at
the national and continental level.  These data should be displayed and analyzed at
scales appropriate for 1:10,000,000-scale data.  No responsibility is assumed by
Natural Resources Canada, Instituto Nacional de Estadística y Geografía, the U.S.
Geological Survey, or the Commission for Environmental Cooperation in the use of
these data.</purpose>
         <supplinf>The standard distribution formats for this data set are listed below.  Users
interested in receiving the data as a GRID or BIN file may contact the CEC.
For more information on NALCMS, see http://www.cec.org/Page.asp?PageID=122&amp;ContentID=25501.
Natural Resources Canada has North American Land Cover information available online at
http://www.nrcan.gc.ca/earth-sciences/geography-boundary/remote-sensing/optical/2208#_North_American_Land.
The U.S. Geological Survey has North American Land Cover information available online at
http://landcover.usgs.gov/nalcms.php.
For more information on MODIS, see http://modis.gsfc.nasa.gov/
The following table describes the display of land cover classification in the
.img file:
&gt;Value  Class                                     RGB values
&gt;----------------------------------------------------------------------------
&gt;1      Temperate or sub-polar needleleaf forest  0     0.24  0
&gt;2      Sub-polar taiga needleleaf forest         0.58  0.61  0.44
&gt;3      Tropical or sub-tropical broadleaf
&gt;         evergreen forest                        0     0.39  0
&gt;4      Tropical or sub-tropical broadleaf
&gt;         deciduous forest                        0.12  0.67  0.02
&gt;5      Temperate or sub-polar broadleaf
&gt;         deciduous forest                        0.08  0.55  0.24
&gt;6      Mixed forest                              0.36  0.46  0.17
&gt;7      Tropical or sub-tropical shrubland        0.7   0.62  0.18
&gt;8      Temperate or sub-polar shrubland          0.7   0.54  0.2
&gt;9      Tropical or sub-tropical grassland        0.91  0.86  0.37
&gt;10     Temperate or sub-polar grassland          0.88  0.81  0.54
&gt;11     Sub-polar or polar shrubland-lichen-moss  0.61  0.46  0.33
&gt;12     Sub-polar or polar grassland-lichen-moss  0.73  0.83  0.56
&gt;13     Sub-polar or polar barren-lichen-moss     0.25  0.54  0.45
&gt;14     Wetland                                   0.42  0.64  0.54
&gt;15     Cropland                                  0.9   0.68  0.4
&gt;16     Barren lands                              0.66  0.67  0.68
&gt;17     Urban                                     0.86  0.13  0.15
&gt;18     Water                                     0.3   0.44  0.64
&gt;19     Snow and Ice                              1     0.98  1
&gt;
The Commission for Environmental Cooperation (CEC) is an international organization
created by Canada, Mexico, and the United States of America under the North
American Agreement on Environmental Cooperation (NAAEC).  The CEC was established
to address regional environmental concerns, help prevent potential trade and
environmental conflicts, and to promote the effective enforcement of environmental
law.  The Agreement complements the environmental provisions of the North American
Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA).  Further information on the CEC is available from
http://www.cec.org/ or from
&gt;Commission for Environmental Cooperation
&gt;393, rue St-Jacques Ouest
&gt;Bureau 200
&gt;Montréal (Québec)
&gt;H2Y 1N9 Canada
&gt;
&gt;Telephone: 1 514 350 4300
&gt;Facsimile: 1 514 350 4314
&gt;Electronic mail: info@cec.org
&gt;
The following references provide additional information on processing methodologies
and may be referenced in the process steps, below.
Beaubien, J., Cihlar, J., Simard, G., and Latifovic, R. (1999). Land cover from
multiple thematic mapper scenes using a new enhancement-classification methodology.
Journal of Geophysical Research, 104:27909 &#x96; 27920.
Cihlar, J., Xiao, Q., Beaubien, J., Fung, K., &amp; Latifovic, R. (1998).
Classification by progressive generalization: a new automated methodology for
remote sensing multichannel data. International Journal of Remote Sensing
19:2685-2704.
Guindon et al. (2011). An improved method for the annual mapping of forest
disturbance across Canada based on MODIS 250m data and decision/regression trees.
32nd Canadian Symposium on Remote Sensing, June 13-16, Sherbrooke, Quebec.
Khlopenkov, K., &amp; Trichtchenko, A. (2008). Implementation and evaluation of
concurrent gradient search method for reprojection of MODIS level 1B imagery. IEEE
Transaction on Geoscience and Remote Sensing, 46:2016&#x96;2027.
Latifovic, R., and Olthof, I. 2004. Accuracy assessment using sub-pixel fractional
error matrices of global land cover products derived from satellite data. Remote
Sensing of Environment, 90:153-165
Latifovic, R., Zhu, Z., Cihlar, J., Giri, C., &amp; Olthof, I. (2004). Land cover
mapping of North and Central America - Global Land Cover 2000. Remote Sensing of
Environment, 89:116-127.
Luo, Y., Trishchenko, A., &amp; Khlopenkov, K. (2008). Developing clear-sky, cloud and
cloud shadow mask for producing clear-sky composites at 250-meter spatial
resolution for the seven MODIS land bands over Canada and North America. Remote
Sensing of Environment, Volume 112:4167-4185.
Pavlic, G., and Latifovic, R. (2007). Canada-wide 250-m Water Fraction Coverage
derived from National Topographic Data Base. NRCan, ESS Program: Understanding
Canada from Space, Project: Land Surface Characterization.
Pouliot, D., Latifovic, R., Zabcic, N., Guindon, L., and  Olthof, I. (2013).
Development and assessment of a 250m spatial resolution MODIS annual land cover
time series (2000-2011) for Canada derived from change based updating. In review.
Timoney, K.P., La Roi, G.H., Zoltai, S.C., and Robinson, A.G. (1992)  The high
subarctic forest-tundra of northwestern Canada: Position, width, and vegetation
gradients in relation to climate. Arctic, 45, 1-9.
Trichtchenko, A., Luo Y., &amp; Khlopenkov, K. (2006). A method for downscaling MODIS
land channels to 250m spatial resolution using adaptive regression and
normalization, Proceedings of SPIE &#x96; The International Society for Optical
Engineering v.6366 (2006) art. no. 636607. 8 pp.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>200501</begdate>
               <enddate>200512</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>170</westbc>
            <eastbc>-50</eastbc>
            <northbc>84</northbc>
            <southbc>14</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>NGDA Portfolio Themes</themekt>
            <themekey>NGDA</themekey>
            <themekey>National Geospatial Data Asset</themekey>
            <themekey>Land Use Land Cover Theme</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>GCMD Science keywords</themekt>
            <themekey>Land Surface &gt; Land Use/Land Cover &gt; Land Cover</themekey>
            <themekey>Land Surface &gt; Surface Radiative Properties &gt; Reflectance</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>imageryBaseMapsEarthCover</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>Remote sensing</themekey>
            <themekey>Land cover</themekey>
            <themekey>MODIS</themekey>
            <themekey>Reflectance</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>None</placekt>
            <placekey>Mid-latitude</placekey>
            <placekey>Western Hemisphere</placekey>
            <placekey>Northern Hemisphere</placekey>
            <placekey>North America</placekey>
            <placekey>NAFTA</placekey>
            <placekey>North America Free Trade Agreement</placekey>
            <placekey>Canada</placekey>
            <placekey>Mexico</placekey>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None.</accconst>
      <useconst>None.  Acknowledgement of Natural Resources Canada, Instituto Nacional de Estadística
y Geografía, and the U.S. Geological Survey is required in products derived from
these data.  Acknowledgement of the Commission for Environmental Cooperation would be
appreciated in products derived from these data.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
               <cntper>Customer Services Representative</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>USGS, Earth Resources Observation and  Science (EROS) Center</address>
               <address>Mundt Federal Building</address>
               <address>47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>South Dakota</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1 605 594 6151</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>custserv@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>Canada:
An accuracy assessment was performed on the Canadian data at the 12-class IGBP
level.
To assist in tree life-form identification where crown shape was difficult to
interpret, reference data were obtained through visual assessment of high-
resolution image data in Google Earth, supported by Landsat data.  Within the high-
resolution imagery, random sampling was used to generate 838 reference samples.
Each sample was interpreted and assigned a primary label, a secondary label and a
confidence level.  The primary label referred to the most likely class assigned to
a pixel according to the interpreter, while the secondary label referred to a
second class that could also be considered acceptable in cases where ambiguity
existed in the interpretation or where more than one label could be deemed correct.
Examples of the latter occurred mainly along transition zones where two classes
occurred almost equally within a 250m pixel.
The confidence level was assigned based on the ease with which the land cover was
visually interpreted and on the number of classes present in the 250m pixel.  A
high confidence was assigned to pixels where the high-resolution Google Earth image
was acquired at an appropriate time of year for the class in question (for example,
summer to fall for deciduous), and where one class clearly dominated the land cover
within the pixel.
For the primary label only, overall accuracy was nearly 59% with a Kappa of 0.54.
Overall accuracy increased to 69% and the Kappa increased to 0.65 when considering
either the primary or secondary label as being correct.  For primary labels
interpreted with high confidence, representing 365 of 838 reference samples,
overall accuracy increased again to 75% with a Kappa of 0.72.  The increase in
classification accuracy with high reference-data interpretation confidence was a
function of greater land cover homogeneity within the reference data footprint and
less ambiguity largely due to reference image quality.
The analysis of the classification error matrix revealed known sources of spectral
confusion among land cover classes.  Adjacent forest classes tended to be confused,
as well as deciduous forest, shrubland, shrub-covered wetlands, and certain
croplands.  These classes were difficult to separate with spectral data alone, due
to all classes being primary broadleaved deciduous and the known radiometric
saturation at leaf area index levels in the range of 3-5, which was achieved in all
three classes.  Other issues arose with the herbaceous class, which was either
conifer (according to reference data along the treeline) consisting of open treed
areas with herbaceous understory, or low biomass croplands.  Confusion between
herb, shrub, and deciduous was also due to relatively small disturbance patch sizes
of cuts, primarily in British Columbia, and the point-spread function of the
sensor, leading to reduced detection of objects smaller than seven pixels.
Finally, the lichen/moss class was either herbaceous or wetland according to the
reference data, due to the prevalence of both lichen and moss in  certain wetlands
and the low biomass of  both the lichen/moss and herbaceous classes.
A theoretical analysis of accuracy assessment of global land cover products over
Canada in Latifovic and Olthof (2004) examined accuracy as a function of land cover
homogeneity and thematic resolution.  Based on land cover homogeneity in Canada,
determined from a representative sample of medium resolution (~30m) land cover
products, it was determined that a theoretical accuracy of 70-75% at a 16-land-
cover-class thematic level should be achievable depending on the degree of labeling
error.  Accuracy for the 2005 Canadian land cover data is slightly lower when
considering only the primary reference label and is in the 70% range when
considering the primary or secondary label.  This lower-than-theoretically-
achievable accuracy is due to errors in the reference data labels as is evident
from the increase in accuracy when both labels are considered.  When labeling error
is reduced further by considering only reference data that were interpreted with
100% confidence, the accuracy climbs to 75%.  While this is on the upper range of
the theoretically achievable accuracy, indicating minimal to no labeling error, it
should be noted that the current assessment was done at a 12-class thematic level,
which should increase the achievable accuracy and suggests that some labeling error
is still present in the data set.
Mexico:
No formal accuracy assessment has been performed on the Mexican data,
however, land cover proportions and distributions agree well with independent land
cover and land use estimations of the &#x93;Mapa de Vegetación y Uso de Suelo&#x94;, Serie
III of 2007 by INEGI.
USA:
No formal accuracy assessment has been performed for data products in the United
States and this land cover data set should be considered provisional until a formal
accuracy assessment is conducted.   During processing, the regression tree
algorithm employed for land cover classification offers a cross-validation option
for assessing classification and prediction reliability.  Cross-validation provides
relatively reliable estimates for land cover model performance if the reference
data used for cross-validation are collected based on a statistically valid
sampling design.  The cross-validation values for each zone were used to guide
refinements to model training data and to improve classification results.  The
quantitative value reported describes an average cross-validation value across
several mapped zones and is not implied as a formal indicator of product accuracy.</attraccr>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>70</attraccv>
            <attracce>The above listed value is the overall accuracy obtained for the Canada land cover
data using the reference data set.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>69</attraccv>
            <attracce>For the United States: Informal accuracy indicator based on average values of
cross-validation reports from a regression tree algorithm.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>85</attraccv>
            <attracce>The above listed value is the overall accuracy obtained for the Mexican land
cover data using a subset of 20% of the training samples from the decision tree
model.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
      </attracc>
      <logic>No tests for logical consistency have been performed on this data set.</logic>
      <complete>Data completeness reflects the content of the original MODIS data.</complete>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing, Earth Sciences Sector, Natural Resources
Canada</origin>
                  <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                  <title>MODIS Level 1B 250m swath data, 5-min granules</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Ottawa, Ontario, Canada</pubplace>
                     <publish>NASA</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://ladsweb.nascom.nasa.gov/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2005</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>MOD02QKM</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing, Earth Sciences Sector, Natural Resources
Canada</origin>
                  <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                  <title>MODIS Level 1B 500m swath data, 5-min granules</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Ottawa, Ontario, Canada</pubplace>
                     <publish>NASA</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://ladsweb.nascom.nasa.gov/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2005</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>MOD02HKM</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing, Earth Sciences Sector, Natural Resources
Canada</origin>
                  <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                  <title>MODIS Level 1 Geolocation information, 1km swath data, 5-min granules</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Ottawa, Ontario, Canada</pubplace>
                     <publish>NASA</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://ladsweb.nascom.nasa.gov/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2005</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>MOD03</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing, Earth Sciences Sector, Natural Resources
Canada</origin>
                  <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
                  <title>MODIS Monthly composites</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Internal files</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2005</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Date of data compilation</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>NA Monthly Composites</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Various</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
                  <title>Ancillary data</title>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Various</pubplace>
                     <publish>Various</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>The following data sets were used to aid cluster labelling:
&gt;Data set                           Source
&gt;--------------------------------------------------------------------------
&gt;Water Fraction Map of Canada       http://www.geobase.ca
&gt;  assembled from the National
&gt;  Topographic Data Base (NTDB)
&gt;
&gt;Canada Digital Elevation Data,     http://www.geobase.ca
&gt;  Level 1
&gt;
&gt;National Road Network, Canada      http://www.geobase.ca
&gt;
&gt;Satellite database for the land    CCRS
&gt;  cover of Canada is a sample
&gt;  of LANDSAT TM/ETM+ scenes
&gt;  representing the distribution
&gt;  of land cover across Canada.
&gt;
&gt;Earth Observation for Sustainable  CFS
&gt;  Development (EOSD) of  Forests
&gt;  Land Cover Classification
&gt;
&gt;National Land and Water            http://www.agr.gc.ca/eng/?id=1343071073307#a9
&gt;  Information System (NLWIS)
&gt;  Land Cover for agricultural
&gt;  regions of Canada, circa 2000
&gt;
&gt;Circa-2000 Northern Land Cover     http://geogratis.cgdi.gc.ca
&gt;  of Canada
&gt;
&gt;Classification of Agricultural     Agricultural Financial Services
&gt;  Lands in Alberta, Saskatchewan     Corporation Saskatchewan Crop
&gt;  and the Peace Region of            Insurance Corporation
&gt;  British Columbia                   British Columbia Ministry of
&gt;                                     Agriculture and Lands (Business
&gt;                                     Risk management Division)
&gt;
&gt;Northern Treeline (Timoney         http://data.arcticatlas.org
&gt;  et al., 1992)
&gt;
&gt;North American Regional            http://nomads.ncdc.noaa.gov
&gt;  Reanalysis, Daily Dataset
&gt;  Degree days
&gt;
&gt;Fire data base                     CCRS
&gt;
&gt;Ground truth data                  CCRS</othercit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Various</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2009</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Date of acquisition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Canada ancillary data</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Various</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
                  <title>Ancillary data</title>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Various</pubplace>
                     <publish>Various</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>The following data sets were used to aid cluster labelling:
&gt;Data set                           Source
&gt;--------------------------------------------------------------------------
&gt;Total days of precipitation per    CONAFOR
&gt;  year (1970 &#x96; 2000)
&gt;
&gt;Total of evaporation per year in   CONAFOR
&gt;  mm (1970 &#x96; 2000)
&gt;
&gt;Maximum temperature average per    CONAFOR
&gt;  year in °C (1970 &#x96; 2000)
&gt;
&gt;Monthly average temperature per    CONAFOR
&gt;  year in °C (1970 &#x96; 2000)
&gt;
&gt;Minimum monthly average            CONAFOR
&gt;  temperature per year in °C
&gt;  (1970 &#x96; 2000)
&gt;
&gt;Digital Elevation Model of         CONAFOR
&gt;  Mexico 250m
&gt;
&gt;Classification of Agricultural     Colegio de Posgraduados
&gt;  Lands Mexico                       (COLPOS)
&gt;                                   Secretaría de Agricultura,
&gt;                                     Ganadería, Desarrollo Rural,
&gt;                                     Pesca y Alimentación de
&gt;                                     México (SAGARPA)
&gt;
&gt;Ground truth data for forested     CONAFOR
&gt;  areas in Mexico
&gt;
&gt;Urban areas in Mexico              INEGI
&gt;
&gt;Mapa de Uso de Suelo y Vegetacion  INEGI
&gt;</othercit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Various</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2009</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Date of acquisition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Mexico ancillary data</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>NASA</origin>
                  <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                  <title>Landsat data</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Washington, DC</pubplace>
                     <publish>NASA</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2005</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Landsat</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
                  <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                  <title>DEM (250m) composed of 1 band of Continuous Variable Type</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2005</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>DEM</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
                  <title>2005 Land Cover Map of North America at 250m: Canada</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Ottawa, Ontario, Canada</pubplace>
                     <publish>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Internal file</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2005</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>CCRS_NLCD</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Comisión Nacional para el Conocimiento y Uso de la Biodiversidad (CONABIO)</origin>
                  <origin>Comisión Nacional Forestal (CONAFOR)</origin>
                  <origin>Insituto Nacional de Estadística y Geografía (INEGI)</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
                  <title>Land Cover Map of Mexico for 2005 at 250m</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Mexico City, Mexico</pubplace>
                     <publish>Insituto Nacional de Estadística y Geografía</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Internal file</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2005</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>INEGI_NLCD</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
                  <title>2005 North American Land Cover Database for the United States</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Sioux Falls, South Dakota, USA</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Internal file</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2005</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>USGS_NLCD</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing (CCRS), Earth Sciences Sector, Natural
Resources Canada</origin>
                  <origin>Comisión Nacional para el Conocimiento y Uso de la Biodiversidad (CONABIO)</origin>
                  <origin>Comisión Nacional Forestal (CONAFOR)</origin>
                  <origin>Insituto Nacional de Estadística y Geografía (INEGI)</origin>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)</origin>
                  <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
                  <title>2005 Land Cover of North America at 250 meters</title>
                  <edition>1.0</edition>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Montréal, Québec, Canada</pubplace>
                     <publish>Commission for Environmental Cooperation</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://www.cec.org/naatlas/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2005</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>LandCover2005_v1</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Google</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
                  <title>Google Earth</title>
                  <onlink>&lt;http://earth.google.com/&gt;</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Google Earth</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
                  <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                  <title>2001 North American Land Cover Database for the United States</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Sioux Falls, South Dakota, USA</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>&lt;http://www.mrlc.gov/nlcd01_data.php&gt;</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2001</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>USGS_NLCD_2001</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Earth Resources Observation and Science
(EROS)</origin>
                  <origin>U.S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, Remote Sensing Applications
Center (RSAC)</origin>
                  <pubdate>20121003</pubdate>
                  <title>Multi-Temporal Burn Severity Fire Perimeters</title>
                  <onlink>&lt;http://www.mtbs.gov/dataquery/individualfiredata.html&gt;</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>20121003</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>MTBS</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>A series of monthly MODIS composites were produced prior to the compilation of
land cover data for each country.
Input data used in land cover mapping were generated from the following original
Level 1B MODIS data (collection 5): a) MOD02QKM - Level 1B 250m swath data, 5-min
Granules; b) MOD02HKM - Level 1B 500m swath data, 5-min granules; c) MOD03 &#x96;
Level 1 Geolocation information, 1km swath data, 5-min granules.  All input data
are available from the NASA Level 1 and Atmosphere Archive and Distribution
System (LAADS), http://ladsweb.nascom.nasa.gov/
The MODIS 500m land channels (B3-B7) were downscaled to 250m spatial resolution
as described by Trishchenko et al. (2006) and then re-projected into Lambert
Azimuthal Equal Area projection using software developed at the CCRS (Khlopenkov
et al., 2008). Two original 250m MODIS channels and five downscaled 250m MODIS
land channels were assembled into North-America-wide 1  10-day composites following
the methods developed in Luo et al., (2008).
MODIS 10-day composites were further processed to reduce data noise due to
different viewing conditions and remaining cloud and atmosphere contamination.  A
temporal rank filter was applied, calculated as the maximum of minimum values for
two overlapping moving windows.  For this implementation, a window size of three
ten-day composites was used with one pixel overlap between windows.  After rank
filtering, a procedure to detect residual spikes in the data was applied based on
a neighbourhood comparison.  Within a moving window of 3 composites, if the
neighbouring pixels were both above or below the centre pixel by 25%, the centre
pixel was linearly interpolated from its neighbours.  The filtered 10-day
composites were averaged to generate monthly composites.  The processed data set
contained 12 monthly composites of channels 1 (B1, VIS) and 2 (B2, near-infrared
NIR) at 250m spatial resolution and five channels designed for land applications
(bands B3 to B7) resampled to 250m spatial resolution.</procdesc>
            <srcused>MOD02QKM</srcused>
            <srcused>MOD02HKM</srcused>
            <srcused>MOD03</srcused>
            <procdate>2009</procdate>
            <srcprod>NA Monthly composites</srcprod>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Canadian land cover was generated following the procedure described in Latifovic
et al. (2004) which combines the Enhanced Classification Method (ECM, Beaubien et
al.,  1999) and Classification by Progressive Generalization (CPG, Cihlar et al.,
1998 and  Latifovic et al., 1999).  The principal characteristic of this
classification approach is the preservation of image information and
incorporation of human contextual reasoning for land cover labeling.  It includes
the following generalization steps: 1) initial clustering, 2) cluster
agglomeration based on spectral similarity and cluster size , 3) cluster
agglomeration based on thematic similarity, and 4) cluster labeling.  Initial
clusters were generated using the K-mean classifier with bands 1, 2, and 6 from a
2005 summer composite created by averaging composites for July and August.
Several ancillary GIS layers and other land cover products over regions of Canada
were consulted to refine and improve land cover labeling.</procdesc>
            <srcused>NA Monthly Composites</srcused>
            <srcused>Canada ancillary data</srcused>
            <procdate>2009</procdate>
            <srcprod>CCRS_NLCD</srcprod>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>For Mexico, the monthly composites of MODIS-Terra top-of-the-atmosphere (TOA)
surface radiance data for the first seven spectral bands and the Normalized
Difference Vegetation Index (NDVI) were employed for the land cover
classification process.  For each spectral band and the NDVI, the mean, standard
deviation, minimum, maximum, and range between minimum and maximum were computed
over the year, half-year, four-month, and quarter-year periods.  This resulted in
400 metrics derived from MODIS data.  In addition, ancillary data were employed
including a digital elevation model and derivatives such as slope and aspect,
mean, maximum and minimum temperature; total of precipitation and days with
precipitation; and the number of green days.
Sample data were derived from various sources, including data of the Mexican
Forest Inventory, detailed cropland data, urban cover, and additional digitized
points from reference sources;  20% of the samples were exclusively used for
validation.
The land cover type identification was achieved using a Decision Tree Classifier
(DTC).  C5.0 classification trees were generated for the training data.  Because
exclusively continuous variables were employed, the tree only contains binary
splits.  Boosting with ten iterations was employed.  The trees were applied to
the data and the confidences were computed which were used as weights for
combining the individual classifications.  Several classifications were generated
based on combinations of 1) input data - monthly TOA reflectances, generated
metrics and ancillary data; and 2) complete or subset data sets of training data.
Visual and statistical assessments were carried out to obtain the final
classification.  A distance layer was generated based on an ecoregions map to
combine results of the different classifications; only selected classifications
were selected for regions where they performed better visually and statically.
Finally, a water mask was superimposed; the mask was derived from the &#x93;Mapa de
Uso de Suelo y Vegetacion&#x94; from INEGI.</procdesc>
            <srcused>NA Monthly Composites</srcused>
            <srcused>Mexico ancillary data</srcused>
            <procdate>2009</procdate>
            <srcprod>INEGI_NLCD</srcprod>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>United States classification was achieved by use of a classification and
decision tree method (DT) using a combination of Landsat imagery and ancillary
data (DEM).  The specific DT program employed is called C5, which implements a
gain ratio criterion in tree development and pruning (Quinlan, 1993).  C5 also
implemented several advanced features that can aid and improve land cover
classification, including boosting and cross-validation.  Boosting is a technique
for improving classification accuracy, while cross-validation can provide a
certain level of estimation regarding the land cover classification quality.  In
addition, C5 can generate a confidence estimate for each classified pixel and
record the associated classification logic in a text file that can be readily
interpreted and incorporated into a metadata system.  To conduct the land cover
classification using DT, a large quantity of training data was required.  For
North America mapping , training data were collected from several combined
sources including NLCD 2001 land cover, GAP land cover, NOAA Coastal Change and
Analysis land cover, LANDFIRE  land cover and other data sources.
Following the development of the best classification through decision tree
modeling, additional steps (described in an unpublished technical document; see
the USGS point of contact if additional information is needed) were required to
complete the final land cover product.  Finally, visual inspection of the
classification was made with areas/pixels that were wrongly classified delineated
first as an "area of interest" (AOI); subsequently, limited manual editing was
done to eliminate the classification error within the AOI.</procdesc>
            <srcused>NA Monthly composites</srcused>
            <srcused>Landsat</srcused>
            <srcused>DEM</srcused>
            <procdate>2009</procdate>
            <srcprod>USGS_NLCD</srcprod>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>To produce the seamless land cover map of North America, the three national
land cover products (Canada, Mexico, USA) were edge matched along the borders
using an object-oriented segmentation technique.  Land cover regions that crossed
borders were reclassified using the majority class segment.</procdesc>
            <srcused>CCRS_NLCD</srcused>
            <srcused>USGS_NLCD</srcused>
            <srcused>INEGI_NLCD</srcused>
            <procdate>2009</procdate>
            <srcprod>LandCover2005_v1</srcprod>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>In Version 1 of the 2005 Land Cover data there were three classes that were
incorrectly classified in Mexico: urban, water, and cropland.
Urban area misclassifications included both areas where the extent was
overestimated (e.g. the state of Puebla) and areas where the extent was
underestimated (mainly in northern Mexico.)  Areas that were mis-estimated were
assigned to the most appropriate land cover class by visual interpretation;
Google Earth was used for verification and visual analysis.
Most water misclassifications were underestimations.  It was important to correct
this problem to allow for accurate change detection between this and later data
sets.   The waterbodies were identified on MODIS imagery and both size and shape
of the areas was corrected.  In addition, waterbodies that were not previously
mapped were digitized where appropriate.  A few waterbodies were reduced in size
or eliminated but this was rare.  For waterbodies that experience fluctuating
water levels due to seasonal rains or to water storage and release in artificial
lakes, the highest water mark, as indicated by the post-rainy season image
(October),  was used to map the waterbody size and shape.
There were two problems with the classification of cropland.  First, the
definition of the cropland class is very broad and includes extensive rangeland
and extensive agriculture.   Second, in the Gulf Coast region cropland is
spatially overestimated, but because the actual spatial patterns cannot be mapped
from MODIS images, correction is difficult.  As a result, cropland
classifications were not modified in the version 2.</procdesc>
            <srcused>LandCover2005_v1</srcused>
            <srcused>NA Monthly Composites</srcused>
            <srcused>Google Earth</srcused>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>In Version 1 of the 2005 Land Cover data, Alaska was not correctly aligned with
the MODIS source data.  A new version of the land cover for Alaska was produced
to fix the alignment problem.  The land cover was remodeled using properly
aligned imagery and new training data for the model.  Some small areas in the
extreme north and south of Alaska were missing data and these areas were added
from cross-walked 2001 NLCD data and the MODIS 2010 data (it was assumed that
there were land cover changes in these areas between 2005 and 2010.)
The land cover information for the conterminous United States was adjusted for
more accurate classification.  In particular, an effort was made to improve the
mapping of areas affected by fire, using the MTBS data.  Burned areas were
reclassified as necessary, based on the length of time since the fire occurred.
Shrub areas in the southwestern U.S. which had the wrong Level II class (Class 8
instead of Class 7) were adjusted.</procdesc>
            <srcused>LandCover2005_v1</srcused>
            <srcused>NA Monthly composites</srcused>
            <srcused>DEM</srcused>
            <srcused>USGS_NLCD_2001</srcused>
            <srcused>MTBS</srcused>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Since the development of the Version 1 data for Canada, further quality
assessment and input from users suggested modifications in some areas.  The
original source data were re-analyzed; major changes included reduction of treed
wetland along the western and eastern coasts, correction of water/shadow
confusion in regions of complex terrain, correction of snow/water confusion in
the far north, improved disturbance representation based on change detection
(Guindon et al., 2011), improved forest mapping in the prairies region, some
minor changes to urban areas, and some local improvements to wetland mapping.</procdesc>
            <srcused>NA Monthly Composites</srcused>
            <srcused>Canada ancillary data</srcused>
            <srcused>LandCover2005_v1</srcused>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The updated data sets from Canada, Mexico, and the U.S. were combined into one
data set covering all of North America.</procdesc>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Pixel</rasttype>
         <rowcount>35000</rowcount>
         <colcount>37000</colcount>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <mapproj>
               <mapprojn>Lambert Azimuthal Equal Area</mapprojn>
               <lamberta>
                  <longpc>-100.00</longpc>
                  <latprjc>45.00</latprjc>
                  <feast>0.0</feast>
                  <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
               </lamberta>
            </mapproj>
            <planci>
               <plance>row and column</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>250.0</absres>
                  <ordres>250.0</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>Meters</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>None</horizdn>
            <ellips>Sphere</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6370977</semiaxis>
            <denflat>1.0</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>Land cover classification grid cell</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Any of the data elements in the 2005 North American land cover file</enttypd>
            <enttypds>North American Atlas GIS Group</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Land cover classification grid cell value</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The value is an indication of the land cover class</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>North American Atlas GIS Group</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Temperate or sub-polar needleleaf forest.  Forests generally taller than
three meters and more than 20 percent of total vegetation cover.  This type
occurs across the northern United States, Canada and mountainous zones of
Mexico.  The tree crown cover contains at least 75 percent of needleleaved
species.  Land Cover Classification System (LCCS) code: 20134.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Sub-polar taiga needleleaf forest.  Forest and woodlands with trees generally
taller than three meters and more than 5 percent of total vegetation cover
with shrubs and lichens commonly present in the understory.  The tree crown
cover contains at least 75 percent of needleleaved species.  This type occurs
across Alaska and northern Canada and may consist of treed muskeg or
wetlands.  Forest canopies are variable and often sparse, with generally
greater tree cover in the southern latitude parts of the zone than the north.
LCCS code: 20229.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Tropical or sub-tropical broadleaf evergreen forest.  Forests generally
taller than five meters and more than 20 percent of total vegetation cover.
These occur in the southern United States and Mexico.  These forests have
greater than 75 percent of tree crown cover represented by evergreen species.
LCCS code: 20090.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>4</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Tropical or sub-tropical broadleaf deciduous forest.  Forests generally
taller than five meters and more than 20 percent of total vegetation cover.
These occur in the southern United States and Mexico.  These forests have
greater than 75 percent of tree crown cover represented by deciduous species.
LCCS code: 20132.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>5</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Temperate or sub-polar broadleaf deciduous forest.  Forests generally taller
than three meters and more than 20 percent of total vegetation cover.  These
occur in the northern United States, Canada and mountainous zones of Mexico.
These forests have greater than 75 percent of tree crown cover represented by
deciduous species.  LCCS code: 20227.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>6</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Mixed forest.  Forests generally taller than three meters and more than 20
percent of total vegetation cover.  Neither needleleaf nor broadleaf tree
species occupy more than 75 percent of total tree cover, but are co-dominant.
LCCS codes: 20092, 20090, 20134, 20132, 20229, 20227.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>7</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Tropical or sub-tropical shrubland.  Areas dominated by woody perennial
plants with persistent woody stems less than five meters tall and typically
greater than 20 percent of total vegetation.  This class occurs across the
southern United States and Mexico.  LCCS code: 21450-13476.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>8</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Temperate or sub-polar shrubland.  Areas dominated by woody perennial plants
with persistent woody stems less than three meters tall and typically greater
than 20 percent of total vegetation.  This class occurs across the northern
United States, Canada and highlands of Mexico.  LCCS code: 21450-12050.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>9</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Tropical or sub-tropical grassland.  Areas dominated by graminoid or
herbaceous vegetation generally accounting for greater than 80 percent of
total vegetation cover.  These areas are not subject to intensive management
such as tilling, but can be utilized for grazing.  This class occurs across
the southern United States and Mexico.  LCCS code: 21669.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>10</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Temperate or sub-polar grassland.  Areas dominated by graminoid or herbaceous
vegetation, generally accounting for greater than 80 percent of total
vegetation cover.  These areas are not subject to intensive management such
as tilling, but can be utilized for grazing.  This class occurs across
Canada, United States and highlands of Mexico.  LCCS code: 21537-12212.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>11</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Sub-polar or polar shrubland-lichen-moss.  Areas dominated by dwarf shrubs
with lichen and moss typically accounting for at least 20 percent of total
vegetation cover.  This class occurs across northern Canada and Alaska.  LCCS
codes: 20022-12050, 21454-12212, 21439-3012.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>12</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Sub-polar or polar grassland-lichen-moss.  Areas dominated by grassland with
lichen and moss typically accounting for at least 20 percent of total
vegetation cover.  This class occurs across northern Canada and Alaska.  LCCS
codes: 21454-12212, 20022-12050, 21439-3012.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>13</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Sub-polar or polar barren-lichen-moss.  Areas dominated by a mixture of bare
areas with lichen and moss that typically account for at least 20 percent of
total vegetation cover.  This class occurs across northern Canada and Alaska.
LCCS codes: 21468, 21454-12212, 20022-12050.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>14</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Wetland.  Areas dominated by perennial herbaceous and woody wetland
vegetation which is influenced by the water table at or near surface over
extensive periods of time.  This includes marshes, swamps, bogs, mangroves,
etc., either coastal or inland where water is present for a substantial
period annually.  LCCS codes: 42349, 41809.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>15</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Cropland.  Areas dominated by intensively managed crops.  These areas
typically require human activities for their maintenance.  This includes
areas used for the production of annual crops, such as corn, soybeans, wheat,
maize, vegetables, tobacco, cotton, etc.; perennial grasses for grazing; and
woody crops such as orchards and vineyards.  Crop vegetation accounts for
greater than 20 percent of total vegetation.  This class does not represent
natural grasslands used for light to moderate grazing.
LCCS codes: 10037, 10025, 21441, 21453.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>16</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Barren lands.  Areas characterized by bare rock, gravel, sand, silt, clay, or
other earthen material, with little or no "green" vegetation present
regardless of its inherent ability to support life. Generally,  vegetation
accounts for less than 10 percent of total cover.  LCCS codes: 6001, 6004.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>17</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Urban and built-up.  Areas that contain at least 30 percent or greater urban
constructed materials for human activities (cities, towns, transportation
etc.)  LCCS code: 5003.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>18</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Water.  Areas of open water, generally with less than 25 percent cover of
non-water cover types.  This class refers to areas that are consistently
covered by water.  LCCS codes: 8001, 7001.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>19</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Snow and ice.  Areas characterized by a perennial cover of ice and/or snow,
generally greater than 25 percent of total cover.  LCCS codes: 8005, 8008.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Commission for Environmental Cooperation</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>393, rue St-Jacques Ouest, Bureau 200</address>
               <city>Montréal</city>
               <state>Québec</state>
               <postal>H2Y 1N9</postal>
               <country>Canada</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1 514 350 4300</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>1 514 350 4314</cntfax>
            <cntemail>info@cec.org</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on computer systems at the CCRS,
INEGI, USGS, and the Commission for Environmental Cooperation, no warranty expressed
or implied is made by these agencies regarding the utility of the data on any other
system, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  Use of
trademarks or formats does not constitute endorsement by these agencies.  No
responsibility is assumed by the CCRS, INEGI, USGS, or the CEC in the use of these
data.</distliab>
   </distinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Scientist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>CCRS/NRCan</address>
               <address>588 Booth Street</address>
               <city>Ottawa</city>
               <state>ON</state>
               <postal>K1A 0Y7</postal>
               <country>Canada</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1 613 947 1816</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>1 613 947 1383</cntfax>
            <cntemail>Rasim.Latifovic@nrcan.gc.ca</cntemail>
            <hours>0900 - 1700 ET, M - F (-5h EST/-4h EDT GMT)</hours>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on computer systems at the CCRS,
INEGI, USGS, and the Commission for Environmental Cooperation, no warranty expressed
or implied is made by these agencies regarding the utility of the data on any other
system, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  Use of
trademarks or formats does not constitute endorsement by these agencies.  No
responsibility is assumed by the CCRS, INEGI, USGS, or the CEC in the use of these
data.</distliab>
   </distinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Instituto Nacional de Estadística y Geografía (INEGI)</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Director of Natural Resources and Environment Information</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Av. Héroe de Nacozari Sur 2301. Fraccionamiento Jardines del Parque.</address>
               <city>Aguascalientes</city>
               <state>Aguascalientes</state>
               <postal>20270</postal>
               <country>Mexico</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>52 44 99 10 53 65</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>jose.ornelas@inegi.org.mx</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 (-6h GMT)</hours>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on computer systems at the CCRS,
INEGI, USGS, and the Commission for Environmental Cooperation, no warranty expressed
or implied is made by these agencies regarding the utility of the data on any other
system, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  Use of
trademarks or formats does not constitute endorsement by these agencies.  No
responsibility is assumed by the CCRS, INEGI, USGS, or the CEC in the use of these
data.</distliab>
   </distinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
               <cntper>Customer Services Representative</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>USGS, Earth Resources Observation and  Science (EROS) Center</address>
               <address>Mundt Federal Building</address>
               <address>47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>South Dakota</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1 605 594 6151</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>custserv@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M - F (-6h CST/-5h CDT GMT)</hours>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on computer systems at the CCRS,
INEGI, USGS, and the Commission for Environmental Cooperation, no warranty expressed
or implied is made by these agencies regarding the utility of the data on any other
system, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  Use of
trademarks or formats does not constitute endorsement by these agencies.  No
responsibility is assumed by the CCRS, INEGI, USGS, or the CEC in the use of these
data.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>IMG</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.cec.org/naatlas/</networkr>
                        <networkr>http://www.inegi.org.mx</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>TIFF</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.cec.org/naatlas/</networkr>
                        <networkr>http://www.inegi.org.mx</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>MXD</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.cec.org/naatlas</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>GeoPDF</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.cec.org/naatlas</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>Gratuit-Free</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20131025</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Commission for Environmental Cooperation</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>393, rue St-Jacques Ouest, Bureau 200</address>
               <city>Montréal</city>
               <state>Québec</state>
               <postal>H2Y 1N9</postal>
               <country>Canada</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1 514 350 4300</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>1 514 350 4314</cntfax>
            <cntemail>info@cec.org</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
