<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing (CCRS), Earth Sciences Sector, Natural Resources
Canada</origin>
            <origin>Comisión Nacional para el Conocimiento y Uso de la Biodiversidad (CONABIO)</origin>
            <origin>Comisión Nacional Forestal (CONAFOR)</origin>
            <origin>Insituto Nacional de Estadística y Geografía (INEGI)</origin>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)</origin>
            <pubdate>2013</pubdate>
            <title>2010 Land Cover of North America at 250 meters - National Geospatial Data Asset (NGDA) Land Use Land Cover</title>
            <edition>1.0</edition>
            <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Montréal, Québec, Canada</pubplace>
               <publish>Commission for Environmental Cooperation</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.cec.org/naatlas/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The 2010 North American Land Cover data set was produced as part of the North
American Land Change Monitoring System (NALCMS), a trilateral effort between the
Canada Centre for Remote Sensing, the United States Geological Survey, and three
Mexican organizations including the National Institute of Statistics and Geography
(Instituto Nacional de Estadistica y Geografia), National Commission for the
Knowledge and Use of the Biodiversity (Comisión Nacional Para el Conocimiento y
Uso de la Biodiversidad), and the National Forestry Commission of Mexico (Comisión
Nacional Forestal).  The collaboration is facilitated by the Commission for
Environmental Cooperation, an international organization created by the Canada,
Mexico, and United States governments under the North American Agreement on
Environmental Cooperation to promote environmental collaboration between the three
countries.
The general objective of NALCMS is to devise, through collective effort, a
harmonized multi-scale land cover monitoring approach which ensures high accuracy
and consistency in monitoring land cover changes at the North American scale and
which meets each country&#x92;s specific requirements.
The initial data set of North American Land Cover at 250 meters reflected land
cover information for 2005.  This 2010 data set was produced by updating the 2005
data to show land cover changes as determined from more recent data.  No changes
were mapped in Hawaii because newer data were not available.  Land cover
classification changed between 2005 and 2010 for approximately 1 percent of the
continental area.  For the continental data sets (including surrounding water
fringe) 4150241 pixels (1.03% of the area) changed in the update.   The following
national counts exclude the water fringe: Canada, 3264779 pixels changed (2.05%);
Mexico, 47070 pixels changed (0.15%), and U.S., 836706 pixels changed (0.55%).
The initial data set used to generate land cover information over North America was
produced by the Canada Centre for Remote Sensing from observations acquired by the
Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS/Terra).  All seven land
spectral bands were processed from Level 1 granules into top-of-atmosphere
reflectance covering North America at a 250-meter spatial and 10-day temporal
resolution.
In order to generate a seamless and consistent land cover map of North America,
national maps were generated for Canada by the CCRS; for Mexico by INEGI, CONABIO,
and CONAFOR; and for the United States by the USGS.  Each country used specific
training data and land cover mapping methodologies to create national data sets.
This North America data set was produced by combining the national land cover
data sets.
The countries worked together to produce a definitive list of land cover
classifications for the 2005 data; the same classifications were used for the 2010
data.  This document is available for download from the same site as the data and
is entitled: North American Land Cover Classifications (2005).</abstract>
         <purpose>Information on land cover across North America provided by this data set is
valuable for a range of audiences, including international organizations such as
the United Nations Environment Programme, nongovernmental conservation
organizations, land managers, and scientific researchers.  The continental scale
land cover data generated under NALCMS can be used to address issues such as
climate change, carbon sequestration, biodiversity loss, and changes in ecosystem
structure and function, by helping users to better understand the dynamics and
continental-scale patterns of North America&#x92;s changing environment.
The North American Atlas data are intended for geographic display and analysis at
the national and continental level.  These data should be displayed and analyzed at
scales appropriate for 1:10,000,000-scale data.  No responsibility is assumed by
Natural Resources Canada, Instituto Nacional de Estadística y Geografía, the U.S.
Geological Survey, or the Commission for Environmental Cooperation in the use of
these data.</purpose>
         <supplinf>The standard distribution formats for this data set are listed below.  Users
interested in receiving the data as a GRID or BIN file may contact the CEC.
Land cover monitoring, the goal of the NALCMS project, requires multiple land cover
maps, ideally at annual intervals.  It has been shown that post-classification
change detection, i.e. the comparison of two land cover maps, does not yield
satisfying results because it highly overestimates changes.  Therefore, the NALCMS
builds upon a two-step approach that 1) estimates the change between two sample
years, also called maximum potential change, and 2) updates the classification of
only those pixels that were identified as potential change.  This process ensures
that changes in classification will only focus on areas where a previous algorithm
detected the potential for change and the remainder of the map remains without
modifications.  For more information on NALCMS, see
http://www.cec.org/Page.asp?PageID=122&amp;ContentID=25501.
Natural Resources Canada has North American Land Cover information available online
at
http://www.nrcan.gc.ca/earth-sciences/geography-boundary/remote-sensing/optical/2208#_North_American_Land.
The U.S. Geological Survey has North American Land Cover information available online at
http://landcover.usgs.gov/nalcms.php.
For more information on MODIS, see http://modis.gsfc.nasa.gov/
The following table describes the display of land cover classification in the
.img file:
&gt;Value  Class                                     RGB values
&gt;----------------------------------------------------------------------------
&gt;1      Temperate or sub-polar needleleaf forest  0     0.24  0
&gt;2      Sub-polar taiga needleleaf forest         0.58  0.61  0.44
&gt;3      Tropical or sub-tropical broadleaf
&gt;         evergreen forest                        0     0.39  0
&gt;4      Tropical or sub-tropical broadleaf
&gt;         deciduous forest                        0.12  0.67  0.02
&gt;5      Temperate or sub-polar broadleaf
&gt;         deciduous forest                        0.08  0.55  0.24
&gt;6      Mixed forest                              0.36  0.46  0.17
&gt;7      Tropical or sub-tropical shrubland        0.7   0.62  0.18
&gt;8      Temperate or sub-polar shrubland          0.7   0.54  0.2
&gt;9      Tropical or sub-tropical grassland        0.91  0.86  0.37
&gt;10     Temperate or sub-polar grassland          0.88  0.81  0.54
&gt;11     Sub-polar or polar shrubland-lichen-moss  0.61  0.46  0.33
&gt;12     Sub-polar or polar grassland-lichen-moss  0.73  0.83  0.56
&gt;13     Sub-polar or polar barren-lichen-moss     0.25  0.54  0.45
&gt;14     Wetland                                   0.42  0.64  0.54
&gt;15     Cropland                                  0.9   0.68  0.4
&gt;16     Barren lands                              0.66  0.67  0.68
&gt;17     Urban                                     0.86  0.13  0.15
&gt;18     Water                                     0.3   0.44  0.64
&gt;19     Snow and Ice                              1     0.98  1
&gt;
The Commission for Environmental Cooperation (CEC) is an international organization
created by Canada, Mexico, and the United States of America under the North
American Agreement on Environmental Cooperation (NAAEC).  The CEC was established
to address regional environmental concerns, help prevent potential trade and
environmental conflicts, and to promote the effective enforcement of environmental
law.  The Agreement complements the environmental provisions of the North American
Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA).  Further information on the CEC is available from
http://www.cec.org/ or from
&gt;Commission for Environmental Cooperation
&gt;393, rue St-Jacques Ouest
&gt;Bureau 200
&gt;Montréal (Québec)
&gt;H2Y 1N9 Canada
&gt;
&gt;Telephone: 1 514 350 4300
&gt;Facsimile: 1 514 350 4314
&gt;Electronic mail: info@cec.org
&gt;
The following references provide additional information on processing methodologies
and may be referenced in the process steps, below.
Guindon et al. (2011). An improved method for the annual mapping of forest
disturbance across Canada based on MODIS 250m data and decision/regression trees.
32nd Canadian Symposium on Remote Sensing, June 13-16, Sherbrooke, Quebec.
Timoney, K.P., La Roi, G.H., Zoltai, S.C., and Robinson, A.G. (1992). The high
subarctic forest-tundra of northwestern Canada: Position, width, and vegetation
gradients in relation to climate. Arctic, 45, 1-9.
Pavlic, G., and Latifovic, R. (2007). Canada-wide 250-m Water Fraction Coverage
derived from National Topographic Data Base. NRCan, ESS Program: Understanding
Canada from Space, Project: Land Surface Characterization.
Pouliot, D., Latifovic, R., Zabcic, N., Guindon, L., and  Olthof, I. (2013).
Development and assessment of a 250m spatial resolution MODIS annual land cover
time series (2000-2011) for Canada derived from change based updating. In review.
Olthof, I., Pouliot, D., Fernandes, R., and Latifovic, R, (April 2005).  Landsat-7
ETM+ radiometric normalization comparison for northern mapping applications.
Remote Sensing of Environment, Volume 95, no. 3:388&#x96;398.
Beaubien, J., Cihlar, J., Simard, G., and Latifovic, R. (1999). Land cover from
multiple thematic mapper scenes using a new enhancement-classification methodology.
Journal of Geophysical Research, 104:27909 &#x96; 27920.
Cihlar, J., Xiao, Q., Beaubien, J., Fung, K., &amp; Latifovic, R. (1998) Classification
by progressive generalization: a new automated methodology for remote sensing
multichannel data. International Journal of Remote Sensing 19:2685-2704.
Khlopenkov, K., &amp; Trichtchenko, A. (2008). Implementation and evaluation of
concurrent gradient search method for reprojection of MODIS level 1B imagery. IEEE
Transaction on Geoscience and Remote Sensing, 46:2016&#x96;2027.
Latifovic, R., and Olthof, I. 2004. Accuracy assessment using sub-pixel fractional
error matrices of global land cover products derived from satellite data. Remote
Sensing of Environment, 90:153-165
Latifovic, R., Zhu, Z., Cihlar, J., Giri, C., &amp; Olthof, I. (2004). Land cover
mapping of North and Central America - Global Land Cover 2000. Remote Sensing of
Environment, 89:116-127.
Luo, Y., Trishchenko, A., &amp; Khlopenkov, K. (2008). Developing clear-sky, cloud and
cloud shadow mask for producing clear-sky composites at 250-meter spatial
resolution for the seven MODIS land bands over Canada and North America. Remote
Sensing of Environment, Volume 112:4167-4185.
Trichtchenko, A., Luo Y., &amp; Khlopenkov, K. (2006). A method for downscaling MODIS
land channels to 250m spatial resolution using adaptive regression and
normalization, Proceedings of SPIE &#x96; The International Society for Optical
Engineering v.6366 (2006) art. no. 636607. 8 pp.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>201001</begdate>
               <enddate>201012</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>170</westbc>
            <eastbc>-50</eastbc>
            <northbc>84</northbc>
            <southbc>14</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>NGDA Portfolio Themes</themekt>
            <themekey>NGDA</themekey>
            <themekey>National Geospatial Data Asset</themekey>
            <themekey>Land Use Land Cover Theme</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>GCMD Science keywords</themekt>
            <themekey>Land Surface &gt; Land Use/Land Cover &gt; Land Cover</themekey>
            <themekey>Land Surface &gt; Surface Radiative Properties &gt; Reflectance</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>imageryBaseMapsEarthCover</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>Remote sensing</themekey>
            <themekey>Land cover</themekey>
            <themekey>MODIS</themekey>
            <themekey>Reflectance</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>None</placekt>
            <placekey>Mid-latitude</placekey>
            <placekey>Western Hemisphere</placekey>
            <placekey>Northern Hemisphere</placekey>
            <placekey>North America</placekey>
            <placekey>NAFTA</placekey>
            <placekey>North America Free Trade Agreement</placekey>
            <placekey>Canada</placekey>
            <placekey>Mexico</placekey>
            <placekey>United States</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None.</accconst>
      <useconst>None.  Acknowledgement of Natural Resources Canada, Instituto Nacional de Estadística
y Geografía, and the U.S. Geological Survey is required in products derived from
these data.  Acknowledgement of the Commission for Environmental Cooperation would be
appreciated in products derived from these data.</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
               <cntper>Customer Services Representative</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>USGS, Earth Resources Observation and  Science (EROS) Center</address>
               <address>Mundt Federal Building</address>
               <address>47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>South Dakota</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1 605 594 6151</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>custserv@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>The Quantitative Attribute Accuracy reports listed below reflect the accuracy of
the 2005 data used as a source.  The 2010 data show a change in classification for
approximately 1 percent of the land surface, so attribute accuracy is assumed to be
essentially the same as for the 2005 data set.</attraccr>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>70</attraccv>
            <attracce>The above listed value is the overall accuracy obtained for the Canada land cover
data using the reference data set.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>69</attraccv>
            <attracce>The above listed value is the overall accuracy obtained for the United States
land cover data using a cross-validation estimate from the decision tree model.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
         <qattracc>
            <attraccv>85</attraccv>
            <attracce>The above listed value is the overall accuracy obtained for the Mexican land
cover data using a subset of 20 percent of the training samples from the decision
tree model.</attracce>
         </qattracc>
      </attracc>
      <logic>No tests for logical consistency have been performed on this data set.</logic>
      <complete>Data completeness reflects the content of the original MODIS data.</complete>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing (CCRS), Earth Sciences Sector, Natural
Resources Canada</origin>
                  <origin>Comisión Nacional para el Conocimiento y Uso de la Biodiversidad (CONABIO)</origin>
                  <origin>Comisión Nacional Forestal (CONAFOR)</origin>
                  <origin>Insituto Nacional de Estadística y Geografía (INEGI)</origin>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)</origin>
                  <pubdate>2013</pubdate>
                  <title>2005 Land Cover of North America at 250 meters</title>
                  <edition>2.0</edition>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Montréal, Québec, Canada</pubplace>
                     <publish>Commission for Environmental Cooperation</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://www.cec.org/naatlas/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2005</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>LandCover2005_v2</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing, Earth Sciences Sector, Natural Resources
Canada</origin>
                  <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                  <title>MODIS Level 1B 250m swath data, 5-min granules</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Ottawa, Ontario, Canada</pubplace>
                     <publish>NASA</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://ladsweb.nascom.nasa.gov/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2008</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>MOD02QKM</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing, Earth Sciences Sector, Natural Resources
Canada</origin>
                  <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                  <title>MODIS Level 1B 500m swath data, 5-min granules</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Ottawa, Ontario, Canada</pubplace>
                     <publish>NASA</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://ladsweb.nascom.nasa.gov/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2008</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>MOD02HKM</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing, Earth Sciences Sector, Natural Resources
Canada</origin>
                  <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                  <title>MODIS Level 1 Geolocation information, 1km swath data, 5-min granules</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Ottawa, Ontario, Canada</pubplace>
                     <publish>NASA</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://ladsweb.nascom.nasa.gov/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2008</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>MOD03</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing, Earth Sciences Sector, Natural Resources
Canada</origin>
                  <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
                  <title>MODIS Monthly composites 2005</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Internal files</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2009</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Processing date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>NA Monthly Composites 2005</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing, Earth Sciences Sector, Natural Resources
Canada</origin>
                  <pubdate>2012</pubdate>
                  <title>MODIS Level 1B 250m swath data, 5-min granules</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Ottawa, Ontario, Canada</pubplace>
                     <publish>NASA</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://ladsweb.nascom.nasa.gov/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2008</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>MOD02QKM 2012</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing, Earth Sciences Sector, Natural Resources
Canada</origin>
                  <pubdate>2012</pubdate>
                  <title>MODIS Level 1B 500m swath data, 5-min granules</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Ottawa, Ontario, Canada</pubplace>
                     <publish>NASA</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://ladsweb.nascom.nasa.gov/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2008</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>MOD02HKM 2012</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing, Earth Sciences Sector, Natural Resources
Canada</origin>
                  <pubdate>2012</pubdate>
                  <title>MODIS Level 1 Geolocation information, 1km swath data, 5-min granules</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Ottawa, Ontario, Canada</pubplace>
                     <publish>NASA</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://ladsweb.nascom.nasa.gov/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2008</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>MOD03 2012</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing, Earth Sciences Sector, Natural Resources
Canada</origin>
                  <pubdate>2013</pubdate>
                  <title>MODIS Monthly composites 2010</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Internal files</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2013</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Processing date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>NA Monthly Composites 2010</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Various</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
                  <title>Ancillary data</title>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Various</pubplace>
                     <publish>Various</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>The following data sets were used to aid cluster labelling:
&gt;Data set                           Source
&gt;-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------
&gt;Water Fraction Map of Canada       http://www.geobase.ca
&gt;  assembled from the National
&gt;  Topographic Data Base (NTDB)
&gt;
&gt;Canada Digital Elevation Data,     http://www.geobase.ca
&gt;  Level 1
&gt;
&gt;National Road Network, Canada      http://www.geobase.ca
&gt;
&gt;Satellite database for the land    CCRS
&gt;  cover of Canada is a sample
&gt;  of LANDSAT TM/ETM+ scenes
&gt;  representing the distribution
&gt;  of land cover across Canada.
&gt;
&gt;Earth Observation for Sustainable  CFS
&gt;  Development (EOSD) of  Forests
&gt;  Land Cover Classification
&gt;
&gt;National Land and Water            http://www.agr.gc.ca/eng/?id=1343071073307#a9
&gt;  Information System (NLWIS)
&gt;  Land Cover for agricultural
&gt;  regions of Canada, circa 2000
&gt;
&gt;Circa-2000 Northern Land Cover     http://geogratis.cgdi.gc.ca
&gt;  of Canada
&gt;
&gt;Classification of Agricultural     Agricultural Financial Services
&gt;  Lands in Alberta, Saskatchewan     Corporation Saskatchewan Crop
&gt;  and the Peace Region of            Insurance Corporation
&gt;  British Columbia                   British Columbia Ministry of
&gt;                                     Agriculture and Lands (Business
&gt;                                     Risk management Division)
&gt;
&gt;Northern Treeline (Timoney         http://data.arcticatlas.org
&gt;  et al., 1992)
&gt;
&gt;North American Regional            http://nomads.ncdc.noaa.gov
&gt;  Reanalysis, Daily Dataset
&gt;  Degree days
&gt;
&gt;Fire data base                     CCRS
&gt;
&gt;Ground truth data                  CCRS</othercit>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Various</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2009</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Date of acquisition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Canada ancillary data</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>NASA</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
                  <title>Landsat Thematic Mapper, LandsatLook Images with Geographic Reference</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Washington, DC</pubplace>
                     <publish>NASA</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>Mexico used Landsat data for 76 locations; for each location there was an image for April 2005, and in most
cases also for October 2005.  The following row/path locations were used: 26/40, 26/41, 26/42, 26/43,
26/44, 27/42, 27/43, 28/40, 28/41, 28/42, 28/43, 28/44, 29/39, 29/40, 29/41, 29/42, 29/43, 29/44, 29/45,
30/39, 30/40, 30/41, 30/42, 30/43, 30/44, 31/39, 31/40, 31/41, 31/42, 31/43, 31/44, 31/45, 32/38, 32/39,
32/40, 32/41, 32/42, 32/43, 32/44, 33/38, 33/39, 33/40, 33/41, 33/42, 33/43, 33/44, 34/38, 34/39, 34/40,
34/41, 34/42, 34/43, 35/38, 35/39, 35/40, 35/41, 35/42, 35/43, 36/38, 36/39, 36/40, 36/41, 36/42, 37/38,
37/39, 37/40, 37/41, 38/38, 38/39, 38/40, 38/41, 39/37, 39/38, 39/39, 40/37, 40/38.  Detailed information
on Landsat source IDs, which indicate the specific date of the image, is available from Mexico.</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2005</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Landsat 2005</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>NASA</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
                  <title>Landsat Thematic Mapper, LandsatLook Images with Geographic Reference</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Washington, DC</pubplace>
                     <publish>NASA</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>Mexico used Landsat data for 76 locations; for each location there was an image for April 2010, and for all
but one location there was also an image for October 2010.  The following row/path locations were used:
26/40, 26/41, 26/42, 26/43, 26/44, 27/42, 27/43, 28/40, 28/41, 28/42, 28/43, 28/44, 29/39, 29/40, 29/41,
29/42, 29/43, 29/44, 29/45, 30/39, 30/40, 30/41, 30/42, 30/43, 30/44, 31/39, 31/40, 31/41, 31/42, 31/43,
31/44, 31/45, 32/38, 32/39, 32/40, 32/41, 32/42, 32/43, 32/44, 33/38, 33/39, 33/40, 33/41, 33/42, 33/43,
33/44, 34/38, 34/39, 34/40, 34/41, 34/42, 34/43, 35/38, 35/39, 35/40, 35/41, 35/42, 35/43, 36/38, 36/39,
36/40, 36/41, 36/42, 37/38, 37/39, 37/40, 37/41, 38/38, 38/39, 38/40, 38/41, 39/37, 39/38, 39/39, 40/37,
40/38.  Detailed information on Landsat source IDs, which indicate the specific date of the image, is
available from Mexico.</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2010</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Landsat 2010</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Centre National d&#x92;Études Spatiales (CNES)</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
                  <title>SPOT 5 High Resolution Geometric data</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Paris, France</pubplace>
                     <publish>CNES</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>SPOT data were used for quality assurance.  There were eight SPOT images taken on various dates in 2005 and
one in 2006.  Detailed information on SPOT source IDs, which indicate the specific date of the image, row
and path, and processing level, is available from Mexico.</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://www.astrium-geo.com/en/143-spot-satellite-imagery</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <rngdates>
                     <begdate>20050404</begdate>
                     <enddate>20060226</enddate>
                  </rngdates>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>SPOT 5 HRG 2005</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Centre National d&#x92;Études Spatiales (CNES)</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
                  <title>SPOT 5 High Resolution Geometric data</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Paris, France</pubplace>
                     <publish>CNES</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>SPOT data were used for quality assurance.  There was one SPOT image taken in 2009, and eight SPOT images
taken on various dates in 2010.  Detailed information on SPOT source IDs, which indicate the specific date
of the image, row and path, and processing level, is available from Mexico.</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://www.astrium-geo.com/en/143-spot-satellite-imagery</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <rngdates>
                     <begdate>20091115</begdate>
                     <enddate>20101107</enddate>
                  </rngdates>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>SPOT 5 HRG 2010</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
                  <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                  <title>National Elevation Dataset</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://ned.usgs.gov/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2005</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>DEM</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Natural Resources Canada</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unpublished material</pubdate>
                  <title>Cross-border DEM</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Internal file</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2013</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Data acquisition date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>CADEM</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency (NGA)</origin>
                  <origin>National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA)</origin>
                  <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
                  <title>Shuttle Radar Topography Mission</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Pasadena, CA</pubplace>
                     <publish>Jet Propulsion Laboratory, NASA</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://www2.jpl.nasa.gov/srtm/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2000</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>SRTM</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Earth Resources Observation and Science
(EROS)</origin>
                  <origin>U.S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, Remote Sensing Applications
Center (RSAC)</origin>
                  <pubdate>20121003</pubdate>
                  <title>Multi-Temporal Burn Severity Fire Perimeters</title>
                  <onlink>&lt;http://www.mtbs.gov/dataquery/individualfiredata.html&gt;</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>20121003</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>MTBS</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>NASA</origin>
                  <pubdate>2001</pubdate>
                  <title>Landsat MRLC</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Washington, DC</pubplace>
                     <publish>NASA</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <onlink>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov/</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Online</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2001</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Publication date</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>Landsat MRLC</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
                  <title>2010 Land Cover Map of North America at 250m: Canada</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Ottawa, Ontario, Canada</pubplace>
                     <publish>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Internal file</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2010</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>CCRS_NLCD 2010</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Comisión Nacional para el Conocimiento y Uso de la Biodiversidad (CONABIO)</origin>
                  <origin>Comisión Nacional Forestal (CONAFOR)</origin>
                  <origin>Insituto Nacional de Estadística y Geografía (INEGI)</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
                  <title>Land Cover Map of Mexico for 2010 at 250m</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Mexico City, Mexico</pubplace>
                     <publish>Insituto Nacional de Estadística y Geografía</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Internal file</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2010</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>INEGI_NLCD 2010</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
                  <title>2010 North American Land Cover Database for the United States</title>
                  <geoform>Raster digital data</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Sioux Falls, South Dakota, USA</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>Internal file</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2010</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr>Ground condition</srccurr>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>USGS_NLCD 2010</srccitea>
            <srccontr>Spatial and attribute information</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>A series of monthly MODIS composites were produced prior to the compilation of
land cover data for each country.
Input data used in land cover mapping were generated from the following original
Level 1B MODIS data (collection 5): a) MOD02QKM - Level 1B 250m swath data, 5-min
Granules; b) MOD02HKM - Level 1B 500m swath data, 5-min granules; c) MOD03 &#x96;
Level 1 Geolocation information, 1km swath data, 5-min granules.  All input data
are available from the NASA Level 1 and Atmosphere Archive and Distribution
System (LAADS), http://ladsweb.nascom.nasa.gov/
The MODIS 500m land channels (B3-B7) were downscaled to 250m spatial resolution
as described by Trishchenko et al. (2006) and then re-projected into Lambert
Azimuthal Equal Area projection using software developed at the CCRS (Khlopenkov
et al., 2008). Two original 250m MODIS channels and five downscaled 250m MODIS
land channels were assembled into North-America-wide 1  10-day composites following
the methods developed in Luo et al., (2008).
MODIS 10-day composites were further processed to reduce data noise due to
different viewing conditions and remaining cloud and atmosphere contamination.  A
temporal rank filter was applied, calculated as the maximum of minimum values for
two overlapping moving windows.  For this implementation, a window size of three
ten-day composites was used with one pixel overlap between windows.  After rank
filtering, a procedure to detect residual spikes in the data was applied based on
a neighbourhood comparison.  Within a moving window of 3 composites, if the
neighbouring pixels were both above or below the centre pixel by 25%, the centre
pixel was linearly interpolated from its neighbours.  The filtered 10-day
composites were averaged to generate monthly composites.  The processed data set
contained 12 monthly composites of channels 1 (B1, VIS) and 2 (B2, near-infrared
NIR) at 250m spatial resolution and five channels designed for land applications
(bands B3 to B7) resampled to 250m spatial resolution.</procdesc>
            <srcused>MOD02QKM</srcused>
            <srcused>MOD02HKM</srcused>
            <srcused>MOD03</srcused>
            <procdate>2009</procdate>
            <srcprod>NA Monthly composites 2005</srcprod>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>MODIS monthly composites for 2010 were produced using the same process as for the
2005 data, but with updated source material.</procdesc>
            <srcused>MOD02QKM 2012</srcused>
            <srcused>MOD02HKM 2012</srcused>
            <srcused>MOD03 2012</srcused>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
            <srcprod>NA Monthly composites 2010</srcprod>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Version 2 of the 2005 Land Cover was used as the starting point for all three
countries.  Areas of potential change were identified and then reclassified as
necessary.  Country-specific processes are described in this process step and the
ones below.  Please see the points-of-contact if additional processing
information is needed.
For Canada, the 2010 land cover was derived from a time series of land cover,
developed for Canada from 2000 to 2010 at an annual time step, using MODIS data
as input (Pouliot et al., 2013).  The method used to update land cover for each
year in the time series followed a change- and evidence-based classification
approach.  It was applied separately for six mapping zones.  Mapping zones were
selected to have similar spectral and land cover properties that could be
optimized within the zone so as to reduce class confusion.
Change detection was a critical step, as the basic premise of the method required
changes to be detected with high confidence.  Three methods were used to capture
different types of change and at different temporal scales.  Annual negative
change results were generated in previous research by Guindon et al. (2011),
which mostly captured forest-stand-replacing disturbances such as harvesting and
fire.  New methods were developed to capture annual positive change in disturbed
areas and to account for subtle multi-year change of either a negative or
positive nature.  Negative change refers to vegetation loss and positive change
to vegetation establishment and growth.  In the context of multi-year change,
examples of the negative case include recurrent insect defoliation, gradual
urbanization, and persistent climatic or hydrological alteration.  For the
positive case, examples include gradual regeneration of disturbed areas and
climate-related vegetation change.
To predict the new land cover label for a change area, several sources of
evidence were combined including the class membership output from a decision tree
classifier, class temporal transition likelihood, and regional and neighbourhood
class proportions.  The class with the maximum combined evidence was taken as the
updated land cover label. A base land cover map for 2005 was used for the update
and served as the classification training data source.  To capture class temporal
variability, training samples were taken for pixels that had not changed within
plus or minus 1 year of the base map.  Temporal filtering of the time series was
the final step applied to remove highly improbable land cover transitions once
all maps in the time series were processed.
Several sources of ancillary data were incorporated in the classification to develop
or refine the initial base map.  These included a 250-meter spatial resolution water
fraction map assembled from the National Topographic Data Base at 1:2500000 scale
(Palvic and Latifovic, 2007), digital elevation data at 1:50000 scale, Canada road
network data at 1:250000 scale converted to road density within a 250 meter grid cell,
and an indicator of the Taiga class likelihood based on proximity to the northern
treeline (Timoney et al., 1992) and conifer class density measured within a 50x50
pixel window of the 2005 land cover base map.  Exponentially decreasing membership
functions were defined for the distance and density layers and multiplied to
calculate the final Taiga likelihood estimate.</procdesc>
            <srcused>LandCover2005_v2</srcused>
            <srcused>NA Monthly Composites 2005</srcused>
            <srcused>NA Monthly Composites 2010</srcused>
            <srcused>Canada ancillary data</srcused>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
            <srcprod>CCRS_NLCD 2010</srcprod>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>In Mexico, potential change estimation built on the monthly MODIS image composites of all
seven spectral bands.  Image data from 2010 were normalized to the corresponding band and
month from 2005 using Theil-Sen regression (Olthof et al. 2005).  Next, the normalized
difference vegetation index (NDVI) was calculated.  Based on the NDVI, textural Laplace
and Sobel filters with 3x3 kernel size were applied to enhance change detection along land
cover edges.  In total a set of 120 data layers were used: data for 7 spectral bands, NDVI,
Sobel, and Laplace filters (10 data layers), for 12 months of the year.  This set of data
layers was produced for both 2005 and 2010, and compared between the two subject years.
A small difference in values between the 2005 and 2010 data indicates areas that have not
changed, whereas extreme negative and positive values indicate changes.  For areas of change,
the most appropriate lower and upper cut-off thresholds in the difference image histogram
(lower and upper quantile) must be determined, and also the frequency, i.e. number of times,
out of the 120 data layers used for comparison, that a pixel should be flagged as changed.
The appropriate threshold values for the lower quantile, upper quantile, and frequency were
defined by training an algorithm using pairs of Landsat images from April (the end of the dry
season) and October (the end of the rainy season) for 2005 and 2010, from which change was
estimated by visual interpretation.  The optimal thresholds were defined as: lower
quantile, 1 percent; upper quantile, 99 percent; and frequency (the number of data layers
indicating change), 30.  The resulting change mask identified areas of potential change;
errors remaining in the change mask were removed by manual editing.  The mask was assessed
with 10m SPOT 5 HRG images for nine sites; the overall accuracy was 80 percent, with a
commission error rate of 20 percent and a omission error rate of 50 percent.
Map updating employs the above-described change mask, the baseline version 2 land cover map
from 2005, and spectral data from the year 2010.  Updating builds on the assumption that all
pixels that were not identified as potential change will indicate no change between 2005
and 2010.  For each class, 1,500 samples were selected from unchanged areas within 1-2 km of
potential areas of change; those samples were used to train the decision tree model which was
then applied to classify areas of change within the potential change mask area for the
year 2010.</procdesc>
            <srcused>LandCover2005_v2</srcused>
            <srcused>NA Monthly Composites 2005</srcused>
            <srcused>NA Monthly Composites 2010</srcused>
            <srcused>Landsat 2005</srcused>
            <srcused>Landsat 2010</srcused>
            <srcused>SPOT 5 HRG 2005</srcused>
            <srcused>SPOT 5 HRG 2010</srcused>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
            <srcprod>INEGI_NLCD 2010</srcprod>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>In the United States, land cover for 2010 was mapped by first running a spectral
change analysis model to identify areas that potentially had changed between 2005
and 2010.  Included in the model were burn areas from MTBS, with an effort made
to model burn severity and potential recovery.  Only fires from 2010 and earlier
were considered in the modeling.
Areas of potential change were classified through a process similar to that used
to classify the 2005 data, using a combination of MODIS composite imagery and ancillary
data.  Adjustments to the model were made based on experience gained in producing
the 2005 Version 2 data set.  Classification was achieved by use of a
classification and decision tree method (DT).  The specific DT program employed
is called SEE5, which implements a gain ratio criterion in tree development and
pruning (Quinlan, 1993).  SEE5 also implemented several advanced features that can
aid and improve land cover classification, including boosting and
cross-validation.  Boosting is a technique for improving classification accuracy,
while cross-validation can provide a certain level of estimation regarding the
land cover classification quality.  In addition, SEE5 can generate a confidence
estimate for each classified pixel and record the associated classification logic
in a text file that can be readily interpreted and incorporated into a metadata
system.  To conduct the land cover classification using DT, a large quantity of
training data was required.
The change pixels represent a conservative estimate of change based on both
spectral analysis and thematic change between land cover modeled for both 2005
and 2010.  Much of the change is in fire perimeter areas.  Burned areas were
reclassified as necessary, based on the length of time since the fire occurred.
Alaska was processed separately from the conterminous United States, using DEM, SRTM,  
and CADEM.  The conterminous United States was processed using DEM elevation data. 
Hawaii was not updated because newer data were not available.
The resulting data set was checked against Landsat MRLC for quality assurance.</procdesc>
            <srcused>LandCover2005_v2</srcused>
            <srcused>NA Monthly composites 2005</srcused>
            <srcused>NA Monthly composites 2010</srcused>
            <srcused>MTBS</srcused>
            <srcused>DEM</srcused>
            <srcused>CADEM</srcused>
            <srcused>SRTM</srcused>
            <srcused>Landsat MRLC</srcused>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
            <srcprod>USGS_NLCD 2010</srcprod>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>To produce the seamless land cover map of North America, the three national land cover
products (Canada, Mexico, USA) were edge matched along the borders using an
object-oriented segmentation technique.  Land cover regions that crossed borders were
reclassified using the majority class segment.</procdesc>
            <srcused>CCRS_NLCD 2010</srcused>
            <srcused>USGS_NLCD 2010</srcused>
            <srcused>INEGI_NLCD 2010</srcused>
            <procdate>2013</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Pixel</rasttype>
         <rowcount>35000</rowcount>
         <colcount>37000</colcount>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <planar>
            <mapproj>
               <mapprojn>Lambert Azimuthal Equal Area</mapprojn>
               <lamberta>
                  <longpc>-100.00</longpc>
                  <latprjc>45.00</latprjc>
                  <feast>0.0</feast>
                  <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
               </lamberta>
            </mapproj>
            <planci>
               <plance>row and column</plance>
               <coordrep>
                  <absres>250.0</absres>
                  <ordres>250.0</ordres>
               </coordrep>
               <plandu>Meters</plandu>
            </planci>
         </planar>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>None</horizdn>
            <ellips>Sphere</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6370977</semiaxis>
            <denflat>1.0</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>Land cover classification grid cell</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Any of the data elements in the 2010 North American land cover file</enttypd>
            <enttypds>North American Atlas GIS Group</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Land cover classification grid cell value</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The value is an indication of the land cover class</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>North American Atlas GIS Group</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Temperate or sub-polar needleleaf forest.  Forests generally taller than
three meters and more than 20 percent of total vegetation cover.  This type
occurs across the northern United States, Canada and mountainous zones of
Mexico.  The tree crown cover contains at least 75 percent of needleleaved
species.  Land Cover Classification System (LCCS) code: 20134.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Sub-polar taiga needleleaf forest.  Forest and woodlands with trees generally
taller than three meters and more than 5 percent of total vegetation cover
with shrubs and lichens commonly present in the understory.  The tree crown
cover contains at least 75 percent of needleleaved species.  This type occurs
across Alaska and northern Canada and may consist of treed muskeg or
wetlands.  Forest canopies are variable and often sparse, with generally
greater tree cover in the southern latitude parts of the zone than the north.
LCCS code: 20229.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Tropical or sub-tropical broadleaf evergreen forest.  Forests generally
taller than five meters and more than 20 percent of total vegetation cover.
These occur in the southern United States and Mexico.  These forests have
greater than 75 percent of tree crown cover represented by evergreen species.
LCCS code: 20090.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>4</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Tropical or sub-tropical broadleaf deciduous forest.  Forests generally
taller than five meters and more than 20 percent of total vegetation cover.
These occur in the southern United States and Mexico.  These forests have
greater than 75 percent of tree crown cover represented by deciduous species.
LCCS code: 20132.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>5</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Temperate or sub-polar broadleaf deciduous forest.  Forests generally taller
than three meters and more than 20 percent of total vegetation cover.  These
occur in the northern United States, Canada and mountainous zones of Mexico.
These forests have greater than 75 percent of tree crown cover represented by
deciduous species.  LCCS code: 20227.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>6</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Mixed forest.  Forests generally taller than three meters and more than 20
percent of total vegetation cover.  Neither needleleaf nor broadleaf tree
species occupy more than 75 percent of total tree cover, but are co-dominant.
LCCS codes: 20092, 20090, 20134, 20132, 20229, 20227.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>7</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Tropical or sub-tropical shrubland.  Areas dominated by woody perennial
plants with persistent woody stems less than five meters tall and typically
greater than 20 percent of total vegetation.  This class occurs across the
southern United States and Mexico.  LCCS code: 21450-13476.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>8</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Temperate or sub-polar shrubland.  Areas dominated by woody perennial plants
with persistent woody stems less than three meters tall and typically greater
than 20 percent of total vegetation.  This class occurs across the northern
United States, Canada and highlands of Mexico.  LCCS code: 21450-12050.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>9</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Tropical or sub-tropical grassland.  Areas dominated by graminoid or
herbaceous vegetation generally accounting for greater than 80 percent of
total vegetation cover.  These areas are not subject to intensive management
such as tilling, but can be utilized for grazing.  This class occurs across
the southern United States and Mexico.  LCCS code: 21669.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>10</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Temperate or sub-polar grassland.  Areas dominated by graminoid or herbaceous
vegetation, generally accounting for greater than 80 percent of total
vegetation cover.  These areas are not subject to intensive management such
as tilling, but can be utilized for grazing.  This class occurs across
Canada, United States and highlands of Mexico.  LCCS code: 21537-12212.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>11</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Sub-polar or polar shrubland-lichen-moss.  Areas dominated by dwarf shrubs
with lichen and moss typically accounting for at least 20 percent of total
vegetation cover.  This class occurs across northern Canada and Alaska.  LCCS
codes: 20022-12050, 21454-12212, 21439-3012.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>12</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Sub-polar or polar grassland-lichen-moss.  Areas dominated by grassland with
lichen and moss typically accounting for at least 20 percent of total
vegetation cover.  This class occurs across northern Canada and Alaska.  LCCS
codes: 21454-12212, 20022-12050, 21439-3012.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>13</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Sub-polar or polar barren-lichen-moss.  Areas dominated by a mixture of bare
areas with lichen and moss that typically account for at least 20 percent of
total vegetation cover.  This class occurs across northern Canada and Alaska.
LCCS codes: 21468, 21454-12212, 20022-12050.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>14</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Wetland.  Areas dominated by perennial herbaceous and woody wetland
vegetation which is influenced by the water table at or near surface over
extensive periods of time.  This includes marshes, swamps, bogs, mangroves,
etc., either coastal or inland where water is present for a substantial
period annually.  LCCS codes: 42349, 41809.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>15</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Cropland.  Areas dominated by intensively managed crops.  These areas
typically require human activities for their maintenance.  This includes
areas used for the production of annual crops, such as corn, soybeans, wheat,
maize, vegetables, tobacco, cotton, etc.; perennial grasses for grazing; and
woody crops such as orchards and vineyards.  Crop vegetation accounts for
greater than 20 percent of total vegetation.  This class does not represent
natural grasslands used for light to moderate grazing.
LCCS codes: 10037, 10025, 21441, 21453.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>16</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Barren lands.  Areas characterized by bare rock, gravel, sand, silt, clay, or
other earthen material, with little or no "green" vegetation present
regardless of its inherent ability to support life. Generally,  vegetation
accounts for less than 10 percent of total cover.  LCCS codes: 6001, 6004.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>17</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Urban and built-up.  Areas that contain at least 30 percent or greater urban
constructed materials for human activities (cities, towns, transportation
etc.)  LCCS code: 5003.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>18</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Water.  Areas of open water, generally with less than 25 percent cover of
non-water cover types.  This class refers to areas that are consistently
covered by water.  LCCS codes: 8001, 7001.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>19</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Snow and ice.  Areas characterized by a perennial cover of ice and/or snow,
generally greater than 25 percent of total cover.  LCCS codes: 8005, 8008.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>North American Atlas GIS Group</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Commission for Environmental Cooperation</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>393, rue St-Jacques Ouest, Bureau 200</address>
               <city>Montréal</city>
               <state>Québec</state>
               <postal>H2Y 1N9</postal>
               <country>Canada</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1 514 350 4300</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>1 514 350 4314</cntfax>
            <cntemail>info@cec.org</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on computer systems at the CCRS,
INEGI, USGS, and the Commission for Environmental Cooperation, no warranty expressed
or implied is made by these agencies regarding the utility of the data on any other
system, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  Use of
trademarks or formats does not constitute endorsement by these agencies.  No
responsibility is assumed by the CCRS, INEGI, USGS, or the CEC in the use of these
data.</distliab>
   </distinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Canada Centre for Remote Sensing</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Scientist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>CCRS/NRCan</address>
               <address>588 Booth Street</address>
               <city>Ottawa</city>
               <state>ON</state>
               <postal>K1A 0Y7</postal>
               <country>Canada</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1 613 947 1816</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>1 613 947 1383</cntfax>
            <cntemail>Rasim.Latifovic@nrcan.gc.ca</cntemail>
            <hours>0900 - 1700 ET, M - F (-5h EST/-4h EDT GMT)</hours>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on computer systems at the CCRS,
INEGI, USGS, and the Commission for Environmental Cooperation, no warranty expressed
or implied is made by these agencies regarding the utility of the data on any other
system, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  Use of
trademarks or formats does not constitute endorsement by these agencies.  No
responsibility is assumed by the CCRS, INEGI, USGS, or the CEC in the use of these
data.</distliab>
   </distinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Instituto Nacional de Estadística y Geografía (INEGI)</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Director of Natural Resources and Environment Information</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Av. Héroe de Nacozari Sur 2301. Fraccionamiento Jardines del Parque.</address>
               <city>Aguascalientes</city>
               <state>Aguascalientes</state>
               <postal>20270</postal>
               <country>Mexico</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>52 44 99 10 53 65</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>jose.ornelas@inegi.org.mx</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 (-6h GMT)</hours>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on computer systems at the CCRS,
INEGI, USGS, and the Commission for Environmental Cooperation, no warranty expressed
or implied is made by these agencies regarding the utility of the data on any other
system, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  Use of
trademarks or formats does not constitute endorsement by these agencies.  No
responsibility is assumed by the CCRS, INEGI, USGS, or the CEC in the use of these
data.</distliab>
   </distinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
               <cntper>Customer Services Representative</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>USGS, Earth Resources Observation and  Science (EROS) Center</address>
               <address>Mundt Federal Building</address>
               <address>47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>South Dakota</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1 605 594 6151</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>custserv@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M - F (-6h CST/-5h CDT GMT)</hours>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on computer systems at the CCRS,
INEGI, USGS, and the Commission for Environmental Cooperation, no warranty expressed
or implied is made by these agencies regarding the utility of the data on any other
system, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  Use of
trademarks or formats does not constitute endorsement by these agencies.  No
responsibility is assumed by the CCRS, INEGI, USGS, or the CEC in the use of these
data.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>IMG</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.cec.org/naatlas/</networkr>
                        <networkr>http://www.inegi.org.mx</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>TIFF</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.cec.org/naatlas/</networkr>
                        <networkr>http://www.inegi.org.mx</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>MXD</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.cec.org/naatlas</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>GeoPDF</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://www.cec.org/naatlas</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>Gratuit-Free</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20131206</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Commission for Environmental Cooperation</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>Mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>393, rue St-Jacques Ouest, Bureau 200</address>
               <city>Montréal</city>
               <state>Québec</state>
               <postal>H2Y 1N9</postal>
               <country>Canada</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1 514 350 4300</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>1 514 350 4314</cntfax>
            <cntemail>info@cec.org</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
