<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Marcot, B.G., </origin>
            <origin>M.T. Jorgenson,</origin>
            <origin>A.R. DeGange</origin>
            <pubdate>20140521</pubdate>
            <title>Oblique videos taken during low-altitude transects of the Arctic Network of national park units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013 </title>
            <geoform>video</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Anchorage, AK</pubplace>
               <publish>US Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Marcot, B.G.,</origin>
                  <origin>M.T. Jorgenson,</origin>
                  <origin>A.R. DeGange</origin>
                  <pubdate>20140521</pubdate>
                  <title>Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</title>
                  <geoform>website</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Anchorage, Alaska</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>USGS project website.</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://alaska.usgs.gov/portal/project.php?project_id=349</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>Oblique videos shot from a Panasonic Lumix DMC-FZ200 (24x superzoom with variable focal length) and a Panasonic Lumix DMC-SZ7 (10x superzoom with variable focal length)) of the arctic landscape during low altitude transects. Transects were conducted from small aircraft over the National Park Service’s Arctic Network (Bering Land Bridge National Preserve, Cape Krusenstern National Monument, Gates of the Arctic National Park and Preserve, Kobuk Valley National Park, and Noatak National Preserve) and the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service’s Selawik National Wildlife Refuge in northwest Alaska.</abstract>
         <purpose>Provide images of current conditions and prevalence of land cover types as a baseline for measuring future change, and to complement the existing grid-based sample photography of the region.</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>20130716</begdate>
               <enddate>20130718</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <descgeog>The study area included five units of the National Park Service’s Arctic Network (Bering Land Bridge National Preserve, Cape Krusenstern National Monument, Gates of the Arctic National Park &amp; Preserve, Kobuk Valley National Park, and Noatak National Preserve), the adjacent area of U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service’s Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, and a 10-km buffer around all of these administrative units, totaling 162,868 km2 in an area spanning roughly 500 km east to west and 300 km north to south.  This is also the study area for the USGS’ Wildlife Potential Habitat Forecasting Framework Project (WildCast) that projects effects of climate change on future land cover and wildlife habitat (DeGange et al. 2013)</descgeog>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-169.22000</westbc>
            <eastbc>-149.05000</eastbc>
            <northbc>68.87000</northbc>
            <southbc>64.78000</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>Photogrammetry</themekey>
            <themekey>Arctic Network</themekey>
            <themekey>Low Altitude Air Photo</themekey>
            <themekey>Low Altitude Video</themekey>
            <themekey>Northwest Alaska</themekey>
            <themekey>Land Cover</themekey>
            <themekey>Ecotypes</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115</themekt>
            <themekey>Biota</themekey>
            <themekey>Climatology</themekey>
            <themekey>Environment</themekey>
            <themekey>ImageryBaseMapsEarthCover</themekey>
            <themekey>GeoscientificInformation</themekey>
            <themekey>InlandWaters</themekey>
            <themekey>Oceans</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
            <placekey>Alaska</placekey>
            <placekey>Northwest Arctic</placekey>
            <placekey>Bering Land Bridge National Preserve</placekey>
            <placekey>Selawik National Wildlife Refuge</placekey>
            <placekey>Cape Krusenstern National Monument</placekey>
            <placekey>Gates of the Arctic National Park</placekey>
            <placekey>Gates of the Arctic National Preserve</placekey>
            <placekey>Kobuk Valley National Park</placekey>
            <placekey>Noatak National Preserve</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>It is requested that the authors, the USGS Alaska Science Center the National Park Service and the US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station be cited for any subsequent publications referenced to this dataset. Please contact B.G. Marcot, US Forest Service with any questions. It is strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data to evaluate data set limitations, restrictions or intended use. No warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data and information on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. Inherent in any data set used to develop graphical representations are limitations of accuracy as determined by, among others, the source, scale and resolution of the data. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and information, and aggregate use with other data and information.These data and any derived products are not legal documents and are not intended to be used as such. The information contained in these data may be dynamic and could change over time. The data are not better than the original sources from which they are derived. It is the responsibility of the data user to use the data appropriately and consistent with the limitations of geospatial data in general and these data in particular. It is strongly recommended that the data described or contained herein be acquired directly from the USGS and not indirectly through some other sources which may have changed the data in some way. Neither the originators of this dataset or the USGS shall be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</useconst>
      <browse>
         <browsen>@trip Bering 130716 Lumix camera.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Flight path and video locations over the Bering Sea taken with the Panasonic Lumix cameras.</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <browse>
         <browsen>@trip KobGatSel 130717 Lumix camera.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Flight path and video locations over the Kobuk Valley, Gates of the Arctic and Selawik areas taken with the Panasonic Lumix cameras.</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <browse>
         <browsen>@trip NoaKru 130718 Lumix camera.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Flight path and video locations over the  Noatak and Cape Krusenstern area taken with the Panasonic Lumix cameras.</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <datacred>USGS Alaska Science Center, National Park Service, US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station</datacred>
      <native>All videos are either WMV or MP4 format and 3 Mb to 105 Mb in size.</native>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Bruce G. Marcot, </origin>
            <origin>M. Torre Jorgenson, </origin>
            <origin>Anthony R. DeGange</origin>
            <pubdate>20140521</pubdate>
            <title>USGS Data Series 846: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</title>
            <geoform>document</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>846</sername>
               <issue>1</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds846</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Marcot, B.G.,</origin>
            <origin>M.T. Jorgenson,</origin>
            <origin>A.R. DeGange </origin>
            <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
            <title>Wildlife Potential habitat Forecasting Framework (Wildcast)</title>
            <geoform>website</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Anchorage, Alaska</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>Study information website</othercit>
            <onlink>http://alaska.usgs.gov/science/program.php?pid=53 </onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>Not applicable.</logic>
      <complete>Not applicable.</complete>
      <lineage>
         <method>
            <methtype>Field</methtype>
            <methdesc>Oblique and nadir photographs and videos were shot along flight routes conducted July 16, 17, and 18, 2013, totaling 17 h 46 m flight time and 2,590 km flight distance, at a mean altitude of approximately 300 m above ground level.  Flight routes were selected to provide a broad representation of land cover types within each unit and to overfly specific locations of recent disturbances.  Photographs were geotagged;; all nadir photographs and videos were corrected for image lens distortion and appearance (increased gamma and color enhancement); all oblique photographs were corrected only for appearance; all oblique videos were neither geotagged nor corrected for appearance.</methdesc>
         </method>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Raw videos were organized into folders, renamed by flight date and camera type.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>World Geodetic System of 1984</horizdn>
            <ellips>World Geodetic System of 1984</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.25722210088</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
      <vertdef>
         <altsys>
            <altdatum>National Geodetic Vertical Datum of 1929</altdatum>
            <altres>1.00</altres>
            <altunits>meters</altunits>
            <altenc>Implicit coordinate</altenc>
         </altsys>
      </vertdef>
   </spref>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Alaska Science Center</cntorg>
               <cntper>Dennis Walworth</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>4210 University Dr.</address>
               <city>Anchorage</city>
               <state>AK</state>
               <postal>99508</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>907-786-7001</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>907-786-7150</cntfax>
            <cntemail>dwalworth@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <cntinst>Leave a message.</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>Zip file containing wmv or mp4 video and metadata files.</resdesc>
      <distliab>None</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>zip</formname>
               <filedec>Windows zip</filedec>
               <transize>1500</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://alaska.usgs.gov/science/subprogram.php?sid=184</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20140429</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Bruce Marcot</cntper>
               <cntorg>USDA Forest Service, Pacific Northwest Research Station</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Research Wildlife Biologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>620 SW Main St., Suite 400</address>
               <city>Portland</city>
               <state>OR</state>
               <postal>97208</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>503-808-2010</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>503-808-2020</cntfax>
            <cntemail>bmarcot@fs.fed.us</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
