<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Marcot, B.G., </origin>
            <origin>M.T. Jorgenson,</origin>
            <origin>A.R. DeGange</origin>
            <pubdate>20140521</pubdate>
            <title>Nadir photographs taken during low-altitude transects of the Arctic Network of national park units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013 </title>
            <geoform>raster digital data</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Anchorage, AK</pubplace>
               <publish>US Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <lworkcit>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Marcot, B.G.,</origin>
                  <origin>M.T. Jorgenson,</origin>
                  <origin>A.R. DeGange</origin>
                  <pubdate>20140521</pubdate>
                  <title>Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</title>
                  <geoform>website</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Anchorage, Alaska</pubplace>
                     <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
                  <othercit>USGS project website.</othercit>
                  <onlink>http://alaska.usgs.gov/portal/project.php?project_id=349</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </lworkcit>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>Nadir images taken by automatic time-lapse from a Drift HD-170 (focal length 5.00 mm) and a GoPro Hero3 Black Edition (focal length 2.77 mm) of the arctic landscape during low altitude transects at five second intervals. Transects were conducted from small aircraft over the National Park Service’s Arctic Network (Bering Land Bridge National Preserve, Cape Krusenstern National Monument, Gates of the Arctic National Park and Preserve, Kobuk Valley National Park, and Noatak National Preserve) and the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service’s Selawik National Wildlife Refuge in northwest Alaska.
</abstract>
         <purpose>Provide images of current conditions and prevalence of land cover types as a baseline for measuring future change, and to complement the existing grid-based sample photography of the region.</purpose>
         <supplinf>Images include an EXIF (exchangeable image file format) file that delineates camera metadata for each image. The file also contains pixel count estimates relative to occurences of the region's 44 ecotypes within the image.

</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>20130716</begdate>
               <enddate>20130718</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <descgeog>The study area included five units of the National Park Service’s Arctic Network (Bering Land Bridge National Preserve, Cape Krusenstern National Monument, Gates of the Arctic National Park &amp; Preserve, Kobuk Valley National Park, and Noatak National Preserve), the adjacent area of U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service’s Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, and a 10-km buffer around all of these administrative units, totaling 162,868 km2 in an area spanning roughly 500 km east to west and 300 km north to south.  This is also the study area for the USGS’ Wildlife Potential Habitat Forecasting Framework Project (WildCast) that projects effects of climate change on future land cover and wildlife habitat (DeGange et al. 2013)</descgeog>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-169.22000</westbc>
            <eastbc>-149.05000</eastbc>
            <northbc>68.87000</northbc>
            <southbc>64.78000</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>Photogrammetry</themekey>
            <themekey>Arctic Network</themekey>
            <themekey>Low Altitude Air Photo</themekey>
            <themekey>Low Altitude Video</themekey>
            <themekey>Northwest Alaska</themekey>
            <themekey>Land Cover</themekey>
            <themekey>Ecotypes</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115</themekt>
            <themekey>Biota</themekey>
            <themekey>Climatology</themekey>
            <themekey>Environment</themekey>
            <themekey>ImageryBaseMapsEarthCover</themekey>
            <themekey>GeoscientificInformation</themekey>
            <themekey>InlandWaters</themekey>
            <themekey>Oceans</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
            <placekey>Alaska</placekey>
            <placekey>Northwest Arctic</placekey>
            <placekey>Bering Land Bridge National Preserve</placekey>
            <placekey>Selawik National Wildlife Refuge</placekey>
            <placekey>Cape Krusenstern National Monument</placekey>
            <placekey>Gates of the Arctic National Park</placekey>
            <placekey>Gates of the Arctic National Preserve</placekey>
            <placekey>Kobuk Valley National Park</placekey>
            <placekey>Noatak National Preserve</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>It is requested that the authors, the USGS Alaska Science Center the National Park Service and the US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station be cited for any subsequent publications referenced to this dataset. Please contact B.G. Marcot, US Forest Service with any questions. It is strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data to evaluate data set limitations, restrictions or intended use. No warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data and information on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. Inherent in any data set used to develop graphical representations are limitations of accuracy as determined by, among others, the source, scale and resolution of the data. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and information, and aggregate use with other data and information.These data and any derived products are not legal documents and are not intended to be used as such. The information contained in these data may be dynamic and could change over time. The data are not better than the original sources from which they are derived. It is the responsibility of the data user to use the data appropriately and consistent with the limitations of geospatial data in general and these data in particular. It is strongly recommended that the data described or contained herein be acquired directly from the USGS and not indirectly through some other sources which may have changed the data in some way. Neither the originators of this dataset or the USGS shall be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</useconst>
      <browse>
         <browsen>@trip Bering 130716 Drift camera 01.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Flight path and image locations over the Bering Sea taken with the Drift camera.</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <browse>
         <browsen>@trip Bering 130716 Drift camera 02, w example photo 1063.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Flight path and image locations, with example photo over the Bering Sea taken with the Drift camera.</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <browse>
         <browsen>@trip KobGatSel 130717 Drift camera A.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Flight path and image locations, segment 1, over the  Kobuk Valley, Gates of the Arctic and Selawik areas taken with the Drift camera.</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <browse>
         <browsen>@trip KobGatSel 130717 Drift camera B.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Flight path and image locations, segment 2, over the  Kobuk Valley, Gates of the Arctic and Selawik areas taken with the Drift camera.</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <browse>
         <browsen>@trip KobGatSel 130717 Drift camera C.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Flight path and image locations, segment 3, over the Kobuk Valley, Gates of the Arctic and Selawik areas taken with the Drift camera.</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <browse>
         <browsen>@trip NoaKru 130718 Drift camera.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Flight path and image locations over the Noatak and Cape Krusenstern area taken with the Drift camera.</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <browse>
         <browsen>@trip Bering 130716 GoPro camera, w gaps &amp; movies.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Flight path and image locations over the Bering Sea taken with the GoPro camera.</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <browse>
         <browsen>@trip KobGatSel 130717 GoPro camera.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Flight path and image locations taken over the Kobuk Valley, Gates of the Arctic and Selawik areas with a GoPro camera.</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <browse>
         <browsen>@trip NoaKru 130718 GoPro camera A.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Flight path and image locations, segment 1, over the Noatak and Cape Krusenstern area taken with the GoPro camera.</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <browse>
         <browsen>@trip NoaKru 130718 GoPro camera B.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Flight path and image locations, segment 2, over the Noatak and Cape Krusenstern area taken with the GoPro camera.</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <browse>
         <browsen>@trip NoaKru 130718 GoPro camera C.jpg</browsen>
         <browsed>Flight path and image locations, segment 3, over the Noatak and Cape Krusenstern area taken with the GoPro camera.</browsed>
         <browset>JPEG</browset>
      </browse>
      <datacred>USGS Alaska Science Center, National Park Service, US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station</datacred>
      <native>All photos are JPEG format and 3-12 Mb in size. Camera metadata (EXIF) is contained in an accompanying CSV format file.</native>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Bruce G. Marcot, </origin>
            <origin>M. Torre Jorgenson, </origin>
            <origin>Anthony R. DeGange</origin>
            <pubdate>20140521</pubdate>
            <title>USGS Data Series 846: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</title>
            <geoform>document</geoform>
            <serinfo>
               <sername>846</sername>
               <issue>1</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds846</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Jorgenson, M.T.</origin>
            <origin>J.E. Roth</origin>
            <origin>P.F. Miller</origin>
            <origin>M.J. Macander</origin>
            <origin>M.S. Duffy</origin>
            <origin>A.F. Wells</origin>
            <origin>G.V. Frost</origin>
            <origin>E.R. Pullman</origin>
            <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
            <title>An ecological land survey and landcover map of the Arctic Network.  Natural Resource Technical Report NPS/ARCN/NRTR-2009/270. </title>
            <geoform>document</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Fort Collins, CO</pubplace>
               <publish>National Park Service, Natural Resource Program Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
      <crossref>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Marcot, B.G.,</origin>
            <origin>M.T. Jorgenson,</origin>
            <origin>A.R. DeGange </origin>
            <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
            <title>Wildlife Potential habitat Forecasting Framework (Wildcast)</title>
            <geoform>website</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Anchorage, Alaska</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>Study information website</othercit>
            <onlink>http://alaska.usgs.gov/science/program.php?pid=53 </onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </crossref>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>Not applicable.</logic>
      <complete>Extensively redundant or extraneous photographs were deleted, such as time-lapse images taken when the planes were stationary, long sequences when over deep water (e.g., over Kotzebue Sound), and other images with no usable content.

The Drift camera images were ~50% obscured by the right float of the aircraft during the Bering transect. The images for the remaining transects are free of obstructions.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>Ensured that date and time in each photograph file’s EXIF (exchangeable image file format) data were accurate, as these data linked to the positions acquired from an on-board GPS and used for geotagging each photograph.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <method>
            <methtype>Field</methtype>
            <methdesc>Oblique and nadir photographs and videos were shot along flight routes conducted July 16, 17, and 18, 2013, totaling 17 h 46 m flight time and 2,590 km flight distance, at a mean altitude of approximately 300 m above ground level.  Flight routes were selected to provide a broad representation of land cover types within each unit and to overfly specific locations of recent disturbances.  Photographs were geotagged;; all nadir photographs and videos were corrected for image lens distortion and appearance (increased gamma and color enhancement); all oblique photographs were corrected only for appearance; all oblique videos were neither geotagged nor corrected for appearance.</methdesc>
         </method>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Raw photographs were organized into folders, renamed by flight date and camera type.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Extensively redundant or extraneous photographs were deleted, such as time-lapse images taken when the planes were stationary, long sequences when over deep water (e.g., over Kotzebue Sound), and other images with no usable content.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Ensured that date and time in each photograph file’s EXIF (exchangeable image file format) data were accurate, as these data linked to the GPS waypoints for geotagging each photograph.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Each photograph was adjusted for color saturation and gamma, which served to highlight many details.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>EXIF data from all photograph files -- including photograph file name and computer directory name, photograph date and time, camera type and settings, geotagged digital latitude and longitude, and altitude above mean sea level -- were extracted into spreadsheet files (.xlsx formats) by flight date and camera type.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Each nadir photograph was corrected for lens distortion to adjust for their wide-angle (170d fisheye lens) distortion that occurred from the small focal lengths, and cropped to exclude blank portions of the image that occur after fisheye correction.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The geolocation (latitude and longitude) of each nadir photograph from the was overlaid in GIS (ArcMap 10.0) onto a map of ecotypes of the ARCN region (Jorgenson et al. 2009).  Presence and area of each ecotype within a square window centered on each photograph location were recorded and included in the EXIF spreadsheet files.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>The individual photograph geolocations were intersected in GIS with a digital elevation model (DEM) of the ARCN study area so that ground-level elevation could be determined for each photograph location. Then, the difference between flight altitude above mean sea level (determined enroute via the on-board GPS unit) and ground-level elevation gave flight elevation above ground level for all photographs, which was used to verify the mean flight elevation used in the calculations of photograph time-lapse intervals and areal coverage of each photograph.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <latres>0.00001</latres>
            <longres>0.001</longres>
            <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
         </geograph>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>World Geodetic System of 1984</horizdn>
            <ellips>World Geodetic System of 1984</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
            <denflat>298.25722210088</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
      <vertdef>
         <altsys>
            <altdatum>National Geodetic Vertical Datum of 1929</altdatum>
            <altres>1.00</altres>
            <altunits>meters</altunits>
            <altenc>Implicit coordinate</altenc>
         </altsys>
      </vertdef>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>Nadir Image Camera Metadata</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Camera metadata for a GoPro Hero3 Black Edition and a Drift HD-170. Includes position as implied by correlating exposure time with GPS time intervals. Includes ecotype classification pixel counts.</enttypd>
            <enttypds>Publication: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013.</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Folder</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Name of the computer folder housing the digital image files.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Publication: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>File name</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Name of the photographic image computer file (.jpg)</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Publication: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Date and time</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Date (YY:MM:DD) and time (HH:MM:SS) the photograph was taken.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Publication: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Camera make</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Make of the camera used to take the photograph.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Publication: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Camera model</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Model of the camera used to take the photograph.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Publication: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Height x width</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Size of the digital image in pixels.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Publication: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Size of image file</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels of the digital image (= height x width).</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Publication: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Exposure (sec)</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Shutter speed in seconds.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Publication: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Aperture (F-number)</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>F-stop of the exposure.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Publication: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>ISO</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Sensitivity (“film speed”) setting of the exposure (ISO = International Organization of Standardization).</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Publication: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Flash used?</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Whether camera flash was used for the exposure (all “no”).</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Publication: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Focal length</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Focal length (focus distance to object) setting for the exposure.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Publication: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Latitude</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Latitude of the location of the center of the photograph in digital degrees north of the equator.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Publication: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Longitude</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Longitude of the location of the center of the photograph in digital degrees west of the prime meridian.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Publication: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Flight altitude ASL m</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Altitude of the airplane above sea level (ASL) when the photograph was taken, in meters.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Publication: Low-Altitude Photographic Transects of the Arctic Network of National Park Units and Selawik National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, July 2013</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>DEM elevation m</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Ground-level elevation at the center of the photograph, as taken from a digital elevation model (DEM) map in the ArcMap geographic information system, in meters.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Flight altitude AGL m</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Altitude of the airplane above ground level (AGL) at the center of the photograph, in meters; calculated by:  [Flight altitude ASAL in meters] – ([DEM elevation in feet] / [3.281 feet/meter]).</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Alpine Lake</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Alpine Lake ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Alpine Rocky Circumneutral Wet Sedge Meadow</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Alpine Rocky Circumneutral Wet Sedge Meadow ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Alpine Rocky Dry Acidic Barrens</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Alpine Rocky Dry Acidic Barrens ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Alpine Rocky Dry Alkaline Barrens</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Alpine Rocky Dry Alkaline Barrensecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Alpine Rocky Dry Mafic Barrens</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Alpine Rocky Dry Mafic Barrens ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Alpine Rocky Dry Dryas Dwarf Shrub</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Alpine Rocky Dry Dryas Dwarf Shrub ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Alpine Rocky Moist Ericaceous Dwarf Shrub</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Alpine Rocky Moist Ericaceous Dwarf Shrub ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Coastal Barrens</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Coastal Barrens ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Coastal Dry Crowberry Dwarf Shrub</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Coastal Dry Crowberry Dwarf Shrub ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Coastal Dry Dunegrass Meadow</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Coastal Dry Dunegrass Meadow ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Coastal Loamy Wet Brackish Sedge-Grass Meadow</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Coastal Loamy Wet Brackish Sedge-Grass Meadow ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Coastal Water</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Coastal Water ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Human Modified Barrens</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Human Modified Barrens ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Lowland Acidic Ericaceous Shrub Bog</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Lowland Acidic Ericaceous Shrub Bog ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Lowland Circumacidic Sedge Fen</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Lowland Circumacidic Sedge Fen ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Lowland Lake</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Lowland Lake ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Lowland Moist Dwarf Birch-Ericaceous-Willow Low Shrub</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Lowland Moist Dwarf Birch-Ericaceous-Willow Low Shrub ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Lowland Moist Sedge-Dryas Meadow</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Lowland Moist Sedge-Dryas Meadow ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Lowland Organic-rich Wet Acidic Black Spruce Forest</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Lowland Organic-rich Wet Acidic Black Spruce Forest ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Lowland Organic-rich Wet Circumacidic Alder Tall Shrub</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Lowland Organic-rich Wet Circumacidic Alder Tall Shrub ecotype..</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Lowland Organic-rich Wet Circumacidic Willow Low Shrub</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Lowland Organic-rich Wet Circumacidic Willow Low Shrub ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Riverine Gravelly Dry Alkaline Dryas Dwarf Shrub</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Riverine Gravelly Dry Alkaline Dryas Dwarf Shrub ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Riverine Gravelly Moist Circumalkaline Barrens</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Riverine Gravelly Moist Circumalkaline Barrens ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Riverine Gravelly-loamy Moist Circumalkaline Poplar Forest</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Riverine Gravelly-loamy Moist Circumalkaline Poplar Forest ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Riverine Gravelly-loamy Moist Circumalkaline White Spruce-Poplar Forest</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Riverine Gravelly-loamy Moist Circumalkaline White Spruce-Poplar Forest ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Riverine Gravelly-loamy Moist Circumalkaline White Spruce-Willow Forest</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Riverine Gravelly-loamy Moist Circumalkaline White Spruce-Willow Forest ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Riverine Gravelly-loamy Moist Circumalkaline Willow Low Shrub</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Riverine Gravelly-loamy Moist Circumalkaline Willow Low Shrub ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Riverine Loamy Moist Alder or Willow Tall Shrub</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Riverine Loamy Moist Alder or Willow Tall Shrub ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Riverine Loamy Moist Circumacidic Birch-Willow Low Shrub</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Riverine Loamy Moist Circumacidic Birch-Willow Low Shrub ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Riverine Loamy Wet Circumacidic Wet Sedge Meadow</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Riverine Loamy Wet Circumacidic Wet Sedge Meadow ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Riverine Water</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Riverine Water ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Shadow/Indeterminate</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Shadow/Indeterminate ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Snow</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Snow ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Upland Dry Mafic Barrens</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Upland Dry Mafic Barrens ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Upland Loamy Moist Circumalkaline Willow Low Shrub</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Upland Loamy Moist Circumalkaline Willow Low Shrub ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Upland Moist Dwarf Birch-Ericaceous-Willow Low Shrub</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Upland Moist Dwarf Birch-Ericaceous-Willow Low Shrub ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Upland Organic-rich Moist Acidic Dwarf Birch-Tussock Shrub</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Upland Organic-rich Moist Acidic Dwarf Birch-Tussock Shrub ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Upland Rocky-loamy Moist Alkaline Sedge-Dryas Meadow</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Upland Rocky-loamy Moist Alkaline Sedge-Dryas Meadow ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Upland Rocky-loamy Moist Circumacidic Alder-Willow Tall Shrub</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Upland Rocky-loamy Moist Circumacidic Alder-Willow Tall Shrub ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Upland Rocky-loamy Moist Circumacidic Birch Forest</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Upland Rocky-loamy Moist Circumacidic Birch Forest ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Upland Rocky-loamy Moist Circumacidic Spruce-Birch Forest</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Upland Rocky-loamy Moist Circumacidic Spruce-Birch Forest ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Upland Rocky-loamy Moist White Spruce Forest</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Upland Rocky-loamy Moist White Spruce Forest ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Upland Sandy Dry Acidic White Spruce-Lichen Woodland</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Upland Sandy Dry Acidic White Spruce-Lichen Woodland ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Upland Sandy Dry Alkaline Barrens</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Number of pixels within the image classified as Upland Sandy Dry Alkaline Barrens ecotype.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>None.</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Unknown.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>USGS Alaska Science Center</cntorg>
               <cntper>Dennis Walworth</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>4210 University Dr.</address>
               <city>Anchorage</city>
               <state>AK</state>
               <postal>99508</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>907-786-7001</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>907-786-7150</cntfax>
            <cntemail>dwalworth@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <cntinst>Leave a message.</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>Zip file containing jpg images and metadata files.</resdesc>
      <distliab>None</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>zip</formname>
               <filedec>Windows zip.</filedec>
               <transize>41000</transize>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://alaska.usgs.gov/science/subprogram.php?sid=184</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20140429</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Bruce Marcot</cntper>
               <cntorg>USDA Forest Service, Pacific Northwest Research Station</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Research Wildlife Biologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>620 SW Main St., Suite 400</address>
               <city>Portland</city>
               <state>OR</state>
               <postal>97208</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>503-808-2010</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>503-808-2020</cntfax>
            <cntemail>bmarcot@fs.fed.us</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
