<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)</origin>
            <pubdate>20150423</pubdate>
            <title>Landsat 1-5 Multispectral Scanner (1972-1992) - National Geospatial Data Asset (NGDA)</title>
            <geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
               <pubplace>Sioux Falls, South Dakota USA</pubplace>
               <publish>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation &amp; Science (EROS) Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov
http://glovis.usgs.gov</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The USGS Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center archive holds data collected by the Landsat suite of satellites, beginning with Landsat 1 in 1972. All Landsat data held in the USGS EROS archive are available for download at no charge. </abstract>
         <purpose>The Landsat archive provides a rich collection of information about the Earth's land surface. Major characteristics of changes to the surface of the planet can be detected, measured, and analyzed using Landsat data. The information obtainable from the historical and current Landsat data play a key role in studying surface changes through time.</purpose>
         <supplinf>Landsat represents the world's longest continuously acquired collection of space-based moderate-resolution land remote sensing data. As a joint initiative between the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and NASA, the Landsat Project and the data it collects support government, commercial, industrial, civilian, military, and educational communities throughout the United States and worldwide.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
               <caldate>Unknown</caldate>
            </sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-180</westbc>
            <eastbc>180</eastbc>
            <northbc>82.6</northbc>
            <southbc>-82.7</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>IMAGERY</themekey>
            <themekey>MULTISPECTRAL SCANNER</themekey>
            <themekey>MSS</themekey>
            <themekey>VISIBLE IMAGERY</themekey>
            <themekey>EROS</themekey>
            <themekey>USGS</themekey>
            <themekey>SATELLITE</themekey>
            <themekey>REMOTE SENSING</themekey>
            <themekey>IMAGERY</themekey>
            <themekey>LANDSAT</themekey>
            <themekey>RADIANCE</themekey>
            <themekey>VISIBLE WAVELENGTHS</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>NGDA Portfolio Themes</themekt>
            <themekey>NGDA</themekey>
            <themekey>National Geospatial Data Asset</themekey>
            <themekey>Imagery Theme</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
            <themekey>imageryBaseMapsEarthCover</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>Any downloading and use of these data signifies a user's agreement to comprehension and compliance of the USGS Standard Disclaimer.  Insure all portions of metadata are read and clearly understood before using these data in order to protect both user and USGS interests.</accconst>
      <useconst>There is no guarantee of warranty concerning the accuracy of these data.  Users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since the data was collected and that some parts of these data may no longer represent actual surface conditions.  Users should not use these data for critical applications without a full awareness of their limitations.  Acknowledgement of the originating agencies would be appreciated in products derived from these data.  Any user who modifies the data set is obligated to describe the types of modifications they perform.  User specifically agrees not to misrepresent the data set, nor to imply that changes made were approved or endorsed by the U.S. Geological Survey.  Please refer to http://www.usgs.gov/privacy.html for the USGS disclaimer.
</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
      <secinfo>
         <secsys>none</secsys>
         <secclass>unclassified</secclass>
         <sechandl>none</sechandl>
      </secinfo>
      <native>Oracle</native>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>The identification of features is provided by the distinct electromagnetic energy it emits, reflects, or otherwise transmits. This is called the spectral signature. Other signatures such as tone (lightness or darkness), texture (surface roughness or smoothness), pattern, shadow, shape, and size are as important. Thus, through the use of the thematic mapper sensor, such elements as water features, soils, and vegetation can be identified and distinguished from each other.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>N/A</logic>
      <complete>The Landsat satellites circle the Earth on a sun-synchronous, near-polar orbit imaging the same 185 km (115 miles) ground swath every 16 days (18 days for Landsats 1 through 3). </complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Landsat standard data products are processed using the Level 1 Product Generation System (LPGS), and are processed to the best level of correction possible (Level1T-terrain correction). If full terrain correction is not possible, the data is processed to Level 1G (systematic) or Level 1Gt (systematic-terrain) correction.  A very small number of Landsat TM scenes were processed using the National Land Archive Production System (NLAPS). Processing details can be found on http://landsat.usgs.gov/Landsat_Processing_Details.php</procdesc>
            <procdate>20130107</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
                     <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
                     <city>Sioux Falls</city>
                     <state>SD</state>
                     <postal>57198-0001</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
                  <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
      <cloud>Unknown</cloud>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct>Raster</direct>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype>Pixel</rasttype>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the USGS, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the USGS regarding the use of the data on any other system, nor does the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. </distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>Geographcal-Tagged Image File Format (GeoTIFF, NLAPS Data Format (NDF). For additional information see http://landsat.usgs.gov/Landsat_Processing_Details.php</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://glovis.usgs.gov</networkr>
                        <networkr>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>All Landsat data held in the USGS EROS archive are downloadable at no cost to all users.</fees>
         <ordering>Consult the data sets product page for specific information.</ordering>
         <turnarnd>Many Landsat scenes are available for immediate downloading; scenes not immediately downloadable can be submitted for processing. Processing takes 1-3 days. </turnarnd>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>_</custom>
      <techpreq>Adequate computer capability is the only technical prerequisite for viewing data in digital form.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150423</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>lta@usgs.gov</cntper>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Long Term Archive (LTA)  Representative</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>Long Term Archive (LTA),  U.S. Geological Survey  (USGS)
Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS) Center
47914 252nd Street</address>
               <city>Sioux Falls</city>
               <state>SD</state>
               <postal>57198-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-800-ASK-USGS</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>lta@usgs.gov</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M-F,   -6 h GMT</hours>
            <cntinst>lta@usgs.gov</cntinst>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998 Version 2</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
