<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <origin>National Wildlife Health Center</origin>
            <pubdate>Unpublished material</pubdate>
            <title>Wildlife Health Diagnostic Database (LIMS)</title>
            <geoform>Microsoft Access database</geoform>
            <onlink>http://www.nwhc.usgs.gov/</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The LIMS (laboratory information management system) database is a computerized record of specimens - from serum samples to carcasses - sent to the National Wildlife Health Center (NWHC) for processing and diagnostic workup. Data include history and recordkeeping information (identifier numbers, species, sex, submitter information, etc); types of tests run (virology, bacteriology, parasitology, chemistry, etc.) and some test results for heavy metals, particularly lead; and diagnostic results. The diagnostic coding system is based on SNOMED terminology, with certain modifications and additions to fit Center needs. SNOMED, the Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine, is a structured nomenclature and classification of the terminology used in human and veterinary medicine. Terms are assigned in any or all of the following six categories for each diagnosis: topography - detailed anatomic term for the site of interest; morphology - information on the pathogenic change or process associated with the topography; etiology - cause or causal agent of the disease or dysfunction; disease - disease, disease entity or syndrome; link - qualifier to link one diagnosis to another.</abstract>
         <purpose>LIMS is a process-based record of samples sent to NWHC, and includes documentation on how samples and data move through the Center, as well as results information sent back to the submitter and other contacts. It may not be a representative sample of mortality for any particular species or group; however, the database can be used to determine if a disease/syndrome existed. For example, the database can be used to document avian cholera in mallards in California at a particular location or time, but it cannot be used to say that there was more cholera in 1990 than in 1980, since the number of specimens submitted for diagnostic workup does not necessarily reflect the total number of mortalities. Individuals interested in documenting total mortalities should reference the Epizootiological Database (EPIZOO), also maintained at NWHC.</purpose>
         <supplinf>LIMSs not currently accessible outside NWHC. However, with assistance from
appropriate Center personnel, searches of the database will be performed on request to the system manager. A complete system overhaul, including interfaces to other portions of the overall NWHC wildlife mortality database e.g. EPIZOO) is in the planning stage.

This dataset is not for a single research project, with a study plan, a defined time frame, and a finite number of options for collecting, storing and analyzing data.  This is a long term dataset documenting wildlife mortality and has been growing, changing and evolving over the last 40 years.  The number of people involved in providing and processing information over the years reaches into the thousands.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>19750701</begdate>
               <enddate>Present</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>In work</progress>
         <update>continually</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <descgeog>Range includes 50 U.S. states, 1 federal district, and all U.S. dependent areas (in the Caribbean and the Pacific Ocean). Irregular submissions have been received from other areas, primarily Canada.</descgeog>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>144.616667</westbc>
            <eastbc>-64.566667</eastbc>
            <northbc>71.833333</northbc>
            <southbc>13.233333</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>none</themekt>
            <themekey>wildlife</themekey>
            <themekey>epizootics</themekey>
            <themekey>mortality</themekey>
            <themekey>morbidity</themekey>
            <themekey>diseases</themekey>
            <themekey>avian</themekey>
            <themekey>mammals</themekey>
            <themekey>endangered species</themekey>
            <themekey>birds</themekey>
            <themekey>wildlife health</themekey>
            <themekey>amphibian</themekey>
            <themekey>reptile</themekey>
            <themekey>marine invertebrate</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>none</placekt>
            <placekey>Range includes 50 U.S. states, 1 federal district, and all U.S. dependent areas (in the Caribbean and the Pacific Ocean). Irregular submissions have been received from other areas, primarily Canada.</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <taxonomy>
         <keywtax>
            <taxonkt>Most of the records in this dataset represent specimens covered under the Kingdom Animalia in the Integrated Taxonomic Information System (ITIS, www.itis.gov).  However, ancillary information is available on microbes, plants and fungi where these contributed to or caused morbidity or mortality in the primary specimen of interest.</taxonkt>
            <taxonkey>Algae</taxonkey>
            <taxonkey>Amphibians</taxonkey>
            <taxonkey>Birds</taxonkey>
            <taxonkey>Crustaceans</taxonkey>
            <taxonkey>Fishes</taxonkey>
            <taxonkey>Fungi</taxonkey>
            <taxonkey>Insects</taxonkey>
            <taxonkey>Lichens</taxonkey>
            <taxonkey>Mammals</taxonkey>
            <taxonkey>Mosses</taxonkey>
            <taxonkey>Plants</taxonkey>
            <taxonkey>Protists</taxonkey>
            <taxonkey>Reptiles</taxonkey>
            <taxonkey>Shrubs</taxonkey>
            <taxonkey>Trees</taxonkey>
            <taxonkey>Viruses</taxonkey>
         </keywtax>
         <taxonsys>
            <classsys>
               <classcit>
                  <citeinfo>
                     <origin>Integrated Taxonomic Information System</origin>
                     <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
                     <title>Integrated Taxonomic Information System</title>
                     <geoform>Online repository of taxonomic information</geoform>
                     <onlink>http://www.itis.usda.gov/</onlink>
                  </citeinfo>
               </classcit>
            </classsys>
            <idref>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Sibley, David</origin>
                  <pubdate>2000</pubdate>
                  <title>The Sibley guide to birds</title>
                  <geoform>Microsoft Access database</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>New York, NY</pubplace>
                     <publish>Alfred A. Knopf</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </idref>
            <idref>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Floyd, Ted</origin>
                  <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                  <title>Smithsonian field guide to the birds of North America</title>
                  <geoform>Microsoft Access database</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>New York, NY</pubplace>
                     <publish>HarperCollins</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </idref>
            <idref>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Peterson, Roger Tory</origin>
                  <pubdate>1980</pubdate>
                  <title>Peterson Field Guides: A Field Guide to the Birds: a Completely New Guide to All the Birds of Eastern and Central North America</title>
                  <geoform>Microsoft Access database</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Boston, MA</pubplace>
                     <publish>Houghton Mifflin</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </idref>
            <idref>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Peterson, Roger Tory</origin>
                  <pubdate>1961</pubdate>
                  <title>Peterson Field Guides: A Field Guide to Western Birds</title>
                  <geoform>Microsoft Access database</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Boston, MA</pubplace>
                     <publish>Houghton Mifflin</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </idref>
            <idref>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Conant, Roger</origin>
                  <pubdate>1975</pubdate>
                  <title>Peterson Field Guides: A Field guide to Reptiles and Amphibians: Eastern and Central North America</title>
                  <geoform>Microsoft Access database</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Boston, MA</pubplace>
                     <publish>Houghton Mifflin</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </idref>
            <idref>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>Stebbins, Robert C.</origin>
                  <pubdate>1966</pubdate>
                  <title>Peterson Field Guides: A Field Guide to Western Reptiles and Amphibians</title>
                  <geoform>Microsoft Access database</geoform>
                  <pubinfo>
                     <pubplace>Boston, MA</pubplace>
                     <publish>Houghton Mifflin</publish>
                  </pubinfo>
               </citeinfo>
            </idref>
            <ider>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntperp>
                     <cntper>USGS National Wildlife Health Center personnel</cntper>
                     <cntorg>National Wildlife Health Center</cntorg>
                  </cntperp>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
                     <address>6006 Schroeder Road</address>
                     <city>Madison</city>
                     <state>WI</state>
                     <postal>53711-6223</postal>
                     <country>United States</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>608-270-2400</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>N/A</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </ider>
            <taxonpro>expert advice;;identification keys;;personnel expertise</taxonpro>
            <taxoncom>Species were coded to the lowest taxonomic category possible - since we are dealing with dead animals, in some cases, decomposition only allowed for coding to order or family.  However, in most cases, specimens were coded to genus/species and in some cases to subspecies.  All codes are mapped to ITIS.</taxoncom>
         </taxonsys>
         <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
         </taxoncl>
         <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
         </taxoncl>
         <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Fungi</taxonrv>
         </taxoncl>
         <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Bacteria</taxonrv>
         </taxoncl>
         <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Archaea</taxonrv>
         </taxoncl>
      </taxonomy>
      <accconst>none</accconst>
      <useconst>none</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Jennifer Buckner</cntper>
               <cntorg>National Wildlife Health Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>6006 Schroeder Road</address>
               <city>Madison</city>
               <state>WI</state>
               <postal>53711-6223</postal>
               <country>United States</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>608-270-2443</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>jbuckner@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>Data are verified upon completion by case pathologist. Random subsets of records are verified for all fields on an intermittent basis.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>Values for selected fields are constrained and tested during data entry. When all work is complete, an assigned pathologist/clinician is responsible for reviewing the information, verifying its accuracy, determining a final diagnosis and issuing a final report. A summary of this information is then incorporated into the master file and becomes a part of the permanent record. Various NWHC standard operating procedures are utilized during data processing - interested individuals should reference the NWHC SOP manual for specifics. Contact the PROCESS CONTACT listed below for additional information.</logic>
      <complete>LIMS is a computerized record of samples sent to NWHC for diagnostic evaluation; it may
not be a representative sample of mortality for any particular species or group. The number
of specimens submitted for diagnostic workup does not reflect the total number of
mortalities. Individuals interested in documenting total mortalities should reference the
Wildlife Mortality Event Database (EPIZOO), also maintained at NWHC.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <method>
            <methtype>Field and Lab</methtype>
            <methdesc>Specimens are submitted to NWHC to determine cause of death.  Personnel from various laboratories run series of tests to isolate and identify causative factors in the mortality.  Each group - field investigations, necropsy, microbiology, virology, chemistry, parasitology, histology - has internal protocols for handling specimens and running particular tests. </methdesc>
            <methcite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>USGS National Wildlife Health Center</origin>
                  <pubdate>Unpublished material</pubdate>
                  <title>Necro-SOP-001-1 Necropsy Suite Operations &amp; Safety</title>
                  <geoform>Word document</geoform>
               </citeinfo>
            </methcite>
         </method>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Partners and submitters contact trained wildlife disease specialists at NWHC to discuss wildlife mortality and specimen submission. Wildlife specimens are accepted based on _____ criteria, received and logged into the system, then routed for diagnostic evaluation. At each step (necropsy, lab work, records), additional data is both manually and electronically incorporated into the file. Once all tests are complete, an assigned pathologist/clinician is responsible for reviewing the information, verifying its accuracy, determining a final diagnosis, and issuing a final report. A summary of this information is then incorporated into the master file and becomes a part of the permanent record. Various NWHC standard operating procedures are utilized during data; processing - interested individuals should reference the NWHC SOP manual for specifics. Contact the PROCESS CONTACT listed below for additional information.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Not complete</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <indspref>INCITS 38:2009 U.S. state codes
INCITS 31:2009 U.S. county codes
SCCAI 2011 for international country codes and Canadian 2nd and 3rd geographic entities (based on ISO 3166-1)</indspref>
   </spdoinfo>
   <eainfo>
      <overview>
         <eaover>A complete description of the data set is provided in the document referenced in 5.2.2 (Diagnostic Database Coding Dictionary), including field lengths, descriptions and attribute value indicators.</eaover>
         <eadetcit>Cleary, K.R. 1995. Diagnostic Database Coding Dictionary. National Wildlife Health
Center, Madison, WI. 66 pp.</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Jennifer Buckner</cntper>
               <cntorg>USGS National Wildlife Health Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>6006 Schroeder Road</address>
               <city>Madison</city>
               <state>WI</state>
               <postal>53711-6223</postal>
               <country>United States</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>608-270-2443</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>jbuckner@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the National Wildlife Health Center, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a National Wildlife Health Center server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data. The National Wildlife Health Center shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>MDB or ACCDB</formname>
               <formvern>Microsoft Access 2010</formvern>
               <formspec>Windows XP/7 or higher</formspec>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>http://bison.ornl.gov/ipt/archive.do?r=usgs-nwhc-aviancholeraandpox-1975-2014</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None</fees>
      </stdorder>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150224</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
               <cntper>Jennifer Buckner</cntper>
               <cntorg>National Wildlife Health Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Diagnostic Case Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>6006 Schroeder Road</address>
               <city>Madison</city>
               <state>WI</state>
               <postal>53711-6223</postal>
               <country>United States</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>608-270-2443</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>jbuckner@usgs.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
