<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey,  Alaska Science Center Polar Bear Research Program</origin>
            <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
            <title>U.S. Geological Survey Polar Bear Mark-Recapture Records, Alaska Portion of the Southern Beaufort Sea, 2001-2010</title>
            <geoform>tabular digital data</geoform>
            <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7VQ30Q5</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>These data were collected by the U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center, Polar Bear Research Program as part of long-term research on the southern Beaufort Sea polar bear population.</abstract>
         <purpose>These data were compiled for the purpose of estimating annual polar bear survival rates and abundance using Cormack-Jolly-Seber open-population mark-recapture models.</purpose>
         <supplinf>Full citation of publication: Bromaghin, J.F., T.L. McDonald, I. Stirling, A.E. Derocher, E.S. Richardson, E.V. Regehr, D.C. Douglas, G.M. Durner, T.C. Atwood, and S.C. Amstrup. 2015. Polar bear population dynamics in the southern Beaufort Sea during a period of sea ice decline. Ecological Applications.   http://dx.doi.org/10.1890/14-1129.1

See manuscript for all data sources.

Polar bears were captured up to 160 km from the coast in the U.S. portion of the southern Beaufort Sea from late March to early May from 2001 to 2010. The communities of Barrow, Deadhorse, and Kaktovik were used as logistical bases to support field operations, excluding Barrow in 2001 and Kaktovik in 2006. Adult, subadult, and yearling bears were captured using projectile syringes containing the immobilizing drug Telazol™ that were fired from a helicopter. Cubs of the year were manually captured and injected with a light dose of Telazol™ immediately prior to handling. All individuals were given two identifying marks: a unique identification number was tattooed on the inner lip and ear tags, containing the same unique identification number, were placed in both ears. Captures were nonselective with respect to gender and age, however females with radio collars were often targeted for capture in order to retrieve collars. All field procedures were approved by the USGS Alaska Science Center Animal Care and Use Committee.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>2001</begdate>
               <enddate>2010</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>Complete</progress>
         <update>None planned</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <descgeog>Arctic Ocean, southern Beaufort Sea, Alaska</descgeog>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-159.2492167</westbc>
            <eastbc>-139.25235</eastbc>
            <northbc>71.9712</northbc>
            <southbc>69.54198185</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115</themekt>
            <themekey>Biota</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>Integrated Taxonomic Information systems (ITIS)</themekt>
            <themekey>Polar Bear</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>mark-recapture</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>CSAS Biocomplexity Thesaurus</themekt>
            <themekey>survival</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>Integrated Taxonomic Information System (ITIS)</themekt>
            <themekey>Ursus maritimus</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
            <placekey>southern Beaufort Sea</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
            <placekey>Arctic Ocean</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
            <placekey>Alaska</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <taxonomy>
         <keywtax>
            <taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
            <taxonkey>mammals</taxonkey>
         </keywtax>
         <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
            <taxoncl>
               <taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
               <taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
               <taxoncl>
                  <taxonrn>Subphylum</taxonrn>
                  <taxonrv>Vertebrata</taxonrv>
                  <taxoncl>
                     <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
                     <taxonrv>Mammalia</taxonrv>
                     <taxoncl>
                        <taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
                        <taxonrv>Carnivora</taxonrv>
                        <taxoncl>
                           <taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
                           <taxonrv>Ursidae</taxonrv>
                           <taxoncl>
                              <taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
                              <taxonrv>Ursus</taxonrv>
                              <taxoncl>
                                 <taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
                                 <taxonrv>Ursus maritimus Phipps, 1774</taxonrv>
                                 <common>Polar Bear</common>
                              </taxoncl>
                           </taxoncl>
                        </taxoncl>
                     </taxoncl>
                  </taxoncl>
               </taxoncl>
            </taxoncl>
         </taxoncl>
      </taxonomy>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>For purposes of publication or dissemination, citations or credit should be given to the U.S. Geological Survey.

The data are for non-commercial use only. No third party distribution is permitted.

It is strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data to evaluate data set limitations, restrictions or intended use. It is the responsibility of the data user to use the data appropriately and consistent with the limitations of data in general and these data in particular.</useconst>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <attracc>
         <attraccr>Data were proofed and verified.</attraccr>
      </attracc>
      <logic>All or nearly all of these records stem from the physical capture of bears.  However, a small number of bears wearing satellite radio collars/tags may have been located by telemetry and visually observing the bear from the air.  Potential multiple observations of an individual within a calendar year were amalgamated into a single capture record for that year.</logic>
      <complete>A few longitude and latitude measurements are missing because of GPS unit failure. For records missing coordinates, data providers verified that all captures took place in the southern Beaufort Sea, Alaska.</complete>
      <posacc>
         <horizpa>
            <horizpar>+ or - 30 meters.</horizpar>
         </horizpa>
      </posacc>
      <lineage>
         <method>
            <methtype>Field</methtype>
            <methdesc>Mark-recapture</methdesc>
         </method>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Field observation data are entered into a Microsoft Access database from paper field data sheets and are double-checked by a second person.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Tooth aging lab results are received in Excel spreadsheets and are entered into the Microsoft Access database, matching the Bear Id.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Data are exported from the Access database and converted to CSV file.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>An Access database query summed the total hunting hours for each year and the annual sums were added to the data export CSV.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <indspref>Arctic Ocean, southern Beaufort Sea, Alaska</indspref>
      <direct>Point</direct>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <latres>0.00001</latres>
            <longres>0.00001</longres>
            <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
         </geograph>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn>World Geodetic System of 1984</horizdn>
            <ellips>World Geodetic System of 1984</ellips>
            <semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
            <denflat>299.25722210088</denflat>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>Polar Bear Capture Data</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Information about polar bears which were captured as part of the US Geological Survey 2001-2010 Southern Beaufort Sea Alaska Polar Bear study.</enttypd>
            <enttypds>USGS Polar Bear Research Program</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>bear_id</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>A unique international identification number for a bear. A unique identification number was assigned to each bear upon first capture, and used to identify each bear if they were subsequently recaptured. The identification number was tattooed on the bear’s inner lip, and ear tags (containing the same unique identification number) were placed in both ears. If a previously tattooed and ear-tagged bear was recaptured, both the tattoo and ear tag numbers were checked to verify the bear identification number.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS Polar Bear Research Program</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>1737</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>40560</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>Unit-less</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>bear_sex</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The gender of a bear determined visually or genetically. The gender of each bear (including cubs of the year) was determined visually following capture. Samples were collected for genetic analysis which was used to confirm gender and establish a genetic identity. Genetic analysis was performed by a commercial genetics laboratory with extensive experience working with polar bear samples.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS Polar Bear Research Program</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>F, M</edomv>
                  <edomvd>F= Female, M= Male</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>birth_year</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The birth-year of a bear was determined from information on bear age and all births were assumed to occur on 1 January. Ages of bears first captured as dependent young were determined based on their size. Cubs-of-the-year are easily distinguished because of their small size. Yearlings and 2-year-olds are generally one-third and two-thirds the size of their mother, respectively. Ages of bears first captured as independent animals were estimated by counting annuli in a cross section of a vestigial premolar tooth sample performed by either a lab at the University of Alberta or C-D and Associates Biological Consulting. Estimating age from annuli is usually very accurate for young bears, but accuracy may decrease as age increases.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS Polar Bear Research Program</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>1970</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>2010</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>Year</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>cap_year</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The year when a bear was captured.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS Polar Bear Research Program</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>2001</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>2010</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>Year</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>cap_lat</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The latitude measurement of the location where a bear was captured. The latitude measurement was expressed in decimal degree format and collected using a GPS unit in the helicopter. The measurement corresponds to the location where the helicopter landed after the bear succumbed to effects of the immobilizing drug, not to the location of first observation. Typically, the helicopter landed ~ 50 meters from the bear. Missing latitudes have a value of "NA".</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS Polar Bear Research Program</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>69.541982</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>71.9712</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>Decimal degrees (Datum: WGS 1984)</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>cap_lon</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The longitude measurement of the location where a bear was captured. The longitude measurement was expressed in decimal degree format and collected using a GPS unit in the helicopter. The measurement corresponds to the location where the helicopter landed after the bear succumbed to effects of the immobilizing drug, not to the location of first observation. Typically, the helicopter landed ~50 meters from the bear. Missing longitudes have a value of "NA".</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS Polar Bear Research Program</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>-159.2492167</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>-139.25235</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>Decimal degrees (Datum: WGS 1984)</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>cap_radio</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>True/False indicator of whether or not a bear had an active satellite radio collar or satellite radio tag. This was verified at time of deployment or when receiving satellite telemetry. Only adult females were fitted with satellite radio collars. A limited number of ear-tag and glue-to-fur transmitters were deployed on male and female adults and subadults. Glue-to-fur tags remained on individuals for approximately 2 months before dropping off, while most satellite radio collars were programmed to drop off individuals after approximately 14 months. No data were available on the length of time that ear-tag transmitters remained operable. Adult females with satellite radio collars were often targeted for recapture so that collars could be retrieved.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS Polar Bear Research Program</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>TRUE</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The bear had an active satellite  radio collar or satellite radio tag.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>FALSE</edomv>
                  <edomvd>The bear did not have an active satellite radio collar or satellite radio tag.</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>hunt_hours</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>The number of hours spent actively searching for polar bears each year was determined from times recorded on data collection forms while in the field. The number was verified by comparing times on data collection forms to track logs collected from the GPS unit used in the helicopter. The GPS unit collected location data (latitude and longitude) mostly at 30-second intervals while the helicopter was in flight. Following each flight mission, the GPS data were downloaded from the GPS unit to a computer and plotted on a map using standard mapping software. The number does not include time spent ferrying from one logistical base to another, flying directly to logistical bases to refuel or at the end of a flight mission. The number does include any time spent flying over the sea ice and directly from logistical bases to location waypoints to resume following previously detected tracks or to the last known locations of satellite radio collared/tagged individuals only when the flight crew actively searched for bears along the way.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>USGS Polar Bear Research Program</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>The number of hours spent actively searching for polar bears each year was determined from times recorded on data collection forms while in the field.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <overview>
         <eaover>The dataset consists of one file of tabular data. These data include: a unique bear identification, bear sex, birth year, capture year, capture location (latitude and longitude), indicator of satellite radio status, and search effort.</eaover>
         <eadetcit>USGS Polar Bear Research program</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing</addrtype>
               <address>4210 University Drive</address>
               <city>Anchorage</city>
               <state>AK</state>
               <postal>99508</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(907)786-7000</cntvoice>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>CSV (comma separated values) file of U.S. Geological Survey Dataset used in Bromaghin et al. 2015: U.S. Geological Survey Polar Bear Mark-Recapture Records, Alaska Portion of the Southern Beaufort Sea, 2001-2010.</resdesc>
      <distliab>It is strongly recommended that the data described or contained herein be acquired directly from the U. S. Geological Survey and not indirectly through some other sources which may have changed the data in some way. 

The data are released on the condition that neither the U.S. Geological Survey nor the United States Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized use.

No warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data and information on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. Neither the originators of this dataset, nor the U.S. Geological Survey, nor the U.S. Government shall be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. 

Any use of trade, firm or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.

This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and information, and aggregate use with other data and information. These data and any derived products are not legal documents and are not intended to be used as such.</distliab>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20150312</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing</addrtype>
               <address>4210 University Drive</address>
               <city>Anchorage</city>
               <state>AK</state>
               <postal>99508</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>907-786-7000</cntvoice>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
