<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<DIF xmlns="http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/ http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/dif_v9.7.1.xsd">
   <Entry_ID>G02195</Entry_ID>
   <Entry_Title>Arctic Landfast Sea Ice 1953-1998</Entry_Title>
   <Data_Set_Citation>
      <Dataset_Creator>Konig Beatty, C. S.</Dataset_Creator>
      <Dataset_Title>Arctic Landfast Sea Ice 1953-1998</Dataset_Title>
      <Dataset_Release_Date>2012-10-31</Dataset_Release_Date>
      <Dataset_Release_Place>Boulder, Colorado USA</Dataset_Release_Place>
      <Dataset_Publisher>NSIDC: National Snow and Ice Data Center</Dataset_Publisher>
      <Version>1</Version>
      <Dataset_DOI>doi:10.7265/N5ZW1HV4</Dataset_DOI>
      <Online_Resource>http://nsidc.org/data/G02195</Online_Resource>
      <Dataset_Series_Name>G02195</Dataset_Series_Name>
   </Data_Set_Citation>
   <Reference>
      <Author>Konig Beatty, C. S.</Author>
      <Publication_Date>2007</Publication_Date>
      <Title>Arctic Landfast Sea Ice</Title>
      <Series>PhD Thesis, Center for Atmosphere Ocean Science Department of Mathematics New York University</Series>
      <Other_Reference_Details>
         <Type>Literature Citation</Type>
      </Other_Reference_Details>
   </Reference>
   <Personnel>
      <Role>Investigator</Role>
      <First_Name>Christof</First_Name>
      <Middle_Name>S.</Middle_Name>
      <Last_Name>Konig Beatty</Last_Name>
      <Email>Christof.KonigBeatty@uclouvain.be</Email>
      <Contact_Address>
         <Country/>
      </Contact_Address>
   </Personnel>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Oceans</Topic>
      <Term>Sea Ice</Term>
   </Parameters>
   <ISO_Topic_Category>Climatology/Meteorology/Atmosphere</ISO_Topic_Category>
   <Keyword>landfast ice</Keyword>
   <Temporal_Coverage>
      <Start_Date>1953-01-01</Start_Date>
      <Stop_Date>1998-12-31</Stop_Date>
   </Temporal_Coverage>
   <Data_Set_Progress>complete</Data_Set_Progress>
   <Spatial_Coverage>
      <Southernmost_Latitude>55</Southernmost_Latitude>
      <Northernmost_Latitude>90</Northernmost_Latitude>
      <Westernmost_Longitude>-180</Westernmost_Longitude>
      <Easternmost_Longitude>180</Easternmost_Longitude>
   </Spatial_Coverage>
   <Location>
      <Location_Category>Ocean</Location_Category>
      <Location_Type>Arctic Ocean</Location_Type>
      <Location_Subregion1/>
      <Location_Subregion2/>
      <Location_Subregion3/>
      <Detailed_Location/>
   </Location>
   <Data_Resolution>
      <Latitude_Resolution>.2 degrees</Latitude_Resolution>
      <Longitude_Resolution>.2 degrees</Longitude_Resolution>
      <Temporal_Resolution>1 month</Temporal_Resolution>
   </Data_Resolution>
   <Data_Set_Language>English</Data_Set_Language>
   <Data_Center>
      <Data_Center_Name>
         <Short_Name>NOAA</Short_Name>
         <Long_Name>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</Long_Name>
      </Data_Center_Name>
      <Data_Center_URL>http://nsidc.org/noaa/</Data_Center_URL>
      <Personnel>
         <Role>Data Center Contact</Role>
         <First_Name>NOAA</First_Name>
         <Last_Name>User Services</Last_Name>
         <Email>nsidc@nsidc.org</Email>
         <Phone>1-303-492-6199</Phone>
         <Fax>1-303-492-2468</Fax>
         <Contact_Address>
            <Address>National Snow and Ice Data Center</Address>
            <Address>CIRES, 449 UCB</Address>
            <Address>University of Colorado</Address>
            <City>Boulder</City>
            <Province_or_State>CO</Province_or_State>
            <Postal_Code>80309-0449</Postal_Code>
            <Country>USA</Country>
         </Contact_Address>
      </Personnel>
   </Data_Center>
   <Distribution>
      <Distribution_Media>FTP</Distribution_Media>
      <Distribution_Size>233 - 668 MB</Distribution_Size>
      <Distribution_Format>NetCDF</Distribution_Format>
   </Distribution>
   <Reference>D. J. Acheson. 1990. Elementary Fluid Dynamics. Oxford Applied Mathematics and Computing Science Series. Oxford University Press.

Arctic Climate Impact Assessment Modeling and Scenarios Workshop, Stockholm, Sweden, January 19-21 2001. ACIA.

D. G. Barber and J. M. Hanesiak. 2004. Meteorological forcing of sea ice concentrations in the southern Beaufort Sea over the period 1979 to 2000. Journal of Geophysical Research, 109(C06014).

I. Bratchie. 1984. Rheology of an ice-floe field. Annals of Glaciology 5: 23-28.

K. Bryan, S. Manabe, and R. L. Pacanowski. 1975. A global ocean-atmosphere climate model. Part II: The oceanic circulation. Journal of Physical Oceanography 5: 30-46.

W. J. Campbell. 1965. The wind-driven circulation of ice and water in a polar ocean. Journal of Geophysical Research 70: 3279-3301.

MANICE - Manual of Standard Procedures for Observing and Reporting Ice Conditions. 2002. Canadian Ice Service - Environment Canada, 373 Sussex Drive, LaSalle Academy, Block 'E', Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0H3, ninth edition, April 2002.

R. Colony and R. S. 1975. Pritchard. Integration of elastic-plastic constitutive laws. AIDJEX Bulletin 30: 55-80.

M. D. Coon. 1980. A review of AIDJEX modeling. In R. S. Pritchard, editor, Sea ice processes and models. University of Washington Press: 12-25.

M. D. Coon, G. A. Maykut, R. S. Pritchard, and D. A. Rothrock. 1974. Modeling pack ice as an elastic-plastic material. AIDJEX Bulletin 24: 1-105.

D. V. Divine, R. Korsnes, A. P. Makshtas, F. Godtliebsen, and H. Svendsen. 2005. Atmospheric-driven state transfer of shore-fast ice in the northeastern Kara Sea. Journal of Geophysical Research 110(C09013).

J. A. Dumas, G. M. Flato, and R. D. Brown. 2006. Future projections of landfast ice thickness and duration in the Canadian Arctic. Journal of Climate 19: 5175-5189.

D. R. Durran. 1999. Numerical methods for wave equations in geophysical fluid dynamics, volume 32 of Texts in Applied Mathematics. Springer-Verlag New York.

A. I. Felzenbaum. 1961. The theory of steady drift of ice and the calculation of the long period mean drift in the central part of the Arctic Basin. Problems of the North 2: 13-44.

F. Fetterer and V. Troisi. 1997. AARI 10-day Arctic ocean EASE-grid sea ice observations. Boulder, CO, USA: National Snow and Ice Data Center. Digital media.

F. Fetterer and V. Troisi. 1997. Data set documentation to AARI 10-day Arctic ocean EASE-grid sea ice observations. http://nsidc.org/data/docs/daac/nsidc0050_aari_ease_seaice.gd.html.

G. M. Flato and W. D. Hibler. 1992. Modeling pack ice as a cavitating fluid. Journal of Physical Oceanography 22: 626-651.

J. N. Goodier and P. G. Hodge. 1958. Elasticity and Plasticity. Wiley. 

J. M. N. T. Gray and Peter D. Killworth. 1995. Stability of the viscous-plastic sea ice rheology. Journal of Physical Oceanography 25: 971-978.

J. M. N. T. Gray and L. W. Morland. 1994. A two-dimensional model for the dynamics of sea ice. Philosophical Transactions: Physical Sciences and Engineering 347(1682): 219-290.

W. D. Hibler. 1977. A viscous sea ice law as a stochastic average of plasticity. J. Geophys. Res 82(27): 3932-3938.

W. D. Hibler. 1979. A dynamic thermodynamic sea ice model. Journal of Physical Oceanography 9: 815-846.

W. D. Hibler. 1980. Modeling a variable thickness sea ice cover. Monthly Weather Review, 108: 1943-1973.

W. D. Hibler. 1986. Ice dynamics. In The Geophysics of Sea Ice 146 of NATO ASI, Series B, Physics. Norbert Untersteiner, editor. Plenum Press, New York: 577-640. 

W. D. Hibler and E. Schulson. 2000. On modeling anisotropic failure and flow of flawed sea ice. Journal of Geophysical Research 105: 17105-17120.

D. M. Holland. 2006. A 1-d elastic-plastic sea-ice model solved with an implicit Eulerian-Lagrangian method. Ocean Modelling, (accepted).

E. C. Hunke and J. K. Dukowicz. 1997. An elastic-viscous-plastic model for sea ice dynamics. Journal of Physical Oceanography 27: 1849-1867.

C. F. Ip, W. D. Hibler, and G. M. Flato. 1991. On the effect of rheology on seasonal sea-ice simulations. Annals of Glaciology 15: 17-25.

O. M. Johannessen, M. Miles, and E. Bjorgo. 1995. The Arctic's shrinking sea ice. Nature 376: 126-127.

E. Kalnay et al. 1996. The NCEP/NCAR 40-year reanalysis project. Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society 77(3): 437-470.

J. L. Lieser. 2004. A numerical model for short-term sea ice forecasting in the Arctic. PhD thesis, University at Bremen.

R. W. Macdonald, D. W. Paton, E. C. Carmack, and A. Omstedt. 1995. The freshwater budget and under-ice spreading of Mackenzie river water in the Canadian Beaufort Sea based on salinity and 18O/16O measurements in water and ice. Journal of Geophysical Research 100(C1): 895-919.

R. W. Macdonald, E. C. Carmack, and D. W. Paton. 1999. Using the delta 18O composition in landfast ice as a record of Arctic estuarine processes. Marine Chemistry 65: 3-24.

S. Manabe, K. Bryan, and M. J. Spelman. 1979. A global ocean-atmosphere climate model with seasonal variation for future studies of climate sensitivity. Dynamics of Atmospheres and Oceans 3: 393-426.

M. G. McPhee. 1975. Ice-ocean momentum transfer for the AIDJEX ice model. AIDJEX Bulletin 29: 93-111.

J. M. Oberhuber. 1993. Simulation of the Atlantic circulation with a coupled sea icemixed layer-isopycnal general circulation model. Part I: Model description. Journal of Physical Oceanography 23(5): 808-829.

C. L. Parkinson and W. M. Washington. 1979. A large-scale numerical model of sea ice. Journal of Geophysical Research 84: 311-337.

E. P. Popov. Mechanics of materials. 1952. Prentice-Hall., 1952. 

S. J. Prinsenberg, A. Van der Baaren, G. A. Fowler, and I. K. Peterson. 1997. Pack ice stress and convergence measurements by satellite-tracked ice beacons. In OCEANS ’97. MTS/IEEE Conference Proceedings 2: 1283-1289, 6-9 Oct 1997.

R. S. Pritchard. 2001. Long-term sea ice dynamics simulations using an elastic-plastic constitutive law. Journal of Geophysical Research 106(C12): 31333-31344.

R. S. Pritchard. 1975. An elastic-plastic constitutive law for sea ice. Journal of Applied Mechanics 42E: 379-384.

D. A. Rothrock. 1975. The mechanical behavior of pack ice. Annual Review of Earth and Planetary Sciences 3: 317-342.

D. A. Rothrock, Y. Yu, and G. A. Maykut. 1999. Thinning of the Arctic sea-ice cover. Geophysical Research Letters 26(23): 3469-3472.

S. Rysgaard, T. G. Nielsen, and B. W. Hansen. 1999. Seasonal variation in nutrients, pelagic primary production and grazing in a high-Arctic coastal marine ecosystem, Young Sound, Northeast Greenland. Marine Ecology Progress Series 179: 13-25.

Colón Pablo Clemente-Colón</Reference>
   <Summary>
      <Abstract>The files in this data set contain landfast sea ice data (monthly means) gathered from both Russian Arctic and Antarctic Research Institute (AARI) and Canadian Ice Service (CIS) sources.  Details on processing and treatment are given in the contributor's PhD thesis (Konig 2007), provided through the PhD Thesis link above.   The data are provided in netCDF format. 

The time span over which data are available is split into 3 ranges: for 1953-1967 there are only AARI data, for 1968-1990 both AARI and CIS data are available, and from 1991-1998 only CIS data are available. 

There are a total of six files: two for the 1953-1967 data, two for the 1968-1990 data, and two for the 1991-1998 data. There are two files for each range because the files with "_noNaN" in their names contain "-1000" as the missing value, and the other files use "nan" as the missing value. Otherwise the data in those files are identical. 

AARI data were obtained from NSIDC data set AARI 10-Day Arctic Ocean EASE-Grid Sea Ice Observations (Fetterer and Troisi, 1997) that was later replaced by Sea Ice Charts of the Russian Arctic in Gridded Format, 1933-2006 (AARI, 2007).

Fetterer, F., and V. Troisi. 1997. AARI 10-Day Arctic Ocean EASE-Grid Sea Ice Observations. Boulder, CO, USA: National Snow and Ice Data Center. http://nsidc.org/data/nsidc-0050.html.

Arctic and Antarctic Research Institute. 2007. Sea ice charts of the Russian Arctic in gridded format, 1933-2006. Edited and compiled by V. Smolyanitsky, V. Borodachev, A. Mahoney, F. Fetterer, and R. Barry. Boulder, Colorado USA: National Snow and Ice Data Center. http://nsidc.org/data/g02176.html.

Notice to Data Users: The documentation for this data set was provided solely by the contributor and was not further developed, thoroughly reviewed, or edited by NSIDC. Thus, support for this data set may be limited.</Abstract>
   </Summary>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>VIEW RELATED INFORMATION</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>http://nsidc.org/data/docs/noaa/g02195-fastice/arctic_landfast_sea_ice_thesis.pdf</URL>
      <Description>Documentation</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>GET DATA</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>ftp://sidads.colorado.edu/pub/DATASETS/NOAA/G02195/</URL>
      <Description>FTP</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>VIEW RELATED INFORMATION</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>http://nsidc.org/data/nsidc-0050.html</URL>
      <Description> AARI 10-Day Arctic Ocean EASE-Grid Sea Ice Observations</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>VIEW RELATED INFORMATION</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>http://nsidc.org/data/g02176.html</URL>
      <Description>Sea ice charts of the Russian Arctic in gridded format, 1933-2006</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Metadata_Name>CEOS IDN DIF</Metadata_Name>
   <Metadata_Version>VERSION 9.9</Metadata_Version>
   <DIF_Creation_Date>2012-10-31</DIF_Creation_Date>
   <Last_DIF_Revision_Date>2015-09-11</Last_DIF_Revision_Date>
   <DIF_Revision_History> 2012-11-08,  Minor edits to the summary. No QC needed.
 2012-10-31
 2012-10-31, New data set.
 2012-11-09,  Author got married so I had to update last name. No QC needed.
 2013-03-12, Amy Randall,  Added DOI to metadata record
 2013-10-14, Deann Miller, Fixed documentation link for search.
 2014-02-11, Deann Miller,  Catalog page wasn't showing, getting error message because there was no author listed for the literature citation.
 2015-09-11, Ann Windnagel,  Added the spatial resolution units to the spatial resolution X and Y boxes, and removed the erroneous units from the Parameter Units box. No QC needed.
</DIF_Revision_History>
   <Extended_Metadata>
      <Metadata>
         <Group>NSIDC</Group>
         <Name>Version Summary</Name>
         <Value/>
      </Metadata>
      <Metadata>
         <Group>NSIDC</Group>
         <Name>Current Version</Name>
         <Value>1</Value>
      </Metadata>
   </Extended_Metadata>
</DIF>
