<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<DIF xmlns="http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/ http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/dif_v9.7.1.xsd">
   <Entry_ID>GGD294</Entry_ID>
   <Entry_Title>Active layer and borehole temperatures from La Foppa rock glaciers, Val Vallaccia, Central Italian Alps</Entry_Title>
   <Data_Set_Citation>
      <Dataset_Title>Active layer and borehole temperatures from La Foppa rock glaciers, Val Vallaccia, Central Italian Alps</Dataset_Title>
      <Dataset_Release_Date>2003-06-18</Dataset_Release_Date>
      <Version>1</Version>
      <Online_Resource>http://nsidc.org/data/GGD294</Online_Resource>
      <Dataset_Series_Name>GGD294</Dataset_Series_Name>
   </Data_Set_Citation>
   <Personnel>
      <Role>Investigator</Role>
      <Last_Name/>
      <Contact_Address>
         <Address>Via Milano</Address>
         <City>Bormio (SO)</City>
         <Country>Italy</Country>
      </Contact_Address>
   </Personnel>
   <Personnel>
      <Role>Investigator</Role>
      <First_Name>Mauro</First_Name>
      <Last_Name>Guglielmin</Last_Name>
      <Email>mauro.guglielmin@uninsubria.it</Email>
      <Phone>39 2 67655152</Phone>
      <Contact_Address>
         <City>Varese</City>
         <Postal_Code>21110</Postal_Code>
         <Country>Italy</Country>
      </Contact_Address>
   </Personnel>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Cryosphere</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Permafrost</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Land Surface</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Permafrost</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Cryosphere</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Rock Glaciers</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Land Surface</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Rock Glaciers</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Cryosphere</Topic>
      <Term>Snow/Ice</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Snow/Ice Temperature</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Cryosphere</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Soil Temperature</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Land Surface</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Soil Temperature</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Keyword>Boreholes</Keyword>
   <Keyword>BTS Measurements</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Continuous Permafrost</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Discontinuous Permafrost</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Meteorology</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Rock Glaciers</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Soil Temperature</Keyword>
   <Temporal_Coverage>
      <Start_Date>1993-01-01</Start_Date>
   </Temporal_Coverage>
   <Spatial_Coverage>
      <Southernmost_Latitude>46.5</Southernmost_Latitude>
      <Northernmost_Latitude>46.5</Northernmost_Latitude>
      <Westernmost_Longitude>10</Westernmost_Longitude>
      <Easternmost_Longitude>10</Easternmost_Longitude>
   </Spatial_Coverage>
   <Location>
      <Location_Category>Continent</Location_Category>
      <Location_Type>Europe</Location_Type>
      <Location_Subregion1>Southern Europe</Location_Subregion1>
      <Location_Subregion2>Italy</Location_Subregion2>
      <Location_Subregion3/>
      <Detailed_Location>Val Vallaccia, Central Italian Alps, Italy</Detailed_Location>
   </Location>
   <Data_Set_Language>English</Data_Set_Language>
   <Data_Center>
      <Data_Center_Name>
         <Short_Name>FGDC</Short_Name>
         <Long_Name>Frozen Ground Data Center</Long_Name>
      </Data_Center_Name>
      <Data_Center_URL>http://nsidc.org/fgdc/</Data_Center_URL>
      <Personnel>
         <Role>Data Center Contact</Role>
         <First_Name>FGDC</First_Name>
         <Last_Name>User Services</Last_Name>
         <Email>nsidc@nsidc.org</Email>
         <Phone>1-303-492-6199</Phone>
         <Fax>1-303-492-2468</Fax>
         <Contact_Address>
            <Address>National Snow and Ice Data Center</Address>
            <Address>CIRES, 449 UCB</Address>
            <Address>University of Colorado</Address>
            <City>Boulder</City>
            <Province_or_State>CO</Province_or_State>
            <Postal_Code>80309-0449</Postal_Code>
            <Country>USA</Country>
         </Contact_Address>
      </Personnel>
   </Data_Center>
   <Distribution>
      <Distribution_Format>Microsoft Excel</Distribution_Format>
   </Distribution>
   <Reference>Calderoni, G., Guglielmin, M., Lozej, A., Tellini, C. 1993. Researches on rock glaciers in the Italian Central Alps (Valtellina, Sondrio, Italia). International Conference on Permafrost, VI, Beijing. Proceedings, vol. 1, p. 72-77. Cannone, N., Guglielmi, M, Smiraglia, C. (1995): Rapporti tra vegetazione e permafrost discontinuo in ambiente alpino. Val Vallaccia (Livigno, Sondrio). Rivista Geografica Italiana, 102, 91-111. Guglielmin, M. (1997): Periglacial Phenomena, permafrost
      distribution and glacial evolution in Foscagno area, Livigno (SO), Italy, In IV Intern. Conference on Geomorphology, Italy, 1997 -Guide for the excursion- Mountain permafrostand slope stability in the periglacial belt of the Alps', Suppl. Geogr. Fis. Dinam. Quat. 193, 195-199. Guglielmin, M. con contributi di A. Notarpietro (1997) Il Permafrost Alpino. Concetti, morfologia e metodi di individuazione (con tre indagini esemplificative in Alta Valtellina). Quaderni di Geodinamica alpina e
      Quaternaria, CNR, 5, 117 pp. Guglielmi, M. (1989): I rock glacier del Passo del Foscagno (Alta Valtellina, Sondrio). Natura Bresciana, 26, 35-47. Guglielmin, M., Lozej, A., Tellini, C. 1994. Permafrost distribution and rock glaciers in the Livigno area (Northern Italy). Permafrost and Periglacial Processes, 5, p. 1-12. Guglielmin, M. and Tellini, C. (1995) Relazioni tra permafrost alpino e copertura nevosa: risultati preliminari (area del Foscagno, Sondrio, Italia). Geogr. Fis. Dinam.
      Quat. 18, 25-29. Guglielmin, M., Rossettin G. and Tellini, C. (1997) Perg?lisol alpin et variations climatiques dans les Alpes Centrales (valtellina, Italie), IV Intern. Conf. On Geomorphology, Abstract, Suppl. Geogr. Fis. Din. Quat., III, 1, 192, Submitted to Arctic and Alpine Research. Guglielmin, M., Smiraglia, C. and Cannone, N. (1997) The rock glaciers of the Lombardy Alps (Italy) as indicators of mountain permafrost, IV Intern. Conf. On Geomorphology, Abstract, Suppl. Geogr. Fis.
      Din. Quat., III, 1, 193, Submitted to Geomorphology. Guglielmin, M. and Tellini, C. (1994): Rilevamento del permafrost con il metodo BTS (Bottom Temperature of the Winter Snow Cover) nell'alta Valtellina (Sondrio, ITALIA).- Geogr. Fis. Din. Quat., 17, 47-54. Guglielmin, M. and Tellini, C. (1993): First example of permafrost mapping with BTS in the Italian Alps (Livigno, Sondrio, Italy). Acta Naturalia, 29, 1/2, 39-46. Guglielmin, M. and C. Tellini. 1992. Contributo alla conoacenza dei rock
      glaciers delle Alpi Italiane. I rock glaciers del Livignasco (Alta Valtellina, Sondrio). Riv. Geogr. It., 99, p. 395-414. Lozej, A. and Guglielmin, M. 1992. Prospezioni geoelettriche sul rock glacier de 'La Foppa', Livigno, Sondrio (Italia). GEAM- Boll. Ass. Min. Subalp., XXIV, 4, dicembre, p. 373-382.</Reference>
   <Summary>
      <Abstract>The La Foppa site is a glacial cirque located in the upper part of the Val Vallaccia, near Livigno, in the Italian Central Alps. The La Foppa cirque is characterized by five rock glaciers, of which four are active and one is of uncertain activity or is inactive. These rock glaciers, especially the two largest, named La Foppa I and La Foppa II, have been the subject of geophysical investigations (Lozej and Guglielmin, 1992; Guglielmin et al., 1994; Guglielmin 1997) including BTS
       measurements (bottom temperature of snow; more than 70 measurements between 1990 and 1993) and STG measurements (shallow temperature of ground in summer) (Calderoni et al. 1993; Guglielmin and Tellini 1992, 1994; Guglielmin 1997). The distribution of BTS and STG measurements indicate that above 2800 asl the permafrost is continuous whereas below this elevation it is constrained inside the rock glaciers, where it is not continuous. Three boreholes have been established. One is in the
       frontal part of La Foppa I where the BTS values are always lower than -3 degrees C, and where the active layer detected with vertical electrical soundings (V.E.S.) ranges from 0.8 to 2.7 meters. The second borehole is in the central part of La Foppa I, where the BTS values range between -0.5 and -2.1 degrees C, and the V.E.S. indicate an active layer of 3 - 5.5 meters thick. The third borehole is located on the moraine ridge (of Late Glacial age) at 10 meters of the lateral slope of La
       Foppa I that overlaps the moraine ridge. Here the BTS values and V.E.S. point out the absence of permafrost. Near the third borehole there is a meteorological station that measures air temperature at 4 meters above the ground, snow cover, snow temperature every 20 cm up to 420 cm, precipitation, wind speed and direction, atmospheric pressure, relative humidity, and soil temperature at 2 and 30 cm depth. Borehole data are recorded on data loggers. A sample of the data is presented on the
       CAPS Version 1.0 CD-ROM. In this data file, data values must be divided by 10 to obtain the correct value.</Abstract>
   </Summary>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>VIEW RELATED INFORMATION</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>http://nsidc.org/data/docs/fgdc/ggd294_boreholes_italy/index.html</URL>
      <Description>Documentation</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>GET DATA</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>mailto:mauro.guglielmin@uninsubria.it</URL>
      <Description>Get External Data</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Metadata_Name>CEOS IDN DIF</Metadata_Name>
   <Metadata_Version>VERSION 9.9</Metadata_Version>
   <DIF_Creation_Date>2003-06-18</DIF_Creation_Date>
   <Last_DIF_Revision_Date>2012-09-18</Last_DIF_Revision_Date>
   <DIF_Revision_History> 2003-06-18, yohe, 2003-12-04, yohe, 2004-01-27, yohe, 2010-03-01, Deann Miller, Fixed References section. Some of the citations were running together. Fixed per the GCMD. 2012-08-23, Deann Miller, updated Access Data URL to email PI. This is a brokered data set 2012-09-18, Deann Miller, added dist. format </DIF_Revision_History>
   <Extended_Metadata>
      <Metadata>
         <Group>NSIDC</Group>
         <Name>Version Summary</Name>
         <Value/>
      </Metadata>
      <Metadata>
         <Group>NSIDC</Group>
         <Name>Current Version</Name>
         <Value>1</Value>
      </Metadata>
   </Extended_Metadata>
</DIF>
