<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<DIF xmlns="http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/ http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/dif_v9.7.1.xsd">
   <Entry_ID>GGD220</Entry_ID>
   <Entry_Title>Meteorology and soil temperatures, Hot Weather Creek, Ellesmere Island, NWT, Canada</Entry_Title>
   <Data_Set_Citation>
      <Dataset_Creator>Altl, B.T</Dataset_Creator>
      <Dataset_Title>Meteorology and soil temperatures, Hot Weather Creek, Ellesmere Island, NWT, Canada</Dataset_Title>
      <Dataset_Release_Date>1998-01-01</Dataset_Release_Date>
      <Dataset_Release_Place>Boulder, Colorado USA</Dataset_Release_Place>
      <Dataset_Publisher>NSIDC: National Snow and Ice Data Center</Dataset_Publisher>
      <Version>1</Version>
      <Online_Resource>http://nsidc.org/data/GGD220</Online_Resource>
      <Dataset_Series_Name>GGD220</Dataset_Series_Name>
   </Data_Set_Citation>
   <Personnel>
      <Role>Investigator</Role>
      <First_Name>Claude L.</First_Name>
      <Last_Name>Labine</Last_Name>
      <Email>clabine@ibm.net</Email>
      <Phone>1-403-454-2505</Phone>
      <Fax>1-403-454-2655</Fax>
      <Contact_Address>
         <Address>11564-149 St.</Address>
         <City>Edmonton</City>
         <Province_or_State>Alberta</Province_or_State>
         <Postal_Code>T5M 1W7</Postal_Code>
         <Country>Canada</Country>
      </Contact_Address>
   </Personnel>
   <Personnel>
      <Role>Investigator</Role>
      <First_Name>Bea Taylor</First_Name>
      <Last_Name>Alt</Last_Name>
      <Email>bea@freenet.carleton.ca</Email>
      <Phone>1-613-822-2562</Phone>
      <Fax>1-613-822-1537</Fax>
      <Contact_Address>
         <Address>5034 Lentrim Road</Address>
         <City>Carlsbad Springs</City>
         <Province_or_State>Ontario</Province_or_State>
         <Postal_Code>K0A 1K0</Postal_Code>
         <Country>Canada</Country>
      </Contact_Address>
   </Personnel>
   <Personnel>
      <Role>Investigator</Role>
      <First_Name>Kathy</First_Name>
      <Last_Name>Young</Last_Name>
      <Email>klyoung@yorku.ca</Email>
      <Contact_Address>
         <Address>Hamilton, ON L8S 4L</Address>
         <City>Hamilton</City>
         <Province_or_State>Ontario</Province_or_State>
         <Postal_Code>L8S 4K1</Postal_Code>
         <Country>Canada</Country>
      </Contact_Address>
   </Personnel>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Atmosphere</Topic>
      <Term>Atmospheric Radiation</Term>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Cryosphere</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Permafrost</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Land Surface</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Permafrost</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Cryosphere</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Soil Temperature</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Land Surface</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Soil Temperature</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Keyword>Air Temperature</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Climate Change</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Meteorology</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Snow</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Soil Temperature</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Solar Radiation</Keyword>
   <Temporal_Coverage>
      <Start_Date>1988-06-01</Start_Date>
      <Stop_Date>1994-04-30</Stop_Date>
   </Temporal_Coverage>
   <Spatial_Coverage>
      <Southernmost_Latitude>79.965</Southernmost_Latitude>
      <Northernmost_Latitude>79.965</Northernmost_Latitude>
      <Westernmost_Longitude>-84.442</Westernmost_Longitude>
      <Easternmost_Longitude>-84.442</Easternmost_Longitude>
   </Spatial_Coverage>
   <Location>
      <Location_Category>Continent</Location_Category>
      <Location_Type>North America</Location_Type>
      <Location_Subregion1>Canada</Location_Subregion1>
      <Location_Subregion2/>
      <Location_Subregion3/>
      <Detailed_Location>Hot Weather Creek Plateau Site, Fosheim Peninsula,</Detailed_Location>
   </Location>
   <Data_Set_Language>English</Data_Set_Language>
   <Data_Center>
      <Data_Center_Name>
         <Short_Name>FGDC</Short_Name>
         <Long_Name>Frozen Ground Data Center</Long_Name>
      </Data_Center_Name>
      <Data_Center_URL>http://nsidc.org/fgdc/</Data_Center_URL>
      <Personnel>
         <Role>Data Center Contact</Role>
         <First_Name>FGDC</First_Name>
         <Last_Name>User Services</Last_Name>
         <Email>nsidc@nsidc.org</Email>
         <Phone>1-303-492-6199</Phone>
         <Fax>1-303-492-2468</Fax>
         <Contact_Address>
            <Address>National Snow and Ice Data Center</Address>
            <Address>CIRES, 449 UCB</Address>
            <Address>University of Colorado</Address>
            <City>Boulder</City>
            <Province_or_State>CO</Province_or_State>
            <Postal_Code>80309-0449</Postal_Code>
            <Country>USA</Country>
         </Contact_Address>
      </Personnel>
   </Data_Center>
   <Distribution>
      <Distribution_Media>FTP</Distribution_Media>
      <Distribution_Format>ASCII Text (.txt)</Distribution_Format>
   </Distribution>
   <Reference>Alt, B.T., Labine, C.L., Headley, A., Koerner, R.M., and Edlund, S.A. 1992a. High Arctic IRMA (Integrated Research and Monitoring Area) automatic weather station field data 1990-91, Parts 1&amp;amp;2; Geological Survey of Canada, Open File 2562. Alt, B.T., Labine, C.L., Headley, A., Koerner, R.M., and Edlund, S.A. 1992b. High Arctic IRMA (Integrated Research and Monitoring Area) automatic weather station field data 1990-91, Part 3; Geological Survey of Canada, Open File 2562.
      Alt, B.T., and Maxwell, B.1990. The Queen Elizabeth Islands. A case study for Arctic climate data availability and regional climate analysis; in Canada's Missing Dimension. Science and History in the Canadian Arctic Islands, (ed.) C.R. Harington, v. 1, p. 294 - 326. Bourgeois, J., Edlund, S.A., Koerner, R.M., Fisher, D.A., Alt, B.T., Garneau, M., Peters, B., Labine, C., Robinson, S.D., Woo, M.-K., Hamilton, P., Pollard, W.H., and Lewkowicz, A.G . 1993. Cooperative work in the high Arctic
      IRMA (Integrated Research and Monitoring Area); Abstract, Geological Survey of Canada, Geoscience Forum 1993. Burn, C.R. and Lewkowicz, A.G.1990. Canadian landforms examples - 17 retrogressive thaw slumps; Canadian Geographer, v. 34, no. 3, p. 273 - 276. Edlund, S.A. 1989a. Vegetation indicates potentially unstable Arctic terrain; GEOS, v. 18, p. 9 - 13. Edlund, S.A. 1989b. Vegetation patterns assist in identifying potentially thaw-sensitive terrain on central Ellesmere Island, Arctic
      Canada; Abstract; Proceedings, 40th Arctic Science Conference, Fairbanks, Alaska, 14 - 16 September 1989, 24 p. Edlund, S.A. 1989c. The coincidence of regional vegetation distribution patterns and summer temperatures in Arctic Canada; Abstract of poster; Proceedings, 40th Arctic Science Conference, Fairbanks, Alaska, 14 -16 September 1989, 53 p. Edlund, S.A. 1990a. Arctic bioclimate indicators, a key to understanding northern paleoenvironments; abstract; GSC Forum of Activities. Edlund,
      S.A. 1990b. Woody plants as bioclimatic indicators in Arctic Canada; abstract; Proceedings, Symposium, Climate of Northern Latitudes-- Past, Present and Future; University of Tromso, Tromso, Norway, April 2-4, 1990. Edlund, S.A. 1990c. Bioclimatic zones in the Canadian Arctic Archipelago; in Canada's Missing Dimension Science and History in the Canadian Arctic Islands, (ed.) C.R. Harington; v. 1, p. 421 - 441. Edlund, S.A., Alt, B.T., Harry, D.G., and Luckman, B.H. 1989a. Plant
      distribution indicators of potential terrain instability (abstract); Program with abstracts, Geological Survey of Canada, Forum 1989, Ottawa. Edlund, S.A., Alt, B.T., Harry, D.G., and Luckman, B.H. 1989b. Plant distribution indicators of potential terrain instability; Abstract; Geological Survey of Canada, Forum 1989. Edlund, S.A., Alt, B., Taylor, A.E., and Young, K.L. 1990. Multidisciplinary research in the intermontane zone of Ellesemere Island, N.W.T. (abstract); Program with
      abstracts, Geological Survey of Canada, Forum 1990, Ottawa. Edlund, S.A., Alt, B.T., and Young, K.L. 1989a. Interaction of climate, vegetation, and soil hydrology at Hot Weather Creek, Fosheim Peninsula, Ellesmere Island, Northwest Territories; Current Research, Part D, Geological Survey of Canada, Paper 89-1D, p. 125 - 133. Edlund, S.A., Alt, B.T., and Young, K.L. 1989b. Vegetation, hydrology and climate at Hot Weather Creek, Ellesmere Island, Northwest Territories; Abstract; Program,
      Canadian Committee on Climate Fluctuations and Man, Annual Meeting, Ottawa, Ontario, 25-27 January 1989, CCCFM Newsletter, v. 5, p. 65. Edlund, S.A., Alt, B.T., and Young, K.L. 1989c. Vegetation indicates potentially unstable Arctic terrain; GEOS, v. 18, no. 3, p. 9 -13. Edlund, S.A., Woo, M.-K., and Young, K.L. 1990a. Climate, hydrology and vegetation patterns Hot Weather Creek, Ellesmere Island, Arctic Canada; Nordic Hydrology, v. 21, p. 273 - 286. Edlund, S.A., Woo, M.-K., and Young,
      K.L. 1990b. Vegetation patterns, climate and hydrology at Hot Weather Creek, Ellesmere Island, Arctic Canada; Journal of Nordic Hydrology, v. 15, no. 4. Edlund, S.A., Woo, M.-K., Young, K.L., Alt, B.T., and Headley, A.N. 1991. Three years of environmental monitoring at GSC's global change observatory, Hot Weather Creek, Ellesmere Island; Abstract; Geological Survey of Canada, Forum 1991. Edlund, S.A., Young, K.L., and Woo, M.-K. 1990. Aspects of vegetation and soil hydrology of Hot Weather
      Creek, Ellesmere Island, Arctic Canada; Abstract, Proceedings, Eighth International Northern Regions Basin Symposium and Workshop, Abisko, Sweden. Egginton, P.A., and Hodgson, D.A. 1990. Preliminary assessment of selected drainage basins in western Fosheim Peninsula, Ellesmere Island, as sites for global change studies; Current Research, Part D, Geological Survey of Canada, Paper 90-1D, p. 71 - 77. Fyles, J.G. 1989. High terrace sediments of Neogene age, west central Ellesmere Island,
      Northwest Territories; Current Research Part D, Geological Survey of Canada, Paper 89-1D, p. 101 - 104. Garneau, M. editor. in press. The High Arctic Global Change Observatory of the Geological Survey of Canada-- 5 years of multidisciplinary research on the Climate Change Program. Geological Survey of Canada Bulletin, Geological Survey of Canada, Ottawa, includes Introduction, 19 papers, Conclusions and 9 appendices. Hamilton, P.B., and Edlund, S.A. 1994. Occurrence of Prasiola fluviatilis
      (Chlorophyta) on Ellesmere Island in the Canadian Arctic; J. Phycol., v. 30, p. 217 - 221. Headley, A. 1990. A comparison of wind speeds recorded simultaneously at three metres and ten metres above ground; Canadian Climate Centre, Atmospheric Environment Service, Report No. 90 - 1, 36 p. Hodgson, D. A. 1985. The last glaciation of west-central Ellesmere Island, Arctic Archipelago, Canada; Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences, v. 22, no. 3, p. 347 - 368. Heron, R., and Woo, M.-K. 1978.
      Snowmelt computation for a high Arctic site; Proceedings of the 35th Eastern Snow Conference, p.162 - 172. Hodgson, D.A., and Edlund, S.A. 1978. Surficial materials and biophysical regions, eastern Queen Elizabeth Islands, part II; Geological Survey of Canada Open File, Open File 501. Hodgson, D.A., St-Onge, D.A., and Edlund, S.A. 1991. Surficial materials of Hot Weather Creek basin, Ellesmere Island, Northwest Territories; Current Research, Part E, Geological Survey of Canada, Paper
      91-1E, p. 157 - 163. Labine, C.L., Alt, B.A., Atkinson, D., Headley, A., Koerner, R.M., Edlund, S.A., and Waszkiewicz, M. 1994 High Arctic IRMA automatic weather station field data 1991 - 1992. Part 1-- Documentation, Part 2-- Plots; GSC Open File Report 2898. Lewkowicz, A.G. 1989. Active-layer detachments on the Fosheim Peninsula, Ellesmere Island-- the importance of the summer of 1988; Canadian Association of Geographers, Ontario Division Conference, University of Guelph, October, 1989.
      Lewkowicz, A.G. 1990a. Frequency and magnitude of active-layer detachments on the Fosheim Peninsula, Ellesmere Island-- past, present and future. Abstract.; 19th Annual Arctic Workshop, Institute for Arctic and Alpine Research, University of Colorado, March 1990. Lewkowicz, A.G. 1990b. Morphology, frequency and magnitude of active-layer detachment slides, Fosheim Peninsula, Ellesmere Island, N.W.T.; Permafrost-Canada, Proceedings of the Fifth Canadian Permafrost Conference, Quebec City,
      June 1990, Universite Laval, Quebec, p. 111 - 118. Lewkowicz, A.G. 1990c. Active-layer detachments, Fosheim Peninsula, Ellesmere Island. Abstract; Canadian Association of Geographers, Annual Meeting, University of Alberta, June 1990. Lewkowicz, A.G.1990d. Climatic change and permafrost slope processes. Abstract.; Canadian Association of Geographers, Annual Meeting, University of Alberta, June 1990. Lewkowicz, A.G. 1992. Slope hummocks on Fosheim Peninsula, Ellesmere Island; Current
      Research, Part B; Geological Survey of Canada, Paper 92-1B. Lewkowicz, A.G., and Wolfe, P.M.1994. Sediment transport in Hot Weather Creek, Ellesmere Island, Canada; Arctic and Alpine Research, 26, 213-226. Luckman, B.H., Edlund, S.A., and Harry, D.G. 1988. Active-layer detachments during late summer, 1988, Fosheim Peninsula, Ellesmere Island; CAGONT `88 Permafrost Abstracts; Program and Abstracts; Annual meeting Canadian Association of Geographers Ontario Division, 13 p. Luckman, B.H.,
      Harry, D.G., Edlund, S.A., and Alt, B. 1989. Global change, ground ice and geomorphic processes-- some observations from the Fosheim Peninsula, Ellesmere Island, N.W.T., Canada; Abstracts, 18th Annual Arctic Workshop, April 13-15, 1989, Global environmental change and the Arctic, Lethbridge, Alberta. Peters, B., and Headley, A. 1992. A comparison of winds at Hot Weather Creek and Eureka, N.W.T.; Canadian Climate Centre, Atmospheric Environment Service, Report No. 92 - 2, 22 p. Pollard,
      W.H. 1991. Observations on massive ground ice on Fosheim Peninsula, Ellesmere Island, Northwest Territories; Current Research, Part E, Geological Survey of Canada, Paper 91-1E, p. 223 - 231. Sutherland, P.D. 1984. A reassessment of Independence I.-- Some observations from the Eureka Upland, high Arctic Canada; Abstract, 17th Annual Meeting of the Canadian Archaeological Association, Victoria. Sutherland, P.D. 1989. An inventory and assessment of the prehistoric archaeological resources of
      Ellesmere Island National Park Reserve; Canadian Parks Service. Sutherland, P.D. 1990. A piece of the paleoeskimo mosaic-- continuity and change on northern Ellesmere Island; Abstract, 23rd Annual Meeting of the Canadian Archaeological Association, Whitehorse, Yukon . Sutherland, P.D. 1992. Prehistoric adaptations to changing environments on western Ellesmere Island and Axel Heiberg; Progress report on the 1992 Field Project; p. 27. Sutherland, P.D. 1995. Hydrometeorological investigations
      on a small valley glacier in the Sawtooth Range, Ellesmere Island, Northwest Territories; Master's Thesis; Wilfrid Laurier University, p. 205. Wolfe, P.M. 1992. Suspended sediment and solute transport in Hot Weather Creek, Fosheim Peninsula, Ellesmere Island, Northwest Territories, 1990-1991; B.Sc. Honours Thesis, University of Toronto Department of Geography. Wolfe, P.M. and English, M.C. 1994. Hydrometeorological relationships in a glacierized catchment in the Canadian High Arctic.
      Hydrological Processes, v. 4, p. 911-921. Woo, M.-K., Edlund, S.A., and Young, K.L. 1991. Occurrence of early snow-free zones on Fosheim Peninsula, Ellesmere Island, Northwest Territories; Current Research, Part B, Geological Survey of Canada, Paper 91-1B, p. 9 - 14. Woo, M.-K., Rouse, W.R., Lewkowicz, A.G., and Young, K.L. 1992. Adaptation to permafrost in the Canadian North-- Present and future; Canadian Climate Centre, Atmospheric Environment Service, Report No. 92 - 3, 61 p. Woo,
      M.-K., Young, K.L., and Edlund, S.A. 1990. 1989 observations of soil, vegetation, and microclimate, and effects on slope hydrology, Hot Weather Creek basin, Ellesmere Island, Northwest Territories; Current Research, Part D, Geological Survey of Canada, Paper 90-1D, p. 85 - 93.</Reference>
   <Summary>
      <Abstract>The instrumentation was installed in June 1988 and was initially maintained by the Arctic Adaptation Division Canadian Climate Centre, Atmospheric Environment Service (CCC/AES) with field support by Geological Survey of Canada (GSC). It consists of a Campbell Scientific CR10 micrologger with meteorological sensors for air temperature an relative humidity, wind speed and direction, and solar incoming radiation. It also supports a snow depth sensor, an experimental vegetation
       temperature and four ground temperatures. It is powered by a 25-AH, 12-volt gel cell (a second gel cell was added in 1989) charged by a 10-watt solar panel. Hourly and Daily sampling was carried out. Data have been quality controlled and fully documented (see documentation files accompanying the data). The High Arctic Integrated Research and Monitoring Area (IRMA) of the GSC was established on Fosheim Peninsula to support interdisciplinary studies related to environmental change. Research
       carried out between 1989 and 1994, had as primary objective to determine relationships between geomorphic processes and climate in order to help predict the potential geologic impact of global change. Establishment of detailed paleoclimatic records for this region has also been considered essential to provide a context for ongoing climate change. Paleoecological studies (records of peat cores, lakes cores, ice cores, sea cores and archeological records) in concert with other methodologies
       have been used to outline climatic variability (short, middle or long-term variabilities) and are a primary research component in the region. A major compilation of 20 papers has been produced (see Garneau in press) involving 34 participants from government, universities and industry. The synthesis includes the results from studies of modern conditions (climate, flora and fauna), quaternary geology and glacial history, paleoenvironmental records (i.e. ice cores, ocean, lakes, peat,
       archeological sites), permafrost dynamics and hydrologic systems. Nine appendices complete the document including a comprehensive bibliography and various data series (climate, vegetation, insects, geophysics, plant and arthropod macrofossils and radiocarbon dates) to provide background forfuture projects in the area. These data are on the CAPS Version 1.0 CD-ROM, and were identified for inclusion through the efforts of Kathy Young, Ph.D. graduate of Department of Geography, McMaster
       University, Hamilton, Ontario.</Abstract>
   </Summary>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>VIEW RELATED INFORMATION</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>http://nsidc.org/data/docs/fgdc/ggd220_soiltemp_ellesmere/index.html</URL>
      <Description>Documentation</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>GET DATA</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>ftp://sidads.colorado.edu/pub/DATASETS/fgdc/ggd220_soiltemp_ellesmere/</URL>
      <Description>FTP</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Metadata_Name>CEOS IDN DIF</Metadata_Name>
   <Metadata_Version>VERSION 9.9</Metadata_Version>
   <DIF_Creation_Date>1998-01-01</DIF_Creation_Date>
   <Last_DIF_Revision_Date>2012-08-24</Last_DIF_Revision_Date>
   <DIF_Revision_History> 1998-01-01, Transferred from mddb dataset_citation.release_date 2003-05-14, kgentsch, Mass publish of changed datasets to Bipolar. 2003-05-14, kgentsch, Mass publish of changed datasets to Bipolar. 2004-10-11, yohe, 2012-08-22, Deann Miller, added dist. media and format 2012-08-24, Deann Miller, added creator &amp; publisher info </DIF_Revision_History>
   <Extended_Metadata>
      <Metadata>
         <Group>NSIDC</Group>
         <Name>Version Summary</Name>
         <Value/>
      </Metadata>
      <Metadata>
         <Group>NSIDC</Group>
         <Name>Current Version</Name>
         <Value>1</Value>
      </Metadata>
   </Extended_Metadata>
</DIF>
