<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<DIF xmlns="http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/ http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/dif_v9.7.1.xsd">
   <Entry_ID>GGD651</Entry_ID>
   <Entry_Title>Arctic EASE-Grid Freeze and Thaw Depths, 1901 - 2002</Entry_Title>
   <Data_Set_Citation>
      <Dataset_Creator>Zhang, T., J. McCreight, and R.G. Barry</Dataset_Creator>
      <Dataset_Title>Arctic EASE-Grid Freeze and Thaw Depths, 1901 - 2002</Dataset_Title>
      <Dataset_Release_Date>2006-01-31</Dataset_Release_Date>
      <Dataset_Release_Place>Boulder, Colorado USA</Dataset_Release_Place>
      <Dataset_Publisher>NSIDC: National Snow and Ice Data Center</Dataset_Publisher>
      <Version>1</Version>
      <Online_Resource>http://nsidc.org/data/GGD651</Online_Resource>
      <Dataset_Series_Name>GGD651</Dataset_Series_Name>
   </Data_Set_Citation>
   <Personnel>
      <Role>Investigator</Role>
      <First_Name>Tingjun</First_Name>
      <Middle_Name>Z</Middle_Name>
      <Last_Name>Zhang</Last_Name>
      <Email>nsidc@nsidc.org</Email>
      <Phone>1-303-492-6199</Phone>
      <Fax>1-303-492-2359</Fax>
      <Contact_Address>
         <Address>UCB449</Address>
         <City>Boulder</City>
         <Province_or_State>Colorado</Province_or_State>
         <Postal_Code>80309-0449</Postal_Code>
         <Country>USA</Country>
      </Contact_Address>
   </Personnel>
   <Personnel>
      <Role>Investigator</Role>
      <First_Name>R.</First_Name>
      <Middle_Name>G.</Middle_Name>
      <Last_Name>Barry</Last_Name>
      <Contact_Address>
         <Address>449 UCB</Address>
         <City>Boulder</City>
         <Province_or_State>CO</Province_or_State>
         <Postal_Code>80309-0449</Postal_Code>
         <Country>USA</Country>
      </Contact_Address>
   </Personnel>
   <Personnel>
      <Role>Technical Contact</Role>
      <First_Name>NSIDC</First_Name>
      <Last_Name>User Services</Last_Name>
      <Email>nsidc@nsidc.org</Email>
      <Phone>1-303-492-6199</Phone>
      <Fax>1-303-492-2468</Fax>
      <Contact_Address>
         <Address>CIRES, 449 UCB</Address>
         <Address>University of Colorado</Address>
         <City>Boulder</City>
         <Province_or_State>CO</Province_or_State>
         <Postal_Code>80309-0449</Postal_Code>
         <Country>USA</Country>
      </Contact_Address>
   </Personnel>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Cryosphere</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Active Layer</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Land Surface</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Active Layer</Variable_Level_1>
      <Detailed_Variable>Freeze/Thaw Depth</Detailed_Variable>
   </Parameters>
   <ISO_Topic_Category>Geoscientific Information</ISO_Topic_Category>
   <Keyword>edaphic factor</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Freeze depth</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Freezing Degree Days</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Freezing Index</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Seasonal Thaw Layer</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Stefan solution</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Thaw Depth</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Thaw Depth Measurements</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Thaw Depths</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Thawing Degree-day</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Thawing Degree Days</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Thawing Index</Keyword>
   <Temporal_Coverage>
      <Start_Date>1901-01-01</Start_Date>
      <Stop_Date>2002-12-31</Stop_Date>
   </Temporal_Coverage>
   <Data_Set_Progress>complete</Data_Set_Progress>
   <Spatial_Coverage>
      <Southernmost_Latitude>50</Southernmost_Latitude>
      <Northernmost_Latitude>90</Northernmost_Latitude>
      <Westernmost_Longitude>-180</Westernmost_Longitude>
      <Easternmost_Longitude>180</Easternmost_Longitude>
   </Spatial_Coverage>
   <Location>
      <Location_Category>Geographic Region</Location_Category>
      <Location_Type>Arctic</Location_Type>
      <Location_Subregion1/>
      <Location_Subregion2/>
      <Location_Subregion3/>
      <Detailed_Location/>
   </Location>
   <Quality>The relationship between freeze/thaw depth and freezing and thawing indices has been demonstrated in several places. For example, Brown et al. (2000) review the relationship between thaw depth and the annual thawing index. Romanovsky and Osterkamp (1995), Zhang et al. (1997), Nelson et al. (1998), Klene et al. (2001), and Hinkel and Nelson (2003) all demonstrate the general validity of the approach. Nelson et al. (1997) used the approach to map to map active layer depth for the
      Kuparuk River Basin in Alaska. Zhang et al. (2005b) also use the approach to map active layer depth in the Ob, Yenisey, and Lena River Basins of Russia. The quality of the input freezing and thawing indices is described in Frauenfeld, et al. (submitted) and in the documentation for the data set. The investigators conclude they are adequate for broad scale analysis. The difficulty lies in calculating the edaphic factors. There is some uncertainty in the estimation of the edaphic factors as
      discussed in Zhang et al. (2005b). Overall this approach is reasonable for broad scale calculations and for estimating the response of freeze and thaw depth to different climatological factors.</Quality>
   <Data_Set_Language>English</Data_Set_Language>
   <Originating_Center>FGDC</Originating_Center>
   <Data_Center>
      <Data_Center_Name>
         <Short_Name>FGDC</Short_Name>
         <Long_Name>Frozen Ground Data Center</Long_Name>
      </Data_Center_Name>
      <Data_Center_URL>http://nsidc.org/fgdc/</Data_Center_URL>
      <Personnel>
         <Role>Data Center Contact</Role>
         <First_Name>FGDC</First_Name>
         <Last_Name>User Services</Last_Name>
         <Email>nsidc@nsidc.org</Email>
         <Phone>1-303-492-6199</Phone>
         <Fax>1-303-492-2468</Fax>
         <Contact_Address>
            <Address>National Snow and Ice Data Center</Address>
            <Address>CIRES, 449 UCB</Address>
            <Address>University of Colorado</Address>
            <City>Boulder</City>
            <Province_or_State>CO</Province_or_State>
            <Postal_Code>80309-0449</Postal_Code>
            <Country>USA</Country>
         </Contact_Address>
      </Personnel>
   </Data_Center>
   <Distribution>
      <Distribution_Media>FTP</Distribution_Media>
      <Distribution_Size>479.4 MB</Distribution_Size>
      <Distribution_Format>ASCII Text (.txt)</Distribution_Format>
   </Distribution>
   <Reference>Brown, J., K. M. Hinkel, and F. E. Nelson. 2000. The Circumpolar Active Layer Monitoring (CALM) program: Research designs and initial results. Polar Geogr., 24(3), 163-258. Frauenfeld, O. W., T. Zhang, and J. L. McCreight. Submitted. Climatology and variability of the 20th century Northern Hemisphere freezing/thawing index. International Journal of Climatology. Hinkel, K. M., and F. E. Nelson. 2003. Spatial and temporal patterns of active layer thickness at Circumpolar Active
      Layer Monitoring (CALM) sites in northern Alaska, 1995-2000. J. Geophys. Res., 108(D2), 8168. doi:10.1029/2001JD000927. Klene, A. E., F. E. Nelson, N. I. Shiklomanov, and K. M. Hinkel. 2001. The N-factor in natural landscapes: Variability of air and soil-surface temperatures, Kuparuk River Basin, Alaska. Arct. Antarct. Alp. Res., 33(2), 140-148. Knowles, K. 2004. EASE-Grid land cover data resampled from AVHRR Global 1 km land cover, Version 2, March 1992 - April 1993. Boulder CO, USA:
      National Snow and Ice Data Center. Digital Media. Mitchell T. D. and P. D. Jones. 2005. An improved method of constructing a database of monthly climate observations and associated high-resolution grids. International Journal of Climatology 25, 693-712. Nelson, F. E., N. I. Shiklomanov, G. R. Mueller, K. M. Hinkel, D. A. Walker, and J. G. Bockheim. 1997. Estimating active-layer thickness over a large region: Kuparuk River basin, Alaska, U.S.A. Arct. Alp. Res., 29(4), 367-378. Nelson, F.
      E., and S. I. Outcalt. 1987. A computational method for prediction and regionalization of permafrost. Arct. Alp. Res., 19, 279-288. Nelson, F. E., S. I. Outcalt, J. Brown, N. I. Shiklomanov, and K. M. Hinkel. 1998. Spatial and temporal attributes of the active-layer thickness record, Barrow, Alaska, U.S.A., in Lewkowicz, A. and M. Allard (editors). 1998. Proceedings of 7th International Conference on Permafrost pp. 797-802, Ste-Foy, Canada: Cent. d'Etudes Nordique, Univ. Laval. Romanovsky,
      V. E., and T. E. Osterkamp. 1995. Interannual variations of the thermal regime of the active layer and near-surface permafrost in Northern Alaska. Permafrost Periglacial Proc., 6, 313-335. Zhang, T., O. W. Frauenfeld, J. McCreight, and R. G. Barry. 2005a. Northern Hemisphere EASE-Grid annual freezing and thawing indices, 1901 - 2002. Boulder, CO: National Snow and Ice Data Center. Digital media. Zhang, T., O. W. Frauenfeld, M. C. Serreze, A. Etringer, C. Oelke, J. McCreight, R. G. Barry,
      D. Gilichinsky, D. Yang, H. Ye, F. Ling, and S. Chudinova. 2005b. Spatial and temporal variability in active layer thickness over the Russian Arctic drainage basin. J Geophysical Research, Vol. 110, D16101. doi:10.1029/2004JD005642. Zhang, T., T. E. Osterkamp, and K. Stamnes. 1997. Effects of climate on the active layer and permafrost on the north slope of Alaska, U.S.A. Permafrost Periglacial Proc., 8, 45-67.</Reference>
   <Summary>
      <Abstract>This data set contains mean, median, minimum and maximum freeze and thaw depths for each year from 1901 to 2002 on the 25 km resolution Equal-Area Scalable Earth Grid (EASE-Grid) for areas north of 50 deg. Freeze and thaw depths are estimated using a variant of the Stefan solution using an edaphic factor and freezing or thawing indices as inputs. The edaphic factor is estimated based on different land surface types; the freezing and thawing indices are from Northern Hemisphere
       EASE-Grid annual freezing and thawing indices, 1901 - 2002 (Zhang, et al. 2005). Two ASCII files are available for each year for freeze depth and thaw depth, respectively. Each file is approximately 25.6 MB in size. In addition, there is one 10.5 MB ASCII file defining the latitude and longitude coordinates for each grid point. The data set is available via FTP as three compressed files.</Abstract>
   </Summary>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>VIEW RELATED INFORMATION</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>http://nsidc.org/data/docs/fgdc/ggd651_frzthw_depth_efact/</URL>
      <Description>Documentation</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>GET DATA</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>ftp://sidads.colorado.edu/pub/DATASETS/fgdc/ggd651_frzthw_depth_efact/</URL>
      <Description>FTP</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>VIEW RELATED INFORMATION</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>http://nsidc.org/data/ease/</URL>
      <Description>All About EASE-Grid</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>VIEW RELATED INFORMATION</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>http://nsidc.org/data/ggd649.html</URL>
      <Description>Northern Hemisphere EASE-Grid Annual Freezing and Thawing Indices, 1901 - 2002</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Metadata_Name>CEOS IDN DIF</Metadata_Name>
   <Metadata_Version>VERSION 9.9</Metadata_Version>
   <DIF_Creation_Date>2006-01-31</DIF_Creation_Date>
   <Last_DIF_Revision_Date>2012-09-18</Last_DIF_Revision_Date>
   <DIF_Revision_History> 2006-01-31, Transferred from mddb dataset_citation.release_date 2006-02-07, Mark Parsons, madew edits in response to QC. 2006-02-14, Mark Parsons, minor edits from Jane. Please resubmit to the GCMD 2006-02-14, Mark Parsons, Changed in response to QC 2010-03-01, Deann Miller, Fixed References section. Some of the citations were running together. Fixed per GCMD. 2012-07-31, Deann Miller, Removed the World Data Center for Glaciology as publisher for this data set and any
      other data sets listed in the Reference section of the metadata because the center no longer exists. 2012-08-28, Deann Miller, Added an archiving data center. 2012-09-18, Deann Miller, deleted dupe URLs in Related URL field </DIF_Revision_History>
   <Extended_Metadata>
      <Metadata>
         <Group>NSIDC</Group>
         <Name>Version Summary</Name>
         <Value/>
      </Metadata>
      <Metadata>
         <Group>NSIDC</Group>
         <Name>Current Version</Name>
         <Value>1</Value>
      </Metadata>
   </Extended_Metadata>
</DIF>
