<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<DIF xmlns="http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/ http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/dif_v9.7.1.xsd">
   <Entry_ID>GGD601</Entry_ID>
   <Entry_Title>Land Resources of Russia -- Maps of Soil Characteristics</Entry_Title>
   <Data_Set_Citation>
      <Dataset_Creator>Stolbovoi, V. and I. Savin</Dataset_Creator>
      <Dataset_Title>Land Resources of Russia -- Maps of Soil Characteristics</Dataset_Title>
      <Dataset_Release_Date>2002-01-01</Dataset_Release_Date>
      <Dataset_Release_Place>Boulder, Colorado USA</Dataset_Release_Place>
      <Dataset_Publisher>NSIDC: National Snow and Ice Data Center</Dataset_Publisher>
      <Version>1</Version>
      <Online_Resource>http://nsidc.org/data/GGD601</Online_Resource>
      <Dataset_Series_Name>GGD601</Dataset_Series_Name>
   </Data_Set_Citation>
   <Personnel>
      <Role>Investigator</Role>
      <First_Name>Vladimir</First_Name>
      <Last_Name>Stolbovoi</Last_Name>
      <Contact_Address>
         <Country>Austria</Country>
      </Contact_Address>
   </Personnel>
   <Personnel>
      <Role>Investigator</Role>
      <First_Name>Boris</First_Name>
      <Last_Name>Sheremet</Last_Name>
      <Contact_Address>
         <Country>Russia</Country>
      </Contact_Address>
   </Personnel>
   <Personnel>
      <Role>Investigator</Role>
      <First_Name>Igor</First_Name>
      <Last_Name>Savin</Last_Name>
      <Contact_Address>
         <Country>Russia</Country>
      </Contact_Address>
   </Personnel>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Land Surface</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Cryosols</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Cryosphere</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Cryosols</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Land Surface</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Permafrost</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Cryosphere</Topic>
      <Term>Snow/Ice</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Permafrost</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Cryosphere</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Permafrost</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Land Surface</Topic>
      <Term>Soils</Term>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Land Surface</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Soil Temperature</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Cryosphere</Topic>
      <Term>Frozen Ground</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Soil Temperature</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Keyword>Soil Properties</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Soil Temperature</Keyword>
   <Temporal_Coverage>
      <Start_Date>1988-01-01</Start_Date>
      <Stop_Date>2002-12-31</Stop_Date>
   </Temporal_Coverage>
   <Spatial_Coverage>
      <Southernmost_Latitude>41.2</Southernmost_Latitude>
      <Northernmost_Latitude>77.7</Northernmost_Latitude>
      <Westernmost_Longitude>-169.5</Westernmost_Longitude>
      <Easternmost_Longitude>27.3</Easternmost_Longitude>
   </Spatial_Coverage>
   <Location>
      <Location_Category>Continent</Location_Category>
      <Location_Type>Europe</Location_Type>
      <Location_Subregion1>Eastern Europe</Location_Subregion1>
      <Location_Subregion2>Russia</Location_Subregion2>
      <Location_Subregion3/>
      <Detailed_Location>Russia</Detailed_Location>
   </Location>
   <Data_Set_Language>English</Data_Set_Language>
   <Data_Center>
      <Data_Center_Name>
         <Short_Name>FGDC</Short_Name>
         <Long_Name>Frozen Ground Data Center</Long_Name>
      </Data_Center_Name>
      <Data_Center_URL>http://nsidc.org/fgdc/</Data_Center_URL>
      <Personnel>
         <Role>Data Center Contact</Role>
         <First_Name>FGDC</First_Name>
         <Last_Name>User Services</Last_Name>
         <Email>nsidc@nsidc.org</Email>
         <Phone>1-303-492-6199</Phone>
         <Fax>1-303-492-2468</Fax>
         <Contact_Address>
            <Address>National Snow and Ice Data Center</Address>
            <Address>CIRES, 449 UCB</Address>
            <Address>University of Colorado</Address>
            <City>Boulder</City>
            <Province_or_State>CO</Province_or_State>
            <Postal_Code>80309-0449</Postal_Code>
            <Country>USA</Country>
         </Contact_Address>
      </Personnel>
   </Data_Center>
   <Distribution>
      <Distribution_Media>FTP</Distribution_Media>
      <Distribution_Format>ESRI Shapefile</Distribution_Format>
   </Distribution>
   <Multimedia_Sample>
      <File>http://nsidc.org/fgdc/maps/images/soil_rus_tmb.gif</File>
      <URL>http://nsidc.org/fgdc/maps/russia_soil_browse.html</URL>
      <Caption>Map Thumbnail</Caption>
   </Multimedia_Sample>
   <Multimedia_Sample>
      <File>http://nsidc.org/fgdc/maps/images/soil_rus_300.gif</File>
      <URL/>
      <Caption>Browse image of Russian national soil classifications.</Caption>
   </Multimedia_Sample>
   <Reference>Arinushkina E.V. 1970. Manual for Chemical Analysis of Soils. 2nd Ed. Publ. Moscow State University, Moscow, 487 pp. [In Russian] Blagodatski, S.A., A.A. Larionova and I.V. Evdokimova, 1993. Contribution of root respiration to CO2 emission from soil. In: Soil Respiration. In: Proceedings of the Institute of Physico-Chemical and Biological Problems of Soil Science of Academy of Science of Russia, Puschino, 26Ð32 (in Russian). Dokuchaev, V.V. 1951. Selected Works, Vols. I and II,
      Moscow-Leningrad. FAO-UNESCO. 1998. Soil Map of the World, Revised Legend. World Resources Report No. 60. FAO, Rome, ISBN 92-5-102622-X. FAO. 1998. World Reference Base of Soil Resources. World Soil Resources Reports 84, Rome, 88 pp. Fridland V.M. (Ed.) 1988. Soil Map of the Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic at Scale 1:2.5 Million. All Union Academy of Agricultural Science, Moscow. Government Administration for Geodesy and Cartography (GUGK), 16 sheets. Fridland V.M. 1982. Main
      Principles and Elements of Basic Soil Classification and Program for Development. All Union Academy of Agricultural Science, Moscow, 149 pp. [In Russian] Fridland, V.M. 1972. The structure of Soil Cover. Mysl, Moscow. Grishina, L.A., 1986. Humus formation and humus status of soils. Publ. Moscow State University, 244 (in Russian). Guidelines for Soil Profile Description. 1990. 3rd Ed. (Revised). FAO, Rome, 70 pp. Kogut, B. and A. Frid. 1993. Comparative Evaluation of Methods of Determining
      Humus Concentration in Soils. Pochvovedenie 9:119Ð123. [In Russian] Kudeyarov, V.N., F.I. Hakimov, N.F. Deyeva, A.A. IlÕina, T.V. Kuznetzova, and A.V. Timchenko, 1996. Evaluation of respiration of Russian soils. Eurasian Soil Science, 28 (3). Madsen, H.B. and R.J.A. Jones. 1993. Guidelines for Completing Soil Attribute Tables I and II: Users Guide, Soil Database of Europe. Unpublished manuscript, SESCPe, INRA, France. Makarov, B.N., 1993. Soil respiration and its role in carbon nutrition
      of the plants. Agrokhimia, 8, 94Ð104 (in Russian). Rode, A.A. 1975. Explanatory Dictionary of Soil Science. Nauka, Moscow. Rode, A.A. 1978. The Problems of the Soil Water Regime. Gydrometizdat, Leningrad, 212 pp. [In Russian] Shishov L.L., and I.A. Sokolov. 1992. A New Version of Soil Classification in the Soviet Union. Pochvovedenie 4:112-120. [In Russian] Shishov, L.L., V.D. Tonkonogov, and I.I. Lebedeva. 1998. Russian Soil Classification. Academy of Agricultural Science, Mowcow, 236 pp.
      [In Russian] Soil Taxonomy. 1999. Second Edition by Soil Survey Staff, Agriculture Handbook, Number 436. United States Department of Agriculture Natural Resources Conservation Service, Washington DC, 869 pp. Soil and Physiographic Database for North and Central Eurasia at 1:5 Million Scale. 1999. Land and Water Digital Media Series, 7, CD-ROM. FAO, Rome. Stolboboi V. 2000. Soils of Russia: Correlated with the Revised Legend of the FAO Soil Map of the World and World Reference Base for Soil
      Resources. Research Report, RR-00-13. IIASA, Laxenburg, Austria,112 pp. Stolbovoi V., 2001. Soil Respiration in the Full Carbon Account for Russia. Sixth International Carbon Dioxide Conference, 2001 Sendai Japan, Extended Abstracts, pp. 434-437. Stolbovoi V., L. Montanarella, V.Medvedev, N. Smeyan, L.Shishov, V.Ungureanu, G.Dobrovolski, M.Jamagne, D.King, V.Rozhkov, I.Savin, 2001. Integration of Data on the Soils of Russia, Byelorus, Moldova and Ukraine into the Soil Geographic Database
      of the European Community. Eurasian Soil Science, Vol. 34, No. 7, pp.687-703. Stolbovoi V., and B.V. Sheremet. 1995. A New Soil Map of Russia, Compiled in FAO System. Pochvovedenie 2:149Ð158. [In Russian] Stolbovoi V.S., and B.V. Sheremet. 1996. Soil Map of Russia, Scale 1:8 Million, in the U.S. Soil Taxonomy System. Eurasian Soil Science 28(12):73Ð82. Stolbovoi V.S., and I.Y. Savin. 1996. Experience of RUSOTER Digital Database Compilation. Pochvovedenie 11:1295Ð1302. [In Russian]
      Stolbovoi V. and I. McCallum, eds. 2002. Land resources of Russia. Laxenburg, Austria: International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis and the Russian Academy of Science. CD-ROM. USDA. 1999. Soil Taxonomy, 2nd Ed. by Soil Survey Staff, Agriculture Handbook, Number 436, United States Department of Agriculture, Natural Resources Conservation Service, Washington DC, 869 pp. Van Engelen, V.W.P., and T.T. Wen. 1993. Global and National Soil and Terrain Digital Databases (SOTER). Procedures
      Manual (Revised Version). ISRIC, Wageningen, Netherlands, 115 pp. World Soil Resources. An explanatory note on the FAO World Soil Resources Map at 1:25,000,000 scale. 1993. World Soil Resources Reports, 66 Rev. 1, FAO, Rome, 66 pp.</Reference>
   <Summary>
      <Abstract>This data set consists of maps of various soil characteristics for all of Russia. The maps are available as ESRI Shapefiles and they are accompanied by databases of soil profiles and related characteristics. The soil classification Shapefile was generalized from the standard 1:2,500,000 soil map of Russia (Fridland, 1988). Several different soil classifications are presented as well as detailed soil characteristics. Additionally, investigators compiled two databases (.dbf files)
       of detailed soil characteristics from 234 measured soil profiles. These data were extracted from a larger collection entitled Land Resources of Russia. Data and documentation © 2002 copyright International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis and the Russian Academy of Sciences.</Abstract>
   </Summary>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>VIEW RELATED INFORMATION</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>http://nsidc.org/data/docs/fgdc/ggd601_russia_soil_maps/index.html</URL>
      <Description>Documentation</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>GET DATA</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>ftp://sidads.colorado.edu/pub/DATASETS/fgdc/ggd601_russia_soil_maps/</URL>
      <Description>FTP</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>VIEW RELATED INFORMATION</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>http://nsidc.org/data/gis/</URL>
      <Description>GIS Data and Resources at NSIDC</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Metadata_Name>CEOS IDN DIF</Metadata_Name>
   <Metadata_Version>VERSION 9.9</Metadata_Version>
   <DIF_Creation_Date>2002-01-01</DIF_Creation_Date>
   <Last_DIF_Revision_Date>2012-08-30</Last_DIF_Revision_Date>
   <DIF_Revision_History> 2002-01-01, Transferred from mddb dataset_citation.release_date 2003-05-14, kgentsch, Mass publish of changed datasets to Bipolar. 2003-05-14, kgentsch, Mass publish of changed datasets to Bipolar. 2003-07-09, yohe, 2004-06-04, yohe, 2007-09-18, lfrench, John added sample image URLs to multimedia in DIF. Also corrected some spatial coverage errors. GGDs 320, 600, 601, 602, 603, 648. Send to GCMD. 2010-03-01, Deann Miller, Fixed References Section. Some of the
      citations were running together. Fixed per the GCMD. 2010-03-01, Deann Miller, Reference fix took on newice but didn't take on biploar. 2010-03-01, Deann Miller, Again, fix didn't take on bipolar. 2010-03-01, Deann Miller, AGAIN!! 2010-03-01, Deann Miller, AGAIN!!! 2012-02-13, Deann Miller, Fixed temporal coverage for EDB. 2012-06-25, Deann Miller, Moved CD-ROM to correct location in citation 2012-06-25, Deann Miller, corrected citation 2012-08-23, Deann Miller, added dist. media &amp;
      format based on data 2012-08-30, Deann Miller, added creator / pub info </DIF_Revision_History>
   <Extended_Metadata>
      <Metadata>
         <Group>NSIDC</Group>
         <Name>Version Summary</Name>
         <Value/>
      </Metadata>
      <Metadata>
         <Group>NSIDC</Group>
         <Name>Current Version</Name>
         <Value>1</Value>
      </Metadata>
   </Extended_Metadata>
</DIF>
