<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<DIF xmlns="http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/ http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/dif_v9.7.1.xsd">
   <Entry_ID>NSIDC-0543</Entry_ID>
   <Entry_Title>AMSR-E/Aqua Monthly Global Microwave Land Surface Emissivity</Entry_Title>
   <Data_Set_Citation>
      <Dataset_Creator>Norouzi, H., M. Temimi, W. B. Rossow, and R. Khanbilvardi.</Dataset_Creator>
      <Dataset_Title>AMSR-E/Aqua Monthly Global Microwave Land Surface Emissivity</Dataset_Title>
      <Dataset_Release_Date>2013-08-21</Dataset_Release_Date>
      <Dataset_Release_Place>Boulder, Colorado USA</Dataset_Release_Place>
      <Dataset_Publisher>NASA NSIDC DAAC: NASA National Snow and Ice Data Center Distributed Active Archive Center</Dataset_Publisher>
      <Version>1</Version>
      <Dataset_DOI>doi:10.5067/SFBY6Q6JYS3L</Dataset_DOI>
      <Online_Resource>http://nsidc.org/data/NSIDC-0543</Online_Resource>
      <Dataset_Series_Name>NSIDC-0543</Dataset_Series_Name>
   </Data_Set_Citation>
   <Reference>
      <Author>Norouzi, H., M. Temimi, W. B. Rossow, R. Khanbilvardi, C. Pearl, and M. Azarderakhsh</Author>
      <Publication_Date>2011</Publication_Date>
      <Title>The Sensitivity of Land Emissivity Estimates from AMSR-E at C- and X-Bands to Surface Properties</Title>
      <Series>Journal of Hydrology, Earth Systems Science</Series>
      <Issue>15</Issue>
      <Pages>3577-3589</Pages>
      <DOI>&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5194/hess-15-3577-2011"&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.5194/hess-15-3577-2011&lt;/a&gt;</DOI>
      <Other_Reference_Details>
         <Type>Literature Citation</Type>
      </Other_Reference_Details>
   </Reference>
   <Personnel>
      <Role>Technical Contact</Role>
      <First_Name>NSIDC</First_Name>
      <Last_Name>User Services</Last_Name>
      <Email>nsidc@nsidc.org</Email>
      <Phone>1-303-492-6199</Phone>
      <Fax>1-303-492-2468</Fax>
      <Contact_Address>
         <Address>CIRES, 449 UCB</Address>
         <Address>University of Colorado</Address>
         <City>Boulder</City>
         <Province_or_State>CO</Province_or_State>
         <Postal_Code>80309-0449</Postal_Code>
         <Country>USA</Country>
      </Contact_Address>
   </Personnel>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Land Surface</Topic>
      <Term>Surface Radiative Properties</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Emissivity</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <ISO_Topic_Category>Climatology/Meteorology/Atmosphere</ISO_Topic_Category>
   <Keyword>AMSR-E</Keyword>
   <Keyword>AMSR-E-related project</Keyword>
   <Keyword>EMISSIVITY</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Land Surface</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Land Surface Temperature</Keyword>
   <Keyword>SSM/I</Keyword>
   <Keyword>TOVS</Keyword>
   <Keyword>TOVS-project</Keyword>
   <Sensor_Name>
      <Short_Name>AMSR-E</Short_Name>
      <Long_Name>Advanced Microwave Scanning Radiometer-EOS</Long_Name>
   </Sensor_Name>
   <Source_Name>
      <Short_Name>AQUA</Short_Name>
      <Long_Name>Earth Observing System, AQUA</Long_Name>
   </Source_Name>
   <Temporal_Coverage>
      <Start_Date>2002-07-01</Start_Date>
      <Stop_Date>2008-06-30</Stop_Date>
   </Temporal_Coverage>
   <Data_Set_Progress>complete</Data_Set_Progress>
   <Spatial_Coverage>
      <Southernmost_Latitude>-90</Southernmost_Latitude>
      <Northernmost_Latitude>90</Northernmost_Latitude>
      <Westernmost_Longitude>-180</Westernmost_Longitude>
      <Easternmost_Longitude>180</Easternmost_Longitude>
   </Spatial_Coverage>
   <Location>
      <Location_Category>Geographic Region</Location_Category>
      <Location_Type>Global Land</Location_Type>
      <Location_Subregion1/>
      <Location_Subregion2/>
      <Location_Subregion3/>
   </Location>
   <Data_Resolution>
      <Latitude_Resolution>0.25 deg</Latitude_Resolution>
      <Longitude_Resolution>0.25 deg</Longitude_Resolution>
      <Temporal_Resolution>1 month</Temporal_Resolution>
   </Data_Resolution>
   <Project>
      <Short_Name>NOAA-CREST</Short_Name>
      <Long_Name>NOAA Cooperative Remote Sensing Science and Technology Center</Long_Name>
   </Project>
   <Project>
      <Short_Name>NEWS</Short_Name>
      <Long_Name>NASA Energy and Water Study</Long_Name>
   </Project>
   <Quality>Several quality controls have been conducted and the standard deviation of instantaneous emissivity estimates within each month to be less than 0.015. The results have been also evaluated with other available global data such as SSM/I.</Quality>
   <Data_Set_Language>English</Data_Set_Language>
   <Data_Center>
      <Data_Center_Name>
         <Short_Name>NASA NSIDC DAAC</Short_Name>
         <Long_Name>NASA National Snow and Ice Data Center Distributed Active Archive Center</Long_Name>
      </Data_Center_Name>
      <Data_Center_URL>http://nsidc.org/daac/index.html</Data_Center_URL>
      <Personnel>
         <Role>Data Center Contact</Role>
         <First_Name>NSIDC</First_Name>
         <Last_Name>User Services</Last_Name>
         <Email>nsidc@nsidc.org</Email>
         <Phone>1-303-492-6199</Phone>
         <Fax>1-303-492-2468</Fax>
         <Contact_Address>
            <Address>National Snow and Ice Data Center</Address>
            <Address>CIRES, 449 UCB</Address>
            <Address>University of Colorado</Address>
            <City>Boulder</City>
            <Province_or_State>CO</Province_or_State>
            <Postal_Code>80309-0449</Postal_Code>
            <Country>USA</Country>
         </Contact_Address>
      </Personnel>
   </Data_Center>
   <Distribution>
      <Distribution_Media>FTP</Distribution_Media>
      <Distribution_Size>95 MB</Distribution_Size>
      <Distribution_Format>HDF</Distribution_Format>
   </Distribution>
   <Reference>Aires, F., C. Prigent, and W. B. Rossow. 2004. Temporal Interpolation of Global Surface Skin Temperature Diurnal Cycle over Land under Clear and Cloudy Conditions. Journal of Geophysical Research-Atmospheres. 109. doi:10.1029/2003jd003527.

English, S. J. 1995. Airborne Radiometric Observations of Cloud Liquid-Water Emission at 89 and 157 GHz – Application to Retrieval of Liquid-Water Path. Quarterly Journal of the Royal Meteorological Society. 121:1501-1524. 

Jimenez, C., C. Prigent, B. Mueller, S. I. Seneviratne, M. F. McCabe, E. F. Wood., W. B. Rossow, G. Balsamo, A. K. Betts, P. A. Dirmeyer, J. B. Fisher, M. Jung, M. Kanamitsu, R. H. Reichle, M. Reichstein, M. Rodell, J. Sheffield, K. Tu, and K. Wang. 2011. Global Intercomparison of 12 Land Surface Heat Flux Estimates. Journal of Geophysical Research-Atmospheres. 116. doi:10.1029/2010jd014545.

Kawanishi, T., T. Sezai, Y. Ito, K. Imaoka, T. Takeshima, Y. Ishido, A. Shibata, M. Miura, H. Inahata, and R. W. Spencer. 2003. The Advanced Microwave Scanning Radiometer for the Earth Observing System (AMSR-E), NASDA's Contribution to the EOS for Global Energy and Water Cycle Studies. IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing, 41:184-194. doi:10.1109/tgrs.2002.808331. 

Liebe, H. J., G. A. Hufford, and M. G. Cotton. 1993. Propagation Modelling of Moist Air and Suspended Water/Ice Particles at Frequencies below 1000 GHz. Specialist Meeting of the Electromagnetic Wave Propagation Panel Symposium, AGARD Conference Proceedings 542, Atmospheric Propagation Effects through Natural and Man–Made Obscurants for Visible through MW-Wave Radiation, March 1–10, 1993: Palma de Mallorca, Spain.

Lin, B., and W. B. Rossow. 1994. Observations of Cloud Liquid Water Path over Oceans – Optical and Microwave Remote-Sensing Methods. Journal of Geophysical Research-Atmospheres. 99:20907-20927.

Moncet, J., P. Liang, A. Lipton, J. Galantowicz, and C. Prigent. 2011. Discrepancies between MODIS and ISCCP Land Surface Temperature Products Analyzed with Microwave Measurements. J. Geophys. Res. doi:10.1029/2010JD015432. 

Njoku, E. G., and L. Li. 1999. Retrieval of Land Surface Parameters using Passive Microwave Measurements at 6–18 GHz. IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing. 37: 79-93.

Norouzi, H., M. Temimi, W. Rossow, C. Pearl, M. Azarderakhsh, and R. Khanbilvardi. 2011. The Sensitivity of Land Emissivity Estimates from AMSR-E at C- and X-Bands to Surface Properties. Journal of Hydrology, Earth Systems Science. 15:3577–3589. doi:10.5194/hess-15-3577-2011. 

Norouzi, H., W. Rossow, M. Temimi, C. Prigent, M. Azarderakhsh, S. Boukabara, and R. Khanbilvardi. 2012. Using Microwave Brightness Temperature Diurnal Cycle To Improve Emissivity Retrievals Over Land. Remote Sensing of Environment. 123:470–482. doi:10.1016/j.rse.2012.04.015. 

Prigent, C., Rossow, W. B., and E. Matthews. 1998. Global Maps of Microwave Land Surface Emissivities: Potential for Land Surface Characterization. Radio Science. 33:745–751.

Prigent, C., W. B. Rossow, and E. Matthews. 1997. Microwave Land Surface Emissivities Estimated from SSM/I Observations. Journal of Geophysical Research-Atmospheres. 102:21867-21890.

Rossow, W. B., and R. A. Schiffer. 1991. ISCCP Cloud Data Products. Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society. 72, 2–20.

Rossow, W. B., and R. A. Schiffer. 1999. Advances in Understanding Clouds from ISCCP. Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society. 80:2261–2287. 

Zhang, Y. C., Rossow, W. B., and Stackhouse, P. W. 2006. Comparison of Different Global Information Sources used in Surface Radiative Flux Calculation: Radiative Properties of the Near-Surface Atmosphere. Journal of Geophysical Research-Atmospheres. 111. doi:10.1029/2005jd006873.</Reference>
   <Summary>
      <Abstract>This data set is a global land emissivity product using passive microwave observations from the Advanced Microwave Scanning Radiometer - Earth Observing System (AMSR-E). The data set complements existing land emissivity products from the Special Sensor Microwave Imager (SSM/I) and Advanced Microwave Sounding Unit (AMSU) by adding land emissivity estimates at two lower frequencies, 6.9 and 10.65 GHz (C- and X-band, respectively). Observations at these low frequencies penetrate deeper into the soil layer. Land surface emissivity estimates for this data set were collected at the following vertically and horizontally polarized (V-pol and H-pol) frequencies: 6.9, 10.65, 18.7, 23.8, 36.5, and 89.0 GHz. Ancillary data used in the analysis, such as surface skin temperature and cloud mask, were obtained from International Satellite Cloud Climatology Project (ISCCP). Atmospheric properties were obtained from TIROS Operational Vertical Sounder (TOVS) observations to determine the small upwelling and downwelling atmospheric emissions as well as the atmospheric transmission. The data set is in monthly format that is extracted from instantaneous emissivity estimates. Data are stored in HDF4 files and are available via FTP.</Abstract>
   </Summary>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>VIEW RELATED INFORMATION</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>http://nsidc.org/data/docs/daac/nsidc0543_amsre_emiss/index.html</URL>
      <Description>Documentation</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>GET DATA</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>ftp://sidads.colorado.edu/pub/DATASETS/nsidc0543_amsre_emiss/</URL>
      <Description>FTP</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>VIEW RELATED INFORMATION</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>http://nsidc.org/data/amsre/index.html</URL>
      <Description>AMSR-E/Aqua Product Web Site</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>VIEW RELATED INFORMATION</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>http://nsidc.org/data/amsr_validation/</URL>
      <Description>AMSR-E Validation Product Web Site</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Metadata_Name>CEOS IDN DIF</Metadata_Name>
   <Metadata_Version>VERSION 9.9</Metadata_Version>
   <DIF_Creation_Date>2013-08-21</DIF_Creation_Date>
   <Last_DIF_Revision_Date>2015-07-28</Last_DIF_Revision_Date>
   <DIF_Revision_History> 2013-08-21, Karla LeFevre,  Publishing b/c this data set has already been reviewed by MD Manager. 
 2013-08-21, Karla LeFevre,  Publishing b/c this data set has already been reviewed by MD Manager. 
 2015-07-28, Gloria Hicks, Added keyword for Drupal migration. 
 2013-08-22, Karla LeFevre,  Added literature citation. 
 2015-07-21, Michon Scott, Added keyword as part of Drupal migration.
</DIF_Revision_History>
   <Extended_Metadata>
      <Metadata>
         <Group>NSIDC</Group>
         <Name>Version Summary</Name>
         <Value/>
      </Metadata>
      <Metadata>
         <Group>NSIDC</Group>
         <Name>Current Version</Name>
         <Value>1</Value>
      </Metadata>
   </Extended_Metadata>
</DIF>
