<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<DIF xmlns="http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/ http://gcmd.gsfc.nasa.gov/Aboutus/xml/dif/dif_v9.7.1.xsd">
   <Entry_ID>NSIDC-0072</Entry_ID>
   <Entry_Title>Adjusted Monthly Precipitation, Snowfall and Rainfall for Canada (1874-1990)</Entry_Title>
   <Data_Set_Citation>
      <Dataset_Creator>P. Groisman</Dataset_Creator>
      <Dataset_Title>Adjusted Monthly Precipitation, Snowfall and Rainfall for Canada (1874-1990)</Dataset_Title>
      <Dataset_Release_Date>2000-01-01</Dataset_Release_Date>
      <Dataset_Release_Place>Asheville, North Carolina USA</Dataset_Release_Place>
      <Dataset_Publisher>NCDC: National Climatic Data Center</Dataset_Publisher>
      <Version>1</Version>
      <Online_Resource>http://nsidc.org/data/NSIDC-0072</Online_Resource>
      <Dataset_Series_Name>NSIDC-0072</Dataset_Series_Name>
   </Data_Set_Citation>
   <Personnel>
      <Role>Investigator</Role>
      <First_Name>Pavel</First_Name>
      <Middle_Name>YA.</Middle_Name>
      <Last_Name>Groisman</Last_Name>
      <Email>pgroisman@ncdc.noaa.gov</Email>
      <Phone>1-704-271-4307</Phone>
      <Contact_Address>
         <Address>National Climatic Data Center</Address>
         <Address>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</Address>
         <City>Asheville</City>
         <Province_or_State>NC</Province_or_State>
         <Postal_Code>28801</Postal_Code>
         <Country/>
      </Contact_Address>
   </Personnel>
   <Personnel>
      <Role>Investigator</Role>
      <First_Name>Mark</First_Name>
      <Middle_Name>C.</Middle_Name>
      <Last_Name>Serreze</Last_Name>
      <Email>serreze@nsidc.org</Email>
      <Phone>1-303-492-6199</Phone>
      <Fax>1-303-492-2468</Fax>
      <Contact_Address>
         <Address>National Snow and Ice Data Center</Address>
         <Address>CIRES, 449 UCB</Address>
         <Address>University of Colorado</Address>
         <City>Boulder</City>
         <Province_or_State>CO</Province_or_State>
         <Postal_Code>80309-0449</Postal_Code>
         <Country/>
      </Contact_Address>
   </Personnel>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Atmosphere</Topic>
      <Term>Precipitation</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Precipitation Amount</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Atmosphere</Topic>
      <Term>Precipitation</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Precipitation Rate</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Atmosphere</Topic>
      <Term>Precipitation</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Rain</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Atmosphere</Topic>
      <Term>Precipitation</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Snow</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Parameters>
      <Category>EARTH SCIENCE</Category>
      <Topic>Terrestrial Hydrosphere</Topic>
      <Term>Snow/Ice</Term>
      <Variable_Level_1>Snow Cover</Variable_Level_1>
   </Parameters>
   <Keyword>Adjusted Data</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Canada</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Canadian Arctic</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Corrected Data</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Evaporation Loss</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Ground Stations</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Instrumental Inhomogeneities</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Mean Monthly Precipitation</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Mean Monthly Rainfall</Keyword>
   <Keyword>MEAN MONTHLY SNOWFALL</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Nipher Rain Gauge</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Nipher Snow Gauge</Keyword>
   <Keyword>NOAA</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Rainfall Adjustment</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Snowfall Adjustment</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Snow Ruler</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Station Data</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Trace Precipitation</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Wetting Loss</Keyword>
   <Keyword>Wind-induced Undercatch</Keyword>
   <Sensor_Name>
      <Short_Name>RAIN GAUGES</Short_Name>
   </Sensor_Name>
   <Sensor_Name>
      <Short_Name>SNOW MEASURING ROD</Short_Name>
   </Sensor_Name>
   <Source_Name>
      <Short_Name>GROUND STATIONS</Short_Name>
   </Source_Name>
   <Source_Name>
      <Short_Name>GROUND-BASED OBSERVATIONS</Short_Name>
   </Source_Name>
   <Temporal_Coverage>
      <Start_Date>1874-01-01</Start_Date>
      <Stop_Date>1990-12-31</Stop_Date>
   </Temporal_Coverage>
   <Data_Set_Progress>complete</Data_Set_Progress>
   <Spatial_Coverage>
      <Southernmost_Latitude>41</Southernmost_Latitude>
      <Northernmost_Latitude>84</Northernmost_Latitude>
      <Westernmost_Longitude>-141</Westernmost_Longitude>
      <Easternmost_Longitude>-52</Easternmost_Longitude>
      <Minimum_Altitude>0 meters</Minimum_Altitude>
      <Maximum_Altitude>2517 meters</Maximum_Altitude>
   </Spatial_Coverage>
   <Location>
      <Location_Category>Continent</Location_Category>
      <Location_Type>North America</Location_Type>
      <Location_Subregion1>Canada</Location_Subregion1>
      <Location_Subregion2/>
      <Location_Subregion3/>
      <Detailed_Location/>
   </Location>
   <Location>
      <Location_Category>Geographic Region</Location_Category>
      <Location_Type>Arctic</Location_Type>
      <Location_Subregion1/>
      <Location_Subregion2/>
      <Location_Subregion3/>
      <Detailed_Location/>
   </Location>
   <Project>
      <Short_Name>EOSDIS</Short_Name>
      <Long_Name>Earth Observing System Data Information System</Long_Name>
   </Project>
   <Project>
      <Short_Name>ESIP</Short_Name>
      <Long_Name>Earth Science Information Partners Program</Long_Name>
   </Project>
   <Data_Set_Language>English</Data_Set_Language>
   <Data_Center>
      <Data_Center_Name>
         <Short_Name>NOAA</Short_Name>
         <Long_Name>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</Long_Name>
      </Data_Center_Name>
      <Data_Center_URL>http://nsidc.org/noaa/</Data_Center_URL>
      <Personnel>
         <Role>Data Center Contact</Role>
         <First_Name>NOAA</First_Name>
         <Last_Name>User Services</Last_Name>
         <Email>nsidc@nsidc.org</Email>
         <Phone>1-303-492-6199</Phone>
         <Fax>1-303-492-2468</Fax>
         <Contact_Address>
            <Address>National Snow and Ice Data Center</Address>
            <Address>CIRES, 449 UCB</Address>
            <Address>University of Colorado</Address>
            <City>Boulder</City>
            <Province_or_State>CO</Province_or_State>
            <Postal_Code>80309-0449</Postal_Code>
            <Country>USA</Country>
         </Contact_Address>
      </Personnel>
   </Data_Center>
   <Distribution>
      <Distribution_Media>FTP</Distribution_Media>
      <Distribution_Size>45 MB</Distribution_Size>
      <Distribution_Format>ASCII Text (.txt)</Distribution_Format>
   </Distribution>
   <Reference>Goodison, B.E. 1978. Accuracy of Canadian snow gauge measurements. Journal of Applied Meteorology 17:1542-1548. Groisman, P.Ya. D.R. Easterling. 1994. Variability and trends of precipitation and snowfall over the United States and Canada. Journal of Climate 7:184-205. Karl, T.R., Quayle, R.G., Groisman, P.Ya. 1993. Detecting climate variations and change: New challenges for observing and data management systems. Journal of Climate 6:1481-1494. Metcalfe, J.R., B. Routledge, K.
      Devine. 1997. Rainfall measurement in Canada: Changing observational methods and archive adjustment procedures. Journal of Climate 10:92-101. Akima, H., 1978. A method of bivariate interpolation and smooth surface fitting for irregularly distributed data points. ACM Transactions on Mathematical Software 4:148-159. Bradley, R.S., J. England Jr. 1978. Recent climatic fluctuations of the Canadian high Arctic and their significance for glaciology. Arctic Alpine Research 10:715-731. Bruce,
      J.P., R.H. Clark. 1966. Introduction to Hydrometeorology, 319 pp., Permagon Press, Oxford. Currie, B.W., 1947. Water content of snow in cold climates. Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society 28:150-151. Ferguson, H.L., D.M. Pollock. 1971. Estimating snowpack accumulation for runoff prediction. Canadian Hydrology Symposium No.8: Runoff from Snow and Ice. Inland Water Branch, Dept. of Energy, Mines and Resources, Quebec City. 7-27. Golubev, V.S., 1993. Experience of correction of
      precipitation point measurements and analysis of correction procedures. AMS Proceedings: Eighth Symposium on Meteorological Observations and Instrumentation Anaheim, CA. 325-328. Golubev, V.S., V.V. Koknaeva, A.Yu. Simonenko. 1995. Results of atmospheric precipitation measurements by national standard gauges of Canada, USA, and Russia. Meteorologia i Gidrologia 2:102-110. (in Russian) Goodison, B.E., H.L. Ferguson, G.A. McKay. 1981. Comparison of point snowfall measurement techniques. In:
      D.M.Gray and D.M. Male (Eds). 'Handbook on Snow: Principles, processes, management and use. Pergamon Press, p. 200-210. Goodison, B.E., P.Y.T. Louie. 1986. Canadian methods for precipitation measurement and correction. WMO/TD-No. 104. Instruments and observing methods. Report No. 25. Papers presented at the Workshop on the Correct ion of Precipitation Measurements, Zurich, Switzerland, 1-3 April, 1985, 141-145. Goodison, B.E., J.R. Metcalfe. 1989. Canadian participation in the WMO Solid
      Precipitation Measurement Intercomparison: preliminary results. WMO/IAHS/ETH International Workshop on precipitation Measurement, St.-Mor itz, Switzerland, 3-7 December, 1989, 121-125. Goodison, B.E., P.Y.T. Louie and D. Yang. 1998. WMO solid precipitation measurement intercomparison, final report, 212 pp. World Meteorlogical Organization, Geneva. Groisman, P.Y., V.V. Koknaeva, T.A. Belokrylova, and T.R. Karl. 1991. Overcoming biases of precipitation measurement: A history of the USSR
      experience, Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society 72 (11): 1725-1733. Groisman, P.Ya., R.W. Knight, T.R. Karl, R.R. Heim Jr. 1993. Inferences of the North American snowfall and snow cover with recent global temperature changes. Proceedings of 'Snow Watch '92' Conference, Niagara-on the-Lake, Canada, March 30 - April 1, 1992, 44-51. Groisman, P.Ya., T.R. Karl. R.W. Knight, G.L. Stenchikov. 1994. Changes of snow cover, temperature, and radiative heat balance over the Northern
      Hemisphere. Journal of Climate 7:1633-1656. Groisman, P.Ya., D.R. Easterling. 1996. Variability and trends of precipitation and snowfall over North America. In 'Natural and Climate Variability on Decade-to-Century Time Scales', National Academy Press, 67-77. Groisman, P.Ya., T.R. Karl, D.R. Easterling, R.W. Knight, P.B. Jamason, K J. Hennessy, R. Suppiah, Ch.M. Page, J. Wibig, K. Fortuniak, V.N. Razuvaev, A. Douglas, E. Forland, P.-M. Zhai. 1999. Changes in the prob ability of heavy
      precipitation: Important indicators of climatic change. Climatic Change (in press). Groisman, P.Y. 1998. National Climatic Data Center Data Documentation for TD-9816, Canadian Monthly Precipitation, pp. 21, National Climatic Data Center, 151 Patton Ave., Asheville, NC. Hare, F.K., 1980. Long-term annual surface heat and water balances over Canada and the United States south of 60oN: Reconciliation of precipitation, run-off and temperature fields. Atmosphere-Ocean No.18(2): 127-153. Karl,
      T.R., P.Ya. Groisman, R.W. Knight, R.R. Heim Jr. 1993b. Recent variations of snow cover and snowfall in North America and their relation to precipitation and temperature variations. Journal of Climate 6:1327-1344. Kurtyka, J.C., 1953. Precipitation Measurement Study. State of Illinois, Department of Registration and Education, State Water Survey Division , Urbana, Il. Report of Investigation # 20, 178 pp. Mekis, E., W.D. Hogg. 1997. Rehabilitation and analysis of Canadian daily
      precipitation time series. AMS Proceedings of the 10th conference on applied climatology in Reno, Nevada, October 20-23. 300-304. American Meterology Society, Boston, Mass. Neff, E.L., 1977. How much rain does a rain gauge gauge? Journal of Hydrology 35, 213-220. Potter, J.G., 1965. Water content of freshly fallen snow. Department of Transport, Meteorological Branch. Cirular 4232, Technical 569, 12 pp. Sanderson, M., 1975. A comparison of Canadian and United States standard methods of
      measuring precipitation. Journal of Applied Meteorology 14: 1197-1199. Sevruk B., 1982. Methods of correction for systematic error in point precipitation measurement for operational use. WMO, Operational Hydrology Report Geneva. 21:91p. Woo, M.-K., P. Steer. 1979. Measurement of trace rainfall at a high arctic site. Arctic 32:80-84. World Meteorological Organization (WMO), 1973. Annotated bibliography on precipitation measurement instruments. WMO Geneva, Switzerland 2E 343:278 pp. World
      Meteorological Organization (WMO), 1979. Climatic Atlas of North and Central America, Vol. 1. WMO UNESCO Geneva, Switzerland, 39 pp. World Water Balance and Water Resources of the Earth, 1974. Gidrometeoizdat, Leningrad, 638 pp. (in Russian; in English published by UNESCO Press in 1978). Yang, D., B.E. Goodison, J.R. Metcalfe, V.S. Golubev, E. Elomaa, T. Gunther, R.E. Bates, T.Pangburn, C.L. Hanson, D. Emerson, V. Copaciu, and J. Mikovic. 1995. Accuracy of Tretyakov Precipitation Gauge:
      Result of WMO Intercomparison, 52nd Eastern Snow Conference pp. 95-106, Toronto, Canada. Yang, D. 1999. An improved precipitation climatology for the Arctic Ocean. Geophysical Research Letters 26 (11): 1625-1628. Yang, D., S. Ishida, B.E. Goodison, and T. Gunther. 1999. Bias correction of daily precipitation measurements for Greenland. Journal of Geophysical Research 104 (D6): 6171-6181.</Reference>
   <Summary>
      <Abstract>This data set was distributed by NSIDC until October, 2003, when it was withdrawn from distribution because it duplicates the NOAA National Climatic Data Center (NCDC) data set TD-9816 'Canadian Monthly Precipitation' (Groisman, P.Y. 1998. National Climatic Data Center Data Documentation for TD-9816, Canadian Monthly Precipitation. National Climatic Data Center 151 Patton Ave., Asheville, NC. 21 pp.). TD-9816 contains monthly rainfall, snowfall and precipitation (the sum of
       rainfall and snowfall) values from 6,692 stations in Canada. NCDC investigator Pavel Groisman obtained the original data from the Canadian Atmospheric Environment Service (AES) in the early 1990s and adjusted the measurements to account for inconsistencies and changes in instrumentation over the period of record. TD-9816 contains both the original and adjusted data. Related data are the Historical Adjusted Climate Database for Canada, Version December 2002, and Rehabilitated Precipitation
       and Homogenized Temperature Data Sets provided by the Climate Monitoring and Data Interpretation Division's Climate Research Branch, Meteorological Service of Canada. Monthly Rehabilitated Precipitation and Homogenized Temperature Data Sets (updated annually) includes an alternative version of this data set using different correction methods. It is distributed by the Meteorological Service of Canada, who also provides a Microsoft Word document that compares the two different data
       correction methods.</Abstract>
   </Summary>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>GET DATA</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>http://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/oa/ncdc.html</URL>
      <Description>Get External Data</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>VIEW PROJECT HOME PAGE</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>http://www.cccma.bc.ec.gc.ca/hccd/</URL>
      <Description>Meteorological Service of Canada: Monthly Rehabilitated Precipitation and Homogenized Temperature Data Sets</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>VIEW RELATED INFORMATION</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>http://nsidc.org/data/nsidc-0059.html</URL>
      <Description>Former Soviet Union Monthly Precipitation Archive, 1891-1993</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <Related_URL>
      <URL_Content_Type>
         <Type>VIEW PROJECT HOME PAGE</Type>
      </URL_Content_Type>
      <URL>http://nsidc.org/data/docs/daac/nsidc0072_canadian_precip/comparison.html</URL>
      <Description>Comparison of Data Correction Methods</Description>
   </Related_URL>
   <IDN_Node>
      <Short_Name>USA/NASA</Short_Name>
   </IDN_Node>
   <Metadata_Name>CEOS IDN DIF</Metadata_Name>
   <Metadata_Version>VERSION 9.9</Metadata_Version>
   <DIF_Creation_Date>2000-01-01</DIF_Creation_Date>
   <Last_DIF_Revision_Date>2012-09-18</Last_DIF_Revision_Date>
   <DIF_Revision_History> 2000-01-01, Transferred from mddb dataset_citation.release_date 2003-10-09, yohe, 2003-10-09, kgentsch, Retry publishing. Trying to find publishing error. 2003-10-09, kgentsch, Publishing to make sure fix to dif_plus info publishing is fixed. 2003-10-13, yohe, 2005-01-24, yohe, 2008-03-04, Deann Miller, updated data center info. 2010-03-24, Deann Miller, Fixed references section. Some of the citations were running together in the GCMD. 2011-07-28, Deann Miller,
      Removed the unneeded vertical resolution field. 2012-07-10, Deann Miller, corrected dist. size and format 2012-08-28, Deann Miller, Added an archiving data center. 2012-09-18, Deann Miller, deleted catalog page URL in Related URLs field </DIF_Revision_History>
   <Extended_Metadata>
      <Metadata>
         <Group>NSIDC</Group>
         <Name>Version Summary</Name>
         <Value/>
      </Metadata>
      <Metadata>
         <Group>NSIDC</Group>
         <Name>Current Version</Name>
         <Value>1</Value>
      </Metadata>
   </Extended_Metadata>
</DIF>
