<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<dsOverview 
            
                                                     
            ID="507.5"
            type="primary">
   <timeStamp value="2015-02-11 15:08:05 -0700"/>
   <continuingUpdate value="yes" frequency="quarterly"/>
   <title>NCEP/CPC Four Kilometer Precipitation Set, Gauge and Radar</title>
   <summary>
      <p>A prototype, real-time, hourly, multi-sensor National Precipitation
              Analysis has been developed at the National Centers for Environmental
              Prediction (NCEP) in cooperation with the Office of Hydrology (OH). This
              analysis merges two data sources that are currently being collected in
              real-time by OH and NCEP.  Approximately 3000 automated, hourly rain gauge
              observations are available over the contiguous 48 states via the GOES
              Data Collection Platform, and ASOS.  In addition, hourly digital
              precipitation (HDP) radar estimates are obtained as compressed digital
              files via the AWIPS network. The HDP estimates are created by the WSR-88D
              Radar Product Generator on a 131 by 131 4 km grid centered over each
              radar site. The data analysis routines, including a bias correction of the
              radar estimates using the gage data, have been adapted by NCEP on a
              national 4 km grid from algorithms developed by OH ("Stage II") and
              executed regionally at NWS River Forecast Centers.</p>
      <p>The precipitation data in this dataset are received through UCAR/JOSS.</p>
   </summary>
   <creator vocabulary="GCMD"
            name="UCAR/NCAR/CISL/DSS &gt; Data Support Section, Computational and Information Systems Laboratory, National Center for Atmospheric Research, University Corporation for Atmospheric Research"/>
   <contributor vocabulary="GCMD"
                name="DOC/NOAA/NWS/NCEP/CPC &gt; Climate Prediction Center, National Centers for Environmental Prediction, National Weather Service, NOAA, U.S. Department of Commerce"
                citable="no"/>
   <contributor vocabulary="GCMD"
                name="UCAR/JOSS &gt; Joint Office for Science Support, University Corporation for Atmospheric Research"
                citable="no"/>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Atmosphere &gt; Precipitation &gt; Precipitation Amount</variable>
   <contact>Chi-Fan Shih</contact>
   <platform vocabulary="GCMD">GRIDDING METHODS</platform>
   <topic vocabulary="ISO">climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</topic>
   <relatedResource url="http://www.emc.ncep.noaa.gov/mmb/ylin/pcpanl/">NCEP's national multi-sensor hourly precipitation analysis</relatedResource>
   <relatedResource url="http://data.eol.ucar.edu/codiac/dss/id=21.093">EOL codiac dataset: GCIP/EOP Surface: Precipitation NCEP/EMC 4KM Gridded Data (GRIB) Stage IV Data</relatedResource>
   <publicationDate>2000-11-15</publicationDate>
   <contentMetadata>
      <temporal start="9998" end="9998" groupID="Entire Dataset"/>
      <temporalFrequency type="regular" number="1" unit="hour" statistics="accumulation"/>
      <dataType>grid</dataType>
      <format>WMO_GRIB1</format>
      <levels>
         <level type="Ground or water surface" value="0"/>
      </levels>
      <geospatialCoverage>
         <grid definition="polarStereographic"
               numX="1160"
               numY="880"
               startLon="120.376W"
               startLat="22.7736N"
               projLon="105W"
               xRes="4.7625"
               yRes="4.7625"
               pole="N"/>
      </geospatialCoverage>
   </contentMetadata>
</dsOverview>
