<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<dsOverview 
            
                                                     
            ID="871.0"
            type="primary">
   <timeStamp value="2012-07-12 16:04:08 -0600"/>
   <continuingUpdate value="no"/>
   <access pricingRate="standard">all_free</access>
   <title>ADAPTE: Minimum and Maximum Temperature and Relative Humidity for Latin American Cities Data</title>
   <summary>
      <p>Temperature data classified as maximum, mean, and minimum temperature and relative humidity measures from the meteorological station located at the regional airport in Bogota and Buenos Aries, called the National Service of Hydrology and Meteorology. Mexico data was collected from the National Polytechnic Institute of Mexico and National Meteorological System. In Santiago, Chile weather data was provided by the air pollution monitoring network with stations across the city, the REDCAM2 (Red de Monitoreo Automatica de la Calidad del Aire Metropolitana) Automatic Monitoring Network of Metropolitan Air Quality. The data from these stations were averaged to obtain temperature values for the Gran Santiago region. Daily temperature and relative humidity readings were made by automatic-recording instruments.</p>
   </summary>
   <creator vocabulary="GCMD"
            name="UCAR/NCAR/CISL/DSS &gt; Data Support Section, Computational and Information Systems Laboratory, National Center for Atmospheric Research, University Corporation for Atmospheric Research"/>
   <contributor vocabulary="GCMD"
                name="UCAR/NCAR/RAL &gt; Research Applications Laboratory, National Center for Atmospheric Research, University Corporation for Atmospheric Research"/>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Atmosphere &gt; Atmospheric Water Vapor &gt; Humidity</variable>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Atmosphere &gt; Atmospheric Temperature &gt; Maximum/Minimum Temperature</variable>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Atmosphere &gt; Atmospheric Water Vapor &gt; Dew Point Temperature</variable>
   <contact>Steven Worley</contact>
   <platform vocabulary="GCMD">FIXED OBSERVATION STATIONS</platform>
   <platform vocabulary="GCMD">METEOROLOGICAL STATIONS</platform>
   <platform vocabulary="GCMD">WEATHER STATIONS</platform>
   <topic vocabulary="ISO">climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</topic>
   <reference type="journal">
      <authorList>Romero Lankao, P., Borbor-Cordova, M., Abrutsky, R., Gunther, G., and Behrentz, E.</authorList>
      <year>2012</year>
      <title>ADAPTE: A tale of four teams seeking to do integrated research</title>
      <periodical number="2" pages="0-0">Environmental Science and Policy</periodical>
   </reference>
   <reference type="book_chapter">
      <authorList>Romero-Lankao, P., Qin, H., Hughes, S., Borbor-Cordova M., and Haeffner, M.</authorList>
      <year>2012</year>
      <title>Urban Vulnerability and Adaptation to the Health Impacts of Air Pollution and Climate Extremes in Latin American Cites</title>
      <book editor="William G. Holt"
            publisher="Emerald Group Publishing"
            pages="0-0">Urban Areas and Global Climate Change</book>
   </reference>
   <publicationDate>2012-06-20</publicationDate>
   <contentMetadata>
      <temporal start="2003-01-01" end="2006-12-31" groupID="Entire Dataset"/>
      <temporal start="2002-01-01" end="2006-12-31" groupID="Entire Dataset"/>
      <temporal start="2001-01-01" end="2005-12-31" groupID="Entire Dataset"/>
      <temporal start="2000-01-01" end="2004-12-31" groupID="Entire Dataset"/>
      <dataType>platform_observation</dataType>
      <format>comma-separated_values</format>
      <geospatialCoverage>
         <location>Continent &gt; South America &gt; Colombia</location>
         <location>Continent &gt; South America &gt; Chile</location>
         <location>Continent &gt; North America &gt; Mexico</location>
         <location>Continent &gt; South America &gt; Argentina</location>
      </geospatialCoverage>
   </contentMetadata>
</dsOverview>
