<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<dsOverview 
            
                                                     
            ID="728.0"
            type="historical">
   <timeStamp value="2015-11-23 15:24:07 -0700"/>
   <continuingUpdate value="no"/>
   <title>GPCP Combined Precipitation Data (version 2.0)</title>
   <summary>
      <p>This dataset contains version 2.0 of the Global Precipitation Climatology Project (GPCP) monthly combined satellite-gauge precipitation data as well as error estimates.  A climatology is also available. All data is available on a 2.5 by 2.5 degree global latitude/longitude grid.
              </p>
      <p>
              The general approach used to create the final product was to combine precipitation information
              available from each of several sources into a final merged product, taking
              advantage of the strengths of each data type.  The satellite data included
              microwave estimates based on Special Sensor Microwave/Imager (SSM/I) data,
              and IR precipitation estimates from geostationary and polar-orbiting satellites.
              Additional low-Earth orbit estimates include the TIROS Operational Vertical Sounder (TOVS)
              and OPI data from the NOAA series satellites.  The gauge data are assembled and analyzed
              by the Global Precipitation Climatology Center (GPCC) of the Deutscher Wetterdienst
              and by the Climate Prediction Center of NOAA.
              </p>
      <p>
              A more detailed description of the data can be found <a href="http://rda.ucar.edu/datasets/ds728.0/docs/V2_doc">here</a>.</p>
   </summary>
   <creator vocabulary="GCMD"
            name="UCAR/NCAR/CISL/DSS &gt; Data Support Section, Computational and Information Systems Laboratory, National Center for Atmospheric Research, University Corporation for Atmospheric Research"/>
   <contributor vocabulary="GCMD"
                name="NASA/GSFC/SED/ESD/LA/MAPB &gt; Mesoscale Atmospheric Processes Branch, Laboratory for Atmospheres, Earth Sciences Division, Science and Exploration Directorate, Goddard Space Flight Center, NASA"
                contact="G.J. Huffman;D.T. Bolvin;R.F. Adler"
                citable="yes"/>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Atmosphere &gt; Precipitation &gt; Precipitation Amount</variable>
   <contact>Thomas Cram</contact>
   <platform vocabulary="GCMD">GRIDDING METHODS</platform>
   <topic vocabulary="ISO">climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</topic>
   <reference type="journal">
      <authorList>Adler, R.F., G.J. Huffman, A. Chang, R. Ferraro, P. Xie, J. Janowiak, B. Rudolf, U. Schneider, S. Curtis, D. Bolvin, A. Gruber, J. Susskind, and P. Arkin</authorList>
      <year>2003</year>
      <title>The Version 2 Global Precipitation Climatology Project (GPCP) Monthly Precipitation Analysis (1979-Present)</title>
      <periodical number="4" pages="1147-1167">J. Hydrometeor.</periodical>
   </reference>
   <relatedResource url="http://precip.gsfc.nasa.gov/">GSFC Global Precipitation Analysis web site</relatedResource>
   <publicationDate>1992-02-14</publicationDate>
   <contentMetadata>
      <temporal start="1979" end="2006-07" groupID="Entire Dataset"/>
      <temporalFrequency type="regular" number="1" unit="month"/>
      <temporalFrequency type="climatology" unit="month"/>
      <dataType>grid</dataType>
      <format>proprietary_ASCII</format>
      <levels>
         <level type="Ground or water surface" value="0"/>
      </levels>
      <geospatialCoverage>
         <grid definition="latLon"
               numX="144"
               numY="72"
               startLon="1.25E"
               startLat="88.75N"
               endLon="358.75E"
               endLat="88.75S"
               xRes="2.5"
               yRes="2.5"/>
      </geospatialCoverage>
   </contentMetadata>
</dsOverview>
