<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<dsOverview 
            
                                                     
            ID="260.4"
            type="primary">
   <timeStamp value="2015-11-18 10:41:03 -0700"/>
   <doi>10.5065/D6930R70</doi>
   <continuingUpdate value="no"/>
   <title>Shipboard Automated Meteorological and Oceanographic System (SAMOS) Air-Sea Fluxes</title>
   <summary>
      <p>Bulk turbulent heat and momentum fluxes derived using one-minute interval data collected by the Shipboard Automated Meteorological and Oceanographic System (SAMOS) initiative. The fluxes are provided as three products derived using three widely accepted air-sea flux algorithms (Smith 1988, COARE 3.5, and a variant of Bourassa 2006). Each product is grouped by the years the data are collected. The dataset uses SAMOS data from 19 research vessels with observations spanning 2005-2014. Data coverage is the global oceans, but is concentrated around North America. Data include heat and momentum fluxes along with state variables adjusted to 10 meters.</p>
      <p>The dataset was developed under base support for the SAMOS project which is provided by a grant from the Climate Observing Division of the National Oceanographic and Atmospheric Administration via the Northern Gulf of Mexico Cooperative Institute administered by the Mississippi State University. Additional support for SAMOS is provided by Oceanographic and Technical Services Program of the National Science Foundation (grant OCE #1447797), the Office of Naval Research (via NSF), and the Schmidt Ocean Institute. </p>
   </summary>
   <creator vocabulary="GCMD"
            name="UCAR/NCAR/CISL/DSS &gt; Data Support Section, Computational and Information Systems Laboratory, National Center for Atmospheric Research, University Corporation for Atmospheric Research"/>
   <contributor vocabulary="GCMD"
                name="FSU/COAPS &gt; Center for Ocean-Atmospheric Prediction Studies, Florida State University"
                contact="Shawn R. Smith, (850)644-6918, smith@coaps.fsu.edu"
                citable="yes"/>
   <author>Shawn R. Smith</author>
   <author>Nicholas Lopez</author>
   <author>Mark A. Bourassa</author>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Oceans &gt; Ocean Heat Budget &gt; Heat Flux</variable>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Oceans &gt; Ocean Winds &gt; Wind Stress</variable>
   <contact>Zaihua Ji</contact>
   <platform vocabulary="GCMD">SHIPS</platform>
   <topic vocabulary="ISO">oceans</topic>
   <publicationDate>2015-10-08</publicationDate>
   <contentMetadata>
      <temporal start="2005-05-09" end="2015-06-12" groupID="Entire Dataset"/>
      <temporalFrequency type="regular" number="6" unit="minute"/>
      <temporalFrequency type="regular" number="0" unit="minute"/>
      <temporalFrequency type="regular" number="1" unit="minute"/>
      <temporalFrequency type="regular" number="0" unit="second"/>
      <dataType>grid</dataType>
      <dataType>platform_observation</dataType>
      <format href="http://www.unidata.ucar.edu/software/netcdf/">netCDF</format>
   </contentMetadata>
</dsOverview>
