<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<dsOverview 
            
                                                     
            ID="723.0"
            type="primary">
   <timeStamp value="2015-02-05 15:43:13 -0700"/>
   <continuingUpdate value="yes" frequency="irregularly"/>
   <title>Atmospheric Profiles from COSMIC Occultation Data</title>
   <summary>
      <p>Using a radio occultation technique, scientists are able to use signals broadcast from Global Positioning System (GPS) satellites to retrieve profiles of bending angles, refractivity, temperature, pressure, and water vapor in the atmosphere. Also, profiles of electron density in the ionosphere. Such data are gathered and processed at the Constellation Observing System for Meteorology, Ionosphere, Climate (COSMIC) Data Analysis and Archive Center (CDAAC) in Boulder, Colorado. Various products are produced including atmospheric profiles starting from near Earth's surface to the height of the satellites at 800 kilometers (500 miles) above the Earth surface. At this time only atmospheric profiles of bending angle, refractivity, and dry temperature are available. As we receive more data this archive will continue to expand to include more variable profiles.</p>
   </summary>
   <creator vocabulary="GCMD"
            name="UCAR/NCAR/CISL/DSS &gt; Data Support Section, Computational and Information Systems Laboratory, National Center for Atmospheric Research, University Corporation for Atmospheric Research"/>
   <contributor vocabulary="GCMD"
                name="UCAR/COSMIC/CDAAC &gt; COSMIC Data Analysis and Archive Center, Constellation Observing System for Meteorology, Ionosphere and Climate, University Corporation for Atmospheric Research"
                citable="yes"/>
   <restrictions>
      <access>
         <p> Data access is granted only to users who have registered at <a href="http://cdaac-www.cosmic.ucar.edu/cdaac/index.html">CDAAC</a>
         </p>
      </access>
   </restrictions>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Atmosphere &gt; Atmospheric Temperature &gt; Air Temperature</variable>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Atmosphere &gt; Atmospheric Pressure &gt; Atmospheric Pressure Measurements</variable>
   <contact>Chi-Fan Shih</contact>
   <platform vocabulary="GCMD">GPS &gt; Global Positioning System Satellites</platform>
   <platform vocabulary="GCMD">COSMIC/FORMOSAT-3 &gt; Constellation Observing System for Meteorology, Ionosphere and Climate</platform>
   <project vocabulary="GCMD">GPS/MET &gt; Global Positioning System Meteorology Experiment</project>
   <topic vocabulary="ISO">climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</topic>
   <relatedResource url="http://cdaac-www.cosmic.ucar.edu/cdaac/">COSMIC Data Analysis and Archive Center</relatedResource>
   <relatedResource url="http://www.cosmic.ucar.edu">Constellation Observing System for Meteorology, Ionosphere and Climate</relatedResource>
   <relatedDataset ID="721.0"/>
   <publicationDate>2013-04-25</publicationDate>
   <contentMetadata>
      <temporal start="2006-04-21" end="2013-12-31" groupID="Entire Dataset"/>
      <dataType>location</dataType>
      <format>netCDF</format>
   </contentMetadata>
</dsOverview>
