<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<dsOverview 
            
                                                     
            ID="758.0"
            type="primary">
   <timeStamp value="2014-02-07 11:46:41 -0700"/>
   <continuingUpdate value="no"/>
   <title>USGS 30 ARC-second Global Elevation Data, GTOPO30</title>
   <summary>
      <p>
              GTOPO30 is a global raster digital elevation model (DEM) providing terrain
              elevation data with a horizontal grid spacing of
              30 arc seconds (approximately 1 kilometer). GTOPO30 was derived from several raster
              and vector sources of topographic information. For easier distribution, GTOPO30
              has been divided into <a href="http://rda.ucar.edu/datasets/ds758.0/docs/tiles.gif">tiles</a>.
              Detailed information on the characteristics of GTOPO30
              including the data distribution format, the data sources, production methods, accuracy,
              and hints for users, is found in the GTOPO30
              <a href="http://rda.ucar.edu/datasets/ds758.0/docs/readme.txt">README</a> file.
              </p>
      <p>
              GTOPO30, completed in late 1996, was developed over a three year period through a collaborative effort led by staff at the U.S. Geological Survey's Center for Earth Resources Observation and Science (EROS). The following organizations participated by contributing funding or source data:  the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA), the United Nations Environment Program and Global Resource Information Database (UNEP and GRID), the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID), the Instituto Nacional de Estadistica Geografica e Informatica (INEGI) of Mexico, the Geographical Survey Institute (GSI) of Japan, Manaaki Whenua Landcare Research of New Zealand, and the Scientific Committee on Antarctic Research (SCAR).
              </p>
   </summary>
   <creator vocabulary="GCMD"
            name="UCAR/NCAR/CISL/DSS &gt; Data Support Section, Computational and Information Systems Laboratory, National Center for Atmospheric Research, University Corporation for Atmospheric Research"/>
   <contributor vocabulary="GCMD"
                name="DOI/USGS/EROS &gt; Center for Earth Resources Observation and Science, U.S. Geological Survey, U.S. Department of the Interior"
                citable="yes"/>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Land Surface &gt; Topography &gt; Terrain Elevation</variable>
   <contact>Doug Schuster</contact>
   <platform vocabulary="GCMD">GRIDDING METHODS</platform>
   <topic vocabulary="ISO">elevation</topic>
   <relatedResource url="https://lta.cr.usgs.gov/GTOPO30">This is a USGS data set available in the USGS long term archive.</relatedResource>
   <publicationDate>1997-07-24</publicationDate>
   <contentMetadata>
      <temporal start="9998" end="9998" groupID="Entire Dataset"/>
      <dataType>grid</dataType>
      <format>proprietary_Binary</format>
      <levels>
         <level type="Ground or water surface" value="0"/>
      </levels>
      <geospatialCoverage>
         <grid definition="latLon"
               numX="43200"
               numY="31600"
               startLon="180W"
               startLat="90S"
               endLon="180E"
               endLat="90N"
               xRes="0.0083"
               yRes="0.0083"/>
      </geospatialCoverage>
   </contentMetadata>
</dsOverview>
