<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<dsOverview 
            
                                                     
            ID="866.0"
            type="primary">
   <timeStamp value="2014-06-05 17:30:54 -0600"/>
   <continuingUpdate value="no"/>
   <title>GISS Global Methane and Livestock Distribution, 1-Degree</title>
   <summary>
      <p>A global high resolution data base of animal population
              densities and associated methane (CH4) emissions has been
              developed at the NASA Goddard Institute for Space Studies
              (NASA/GISS). The animal population statistics were based
              primarily on the Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO)
              compilations and other sources. The animals were distributed
              using a 1-degree by 1-degree resolution data base of countries and
              land-use (Matthews, 1983). The animals included are cattle and
              dairy cows, water buffalo, sheep, goats, camels, pigs, horses,
              and caribou. Estimates of methane production from each animal
              type were applied to the animal populations to yield a global
              distribution of methane emissions by animals. About 55% of the
              global annual emissions was concentrated between 25 N and 55 N.
              Estimates of methane emissions from animals were based on the
              research by Crutzen et al (1986).</p>
   </summary>
   <creator vocabulary="GCMD"
            name="UCAR/NCAR/CISL/DSS &gt; Data Support Section, Computational and Information Systems Laboratory, National Center for Atmospheric Research, University Corporation for Atmospheric Research"/>
   <contributor vocabulary="GCMD"
                name="NASA/GSFC/ESD/GISS &gt; Goddard Institute for Space Studies, Earth Sciences Directorate, Goddard Space Flight Center, NASA"
                contact="Elaine Matthews;Lerner"
                citable="yes"/>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Atmosphere &gt; Atmospheric Chemistry/Carbon and Hydrocarbon Compounds &gt; Methane</variable>
   <contact>Bob Dattore</contact>
   <platform vocabulary="GCMD">GRIDDING METHODS</platform>
   <topic vocabulary="ISO">biota</topic>
   <reference type="journal">
      <authorList>Lerner, J., E. Matthews, and I. Fung</authorList>
      <year>1988</year>
      <title>Methane emission from animals: A global high-resolution data base</title>
      <periodical number="2(2)" pages="139-156">Global Biochemical Cycles</periodical>
   </reference>
   <publicationDate>1989-07-20</publicationDate>
   <contentMetadata>
      <temporal start="9998" end="9998" groupID="Entire Dataset"/>
      <dataType>grid</dataType>
      <format>proprietary_ASCII</format>
      <levels>
         <level type="Ground or water surface" value="0"/>
      </levels>
      <geospatialCoverage>
         <grid definition="latLon"
               numX="360"
               numY="180"
               startLon="0.5E"
               startLat="89.5N"
               endLon="359.5E"
               endLat="89.5S"
               xRes="1"
               yRes="1"/>
      </geospatialCoverage>
   </contentMetadata>
</dsOverview>
