<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<dsOverview 
            
                                                     
            ID="285.2"
            type="primary">
   <timeStamp value="2013-02-26 20:44:47 -0700"/>
   <continuingUpdate value="no"/>
   <access pricingRate="standard">all_free</access>
   <title>Polar Science Center Hydrographic Climatology (PHC)</title>
   <summary>
      <p>
              The climatology provides temperature and salinity data at 1X1
              degree intervals for all the earth's oceans, down to a depth
              of 5500m, at incremental depths identical to those provided
              in the National Oceanographic Data Center's (NODC) World Ocean
              Atlas (WOA). This global climatology is the combination of
              NODC's 1998 world climatology (WOA), the EWG Arctic Ocean Atlas
              (AOA), and select Canadian data provided by the Bedford
              Institute of Oceanography (BIO). While the NODC data includes
              the Arctic ocean, the AOA data provides a better description of
              this region. Neither of these data fields provides a good
              representation of the Canadian Archipelago region and nearby
              bays in the winter months. The data from the Bedford Institute
              of Oceanography allowed us to bridge this data hole. These
              three data sets were merged using an optimal interpolation
              routine such that our PHC retains the high quality world
              description provided by the WOA while improving the Arctic with
              the AOA fields and Canadian data.
              </p>
      <p>
              In summary, PHC = WOA (Levitus) '98 everywhere except in our
              arctic domain, where we have blended in the AOA field
              (from EWG), and the BIO data to produce a more realistic arctic
              region.
              </p>
      <p>
              These Version 3.0 data were received from the Polar
              Science Center, Applied Physics Lab., University of Washington,
              during April 2005.
              </p>
   </summary>
   <creator vocabulary="GCMD"
            name="UCAR/NCAR/CISL/DSS &gt; Data Support Section, Computational and Information Systems Laboratory, National Center for Atmospheric Research, University Corporation for Atmospheric Research"/>
   <contributor vocabulary="GCMD"
                name="UWA/APL/PSC &gt; Polar Science Center, Applied Physics Laboratory, University of Washington"/>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Oceans &gt; Ocean Temperature &gt; Water Temperature</variable>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Oceans &gt; Salinity/Density &gt; Salinity</variable>
   <contact>Zaihua Ji</contact>
   <platform vocabulary="GCMD">GRIDDING METHODS</platform>
   <topic vocabulary="ISO">oceans</topic>
   <reference type="journal">
      <authorList>Steele, M., R. Morley, and W. Ermold</authorList>
      <year>2001</year>
      <title>PHC: A global ocean hydrography with a high quality Arctic Ocean</title>
      <periodical number="14" pages="2079-2087">J. Climate</periodical>
   </reference>
   <relatedResource url="http://psc.apl.washington.edu/Climatology.html">PSC/APL University of Washington</relatedResource>
   <relatedDataset ID="285.0"/>
   <publicationDate>2001-12-28</publicationDate>
   <contentMetadata>
      <temporal start="9998" end="9998" groupID="Entire Dataset"/>
      <dataType>grid</dataType>
      <format>proprietary_ASCII</format>
      <geospatialCoverage>
         <grid definition="latLon"
               numX="360"
               numY="180"
               startLon="0.5E"
               startLat="89.5S"
               endLon="359.5E"
               endLat="89.5N"
               xRes="1"
               yRes="1"/>
      </geospatialCoverage>
   </contentMetadata>
</dsOverview>
