<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<dsOverview 
            
                                                     
            ID="352.0"
            type="primary">
   <timeStamp value="2015-11-19 14:28:03 -0700"/>
   <continuingUpdate value="no"/>
   <title>The Comprehensive Historical Upper Air Network</title>
   <summary>
      <p>The Comprehensive Historical Upper-Air Network (CHUAN) represents a global, historical upper-air dataset that has been derived from heterogeneous data available from various sources, including newly digitized data.  The data have been derived from radiosondes, pilot balloons, registering balloons and kites and has been subjected to a systematic quality assessment.  CHUAN has focused on collecting data for pre-1957 .</p>
      <p>
              This product is the "V1.7" corrected (quality controlled) data with no bias or radiation correction applied ("CDC" in CHUAN documentation).  There are other products available in "V1.7", like corrected data with bias and radiation corrections and the raw (non quality controlled) soundings, along with others, that are not available at this time.</p>
      <p>A new version is expected to be available in mid 2014.</p>
   </summary>
   <creator vocabulary="GCMD"
            name="UCAR/NCAR/CISL/DSS &gt; Data Support Section, Computational and Information Systems Laboratory, National Center for Atmospheric Research, University Corporation for Atmospheric Research"/>
   <contributor vocabulary="GCMD"
                name="U-BERN/GI/CRG &gt; Climatology Research Group, Institute of Geography, University of Bern"
                citable="yes"/>
   <author>Stefan Bronnimann</author>
   <author>Alexander Stickler</author>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Atmosphere &gt; Atmospheric Temperature &gt; Air Temperature</variable>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Atmosphere &gt; Atmospheric Water Vapor &gt; Humidity</variable>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Atmosphere &gt; Atmospheric Winds &gt; Upper Level Winds</variable>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Atmosphere &gt; Altitude &gt; Geopotential Height</variable>
   <contact>Grace Peng</contact>
   <platform vocabulary="GCMD">RADIOSONDES</platform>
   <platform vocabulary="GCMD">BALLOONS</platform>
   <topic vocabulary="ISO">climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</topic>
   <reference type="journal">
      <authorList>A. Stickler, A. N. Grant, T. Ewen, T. F. Ross, R. S. Vose, J. Comeaux, P. Bessemoulin, K. Jylhä, W. K. Adam, P. Jeannet, A. Nagurny, A. M. Sterin, R. Allan, G. P. Compo, T. Griesser, and S. Brönnimann</authorList>
      <year>2010</year>
      <title>The Comprehensive Historical Upper-Air Network</title>
      <periodical number="91(6)" pages="741-751">Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society</periodical>
      <doi>10.1175/2009BAMS2852.1</doi>
      <url>http://journals.ametsoc.org/doi/abs/10.1175/2009BAMS2852.1</url>
   </reference>
   <relatedResource url="http://www.historicalupperair.org">Comprehensive Historical Upper-Air Network Data from the University of Bern</relatedResource>
   <publicationDate>2013-11-21</publicationDate>
   <contentMetadata>
      <temporal start="1904-01-01" end="2007-03-27" groupID="Entire Dataset"/>
      <temporalFrequency type="irregular" unit="day"/>
      <dataType>platform_observation</dataType>
      <format>proprietary_ASCII</format>
   </contentMetadata>
</dsOverview>
