<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<dsOverview 
            
                                                     
            ID="552.1"
            type="primary">
   <timeStamp value="2014-08-21 21:59:05 -0600"/>
   <continuingUpdate value="no"/>
   <title>Monthly Discharge Data for World Rivers (except former Soviet Union)</title>
   <summary>
      <p>This dataset contains monthly river discharge rates for 4,425
          locations around the world except for the former Soviet Union.
          This dataset combines the UNESCO set (ds552.0) plus 3,455 gages,
          thus, improving spatial coverage over much of the world with
          major gains in Brazil, Australia and Argentina.  The "new" gauges
          have not been subjected to the rigorous comparisons of the
          benchmark UNESCO portion.  Their locations, names, and
          drainage areas have been edited; and obvious errors (e.g.,
          egregious extremes, replicates) removed from flow rates.  Data
          sources and the edits are documented.</p>
      <p>The USGS offers a CDROM "Hydro-Climatic Data Network:
          Streamflow Data Set, 1874-1988".  This consists of streamflow
          data measured at 1659 sites throughout the US and its
          territories.  Daily mean, monthly mean, annual mean, minimum and
          maximum values of discharge are given for each water year.
          Stations selected distinguish human influences.</p>
   </summary>
   <creator vocabulary="GCMD"
            name="UCAR/NCAR/CISL/DSS &gt; Data Support Section, Computational and Information Systems Laboratory, National Center for Atmospheric Research, University Corporation for Atmospheric Research"/>
   <contributor vocabulary="GCMD"
                name="DE/FIH/GRDC &gt; Global Runoff Data Center, Federal Institute of Hydrology, Germany"
                citable="yes"/>
   <contributor vocabulary="GCMD"
                name="UNESCO/IHP &gt; International Hydrological Programme, United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization"
                citable="yes"/>
   <variable vocabulary="GCMD">EARTH SCIENCE &gt; Hydrosphere &gt; Surface Water &gt; Discharge/Flow</variable>
   <contact>Bob Dattore</contact>
   <platform vocabulary="GCMD">FIXED OBSERVATION STATIONS</platform>
   <topic vocabulary="ISO">inlandWaters</topic>
   <reference type="preprint">
      <authorList>Dai, A. and K.E. Trenberth</authorList>
      <year>2003</year>
      <title>New Estimates of Continental Discharge and Oceanic Freshwater Transport</title>
      <conference host="Amer. Meteor. Soc." location="Long Beach, CA" pages="1-18">Symposium on Observing and Understanding the Variability of Water in Weather and Climate, 83rd Annual AMS Meeting</conference>
   </reference>
   <referenceURL url="http://tenaya.ucsd.edu/~dettinge/global.html">Dettinger publications including: 'Global Characteristics of Stream Flow Seasonality and Variability' (Aug 2000)</referenceURL>
   <relatedResource url="http://grdc.bafg.de">Global Runoff Data Centre</relatedResource>
   <relatedResource url="http://www.wsag.unh.edu/">Water Systems Analysis Group at the University of New Hampshire</relatedResource>
   <relatedResource url="http://hydrology.pnnl.gov">Hydrology Technical Group at Pacific Northwest National Laboratory</relatedResource>
   <relatedResource url="http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/metadata/usgswrd/XML/hcdn.xml">USGS Hydro-Climatic Data Network (HCDN) Dataset</relatedResource>
   <relatedDataset ID="552.0"/>
   <relatedDataset ID="553.1"/>
   <relatedDataset ID="553.2"/>
   <publicationDate>2001-03-20</publicationDate>
   <contentMetadata>
      <temporal start="1807-01-01" end="2000-12-31" groupID="Entire Dataset"/>
      <temporalFrequency type="regular" number="1" unit="month"/>
      <dataType>grid</dataType>
      <dataType>platform_observation</dataType>
      <format>proprietary_ASCII</format>
   </contentMetadata>
</dsOverview>
