<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-fce.449.5" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/eml/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset id="LT_ND_Collado_001" scope="document"><alternateIdentifier>LT_ND_Collado_001</alternateIdentifier><title>Macroalgae Production in Florida Bay from May 2007 to April 2010</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation><givenName>Ligia</givenName><surName>Collado-Vides</surName></individualName><organizationName>Southeast Environmental Research Center</organizationName><positionName>Project Collaborator</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Biological Sciences</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>FIU</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>11200 SW 8th Street</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>OE 167</deliveryPoint><city>Miami</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33199</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">305-348-2274</phone><phone phonetype="fax">305-348-4096</phone><electronicMailAddress>colladol@fiu.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.marinemacroalgae.com/</onlineUrl></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><organizationName>Florida Coastal Everglades LTER Program</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Florida International University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University Park</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>OE 148</deliveryPoint><city>Miami</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33199</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">305-348-6054</phone><electronicMailAddress>fcelter@fiu.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://fcelter.fiu.edu</onlineUrl></metadataProvider><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Ligia</givenName><surName>Collado-Vides</surName></individualName><organizationName>Southeast Environmental Research Center</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Biological Sciences</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>FIU</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>11200 SW 8th Street</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>OE 167</deliveryPoint><city>Miami</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33199</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">305-348-2274</phone><phone phonetype="fax">305-348-4096</phone><electronicMailAddress>colladol@fiu.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.marinemacroalgae.com/</onlineUrl><role>Project Collaborator</role></associatedParty><pubDate>2013-01-31</pubDate><abstract><para>Benthic primary production in Florida Bay is mainly driven by mangroves, seagrass, peryphiton, and macroalgae.  The nutrient dynamics and salinity regimes at Florida Bay are strongly influenced by marine waters from the Gulf of Mexico, oceanic waters from the Atlantic Ocean and fresh waters from the Everglades creating a complex estuary with oligohaline ecotones. Marine and groundwater are sources of P and are expected to decline with increased freshwater inflow (Childers et al. 2006a; Price et al. 2006). The Taylor Slough ecotone, (TS/Ph), which flows into the Bay, is characterized by small tidal influence and clear seasonal variability in water source and quality (Davis et al. 2003; Sutula et al. 2001), receives P from shallow groundwater inputs (Price et al. 2006).Therefore the amount of freshwater inputs from the Everglades will affect salinity, water residence times, and the sources, availability, and flux of organic and inorganic nutrients on Florida Bay. As a consequence gradients of N and P concentrations are characteristic in the Bay with expected low concentration of P and high N on the fresh water end, contrasting with higher levels of P and lower of N towards the marine section of the Bay. This gradient in P concentrations is expected to reflect in differences in both primary production and biomass along the TS/Ph ecotone. One of the Everglades LTER scientist general hypothesis is "that increasing inputs of freshwater will enhance oligotrophy in nutrient-poor coastal systems, as long as the inflowing water has low nutrient content; this dynamic will be most pronounced in the oligohaline ecotone" (LTER program).  In this context we expect to have a differential production of calcareous macroalgae along the TS-Ph transect which reflect the P gradient with low productivity towards the fresh water influenced sites close to the Everglades increasing towards the marine section of the Bay. We document the primary production of calcareous green macroalgae along the TS-Ph transect including three contrasting environments at Florida Bay. The transect include site TS-Ph 9 located near Duck Key in oligotrophic northeastern Florida Bay; TS-Ph 10 is located near Bob Allen Keys in the oligotrophic center Florida Bay and TS-Ph 11 is located near Sprigger Bank at the western open boundary between Florida Bay and the Gulf of Mexico.In order to survey the temporal and spatial variability in production of calcareous marine macroalgae, a monitoring survey was started in 2007 on the three TS-Ph transect. In each site 3 hazard selected quadrats were sampled for biomass, CaCO3 production and species ID, and abundance using Braun Blanquet Index. Surveys are conducted bimonthly.Results show a significant difference on production with a high abundance and biomass at Sprigger Bank (Ts-Ph11) compared with lower values at Bob Allan Key  and Duck Key. Seasonal changes show a higher production in summer compared with winter periods. The long term trend shows a decline on production in Sprigger Bank.  Thalli CaCO3 content has a linear relation with biomass (carbon content) indicating a constant relationship between CaCO3 fixation and algae size-biomass. As a general trend we document a higher calcareous green macroalgae production towards the marine sites, consistent with the fact that the TS-Ph transect shows an enhanced productivity in the TS/Ph toward the marine end of the Bay (Fourqurean et al., 1992).  A decline in calcareous green macroalgae at Sprigger Bank is reported based on 4 years of survey, which might have consequences on sand production for this site, moreover this will eventually change the sediment characteristics of this site. Our long term data set is a base line that will allow us detect potential changes in CaCO3 fixation by calcareous green macroalgae as a consequence of predicted acidification of the oceans.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>macroalgae</keyword><keyword>Florida Bay</keyword><keyword>Biomass</keyword><keyword>long-term ecological research</keyword><keyword>Dry Weight</keyword><keyword>CaCO3</keyword><keyword>Calcium Carbonate</keyword><keyword>2007</keyword><keyword>2010</keyword><keyword>production</keyword><keyword>macroalgae production</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>These data are classified as 'Type 4' whereby Data related to the FCE LTER Program but not funded by the National Science Foundation (NSF) LTER Grant #9910514 are available for scientific purposes no more than 4 years after collection. Recommended maximum lock period = 2 years. In some cases, these data are funded by other agencies but the data are tied to the LTER objectives or were collected at FCE sites. In these cases, the researchers are strongly encouraged to either a) submit links to their databases, allowing direct connection to their web accessible data via the FCE LTER website and through the FCE Database, or b) to also submit their data to the FCE Information Manager at the time they are released to the agency. In either case, the researcher should seek permission of the agency in question to make this link. In these cases, the recommended lock period is identical to that mandated by the funding agency.  Additionally, two copies of the manuscript must be submitted to the Florida Coastal Everglades LTER Program Office, LTER Program Manager, Southeast Environmental Research Center, OE 148, University Park, Florida International University, Miami, Florida 33199.  For a complete description of the FCE LTER Data Distribution and Data User Agreement, please go to FCE Data Management Policy at http://fcelter.fiu.edu/data/data_mgmt_policy.html.</para></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-fce.449.5&amp;urlTail=LT_PP_Collado_001</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Data were collected in the Florida Bay, within Everglades National Park, South Florida</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-80.93798</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-80.489782</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>25.176928</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>24.91293</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Florida Coastal Everglades LTER Study Area: South Florida, Everglades National Park, and Florida Bay</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-81.07794623</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-80.48978207</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>25.76145171</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>24.91293492</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2007-05-07</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2010-04-10</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><maintenance><description><para>This is a long-term macroalgae production data set</para></description></maintenance><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Ligia</givenName><surName>Collado-Vides</surName></individualName><organizationName>Southeast Environmental Research Center</organizationName><positionName>Southeast Environmental Research Center Collaborator</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Biological Sciences</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>FIU</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>11200 SW 8th Street</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>OE 167</deliveryPoint><city>Miami</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33199</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">305-348-2274</phone><phone phonetype="fax">305-348-4096</phone><electronicMailAddress>colladol@fiu.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.marinemacroalgae.com/</onlineUrl></contact><contact scope="document"><organizationName>Florida Coastal Everglades LTER Program</organizationName><positionName>Information Manager</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Florida International University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University Park</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>OE 148</deliveryPoint><city>Miami</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33199</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">305-348-6054</phone><phone phonetype="fax">305-348-4096</phone><electronicMailAddress>fcelter@fiu.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://fcelter.fiu.edu</onlineUrl></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>Florida Coastal Everglades LTER Program</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Florida International University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University Park</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>OE 148</deliveryPoint><city>Miami</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33199</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">305-348-6054</phone><electronicMailAddress>fcelter@fiu.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://fcelter.fiu.edu</onlineUrl></publisher><methods><methodStep><description><para>In each site 3 hazard selected quadrats are sampled,  abundance is estimated using Braun Blanquet Index. Then all calcareous green macroalgae are collected. In the lab samples are cleaned and species ID at species level. Samples are then dried at 68 degrees C for 48 hours. Dry samples are weighted and mass value is recorded. Dry samples are then burned in a furnace for 3 hours at 500 degrees C.   Ashes are weighted and CaCO3 production is recorded. Mass minus CaCo3 is recorded as biomass value. Surveys are conducted bimonthly at three sites (TS/PH.9, 10 and 11).</para></description><instrumentation>Balance, oven, furnace</instrumentation></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><description><para>The Study Extent of this dataset includes the FCE Florida Bay research sites within Everglades National Park, South Florida</para></description></studyExtent><samplingDescription><para>TS-Ph transect including three contrasting environments at Florida Bay is evaluated. The transect include site TS-Ph 9 located near Duck Key in oligotrophic northeastern Florida Bay; TS-Ph 10 is located near Bob Allen Keys in the oligotrophic center Florida Bay and TS-Ph 11 is located near Sprigger Bank at the western open boundary between Florida Bay and the Gulf of Mexico. In each site 3 random quadrats are sampled. First abundance is estimated using a Braun-Blanquet index, then all calcareous green macroalgae are collected. In the lab material is cleaned and identified at the species level following taxonomic keys (Littler and Littler 2000). All material of quadrat is then left in the oven for 48 hours at 68 degrees C. Dry weight is calculated and reported. The same dry material is then burned in a furnace at 500 degrees C for 3 hours; ashes are weighted and reported as CaCO3, biomass is estimated as Dry weight minus ashes.</para></samplingDescription><spatialSamplingUnits><coverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>FCE LTER Site TS/Ph9</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-80.48978207</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-80.48978207</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>25.17692874</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>25.17692874</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></coverage><coverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>FCE LTER Site TS/Ph10</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-80.68097374</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-80.68097374</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>25.02476744</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>25.02476744</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></coverage><coverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>FCE LTER Site TS/Ph11</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-80.93798347</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-80.93798347</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>24.91293492</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>24.91293492</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></coverage></spatialSamplingUnits></sampling><qualityControl><description><para>data are entered by students, evaluated for trend, detecting spikes or valleys, then supervised by PI</para></description></qualityControl></methods><project id="1" scope="document"><title>Florida Coastal Everglades LTER: Coastal Oligotrophic Ecosystems Research-the Coastal Everglades</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Daniel</givenName><surName>Childers</surName></individualName><organizationName>Florida Coastal Everglades LTER Program</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Biological Sciences</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Florida International University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University Park</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>OE 167</deliveryPoint><city>Miami</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33199</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">305-348-3101</phone><phone phonetype="fax">305-348-1986</phone><electronicMailAddress>childers@fiu.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>Lead Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Joseph</givenName><surName>Boyer</surName></individualName><organizationName>Florida Coastal Everglades LTER Program</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Southeast Environmental Research Center</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Florida International University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University Park</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>OE 148</deliveryPoint><city>Miami</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33199</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">305-348-4076</phone><phone phonetype="fax">305-348-4096</phone><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>James</givenName><surName>Fourqurean</surName></individualName><organizationName>Florida Coastal Everglades LTER Program</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Biological Sciences</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Florida International University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University Park</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>OE 167</deliveryPoint><city>Miami</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33199</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">305-348-4084</phone><phone phonetype="fax">305-348-4096</phone><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Rudolf</givenName><surName>Jaffe</surName></individualName><organizationName>Florida Coastal Everglades LTER Program</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Chemistry</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Florida International University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University Park</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>CP 304</deliveryPoint><city>Miami</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33199</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">305-348-2456</phone><phone phonetype="fax">305-348-4096</phone><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Joel</givenName><surName>Trexler</surName></individualName><organizationName>Florida Coastal Everglades LTER Program</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Biological Sciences</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Florida International University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University Park</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>OE 167</deliveryPoint><city>Miami</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33199</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">305-348-1966</phone><phone phonetype="fax">305-348-1986</phone><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><abstract><para>We are investigating how variability in regional climate, freshwater inputs, disturbance, and perturbations affect the coastal Everglades ecosystem. Our long term research program focuses on testing the following central idea and hypotheses:  Regional processes mediated by water flow control population and ecosystem level dynamics at any location within the coastal Everglades landscape. This phenomenon is best exemplified in the dynamics of an estuarine oligohaline zone where fresh water draining phosphorus-limited Everglades marshes mixes with water from the more nitrogen-limited coastal ocean. Hypothesis 1: In nutrient-poor coastal systems, long-term changes in the quantity or quality of organic matter inputs will exert strong and direct controls on estuarine productivity, because inorganic nutrients are at such low levels. Hypothesis 2: Interannual and long-term changes in freshwater flow controls the magnitude of nutrients and organic matter inputs to the estuarine zone, while ecological processes in the freshwater marsh and coastal ocean control the quality and characteristics of those inputs. Hypothesis 3: Long-term changes in freshwater flow (primarily manifest through management and Everglades restoration) will interact with long-term changes in the climatic and disturbance (sea level rise, hurricanes, fires) regimes to modify ecological pattern and process across coastal landscapes.</para></abstract><funding><para>National Science Foundation under Grant # 9910514</para></funding><studyAreaDescription><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>The FCE LTER Project Study area is located in South Florida, mostly in Everglades National Park. There are a total of 21 sampling sites located in two major regions: 1) Shark River Slough and 2) Taylor Slough/Panhandle.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-81.07794623</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-80.48978207</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>25.76145171</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>24.91293492</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2000-05-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2006-04-30</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage></studyAreaDescription><relatedProject id="26" scope="document"><title>FCE LTER II:  Coastal Oligotrophic Ecosystems Research</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Evelyn</givenName><surName>Gaiser</surName></individualName><organizationName>Florida Coastal Everglades LTER Program</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Florida International University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University Park</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>OE 148</deliveryPoint><city>Miami</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33199</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">305-348-6145</phone><phone phonetype="fax">305-348-4096</phone><electronicMailAddress>gaisere@fiu.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>Lead Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Mike</givenName><surName>Heithaus</surName></individualName><organizationName>Florida Coastal Everglades LTER Program</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Biological Sciences</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Marine Biology Program</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Florida International University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Biscayne Bay Campus</deliveryPoint><city>Miami</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33181</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(305) 919-5234</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(305) 919-4030</phone><electronicMailAddress>heithaus@fiu.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Rudolf</givenName><surName>Jaffe</surName></individualName><organizationName>Florida Coastal Everglades LTER Program</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Chemistry</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Florida International University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University Park</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>CP 304</deliveryPoint><city>Miami</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33199</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">305-348-2456</phone><phone phonetype="fax">305-348-4096</phone><electronicMailAddress>jaffer@fiu.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Rene</givenName><surName>Price</surName></individualName><organizationName>Florida Coastal Everglades LTER Program</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Earth Sciences</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Florida International University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University Park</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>PC 344</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>11200 SW 8th Street</deliveryPoint><city>Miami</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33199</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">305-348-3119</phone><phone phonetype="fax">305-348-3877</phone><electronicMailAddress>pricer@fiu.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><abstract><para>Our FCE I research focused on understanding how dissolved organic matter from upstream oligotrophic marshes interacts with a marine source of phosphorus (P), the limiting nutrient, to control estuarine productivity where these two influences meet-in the oligohaline ecotone. This dynamic is affected by the interaction of local ecological processes and landscape-scale drivers (hydrologic, climatological, and human). During FCE I, our ideas about how these "upside-down" estuaries (Childers et al. 2006) function has evolved, and we have modified our central theme to reflect this new understanding. Our focus in FCE II will be even more strongly on the oligohaline ecotone region of our experimental transects. For FCE II, our overarching theme is:  In the coastal Everglades landscape, population and ecosystem-level dynamics are controlled by the relative importance of water source, water residence time, and local biotic processes. This phenomenon is best exemplified in the oligohaline ecotone, where these 3 factors interact most strongly and vary over many [temporal and spatial] scales.Hypothesis 1: Increasing inputs of fresh water will enhance oligotrophy in nutrient-poor coastal systems, as long as the inflowing water has low nutrient content; this dynamic will be most pronounced in the oligohaline ecotone.  Hypothesis 2: An increase in freshwater inflow will increase the physical transport of detrital organic matter to the oligohaline ecotone, which will enhance estuarine productivity. The quality of these allochthonous detrital inputs will be controlled by upstream ecological processes. Hypothesis 3: Water residence time, groundwater inputs, and tidal energy interact with climatic and disturbance regimes to modify ecological pattern and process in oligotrophic estuaries; this dynamic will be most pronounced in the oligohaline ecotone. Childers, D.L., J.N. Boyer, S.E. Davis, C.J. Madden, D.T. Rudnick, and F.H. Sklar, 2006. Relating precipitation and water management to nutrient concentration patterns in the oligotrophic "upside down" estuaries of the Florida Everglades. Limnology and Oceanography, 51(1): 602-616.</para></abstract><funding><para>National Science Foundation under Grant # 9910514 and #0620409</para></funding><studyAreaDescription><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>The FCE LTER Project Study area is located in South Florida, mostly in Everglades National Park. There are a total of 20 sampling sites located in two major regions: 1) Shark River Slough and 2) Taylor Slough/Panhandle.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-81.07794623</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-80.48978207</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>25.76145171</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>24.91293492</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2006-12-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2012-12-01</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage></studyAreaDescription></relatedProject></project><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=FCE,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>LT_PP_Collado_001</entityName><entityDescription>Macroalgae Biomass found in Florida Bay Quadrants</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>LT_PP_Collado_001</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat></physical><attributeList><attribute id="att.1" scope="document"><attributeName>SITENAME</attributeName><attributeLabel>sitename</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Name of LTER site</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">text</storageType><measurementScale><ordinal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Name of LTER site</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></ordinal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="att.2" scope="document"><attributeName>Date</attributeName><attributeLabel>date</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Collection date</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">datetime</storageType><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>DD-MMM-YY</formatString><dateTimePrecision>1</dateTimePrecision><dateTimeDomain><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">2007-05-07</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">2010-04-10</maximum></bounds></dateTimeDomain></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="att.3" scope="document"><attributeName>Quadrant Number</attributeName><attributeLabel>ID number</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Quadrant ID Number</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ordinal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Quadrant ID Number</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></ordinal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="att.4" scope="document"><attributeName>CaCO3</attributeName><attributeLabel>concentration</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Calcium Carbonate per quadrant</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">data</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-9999</code><codeExplanation>Value will never be recorded</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute id="att.5" scope="document"><attributeName>DryWeight</attributeName><attributeLabel>dry weight</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Dry Weight of Macroalgae per quadrant</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">data</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-9999</code><codeExplanation>Value will never be recorded</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute id="att.6" scope="document"><attributeName>Biomass</attributeName><attributeLabel>biomass</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Macroalgae biomass per quadrant</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">data</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-9999</code><codeExplanation>Value will never be recorded</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><method><methodStep><description><para>Calculations: Biomass=Dry Weight minus the CaCO3 per quadrant</para></description></methodStep></method></attribute></attributeList><numberOfRecords>147</numberOfRecords></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><additionalDataset><researchType>Long-Term</researchType><DatasetDistributionTypeandRestrictions>Type 2</DatasetDistributionTypeandRestrictions><addDistribution><submissionDate>2010-08-04</submissionDate></addDistribution><LTERsites><sitename>TS/Ph9, TS/Ph10 and TS/Ph11</sitename></LTERsites><projectHypotheses><para>One of the Everglades LTER scientist general hypothesis is "that increasing inputs of freshwater will enhance oligotrophy in nutrient-poor coastal systems, as long as the inflowing water has low nutrient content; this dynamic will be most pronounced in the oligohaline ecotone" (LTER program).</para></projectHypotheses></additionalDataset></additionalMetadata></eml:eml>