<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-cap.56.9" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://data.gios.asu.edu/eml2_1_0/eml.xsd">
    <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
        <allow>
            <principal>uid=CAP,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
            <permission>all</permission>
        </allow>
        <allow>
            <principal>public</principal>
            <permission>read</permission>
        </allow>
    </access>
    <dataset id="56_1" system="gios_dataset">
        <alternateIdentifier system="gios_dataset">56</alternateIdentifier>
        <title>Land cover classification of Central Arizona-Phoenix using Landsat Thematic Mapper (TM) data - year 1985</title>
        <creator>
            <individualName>
                <givenName>William</givenName>
                <givenName>L.</givenName>
                <surName>Stefanov</surName>
            </individualName>
            <positionName>Christensen &amp; Ramsey/IGERT</positionName>
            <organizationName>Arizona State University</organizationName>
            <address>
                <deliveryPoint>POB871404</deliveryPoint>
                <deliveryPoint>Department of Geological Sciences</deliveryPoint>
                <city>Tempe</city>
                <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
                <postalCode>85287-1404</postalCode>
            </address>
            <phone phonetype="voice">(480) 965-1790</phone>
            <phone phonetype="fax">(480) 965-1787</phone>
            <electronicMailAddress>will.stefanov@asu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        </creator>
        <creator>
            <individualName>
                <givenName>Jayme</givenName>
                <surName>Harris</surName>
            </individualName>
            <address>
                <deliveryPoint>Mars Global Surveyor Space Flight Facility, Arizona State University</deliveryPoint>
                <city>Tempe</city>
                <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
                <postalCode>85287-1404</postalCode>
            </address>
        </creator>
        <language>english</language>
        <series>Land cover classification I</series>
        <abstract>
            <para>Land cover classification for the CAP LTER study region using Landsat Thematic Mapper (TM) data - year 1985</para>
        </abstract><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">Land-Use, Land-Cover and Land Architecture</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">disturbance patterns</keyword><keywordThesaurus>IPA and Core Area CAP Data Portal Controler</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="place">phoenix</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">land architecture</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">land use changes</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">gis</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">land cover</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">database remote sensing gis applications</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">remote sensing</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">landsat</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">classification</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Land-Use, Land-Cover and Land Architecture</keyword><keywordThesaurus>Creator Defined Keyword Set</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">land use</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">maps</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">land cover</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">vegetation</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">methods</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">remote sensing</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">soil</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">disturbances</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">landsat</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">grasses</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary Keyword Set</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">caplter</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">central arizona phoenix longterm ecological research</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">arizona</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">caplter created</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">az</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">cap</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">arid land</keyword><keywordThesaurus>CAPLTER Keyword Set List</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet>
        
        
        
        <intellectualRights>
            <section>
                <para>Copyright Board of Regents, Arizona State University. This dataset is released to the public and may be used for academic, educational, or commercial purposes subject to the following restrictions:</para>
                <para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>While CAP LTER will make every effort possible to control and document the quality of the data it publishes, the data are made available "as is".</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER cannot assume responsibility for damages resulting from mis-use or mis-interpretation of datasets or from errors or omissions that may exist in the data.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists that has resulted in data used in subsequent research.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER expects that any use of data from this server will be accompanied with the appropriate citations and acknowledgments.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER encourages users to contact the original investigator responsible for the data that they are accessing. Where appropriate, researchers whose projects are integrally dependent on CAP LTER data are encouraged to consider collaboration and/or co-authorship with original investigators.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER requests that users submit to the Global Institute of Sustainability, ASU, one copy of any publication resulting from the use of data obtained from this site.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER requests that users not redistribute data obtained from this site. However, links or references to this site may be freely posted.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            </section>
        </intellectualRights>
        <distribution>
            <online>
                <url>http://data.gios.asu.edu/cap/HarvestListFileShow.php?id=56</url>
            </online>
        </distribution>
        <coverage>
            <geographicCoverage>
                <geographicDescription>CAPLTER (Central Arizona Phoenix - Long Term Ecological Research)</geographicDescription>
                <boundingCoordinates>
                    <westBoundingCoordinate>-112.782258</westBoundingCoordinate>
                    <eastBoundingCoordinate>-111.571776</eastBoundingCoordinate>
                    <northBoundingCoordinate>33.843845</northBoundingCoordinate>
                    <southBoundingCoordinate>33.195087</southBoundingCoordinate>
                </boundingCoordinates>
            </geographicCoverage>
        </coverage>
        <purpose>
            <para>A fundamental dataset required for ecosystem analysis consists of the major types of land cover present in the study area and their areal percentages. Land cover refers to the physical nature of the surficial materials present in a given area such as water, grass, clay-rich soil, asphalt, or concrete. Land cover classification can be used as input into a variety of ecological models, and land cover maps can be constructed to aid in planning field sampling strategy. The land cover types can also be linked to different land use categories to investigate temporal and spatial changes in the urban ecosystem.</para>
        </purpose>
        <contact>
            <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
            <organizationName>Global Institute of Sustainability, Arizona State University</organizationName>
            <address>
                <deliveryPoint>POB 875402</deliveryPoint>
                <city>TEMPE</city>
                <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
                <postalCode>85287-5402</postalCode>
            </address>
            <phone phonetype="voice">(480) 965 2975</phone>
            <phone phonetype="fax">(480) 965-8087</phone>
            <electronicMailAddress>caplter.data@asu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        </contact>
        <methods>
            <methodStep>
                <description>
                    <section>
                        <title>Classification of Landsat TM Data</title>
                        <para>Classification refers to several statistical techniques (or algorithms) used to sort and group data into discrete classes which can be uniquely identified. Classification algorithms are routinely used to reduce the large volume of data present in a typical TM (or other sensor) dataset to several classes that are meaningful to the investigator. There are two major types of classification algorithm applied to remotely sensed data: unsupervised and supervised. Unsupervised classification algorithms (such as ISODATA) cluster data according to several user-defined statistical parameters in an iterative fashion until either some percentage of pixels remain unchanged or a maximum number of iterations has been performed. This method of classification is most useful when no previous knowledge or ground truth data of an area is available. The classes determined by the algorithm still require land cover identification by an experienced analyst however, which can be a significant disadvantage to the method.
                        </para>
                        <para>The unsupervised classification technique is used for portions of the CAP LTER region for which limited ancillary data (land use, aerial photographs, zoning maps) are available (essentially the region outside of Maricopa County). Twenty (or more) classes are determined for each TM scene using the ISODATA algorithm, and these classes are assigned a land cover category on the basis of spectral signature, vegetation density, and geologic setting. These land cover classifications are considered to be preliminary pending detailed verification by ground truthing.
                        </para>
                        <para>Supervised classification algorithms rely on user-defined training regions that represent pure samples of a particular class (such as asphalt ). Several different types of supervised classification algorithms exist, but the major types are minimum distance, parallelpiped, and maximum likelihood. Minimum distance algorithms calculate a mean value in spectral space for each training region, and then compare each image pixel value to these means. The image pixel is assigned to whatever class mean it is closest in value to. The parallelpiped algorithm constructs a class volume in data space to further constrain the identification of data points as a given class. Maximum likelihood algorithms assume a Gaussian distribution of pixel values within each training class and tend to be somewhat more accurate in regions of high surficial variability. Image pixels that fall within some standard deviation of the training class mean are assigned to that class. This method has the added advantage of weighting such that image pixels are less likely to be classified as covers with low probability of occurrence in the scene. Maximum likelihood supervised classification is used for regions that have good ground truth data available, such as the Phoenix metro region.
                        </para>
                    </section>
                    <section>
                        <title>Verification of Classification Accuracy</title>
                        <para>The accuracy of any classification must be assessed prior to use in scientific analysis. Accuracy assessment involves the collection of ground truth data for the classified scene. This is done by establishing a number of test pixels within the image for which the actual ground cover is determined by field inspection, use of aerial photographs, or use of some other dataset. An overall classification accuracy is then determined by dividing the number of test pixels correctly classified by the number of total test pixels.
                        </para>
                        <para>Assessment of accuracy for the CAP LTER study area is not straightforward as the major dataset available for comparison is the Maricopa Association of Governments (MAG) Land Use Map. Land use can be thought of as the purpose to which a particular area is devoted, such industrial or recreational use. Use of the MAG dataset for comparison with classified TM data requires interpretation of the land cover types in terms of possible land uses, which is complicated as several land covers may be associated with the same land use category. For example, the institutional MAG land use category corresponds to the asphalt+concrete+soil+/-metal roofs, asphalt+concrete+soil+/-metal roofs+/-grass, and concrete+grass+/-woody veg.+/-asphalt land cover classes. Land use is the primary data format used by the various LTER researchers, so a fairly simple categorization scheme was defined for use in LTER studies. Overall accuracy of the TM classification is 71%, a value which is typical for TM data.
                        </para>
                    </section>
                </description>
                <citation id="2187" system="ces_literature">
                    <title>Investigation of hillslope processes and land cover change using remote sensing and laboratory spectroscopy</title>
                    <creator>
                        <individualName>
                            <givenName>W</givenName>
                            <givenName>L</givenName>
                            <surName>Stefanov</surName>
                        </individualName>
                    </creator>
                    <pubDate>2000</pubDate>
                    <distribution>
                        <online>
                            <url />
                        </online>
                    </distribution>
                    <thesis>
                        <degree>Ph.D.</degree>
                        <institution>
                            <organizationName>Arizona State University</organizationName>
                        </institution>
                    </thesis>
                </citation>
            </methodStep>
        </methods>
        <project>
          <title>Multi-Temporal Remote-Sensing Data Acquisition for CAP LTER Land Cover, Land Use Monitoring, and Modeling</title>
          <personnel>
            <individualName>
              <givenName>John</givenName>
              <surName>Briggs</surName>
            </individualName>
            <organizationName>Konza Prairie Biological Station</organizationName>
            <address>
              <deliveryPoint>218 Bushnell Hall</deliveryPoint>
              <city>Manhattan</city>
              <administrativeArea>KS</administrativeArea>
              <postalCode>NULL</postalCode>
              <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <phone phonetype="voice">785-532-0140</phone>
            <role>Principal Investigator</role>
          </personnel>
          <personnel>
            <individualName>
              <givenName>Philip</givenName>
              <surName>Christensen</surName>
            </individualName>
            <organizationName>School of Earth and Space Exploration</organizationName>
            <address>
              <deliveryPoint>PO Box 871404</deliveryPoint>
              <city>Tempe</city>
              <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
              <postalCode>85287-1404</postalCode>
              <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <phone phonetype="voice">480-965-7105</phone>
            <role>Principal Investigator</role>
          </personnel>
          <personnel>
            <individualName>
              <givenName>William</givenName>
              <surName>Stefanov</surName>
            </individualName>
            <organizationName>Science Applications, Research and Development</organizationName>
            <address>
              <deliveryPoint>ESCG/KX</deliveryPoint>
              <city>Houston</city>
              <administrativeArea>TX</administrativeArea>
              <postalCode>NULL</postalCode>
              <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <phone phonetype="voice">281-483-5139</phone>
            <role>Principal Investigator</role>
          </personnel>
          <personnel>
            <individualName>
              <givenName>Chris</givenName>
              <surName>Eisinger</surName>
            </individualName>
            <organizationName>School of Earth and Space Exploration</organizationName>
            <address>
              <deliveryPoint>PO Box 871404</deliveryPoint>
              <city>Tempe</city>
              <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
              <postalCode>85287-1404</postalCode>
              <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <phone phonetype="voice">480-965-5081</phone>
            <role>Principal Investigator</role>
          </personnel>
          <personnel>
            <individualName>
              <givenName>Jason</givenName>
              <surName>Walker</surName>
            </individualName>
            <organizationName>School of Life Sciences/Plant Biology</organizationName>
            <address>
              <deliveryPoint>PO Box 874501</deliveryPoint>
              <city>Tempe</city>
              <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
              <postalCode>85287-4501</postalCode>
              <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <phone phonetype="voice">480-965-9299</phone>
            <role>Graduate Research Assistant</role>
          </personnel>
          <personnel>
            <individualName>
              <givenName>Matthias</givenName>
              <surName>Moeller</surName>
            </individualName>
            <organizationName>Global Institute of Sustainability</organizationName>
            <address>
              <deliveryPoint>PO Box 875402</deliveryPoint>
              <city>Tempe</city>
              <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
              <postalCode>NULL</postalCode>
              <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <phone phonetype="voice">480-965-0987</phone>
            <role>Principal Investigator</role>
          </personnel>
          <personnel>
            <individualName>
              <givenName>Alexander</givenName>
              <surName>Buyantuyev</surName>
            </individualName>
            <organizationName>School of Life Sciences</organizationName>
            <address>
              <deliveryPoint>Center for Environmental Studies, Arizona State University, POB 875402</deliveryPoint>
              <city>TEMPE</city>
              <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
              <postalCode>85287-5402</postalCode>
              <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <phone phonetype="voice">480-727-7360</phone>
            <role>Graduate Research Assistant</role>
          </personnel>
          <personnel>
            <individualName>
              <givenName>Tun</givenName>
              <surName>Myint</surName>
            </individualName>
            <organizationName>NULL</organizationName>
            <address>
              <deliveryPoint>NULL</deliveryPoint>
              <city>NULL</city>
              <administrativeArea>NULL</administrativeArea>
              <postalCode>NULL</postalCode>
              <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <phone phonetype="voice">NULL</phone>
            <role>Principal Investigator</role>
          </personnel>
          <personnel>
            <individualName>
              <givenName>Philip</givenName>
              <surName>Tarrant</surName>
            </individualName>
            <organizationName>Global Institute of Sustainability</organizationName>
            <address>
              <deliveryPoint>PO Box 875402</deliveryPoint>
              <city>Tempe</city>
              <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
              <postalCode>85287-5402</postalCode>
              <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <phone phonetype="voice">480-727-7860</phone>
            <role>Principal Investigator</role>
          </personnel>
          <personnel>
            <individualName>
              <givenName>B. L.</givenName>
              <surName>Turner II</surName>
            </individualName>
            <organizationName>School of Geographical Sciences and Urban Planning</organizationName>
            <address>
              <deliveryPoint>PO Box 875302</deliveryPoint>
              <city>Tempe</city>
              <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
              <postalCode>85287-5302</postalCode>
              <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <phone phonetype="voice">480-965-1535</phone>
            <role>Principal Investigator</role>
          </personnel>
          <personnel>
            <individualName>
              <givenName>Shai</givenName>
              <surName>Kaplan</surName>
            </individualName>
            <organizationName>School of Geographical Sciences and Urban Planning</organizationName>
            <address>
              <deliveryPoint>NULL</deliveryPoint>
              <city>Tempe</city>
              <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
              <postalCode>NULL</postalCode>
              <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <phone phonetype="voice">NULL</phone>
            <role>Graduate Research Assistant</role>
          </personnel>
          <abstract>
            <para>This project will expand the developing land classification techniques using new analytical techniques and other remote sensing images as they become available. This will provide multiyear increments for spatial change models and overlap with U.S. census information.</para>
            <para>Datasets for Land Cover, Normalized Difference Vegetation Index (NDVI) and Soil Adjusted Vegetation Index (SAVI) are produced on a regular schedule as appropriate remote sensing scenes become available.</para>
          </abstract>
          <designDescription>
            <description>
              <section>
                <para>Land cover type, the primary product of remote-sensing classification, is a fundamental data set for nearly every aspect of the CAP LTER project. Already, it has been used to derive surface cover, aid in biological surveys, plan future science initiatives, and help define the patch typology of the system. The pilot project is currently using 1993 Landsat TM multispectral data to test and refine classification schemes for the urban, desert, and fringe regional of the CAP LTER. These classes, once accurately defined and field checked, will be form the basis of the LTER's patch typology and serve as a past baseline on the ground cover inventory of the Phoenix metropolitan area.</para>
                <para>To examine the temporal effects of urban growth and its impact on the desert ecology, it is critical to have data extending both into the past as well as the future. Past remote-sensing data is needed for patch and change modeling. It will take advantage of spatial patterns prior to large influxes of population and the subsequent change from agriculturally dominated to urban-dominated land cover. Data collected in the future will also provide a monitoring and projecting ability for the science team. More importantly, these data can be used to direct new and alter existing field projects within the CAP LTER. Because this data product will be constantly changing as urban growth continues, it is important to monitor and analyze these changes, as well as link them to land use and socioeconomic change.</para>
                <para>By expanding the remote-sensing analysis and data archive for the CAP LTER project we can extend the land cover classification to form a 60-year historic land cover inventory for Phoenix. This will provide the basis for multithematic, multitemporal, and multispatial scale research.</para>
                <para>Some research questions critical to the LTER science objectives which can be answered with the expansion of the data, both past and future, are:</para>
                <para>What is the distribution and variability of land cover classes in the Valley over time?</para>
                <para>How do these distributions change over time and by urban location? Are there single or multiple sequences? How do these changes relate to population expansion?</para>
                <para>What is the effect of this change on remote sensing, ecological, land use, and land value theoretical models?</para>
                <para>Can growth and economical change be monitored precisely with future data and how well can trends be identified based on projections of past data?</para>
                <para>Is growth happening in geologically metastable areas such as alluvial fans and potential floodplains?</para>
                <para>Research involves parcel and metropolitan level classification. Contact CAP Information Manager for details.</para>
              </section>
            </description>
          </designDescription>
        </project>
        <spatialRaster id="56.CAP_LandCoverClass_1985">
            <entityName>Land cover classification using Landsat Thematic Mapper (TM) data - year 1985</entityName>
            <entityDescription>Land cover classification for the CAP LTER study region using Landsat Thematic Mapper (TM) data- year1985</entityDescription>
            <physical>
                <objectName>56.zip</objectName>
                <dataFormat>
                    <externallyDefinedFormat>
                        <formatName>erdas imagine</formatName>
                    </externallyDefinedFormat>
                </dataFormat>
                <distribution>
                    <online>
                        <url>http://data.gios.asu.edu/datasets/cap/56.zip</url>
                    </online>
                </distribution>
            </physical>
            <attributeList id="CAP_LandCoverClass_1985.attributeList">
                <attribute id="CAP_LandCoverClass_1985.Value">
                    <attributeName>Value</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Thematic Value of the Cell</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html">Integer</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <enumeratedDomain>
                                    <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>0</code>
                                        <definition>Undefined</definition>
                                    </codeDefinition>
                                    <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>1</code>
                                        <definition>Cultivated Vegetation (Active)</definition>
                                    </codeDefinition>
                                    <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>2</code>
                                        <definition>Cultivated Grass</definition>
                                    </codeDefinition>
                                    <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>3</code>
                                        <definition>Fluvial and Lacustrine Sediments
                                            (Canals)</definition>
                                    </codeDefinition>
                                    <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>4</code>
                                        <definition>Compacted Soil (Prior Agricultural
                                            Use)</definition>
                                    </codeDefinition>
                                    <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>5</code>
                                        <definition>Vegetation</definition>
                                    </codeDefinition>
                                    <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>6</code>
                                        <definition>Distributed (Commercial/Industrial)</definition>
                                    </codeDefinition>
                                    <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>7</code>
                                        <definition>Disturbed (Asphalt and Concrete)</definition>
                                    </codeDefinition>
                                    <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>8</code>
                                        <definition>Undisturbed</definition>
                                    </codeDefinition>
                                    <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>9</code>
                                        <definition>Compacted Soil</definition>
                                    </codeDefinition>
                                    <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>10</code>
                                        <definition>Disturbed (Mesic Residential)</definition>
                                    </codeDefinition>
                                    <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>11</code>
                                        <definition>Disturbed (Xeric Residential)</definition>
                                    </codeDefinition>
                                    <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>12</code>
                                        <definition>Water</definition>
                                    </codeDefinition>
                                </enumeratedDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
            </attributeList>
            <spatialReference>
                <horizCoordSysName>WGS_1984_UTM_Zone_12N</horizCoordSysName>
            </spatialReference>
            <horizontalAccuracy>
                <accuracyReport>Not available</accuracyReport>
            </horizontalAccuracy>
            <verticalAccuracy>
                <accuracyReport>Not available</accuracyReport>
            </verticalAccuracy>
            <cellSizeXDirection>28.5</cellSizeXDirection>
            <cellSizeYDirection>28.5</cellSizeYDirection>
            <numberOfBands>1</numberOfBands>
            <rasterOrigin>Upper Left</rasterOrigin>
            <rows>2480</rows>
            <columns>3917</columns>
            <verticals>1</verticals>
            <cellGeometry>pixel</cellGeometry>
        </spatialRaster>
    </dataset>
</eml:eml>