<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-jrn.20060160.9849" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=JRN, o=lter, dc=ecoinformatics, dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <shortName>JornadaStudy_086_smes_cryptogam_crust_quad_data</shortName>
  <title>SMES Cryptogam Crust Data</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Brandon</givenName>
      <surName>Bestelmeyer</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>
	USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range

	P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>bbestelm@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <metadataProvider>
    <organizationName>The Jornada</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>2995 Knox Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-4842</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <onlineUrl>http://jornada.nmsu.edu</onlineUrl>
  </metadataProvider>
  <pubDate>1995</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para> Introduction.

 Animal consumers have important roles in ecosystems (Chew
 1974, 1976), determining plant species composition and structure
 (Harper 1969, Pacala and Crawley 1992, Crawley 1983, 1989),
 regulating rates of plant production and nutrient cycling (Naiman
 1988, McNaughton et al. 1989, Holland et al. 1992), and altering
 soil structure and chemistry (Milchunas et al. 1993, Huntly
 1991).

 Desertification of semi-arid grasslands in the Southwest
 United States by domestic livestock provides an important example
 of herbivore regulation of ecosystem structure and function
 (Schlesinger et al. 1990). The species composition and physical
 structure of these desert grassland ecosystems were significantly
 altered by alien herbivores about 100 years ago (Bahre 1991, York
 and Dick-Peddie 1968, Gardner 1951, Hastings and Turner 1980,
 Buffington and Herbel 1965, Dick-Peddie 1993). To what extent the
 spatial patterns of semi-arid shrubland and grassland plant
 production and soil characteristics are currently controlled by
 plant resource use, abiotic factors, or consumers is not known.

 Desertification is an ecosystem-level phenomenon occurring
 on a global scale with great relevance to human welfare (Nelson
 1988). In order to understand the processes that contribute to
 desertification, we must fully understand interactions among the
 components of arid-land ecosystems. Schlesinger et al. (1990)
 suggest that in the absence of continued livestock perturbations,
 plant resource use and abiotic factors appear to be the principal
 factors accounting for the persistence of desert shrublands in
 desertified semi-arid grasslands. However, Brown and Heske
 (1990a) provide evidence that indigenous small mammal consumers
 may also have a major role in determining vegetation structure in
 those desert ecosystems.

 Brown and Heske (1990a, Heske et al. 1993) found that the
 exclusion of rodents from Chihuahuan Desert creosotebush
 shrubland areas resulted in a significant increase in grass cover
 over a 12 year period. Brown and Heske (1990a) concluded that
 rodents were keystone species in those desert shrub communities,
 greatly influencing vegetation structure. Rodents are also known
 to have significant influences on plant species composition and
 diversity in desert communities (Inouye et al. 1980, Heske et al.
 1993, Brown et al. 1986). Several species of granivorous rodents
 (Family: Heteromidae, genera: Dipodomys, Perognathus,
 Chaetodipus) appear to have the greatest influence on vegetation
 herbivory.

 Soil disturbance through the digging activities of rodents
 can have profound local effects on plant species composition and
 vegetation structure in the Chihuahuan Desert (Moroka et al.
 1982). Digging activities of desert rodents intermix surface
 soils with subsurface soils (Abaturov 1972), and increase
 rainfall infiltration (Soholt 1975). Reported measures of the
 percentage of desert soil surface areas disturbed by rodent
 digging activities in desert enviroments range from 10% (Abaturov
 1972) to 4.5% (Soholt 1975). Burrowing activities increase local
 soil nutrient and water status, creating favorable sites for
 increased plant densities, biomass production, and increased
 species diversity (Morehead et al. 1989, Mun and Whitford 1990).

 Rabbits (Lagomorpha: Black-tailed jackrabbits, Lepus
 californicus, and desert cottontail rabbits, Sylvilagus aduboni)
 are also important consumers of desert vegetation (Brown 1947,
 Johnson and Anderson 1984, Steinberger and Whitford 1983, Ernest
 1994). Rabbits can have significant effects on plant species
 composition and structure resulting from selective herbivory
 (Gibbens et al. 1993, Clark and Wagner 1984, Norris 1950,
 Zeevalking and Fresco 1977). Gibbens et al. (1993) found that
 excluding rabbits from Chihuahuan Desert creosotebush (Larrea
 tridentata) communities over a period of 50 years increased the
 canopy cover of some grasses, and also increased canopy cover of
 some shrub species.

 Small mammal (rodent and rabbit) populations may fluctuate
 considerably with variation in climate and annual plant
 production (Brown et al. 1979, Brown and Heske 1990, Brown and Zeng
 1989, Whitford 1976, Johnson and Anderson 1984). Reproduction in
 desert rodents is known to be induced by plant foliage production
 (Reichman and Van De Graff 1975, Beatley 1969). If small mammals
 are keystone species affecting plant species composition and
 structure in desert ecosystems, then the impacts of small mammals
 on vegetation are probably linked with variation in climate and
 plant production.

 A reciprocal plant-herbivore/granivore feedback system may
 result, where small mammal populations and thus impacts on
 vegetation, are initially determined by climate influences on
 plant food resource availability to the small mammals. Thus, the
 effects of small mammals during dry years will probably be
 different from the effects during wet years because of different
 population sizes. If this is so, one should be able to measure
 differential effects of small mammals on plant communities over
 series of wet or dry years, such as El Nino and La Nina cycles
 (Nicholls 1988). Such reciprocal interactions should also occur
 in relation to long-term (decades) climate change.

 The effects of any one small mammal species population on the
 biotic community will be complicated by competitive
 interactions with other mammal species (Munger and Brown 1981,
 Brown and Zeng 1989, Brown and Heske 1990), however overall impacts
 on vegetation and soils by the combined effects of all small
 mammal species may be closely linked with variation in
 precipitation and plant production. Depending upon the
 persistence of plant food resources such as foliage or seeds, lag
 times in consumer impacts may be expected following periods of
 precipitation and plant production.

 In desert ecosystems, widely scattered shrubs produce a
 patch pattern of fertile islands with high plant biomass
 production and soil nutrients, surrounded by relatively
 unproductive barren soil (West and Klemmedson 1978, Crawford and
 Gosz 1982). Researchers at the Jornada Long-Term Ecological
 Research site in New Mexico have proposed a desertification model
 suggesting that perturbations caused by domestic livestock
 grazing and climate change initiated processes transforming
 grasslands with relatively homogeneous resource distributions to
 shrubland environments with relatively heterogenous resource
 distributions (Schlesinger et al. 1990). This patchy
 vegetation/resource distribution pattern is stable under present
 climate regimes, and appears to be maintained by plant resource
 use and abiotic soil processes (Schlesinger et al. 1990).
 However, Wagner (1976, page 195) suggested that small mammals
 were probably maintaining shrubland dominated ecosystems at the
 Jornada by suppressing grasses through selective herbivory.


 Research Hypotheses.

 The purpose of this study is to determine whether or not the
 activities of small mammals regulate plant community structure,
 plant species diversity, and spatial vegetation patterns in
 Chihuahuan Desert shrublands and grasslands. What role if any do
 indigenous small mammal consumers have in maintaining desertified
 landscapes in the Chihuahuan Desert? Additionally, how do the
 effects of small mammals interact with changing climate to affect
 vegetation patterns over time? This study will provide long-term
 experimental tests of the roles of consumers on ecosystem pattern
 and process across a latitudinal climate gradient. The following
 questions or hypotheses will be addressed.

 1) Do small mammals influence patterns of plant species
 composition and diversity, vegetation structure, and spatial
 patterns of vegetation canopy cover and biomass in Chihuahuan
 Desert shrublands and grasslands? Are small mammals keystone
 species that determine plant species composition and physiognomy
 of Chihuahuan Desert communities as Brown and Heske (1990a) and
 Gibbens et al. (1993) suggest? Do small mammals have a
 significant role in maintaining the existence of shrub islands
 and spatial heterogeneity of creosotebush shrub communities?

 2) Do small mammals affect the taxonomic composition and
 spatial pattern of vegetation similarly or differently in
 grassland communities as compared to shrub communities? How do
 patterns compare between grassland and shrubland sites, and how
 do these relatively small scale patterns relate to overall
 landscape vegetation patterns?

 3) Do small mammals interact with short-term (annual) and
 long-term (decades) climate change to affect temporal changes
 in vegetation spatial patterns and species composition?


 Other Consumers.

 Ants are important consumers in Chihuahuan Desert ecosystems
 (MacKay 1991), and granivorous ants are known to have competitive
 interactions with rodents (Brown and Davidson 1977, Brown et al.
 1979) for plant seed resources. Termites are important
 detritivores in Chihuahuan Desert ecosystems (MacKay 1991) and
 appear to have key roles in plant litter decomposition and
 nutrient cycling (Whitford et al. 1982, Schaefer and Whitford
 1981), and in altering soil structure and hydrologic processes
 (Elkins et al. 1986). Grasshoppers are important herbivores in
 Chihuahuan Desert ecosystems (Rivera 1986, Wisdom 1991, Richman
 et al. 1993), with various species specializing on most of the
 different plant species present in any location (Otte 1976, Joern
 1979). Since manipulations of small mammals will probably affect
 these arthropod consumers, we will monitor these other consumers
 on the measurement plots to document any changes.

 Documentation of changes or lack of changes in ant, termite,
 and grasshopper consumer groups will be needed to interpret the
 results of small mammal manipulations on vegetation and soils.
 For example, if removal of rodents results in an increase of
 seed-harvesting ants, changes or lack of changes in vegetation
 and soils may be attributed to compensatory granivory from the
 increase in ants. Small mammals are the consumer group that
 appears to have the greatest influence on Chihuahuan Desert
 communities (see literature citations above). Given the known
 ecological importance of small mammals and the complexity and
 difficulties that would be associated with manipulating small
 mammals and arthropods, we have chosen to start with experiments
 on small mammals first. If these other consumer groups appear to
 have important interactions with small mammals, we will pursue
 additional experiments in the future to focus on those
 interactions, and to elucidate the ecological roles of these
 arthropod consumers.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>animal</keyword>
    <keyword>cryptobiotic crusts</keyword>
    <keyword>cryptogam crusts</keyword>
    <keyword>cryptogams</keyword>
    <keyword>disturbance</keyword>
    <keyword>longterm</keyword>
    <keyword>microbiotic crusts</keyword>
    <keyword>ongoing</keyword>
    <keyword>plant-animal interactions</keyword>
    <keyword>signature</keyword>
    <keyword>soil crust</keyword>
    <keyword>soil surface</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Jornada Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout> A creosotebush shrub study site and a black grama grassland study
 site have been established at each of the Sevilleta, Jornada and
 Mapimi research locations. Each study site is 1 km by 0.5 km in
 area. Three rodent trapping webs and four replicate experimental
 blocks of plots are randomly located at each study site to measure
 vegetation responses to the exclusion of small mammals. The blocks
 of study plots are all oriented on a site in a X/Y coordinate
 system, with the access road to each site forming the X axis. The
 compass orientation at the Jornada grassland site is to the north,
 and Jornada creosotebush site is oriented to the south. Treatments
 within each block include one unfenced control plot (Treatment: C;
 control), one plot fenced with hardware cloth and poultry wire to
 exclude rodents and rabbits (Treatment: R; rodent), and one plot
 fenced only with poultry wire to exclude rabbits (Treatment: L;
 lagomorph), and one plot fenced with barbed wire to exclude cattle
 (Treatment B; bovine). Note that there are cattle exclosure plots
 only at the Jornada grassland site where cattle are present, for a
 total of 4 measurement plots at each of the grassland site blocks.
 There are only 3 measurement plots at each of the creosotebush site
 blocks. The treatments were randomly assigned to each of the four
 possible plots in each block independently, and their arrangements
 differ from block to block. Each of the plots in a replicate block
 are separated by 20 meters. Each experimental measurement plot
 measures 36 meters by 36 meters (see Figure 4). A grid of 36
 sampling points are positioned at 5.8-meter intervals on a
 systematically located 6 by 6 point grid within each plot. A
 permanent one-meter by one-meter vegetation measurement quadrat is
 located at each of the 36 points. The 36 quadrats are numbered
 1-36, starting with number 1 in the top left corner of each plot,
 and running left to right, then down one row, and then right to
 left, and so on. A 2-foot rebar marks the lower right corner of
 each quadrat, and an aluminum tag on the rebar gives the quad
 number. 3-inch nails were originally placed in the top left corner
 of each quadrat. These may be difficult to see. A 3-meter wide
 buffer area is situated between the grid of 36 points and the
 perimeter of each plot.

 Rodent trapping webs are being used to determine the composition
 of rodent species at each study site, and to estimate densities of
 each species over time. The use of webs and distance measures to
 estimate rodent densities is statistically more robust than grid
 plot sampling and mark-release indices. Each rodent trapping web
 consists of a series of 12 equally spaced lines radiating from a
 central point. Each line consists of 12 trap stations. The first
 trap station is located 5 meters from the center, the next three at
 5 meter intervals, and the remaining 8 at ten meter intervals. Each
 trap line is 100 meters long, and each web is 200 meters in
 diameter.</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>Objectives:
The Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System (JIMS) provides protocol and services for data collection, verification, organization, archives, and distribution in accordance with recommendations and guidelines developed by the LTER Information Managers Committee (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html).

Disclaimer:
While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is". The Jornada Basin LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of data sets.

Quality Assurance Policy:
Data managers interact with researchers during the entire scientific process--from the initial planning of sampling designs and field data collection to archiving and distribution of data. The goal of data management is to build and maintain an archive of Jornada Basin LTER data files that are fully documented, error free, and organized in useful ways. Our protocol for data collection and processing seeks maximum interaction between researchers and data management personnel to avoid confusion and potential loss of data or problems with integrity of data; e.g., identification of historical site treatments that may impact a proposed study or incomplete data set variable descriptions. Site and Data Manager involvement begins during the Project Design phase with the completion of the Jornada Notification of Research form by the researcher prior to the start of work; this alerts both Site and Data Manager to the new study and potential LTER data sets. Upon initiation of a new study, the researcher completes Project Documentation that provides the second level of "metadata" documentation.
In the Data Collection phase, the data manager helps researchers design field and laboratory data sheets that facilitate data entry and analysis. Prior to JIMS data entry the investigator completes Data Set Documentation to provide the metadata that fully describe the data set. Both Project and Data set documentation are provided with the data set when it is requested or obtained from our Web site. JIMS data entry programs error-check and verify data as they are entered. Computer files are subjected to further verification by graphing and/or error-checking programs, and/or examination by field investigators. Final quality assurance of the data rests with the investigator who submits data for inclusion in the Data Management System. Direct communication with the Site Manager, or through a collaborating JRN P.I., is used to encourage the timely submission of documentation and of data by researchers.

Error-checked data files are stored with associated documentation files on the file server. Archived data files are maintained in ASCII format on 30-yr magneto-optical (MO) disks, portable hard drives, CD-R media, and DVD media to guard against loss of data access that can result from changing technology. This may also include proprietary binary format files to facilitate recovery of working versions. Image data are archived on 8mm tape. Routine tape data backups of the file server are done daily, weekly, and monthly. One set of off-site copies are maintained elsewhere on the NMSU campus of routine backup tapes, MO disks, CD disks, and DVD disks with a second set of MO, CD and DVD disks maintained off-campus in case of a catastrophe on campus. The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data manag ement staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data management staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

Policy on Submission of data:
Data submission into JIMS is expected from LTER researchers, LTER collaborators, and their graduate students where data and information is derived from publicly funded research in the U.S. LTER Network, totally or partially from LTER funds from NSF, Institutional Cost-Share, or Partner Agency or Institution where a formal memorandum of understanding with LTER has been established. Other Jornada Basin researchers are encouraged to submit their documented data for inclusion within JIMS to provide them with an archived backup, ensure its longevity, and provide online access to encourage synthesis efforts. Minimally, for non-LTER associated researchers, we request that publications be provided of research conducted on the Jornada Basin.
Initial documentation for a data set must be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager within 90 days of initiation of data collection. Documentation forms are available at http://jornada-www.nmsu.edu/site/dm/readme.php . These consist of Project Abstract and Data Set and Attribute documentation forms, which include objectives of the study, methods, as well as format and content of the data. All data collected during a calendar year should be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager prior to July first of the following year. First time data submissions must be submitted with updated standard Jornada Basin LTER forms previously submitted.

Data Access Policy:
Data will be made publicly available no later than 2 years after submission of the data unless an earlier date is specified by the principal investigator. In the event that an extension of the 2 year period is necessary, the principal investigator may petition the Jornada Basin LTER Executive Committee for a longer protected period. Graduate student research data will be available online after degree completion and they have the opportunity to publish their research.

Policies for re-use, distribution, or the production of derivatives:
Data re-use, distribution and production of derivative products are governed by the LTER Network data policies (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html) in the spirit of having the potential to increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines. Appropriate citation, acknowledgement, notification and collaboration are outlined and recommended. No commercial redistribution of data and derived products are allowed.

Data Acknowledgment Policy:
Please send notification to the Information Manager and Responsible Investigator(s) of the data sets you are downloading and your intended use.
Individuals and institutions utilizing data from the Jornada Basin LTER database are requested to place the following acknowledgment in any publication in which these data are mentioned:
Data sets were provided by the Jornada Basin Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) project. Funding for these data was provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210).

Please send 1 copy of any publication that cites Jornada Basin LTER data to:
     John P. Anderson
     Jornada Experimental Range
     P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
     New Mexico State University
     Las Cruces, NM 88003-0003</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="download">http://jornada-data.nmsu.edu/files/dataset_packages/JornadaStudy_086_smes_cryptogam_crust_quad_data.zip</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>1995-04-10</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2005-10-26</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <maintenance>
    <description>
      <para>
        <literalLayout> mm/dd/yyyy - Date of Comment
 Int - Initials of person making Comment
 KJL = Kevin J. La Fleur
 JPA = John P. Anderson
 DCL = David C. Lightfoot
 Changes/Updates - List any changes made to document

 mm/dd/yyyy Int Changes/Updates
 ---------- --- -----------------------------------------------
 11/14/2000 DCL Form completed by investigator
 06/17/2003 JPA Reformated line lengths.
 09/26/2009 JPA Updated attributes: Year, Season, Type
 05/09/2011 JPA Updated Comments section.
 11/15/2011 JPA Changed responsible investigator for contact person
 to Brandon Bestelmeyer per Deb Peters.
 Added PRJ and DSL ID numbers to top of file. They
 had been previously assigned but were not on this
 form.
 03/15/2012 JPA Made variable names more descriptive and updated
 dataset to match</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </description>
  </maintenance>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Data</givenName>
      <surName>Manager</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>PO Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>The Jornada</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Field micro-cassette tape recorders</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout> Study Site and Experimental Design Description

 A creosotebush shrub study site and a black grama grassland study
 site have been established at each of the Sevilleta, Jornada and
 Mapimi research locations. Each study site is 1 km by 0.5 km in
 area. Three rodent trapping webs and four replicate experimental
 blocks of plots are randomly located at each study site to measure
 vegetation responses to the exclusion of small mammals (see Figures
 1 and 2 for diagrams of the two Jornada sites). The blocks of study
 plots are all oriented on a site in a X/Y coordinate system, with
 the access road to each site forming the X axis. The compass
 orientation at the Jornada grassland site is to the north, and
 Jornada creosotebush site is oriented to the south. Treatments
 within each block include one unfenced control plot (Treatment: C;
 control), one plot fenced with hardware cloth and poultry wire to
 exclude rodents and rabbits (Treatment: R; rodent), and one plot
 fenced only with poultry wire to exclude rabbits (Treatment: L;
 lagomorph), and one plot fenced with barbed wire to exclude cattle
 (Treatment B; bovine). Note that there are cattle exclosure plots
 only at the Jornada grassland site where cattle are present, for a
 total of 4 measurement plots at each of the grassland site blocks.
 There are only 3 measurement plots at each of the creosotebush site
 blocks. The treatments were randomly assigned to each of the four
 possible plots in each block independently, and their arrangements
 differ from block to block. Each of the plots in a replicate block
 are separated by 20 meters (see Figure 3).

 Each experimental measurement plot measures 36 meters by 36
 meters (see Figure 4). A grid of 36 sampling points are positioned
 at 5.8-meter intervals on a systematically located 6 by 6 point grid
 within each plot. A permanent one-meter by one-meter vegetation
 measurement quadrat is located at each of the 36 points. The 36
 quadrats are numbered 1-36, starting with number 1 in the top left
 corner of each plot, and running left to right, then down one row,
 and then right to left, and so on (see Figure 4). A 2-foot rebar
 marks the lower right corner of each quadrat, and an aluminum tag on
 the rebar gives the quad number. 3-inch nails were originally placed
 in the top left corner of each quadrat. These may be difficult to
 see. A 3-meter wide buffer area is situated between the grid of 36
 points and the perimeter of each plot.

 Working on the Study Plots

 Always avoid walking on the quadrats, and do not walk across
 plots or anywhere within a block unless absolutely necessary. We
 are attempting to measure the effects of rodents and rabbits on
 plants and soils, not the effects of humans. When working on a
 plot, always walk on a line just below the rebar and quadrats, or on
 a line to the right of the rebar and quadrats (see dotted lines in
 Figure 4). Please try to walk gently and flat-footed on the study
 plots to minimize soil disturbance. When placing the vegetation
 measurement frame on a quadrat, be careful not to disturb the soil
 with the frame legs or your feet. When leaning over the measurement
 frame, be careful not to put your foot on the quadrat. We must
 measure all human caused disturbances to the soil surface of each
 quadrat.

 Vegetation Quadrat Measurements

 The foliage canopy area and maximum height of each plant species
 is measured from each quadrat. Several other variables are also
 measured from each quadrat, including soil surface disturbance, soil
 surface leaf litter cover, soil surface cryptogam crust cover,
 termite mud casing, and number of rabbit feces. All cover values
 are measured from the vegetation measurement frame, which is 1 meter
 by 1 meter, and partitioned into a grid of 100, 10 cm by 10 cm
 squares. Cover is measured by counting the number of 10cm squares
 that are occupied by the foliage canopy of a particular plant
 species, or by the soil disturbance, leaf litter etc. Portions of
 the 10 cm squares are also measured, down to 0.1 of a square.
 Detailed descriptions of measurement techniques are given below for
 each of the different variables measured.

 Placement of the vegetation quadrat measurement frame

 Walk from quadrat to quadrat along the lines mentioned above and
 marked in Figure 4. When you reach a quadrat, place one leg of the
 frame immediately next to and touching the 2-foot rebar, over the
 quadrat. Place the leg for the opposite corner of the frame (from
 bottom to top of a diamond shape) just inside of the 3-inch nail
 located at a 315 degree angle from the rebar on the plot X/Y, and
 compass coordinate system. The frame should be positioned so that
 the sides are parallel to the sides of the plot and directly over
 the quadrat, and in line with the rows of rebar (see Figure 4). You
 may not be able to see the nail, if not, line the sides of the frame
 with the rows of rebar the best you can.

 Recording Data

 You will record the quadrat data into your tape recorder. Each
 time you start recording data from a new plot (even if you are just
 helping someone else finish a plot), always start your recording by
 stating:

 "These are vegetation quadrat measurements for the Jornada small
 mammal exclosure study."

 Then state the date (month, day, year), the site (G or C), the
 block (1,2, 3, or 4), the plot (1, 2, 3, or 4), and the treatment
 (C, R, or L).

 If you are helping someone else on a plot, state so, and record
 who the other person is.

 Go to the first quadrat you will be taking measurements from, and
 record the quadrat number (1-36) before you start recording data, by
 stating "starting quadrat (n)".

 Note that (n) means whatever the appropriate number or letter is.

 When you are finished recording data for that quadrat, state
 "finished with quadrat (n)."

 Then go on to the next quadrat, and so on.

 When you have finished collecting data from the plot, state
 "finished with quadrat measurements on plot (n), of block (n), at
 site (n), on (date)."

 Additional Observations, Corrections, and Comments

 If you have already recorded data for a variable, e.g., rabbit
 feces, but while looking over the quadrat later, see some more, you
 may either make a correction to the previously recorded values, or
 make another observation (e.g., "correction, rabbit feces count
 (n)", or "rabbit feces count (n)." At any time, if you realize that
 you recorded incorrect data, just state "correction, ....." Always
 start corrections with the statement "correction". Do not try to
 run-back the tape and re-record over mistakes, just state
 "correction", and mention the problem.

 For comments, state "comment" and then record whatever you want
 to say about something. Comments are useful if you are uncertain
 about something, or see something unusual. Try to minimize use of
 comments though.

 Checking Your Tape Recordings

 Be sure to frequently play-back a small portion of your tape to
 verify that the tape recorder is working properly. Stop and
 play-back at least at the end of each line of 6 quadrats. Checking
 your tape after every other quadrat is even better.

 Labeling Your Tapes

 Be sure to label your tape, both on the cardboard case insert,
 and directly on the tape. Use the following format to label your
 tape:

 e.g., SMESVQF96-DL2

 Where: SMES = small mammal exclosure study
 VQ = vegetation quadrat data
 F96 = fall 1996, or S96 for spring 1996
 DL2 = initials for your name, in this case Dave Lightfoot, and the number of the ape, in this case, my second tape.



 Procedures for Vegetation Quadrat Measurements

 Below is a listing of procedures and values and ranges of values
 that you should record for each of the variables measured on the
 vegetation quadrats.

 IMPORTANT NOTE!!! Be sure to record an entry for all six of the
 following variables, even if the measurement or count is zero. So,
 for example, if there are no rabbit feces, record "rabbit feces
 count zero" or if there is no termite casing, record "termite casing
 zero" etc.

 Get into a routine of examining each quadrat for each of the 6
 variables. For example, start with plant cover, starting with the
 dominant plant species, then look for leaf litter, then look for
 cryptogams, then look for soil disturbance, then look for rabbit
 feces, then look for termite casing. And be sure to record a value
 for each of the 6 variables for each quadrat.



 Cryptogam Cover

 State "cryptogam cover (n)" for the cover of cryptogam crusts on
 the soil surface of the quadrat in terms of the 10 cm squares. For
 cover values less than 5, use increments of 1.0. For cover values
 greater than 5, use increments of 5.0. Cryptogams include lichens,
 algae, and moss. Only measure cryptogam cover that is in the open,
 do not attempt to measure within clumps of grass, etc. Some
 cryptogam cover has distinctive margins and is easy to define and
 measure. However, many cryptogam crusts consist of many diffuse
 small patches that are separated by bare soil, and distributed
 throughout the quadrat. For such diffuse cover, determine the
 actual cover in one typical 10 by 10 cm square (e.g., 0.3), then
 count the number of squares with diffuse cover (e.g., 5), and
 multiply the number of squares by the actual cover for a typical
 square (e.g., 0.3 X 5 = 1.5, then round to 1.0 or 2.0, or if the
 value had been greater than 5, round to the nearest increment of
 5.0) for the total cryptogam cover. All cryptogams are pooled into
 one observation, and no height is measured.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
    <qualityControl>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout> Responsible investigator(s):
 ----------------------------
 Brandon Bestelmeyer, Oct2004-present;
 David Lightfoot, Oct1995-Sep2003
 *************************************

 Cryptogam cover is no longer read after 2005, which is when
 sampling of SMES grassland site switched to a 5 year sampling
 interval. The SMES creosotebush site is no longer sampled at
 all.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </qualityControl>
  </methods>
  <project>
    <title>Jornada LTER</title>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
        <givenName>Debra</givenName>
        <surName>Peters</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-2777</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">575-646-5889</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>debpeter@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Lead Principal Investigator</role>
    </personnel>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Data</givenName>
        <surName>Manager</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Information Manager</role>
    </personnel>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>The Jornada Basin Long Term Ecological Research program, in collaboration with 
                         the USDA ARS Jornada Experimental Range, studies the causes and consequences of 
                         desertification: the broad scale expansion of woody plants into grasslands that 
                         results in more "desert like" conditions. We are interested in spatial and 
                         temporal variation in desertification dynamics, and how historic legacies, the 
                         geomorphic template, transport vectors (wind, water, animals), and environmental 
                         drivers (climate, land use, disturbance) interact with the patch structure of the 
                         vegetation to determine past, present, and future ecosystem dynamics across 
                         scales.
                        
                         Our study site is located in the northern Chihuahuan Desert, approximately 25 km 
                         northeast of Las Cruces, New Mexico, USA (+32.5 N, -106.8 W, elevation 1188 m). 
                         Annual precipitation is 24 cm and maximum temperatures average 13 C in January 
                         and 36 C in June. Our study site includes the 78,000 ha Jornada Experimental 
                         Range operated by the USDA Agricultural Research Service, and the 22,000 ha 
                         Chihuahuan Desert Rangeland Research Center (CDRRC) operated by New Mexico State 
                         University. The Jornada Basin LTER project was established in 1982, and is 
                         administered by New Mexico State University. This site is a member of the LTER 
                         Network, one of  more than 25 long term sites funded by the U.S. National Science 
                         Foundation.</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <funding>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210)</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </funding>
  </project>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>JornadaStudy_086_smes_cryptogam_crust_quad_data.csv</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data file information for the following Jornada data set: SMES cryptogam crust data</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>JornadaStudy_086_smes_cryptogam_crust_quad_data.csv</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <numHeaderLines>30</numHeaderLines>
          <numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
          <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url function="download">http://jornada-data.nmsu.edu/sites/jornada-data.nmsu.edu/files/data_files/JornadaStudy_086_smes_cryptogam_crust_quad_data.csv</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1995-04-10</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2005-10-26</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>date</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_cryptogam_crust_date</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Date data was collected (month/day/year)</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>mm/dd/yyyy</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>site</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_cryptogam_crust_site</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Site code</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>C</code>
                  <definition> Creosotebush</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>G</code>
                  <definition> Grassland</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>block</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_cryptogam_crust_block</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Block number</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>N/A</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">4</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>plot</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_cryptogam_crust_plot</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Plot number</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>N/A</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">4</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>treatment</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_cryptogam_crust_treatment</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Treatment type</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>C</code>
                  <definition>Control</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>R</code>
                  <definition>Rodent Exclosure</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>L</code>
                  <definition>Lagomorph Exclosure</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>B</code>
                  <definition>Bovine Exclosure</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>quad</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_cryptogam_crust_quad</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Quad number</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>N/A</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">36</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>cover</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_cryptogam_crust_cover</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Cryptogam crust cover/quad</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>N/A</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>id</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_cryptogam_crust_id</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition> Book -or- Tape Number
B01 = Book number one
SMXVQF95.JA1 - Code on tape</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition> Book -or- Tape Number
B01 = Book number one
SMXVQF95.JA1 - Code on tape</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Comment code</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_cryptogam_crust_comment_code</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>comment code</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>0</code>
                  <definition>no comment</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1</code>
                  <definition>see data history log</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>year</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_cryptogam_crust_year</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Year of collection</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>yyyy</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>season</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_cryptogam_crust_season</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Season</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>S</code>
                  <definition>spring</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>F</code>
                  <definition>fall</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>type </attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_cryptogam_crust_type </attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Data type</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>CR</code>
                  <definition>cryptogamic crust</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Keyfield</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_keyfield</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>spatial primary key field (specific to Jornada Integrated Information Management System [JIIMS])</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>spatial primary key field (specific to Jornada Integrated Information Management System [JIIMS])</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Dataset ID</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_datasetid</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>old dataset identifier (specific to JIIMS)</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>old dataset identifier (specific to JIIMS)</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Point X</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_point_x</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>x spatial coordinate [NEED COORDINATE SYSTEM, DATUM, PROJECTION SYSTEM, ...] (specific to JIIMS)</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>x spatial coordinate [NEED COORDINATE SYSTEM, DATUM, PROJECTION SYSTEM, ...] (specific to JIIMS)</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Point Y</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_point_y</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>y spatial coordinate [NEED COORDINATE SYSTEM, DATUM, PROJECTION SYSTEM, ...] (specific to JIMS)</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>y spatial coordinate [NEED COORDINATE SYSTEM, DATUM, PROJECTION SYSTEM, ...] (specific to JIMS)</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Table ID</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_table_id</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Table identifier (used by JIIMS)</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Table identifier (used by JIIMS)</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Layer ID</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_layer_id</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>GIS layer identifier (used by JIIMS)</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>GIS layer identifier (used by JIIMS)</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
    <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
<ns2:unit id="N/A" />
    </ns2:unitList>
  </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>