<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="387.knb-lter-cap.387.6" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://data.gios.asu.edu/eml2_1_0/eml.xsd">
<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
<allow>
            <principal>uid=CAP,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
            <principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
    <dataset id="387.387_1" scope="system" system="ASU">
        <alternateIdentifier system="gios_dataset">387</alternateIdentifier>
        <shortName>modeled_CO2</shortName>
        <title>Spatial Patterns and Determinants of Atmospheric Carbon Dioxide Concentrations in Phoenix metro area</title>
        <creator>
            <individualName>
                <givenName>Elizabeth</givenName>
                <surName>Wentz</surName>
            </individualName>
            <address>
                <deliveryPoint>School of Geographical Sciences</deliveryPoint>
                <deliveryPoint>Arizona State University</deliveryPoint>
                <deliveryPoint>PO Box 870104</deliveryPoint>
                <city>Tempe</city>
                <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
                <postalCode>85287-5402</postalCode>
                <country>USA</country>
            </address>
        </creator>
        <creator>
            <individualName>
                <givenName>Patricia</givenName>
                <surName>Gober</surName>
            </individualName>
            <address>
                <deliveryPoint>School of Geographical Sciences</deliveryPoint>
                <deliveryPoint>Arizona State University</deliveryPoint>
                <deliveryPoint>PO Box 870104</deliveryPoint>
                <city>Tempe</city>
                <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
                <postalCode>85287-5402</postalCode>
                <country>USA</country>
            </address>
        </creator>
        <creator>
            <individualName>
                <givenName>Robert</givenName>
                <surName>Balling</surName>
            </individualName>
            <address>
                <deliveryPoint>School of Geographical Sciences</deliveryPoint>
                <deliveryPoint>Arizona State University</deliveryPoint>
                <deliveryPoint>PO Box 870104</deliveryPoint>
                <city>Tempe</city>
                <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
                <postalCode>85287-5402</postalCode>
                <country>USA</country>
            </address>
        </creator>
        <creator>
            <individualName>
                <givenName>Thomas</givenName>
                <surName>Day</surName>
            </individualName>
            <address>
                <deliveryPoint>School of Life Sciences</deliveryPoint>
                <deliveryPoint>Arizona State University</deliveryPoint>
                <deliveryPoint>PO Box 870601</deliveryPoint>
                <city>Tempe</city>
                <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
                <postalCode>85287-5402</postalCode>
                <country>USA</country>
            </address>
        </creator>
        <pubDate>2007</pubDate>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>
            <para>The purpose of this work is to describe determinants and spatial patterns of
                atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO2) in Phoenix, Arizona. Specifically, we use
                geographic information systems (GIS) and regression-based analyses to identify the
                human and biological factors that contribute to spatial and temporal variations in
                near-surface atmospheric CO2 levels. We use these factors to create estimated
                surfaces of CO2 for the urban area. We validate our surfaces using independently
                collected records of CO2 from several monitoring stations and transects. To
                investigate the temporal patterns and variations of CO2, we were able to generate
                CO2 surfaces for the early mornings and the afternoons, and on weekdays when traffic
                is heavy and spatially focused and on weekends when it is lighter and more spatially
                dispersed. Our findings suggest there is a distinct relationship between the
                structure of Phoenix CO2 levels and spatial patterns of human activities and
                vegetation densities. Morning CO2 levels are higher than afternoon levels and
                correspond closely to the density of traffic, population, and employment. The
                spatial structure of human activity explains the pattern of CO2 better on weekdays
                than on weekends. CO2 surfaces reflect declining densities of human activity with
                distance from the city center, the pattern of irrigated agriculture in the Phoenix
                area, and riparian habitats on the urban fringe. Spatial and temporal patterns of
                CO2 are useful in understanding urban climate and ecosystem processes</para>
        </abstract><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="place">sonoran desert</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">phoenix</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">urban</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">metropolitan area</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">land architecture</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">land use changes</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">gis</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">geographic information systems</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">geosciences</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Biogeochemical Patterns, Processes, and Human Outcomes</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">modeling</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">human environment feedback</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Climate, Ecosystems and People</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">carbon dioxide</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">urban climatology</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">regression-based mapping</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Land-Use, Land-Cover and Land Architecture</keyword><keywordThesaurus>Creator Defined Keyword Set</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">urban</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">populations</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">census</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">humans</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">monitoring</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">vegetation</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">transects</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">roads</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">normalized vegetation index</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">carbon dioxide</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary Keyword Set</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">caplter</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">central arizona phoenix longterm ecological research</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">arizona</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">caplter created</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">az</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">cap</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">arid land</keyword><keywordThesaurus>CAPLTER Keyword Set List</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet>
        
        <intellectualRights>
            <section>
                <para>Copyright Board of Regents, Arizona State University. This dataset is released
                    to the public and may be used for academic, educational, or commercial purposes
                    subject to the following restrictions:</para>
                <para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>While CAP LTER will make every effort possible to control and
                                document the quality of the data it publishes, the data are made
                                available "as is".</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER cannot assume responsibility for damages resulting from
                                mis-use or mis-interpretation of datasets or from errors or
                                omissions that may exist in the data.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge
                                the work of other scientists that has resulted in data used in
                                subsequent research.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER expects that any use of data from this server will be
                                accompanied with the appropriate citations and
                                acknowledgments.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER encourages users to contact the original investigator
                                responsible for the data that they are accessing. Where appropriate,
                                researchers whose projects are integrally dependent on CAP LTER data
                                are encouraged to consider collaboration and/or co-authorship with
                                original investigators.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER requests that users submit to the Center for
                                Environmental Studies, ASU, one copy of any publication resulting
                                from the use of data obtained from this site.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER requests that users not redistribute data obtained from
                                this site. However, links or references to this site may be freely
                                posted.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            </section>
        </intellectualRights>
        <distribution>
            <online>
                <url>http://data.gios.asu.edu/cap/HarvestListFileShow.php?id=387</url>
            </online>
        </distribution>

        <coverage>
            <temporalCoverage>
                <singleDateTime>
                    <calendarDate>2000-01-16</calendarDate>
                </singleDateTime>
            </temporalCoverage>
            <geographicCoverage>
                <geographicDescription>Central Arizona Phoenix</geographicDescription>
                <boundingCoordinates>
                    <westBoundingCoordinate>-112.633109</westBoundingCoordinate>
                    <eastBoundingCoordinate>-111.364290</eastBoundingCoordinate>
                    <northBoundingCoordinate>33.924291</northBoundingCoordinate>
                    <southBoundingCoordinate>33.103611</southBoundingCoordinate>
                </boundingCoordinates>
            </geographicCoverage>
        </coverage>
        <purpose>
            <para>This research is part of a larger National Science Foundation-funded effort to
                understand interrelationships among CO2 levels, meteorological conditions, human
                activity, and ecosystem processes in urban Phoenix. The ultimate goal is to produce
                an integrated model of CO2 patterns and processes and predict changes in this
                pattern with continued population growth and land use change.</para>
        </purpose>
        <maintenance>
            <description>
                <para>This research has been concluded</para>
            </description>
            <maintenanceUpdateFrequency>asNeeded</maintenanceUpdateFrequency>
        </maintenance>
        <contact id="387.Datamanager">
            <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
            <address>
                <deliveryPoint>Global Institute of Sustainability</deliveryPoint>
                <deliveryPoint>Arizona State University</deliveryPoint>
                <deliveryPoint>POB 875402</deliveryPoint>
                <city>TEMPE</city>
                <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
                <postalCode>85287-5402</postalCode>
                <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <phone phonetype="voice">(480) 965 2975</phone>
            <phone phonetype="fax">(480) 965-8087</phone>
            <electronicMailAddress>caplter.data@asu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        </contact>
        <methods>
            <methodStep>
                <description>
                    <section>
                        <title>Data collection</title>
                        <para>As part of the larger NSF project to study the characteristics of the
                            CO2 dome in Phoenix, atmospheric concentrations of CO2 were measured
                            with an InFrared gas analyzer (model LI-800; Li-Cor, Lincoln NE) along
                            four transects on major roadways through metropolitan Phoenix on 10 14
                            consecutive days from 3 to 16 January, 2000. Transects 1 and 2 were
                            chosen to bisect the urban area, north to south and east to west
                            respectively. Transects 3 and 4 weave in and out of the urbanized area
                            to capture CO2 processesat the urban/rural boundaries. Measurements were
                            taken simultaneously along all four transects at 2 meters above the
                            ground at points approximately one mile apart between the pre-dawn hours
                            of 5:00 and 6:00 and again during the afternoon hours of 14:00 to 15:00.
                            Idso et al. (in press) provides a more complete discussion of data
                            collection methods. Inconsistent and erratic readings along Transect 4
                            led us to drop those observations from our analysis; thus we were left
                            with morning and afternoon CO2 readings from 227 monitoring sites spread
                            non-randomly, but covering a broad cross-section of environments, across
                            the metropolitan area. For each site, we calculated morning and
                            afternoon means across the 14 days (n = 14), and then on weekdays (n =
                            10) and weekends (n = 4) separately. Ideally, our monitoring sites would
                            be randomly distributed across the metropolitan area. This, however, was
                            operationally impossible given that CO2 needed to be collected at
                            roughly the same time across all 227 sites. All sites along a given
                            transect could be taken within an hour, and each transect was monitored
                            simultaneously. Therefore, we assume there was a roadway effect on all
                            transects (Idso 1998b), which we tested during our validation
                            experiment. We separated weekday and weekend observations because
                            intra-urban vehicular traffic is a major source of CO2 emissions and
                            because the intensity and spatial organization of weekend and weekday
                            traffic differs. The sheer amount of traffic along Phoenix-area
                            thoroughfares is more than 40 percent higher on weekdays than on
                            weekends, with Friday as the peak and Sunday as the low point. Moreover,
                            because weekday travel is more work-oriented than weekend travel, it is
                            more geographically concentrated in the early morning and late afternoon
                            hours (Barber 1986). Weekend travel is less concentrated in both time
                            and space. In a related paper characterizing urban CO2 in Phoenix, Idso
                            et al. (in press) found that weekday CO2 levels exceed weekend levels by
                            30 percent in the commercial core of Phoenix but there are no
                            weekday-weekend differences in surrounding residential areas.
                            Independent variables for this study are population density (POP),
                            employment density (EMP), average weekly traffic (AWT), and vegetation
                            density (VEG). Population data were extracted from ESRI&#8217;s 1990 compiled
                            Census data, which are based on the 1990 Census of Population (ESRI
                            1997). From this CD, we extracted total population for 1997 for all
                            Census tracts in Maricopa County, Arizona. Data were converted from an
                            ArcView&#169; shapefile into an Arc/INFO&#169; coverage. Employment and traffic
                            data were obtained from the Maricopa Association of Governments (MAG).
                            Employment data were converted from tabular form to an Arc/INFO point
                            coverage with the total number of employees associated with each point.
                            Average weekly traffic data were converted from MAG&#8217;s 1998 average
                            weekly traffic map into an Arc/INFO coverage. Vegetation data were
                            provided by the Central Arizona Phoenix - Long Term Ecological Research
                            (CAP - LTER) project as normalized difference vegetation index (NDVI).
                            NDVI is an indicator, with a range from 0 to 1, representing vegetation
                            density (green leaf area, biomass, percent green cover, productivity,
                            and photosynthetic activity). The Soil Adjusted Vegetation Index (SAVI)
                            is often used as a measure of vegetation in a desert/urban environment
                            to eliminate soil-induced variations in the index (Heute 1988). Since we
                            wanted to account for differences in soil, we elected to use NDVI.
                            Preliminary results of our analysis showed there were only minor
                            differences between using NDVI and SAVI in our model. The NDVI were
                            calculated in ERDAS&#169; from a May 1998 Thematic Mapper image (cell
                            resolution is approximately 30 meters). The ERDAS image was
                            geographically referenced and converted into an Arc/INFO GRID format.
                            The month of May was selected because the general consensus among the
                            CAP - LTER scientists was that May coincided with maximum leafout and
                            vegetation cover. May is also one of the best times of year for
                            collection of remotely sensed data in this region because cloud cover
                            tends to be minimal (the winter storms are gone, and the monsoon has not
                            yet started). We do not view the differences between May and January as
                            significant, because there is a strong spatial correlation in vegetation
                            patterns from month to month.</para>
                    </section>
                </description>
            </methodStep>
            <methodStep>
                <description>
                    <section>
                        <title>Estimating a CO2 Regression Model</title>
                        <para>We first produced estimates of population, employment, traffic, and
                            vegetation densities in a GIS by calculating the value of each
                            independent variable surrounding each CO2 monitoring site. Lacking a
                            generally accepted buffer size, we calculated buffers at 200, 400, 600,
                            800, 1000, and 1613 meters (one mile). Preliminary results of our
                            regression model indicated that the larger buffers produced slightly
                            stronger correlations between the independent variables and CO2 levels,
                            but the differences were fairly small. We settled on a one-half mile
                            buffer (807 meters) as a compromise. It is small enough to provide
                            spatially detailed estimates of CO2 levels but large enough to produce
                            strong relationships between the independent variables and CO2 levels.
                            To calculate the population value (POP) for each monitoring site, we
                            summed the total population within the buffer based on a percent area of
                            the Census tract (Eq.1). Percent area was used because the buffer size
                            was usually smaller in size than the underlying Census tracts. In these
                            situations, we assumed that population was evenly distributed across the
                            Census tract, and therefore population was estimated by multiplying the
                            total population in the Census tract by the percent area of the buffer.
                            POP = SUM (Ab/At * Pi) where: Ab = area of the census tract i that fell
                            within the buffer At = total area of census tract i Pi= total population
                            of census tract i n = total number of census tracts that intersect
                            buffer Average weekly traffic for each CO2 monitoring site (AWT) was
                            calculated by a percent distance of roads within the buffer, a method
                            similar to the population value (Eq. 2). We extracted the roads that
                            fell within the buffer and calculated the percent of the road length
                            that fell within the buffer. The percent length was multiplied by the
                            average weekly traffic for each road, and the total was summed. AWT =
                            SUM(Db/Dt * Ti) where: Db = distance of road i that fell within the
                            buffer Dt = total distance of road i Ti= total average weekly traffic on
                            road i n = total number of roads that intersect buffer The employment
                            value (EMP) for each CO2 monitoring site was determined by extracting
                            all the employment points that fell within the buffer and summing the
                            number of employees associated with these points (Eq. 3) EMP = SUM(Ei)
                            where: Ei = the number of employees at point i n = total number of
                            employee points that fell within the buffer The vegetation value (VEG)
                            for each monitoring site was calculated in two steps. We first converted
                            the grid cells into points with the NDVI value associated with each
                            point. The points that fell within an 807-meter buffer around the
                            monitoring site were extracted and the vegetation index for all points
                            was summed (Eq. 4). VEG = SUM(NDVIi) where: NDVIi = the NDVI value at
                            point i n = total number of NDVI grid points that fell within the buffer
                            Correlation among the indicators of human activity, POP, EMP, and AWT,
                            are moderate to high, ranging from a correlation coefficient (r) of .72
                            between POP and AWT to .48 between EMP and AWT. Density of all three
                            variables is highest in the city center, but employment is more heavily
                            concentrated there than either population or vehicular traffic. Concern
                            about multicollinearity led us to subject the four independent variables
                            to principal components analysis. The principal components analysis
                            yielded two factors with eigenvalues greater than 1.0 that together
                            accounted for over 80 percent of the spatial variation in the four
                            independent variables. With factor loadings of .90 for AWT, .90 for POP,
                            and .68 for EMP, Factor 1 represents an Urbanization Factor reflecting
                            the intensity of human activity including the presence of jobs,
                            residents, and traffic at any given location. Highest values are in the
                            core of the metropolitan area, and they decline outward. Factor 2, a
                            Vegetation Factor, shows more of the vegetation cover with a loading of
                            .97 for the NDVI. Factor scores for Factor 2 are low in the highly
                            developed Central Business District, but high in a variety of places,
                            including irrigated agricultural fields and the riparian habitat of the
                            Gila River on the outskirts of the metropolitan area, and well
                            established residential neighborhoods built on irrigated citrus groves.
                            Both sets of component scores revealed a statistically significant
                            deviation from normality. Both had positive skewness and positive
                            kurtosis. As a result, both were normalized with a square root
                            transformation. Normalized scores for the urbanization and vegetation
                            factors were then used as independent variables in a regression equation
                            with atmospheric CO2 concentration as the dependent variable. CO2 = a +
                            b1 Urbanization + b2 Vegetation (5) Separate regressions were run for
                            mornings and afternoons and for weekday and weekend averages to
                            determine the relative importance of human activity and vegetation at
                            the different times of the day and week and to obtain the best possible
                            predictions of CO2 levels.</para>
                    </section>
                </description>
            </methodStep>
            <methodStep>
                <description>
                    <section>
                        <title>Creating CO2 Surfaces</title>
                        <para>The usual strategy to display estimated spatial patterns of air
                            pollution in the form of a contoured surface is to use simple
                            interpolation methods to estimate levels between observation units that
                            are small in number and highly dispersed in distribution.
                            Regression-based mapping has improved the traditional interpolation
                            methods by allowing independent variables to predict the concentration
                            of the pollutants rather than estimate levels simply on the basis of
                            nearby points. Briggs et al. (1997) demonstrated this technique with air
                            pollution, and Blennow and Persson (1998) used a similar method for
                            examining frost variations. Briggs et al. (1997) used least squares
                            regression to evaluate relationships between monitored levels of NO2 and
                            exogenous variables, including traffic volume, road type, and land
                            use/land cover in the vicinity of monitoring sites. Model coefficients
                            are then used in a GIS to produce highly detailed NO2 surfaces that
                            reflect the complex nature of spatial variation in urban air pollution.
                            We created CO2 surfaces by calculating estimated CO2 values from maps of
                            the four independent variables across the entire urbanized region. The
                            urbanized region was covered by one-half mile grid squares (each
                            approximately 2,035,571 square meters) corresponding closely to the
                            one-half mile buffer distances we created around our 277 data
                            observation units. A value for AWT, EMP, POP, and NDVI was produced for
                            each of the 5,167 squares. Factor score coefficients were applied to
                            these raw values to produce scores for Factor 1 (urbanization) and
                            Factor 2 (vegetation). Factor scores were then normalized and used as
                            independent variables with the regression coefficients to generate
                            predicted CO2 values for each grid square, where a map of estimated CO2
                            surface can be created. Separate surfaces were produced for mornings and
                            afternoons and on weekdays and weekends producing six maps: (1) average
                            morning, (2) average afternoon, (3) weekday morning, (4) weekend
                            morning, (5) weekday afternoon, and (6) weekend afternoon.</para>
                    </section>
                </description>
            </methodStep>
            <methodStep>
                <description>
                    <section>
                        <title>CO2 Model Validation</title>
                        <para>Validation of the predicted CO2 concentrations was carried out in two
                            ways. First, we compared the CO2 predictions to actual CO2 levels
                            measured at four independent sites. Two sites were located within areas
                            of highly concentrated CO2 and two outside, with each site representing
                            either non-managed desert landscape or managed irrigated land. The
                            problem with these sites is, unlike the 227 transects points, they are
                            between 180 and 600 meters from major roads and thus farther from the
                            major source of CO2 emissions. In a second and related test, we
                            evaluated the effects of collecting the CO2 data along major urban
                            roadways. To test for the roadway effect on our CO2 levels, we selected
                            six sites along major roadways and included highly vegetated, desert,
                            and urban-residential sites with each land cover type inside and outside
                            the areas of high CO2 concentration. CO2, temperature, wind speed, and
                            wind direction data were collected during the pre-dawn hours and
                            afternoon hours. Data were collected on weekdays rather than weekends
                            because we know that traffic patterns are more concentrated on weekdays.
                            To determine the distance decay effects, data were collected adjacent to
                            the roadway, and at 10, 20, 40, 100, and 400-meter intervals along
                            transects that ran perpendicular to the roadway</para>
                    </section>
                </description>
            </methodStep>
        </methods>
        <spatialVector id="387.modeled_CO2">
            <entityName>Spatial Patterns and Determinants of Atmospheric Carbon Dioxide Concentrations in Phoenix metro area</entityName>
            <physical>
                <objectName>387.zip</objectName>
                <dataFormat>
                    <externallyDefinedFormat>
                        <formatName>Shapefile</formatName>
                    </externallyDefinedFormat>
                </dataFormat>
                <distribution>
                    <online>
                        <url>http://data.gios.asu.edu/datasets/cap/387.zip</url>
                    </online>
                </distribution>
            </physical>
            <attributeList>
                <attribute id="387.FID">
                    <attributeName>FID</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Internal feature number.</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html">OID</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Sequential unique whole numbers that are
                                        automatically generated.</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.Shape">
                    <attributeName>Shape</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Feature geometry.</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html">Geometry</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Coordinates defining the features.</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.AREA">
                    <attributeName>AREA</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Area of grid cells in square meters</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html">Float</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>squareMeter</standardUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>0.01</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.PERIMETER">
                    <attributeName>PERIMETER</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Perimeter of grid cells in square
                        meters</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html">Float</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>0.01</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.MODEL_CO2_">
                    <attributeName>MODEL_CO2_</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>MODEL_CO2 grid cell number</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">integer</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Sequential unique whole numbers</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.MODEL_CO21">
                    <attributeName>MODEL_CO21</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>MODEL_CO2 grid cell unique identifier</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">integer</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Sequential unique whole numbers</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.EMP">
                    <attributeName>EMP</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Employment density is the summation of all employees in all
                        employment points that fell within the buffer of each CO2 monitoring
                        site</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html">Float</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>0.01</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.VEG">
                    <attributeName>VEG</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Summation of all NDVI values for all grid points that are
                        within the 807-meter buffer of each CO2 monitoring
                        site</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html">Float</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>0.01</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.POP">
                    <attributeName>POP</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Population density Derived by multiplying total population
                        in the US Census tract by the percent are of the buffer of each CO2
                        monitoring site</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html">Float</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>0.01</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.AWT">
                    <attributeName>AWT</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Average Weekly Traffic as Percent distance of road within
                        each CO2 monitoring site buffer</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html">Float</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>0.01</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.NFACTOR1">
                    <attributeName>NFACTOR1</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>NFACTOR1</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">float</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Real numbers</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.NFACTOR2">
                    <attributeName>NFACTOR2</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>NFACTOR2</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">float</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Real numbers</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.MCO2">
                    <attributeName>Morning CO2</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Average CO2 concentration in parts per million per volume
                        for winter morning</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">float</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>0.01</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.WDMCO2">
                    <attributeName>WDMCO2</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Average CO2 concentration in parts per million per volume
                        for weekday winter morning</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">float</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>0.01</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.WEMCO2">
                    <attributeName>WEMCO2</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Average CO2 concentration in parts per million per volume
                        for weekend winter morning</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">float</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>0.01</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.ACO2">
                    <attributeName>ACO2</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Average CO2 concentration in parts per million per volume
                        for winter afternoon</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">float</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>0.01</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.WDACO2">
                    <attributeName>WDACO2</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Average CO2 concentration in parts per million per volume
                        for weekday winter afternoon</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">float</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>0.01</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.WEACO2">
                    <attributeName>WEACO2</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Average CO2 concentration in parts per million per volume
                        for weekend winter afternoon</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">float</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>0.01</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.FACTOR1">
                    <attributeName>FACTOR1</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Factor 1 (urbanization) loadings from the Principal
                        Component Analysis of POP, AWT, EMP, and VEG</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">float</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>0.01</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="387.FACTOR2">
                    <attributeName>FACTOR2</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Factor 2 (vegetation) loadings from the Principal Component
                        Analysis of POP, AWT, EMP, and VEG</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">float</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
                            </unit>
                            <precision>0.01</precision>
                            <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
                            </numericDomain>
                        </ratio>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
            </attributeList>
            <geometry>Polygon</geometry>
            <geometricObjectCount>5166</geometricObjectCount>
            <spatialReference>
                <horizCoordSysName>WGS_1984_UTM_Zone_12N</horizCoordSysName>
            </spatialReference>
            <horizontalAccuracy>
                <accuracyReport>not assessed</accuracyReport>
            </horizontalAccuracy>
            <verticalAccuracy>
                <accuracyReport>not assessed</accuracyReport>
            </verticalAccuracy>
        </spatialVector>
    </dataset>
</eml:eml>