<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-cap.395.7" system="gios_dataset" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://data.gios.asu.edu/eml2_1_0/eml.xsd">
<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
<allow>
            <principal>uid=CAP,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
            <principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
  <dataset id="395_1" system="gios_dataset">
    <alternateIdentifier system="gios_dataset">395</alternateIdentifier>
    <title>Effects of land cover and water availability on brittlebush (Encelia farinosa) flowering
      phenology and its pollinator community.</title>
    <creator>
            <individualName>
                <givenName>Kaesha</givenName>
        <surName>Neil</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>School of Life Sciences, Arizona State University</organizationName>
    </creator>
    <creator>
            <individualName>
                <givenName>Juanguo</givenName>
        <surName>Wu</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>School of Life Sciences, Arizona State University</organizationName>
      <address>
                <deliveryPoint>School of Life Sciences</deliveryPoint>
                <deliveryPoint>Arizona State University</deliveryPoint>
                <deliveryPoint>PO Box 874501</deliveryPoint>
                <city>Tempe</city>
                <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
                <postalCode>85287-5402</postalCode>
                <country>USA</country>
            </address>
    </creator>
    <pubDate>2008</pubDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <abstract>
            <para>
                Phenology is the seasonal timing of environment-mediated events such as
          growth and reproduction.  Phenology is quantified by determining time of onset
          and end of events, duration, and number of flowers (Augspurger 1983, Rathcke and Lacey
          1985).  Studies of flowering and leafing phenology have dramatically increased
          during the last few decades due to growing concerns over global climate change and because
          phenology is a highly sensitive indicator that researchers can use to study the effects of
          climate change at multiple scales (Chuine et al. 2000, Sparks and Menzel 2002, Peuelas
          et al. 2004, Williams and Abberton 2004).  Urban climatic conditions are
          considered similar to the changing global climate conditions; therefore, many researchers
          study urbanized areas as smaller scale experiments, or models, of global climate change
          (Ziska et al. 2003).  Concerns over climate change are not the only reasons for
          studying urban ecosystems.  It is important to create urban environments
          resilient to social, economic, and ecological collapse.
      </para>
      <para>
                The literature of flowering phenology in urban environments suggests that
          spring-blooming plants in urban environments located in temperate, Mediterranean, and
          boreal ecosystems in North America, Europe, and China tend to bloom earlier in the city
          than in the surrounding un-urbanized habitat (Roetzer et al. 2000, Fitter and Fitter 2002,
          White et al. 2002, Ziska et al. 2003, Zhang et al. 2004).  Moreover, non-woody
          plants, early spring bloomers, and insect-pollinated plants in these environments tend to
          be more sensitive than woody plants, mid- or late-spring bloomers, and wind-pollinated
          plants (Fitter and Fitter 2002, Traidl-Hoffman et al. 2003).  Finally,
          temperature (Heat Island Effect) has been assumed to be the cause of earlier flowering in
          the urban environments since the large-scale advancement of flowering has been strongly
          correlated with global warming. 
      </para>
      <para>
                  Study of flowering phenology in urban ecosystems is important
          because changes in phenology may have wide-reaching consequences.  Explicit study
          of the potential consequences of any changes in flowering phenology in urbanized areas has
          not been widely addressed; however, general ecological consequences from phenological
          changes due to global climate change have been hypothesized and studied, such as earlier
          and extended pollen allergy season (e.g., Van Vliet et al. 2002, Traidl-Hoffman et al.
          2003, Ziska et al. 2003) and mis-matches in synchronized inter-specific interactions
          (e.g., Kudo et al. 2004).  These effects of global climate change may be similar
          to changes and consequences in urban ecosystems.  Other potential consequences
          include effects on:  individual fitness (e.g. offspring production and
          viability); intra-specific interactions (e.g., genetic mixing); plant inter-specific
          interactions (e.g., resource competition); non-plant inter-specific interactions (e.g.,
          pests, pollinators, pathogens, herbivores); economics (e.g., any agriculture occurring
          near or within cities, including the floral industry and crops that require pollination by
          native organisms; also, private gardens); and human health (e.g., pollinosis,
          psychological well-being/appeal).
      </para>
    </abstract><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">Climate, Ecosystems and People</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">human decisions and biodiversity</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">primary production</keyword><keywordThesaurus>IPA and Core Area CAP Data Portal Controler</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="place">sonoran desert</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">phoenix</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">irrigation</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">maricopa county</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">human decisions and biodiversity</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">human environment feedback</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">primary production</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Climate, Ecosystems and People</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">desert botanical garden</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">lower colorado river</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">brittlebush</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">phenology</keyword><keywordThesaurus>Creator Defined Keyword Set</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">urban</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">water</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">deserts</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">plants</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">communities</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">flowers</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">climate</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">climate change</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">ecosystems</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">phenology</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary Keyword Set</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">caplter</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">central arizona phoenix longterm ecological research</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">arizona</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">caplter created</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">az</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">cap</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">arid land</keyword><keywordThesaurus>CAPLTER Keyword Set List</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet>
    
    <intellectualRights>
            <section>
                <para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>While CAP LTER will make every effort possible to control and document the
                quality of the data it publishes, the data are made available "as is".</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER cannot assume responsibility for damages resulting from mis-use or
                mis-interpretation of datasets or from errors or omissions that may exist in the
                data.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                            <para>It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of
                other scientists that has resulted in data used in subsequent research.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER expects that any use of data from this server will be accompanied with
                the appropriate citations and acknowledgments.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER encourages users to contact the original investigator responsible for
                the data that they are accessing. Where appropriate, researchers whose projects are
                integrally dependent on CAP LTER data are encouraged to consider collaboration
                and/or co-authorship with original investigators.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER requests that users submit to the Global Institute of Sustainability,
                ASU, one copy of any publication resulting from the use of data obtained from this
                site.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER requests that users not redistribute data obtained from this site.
                However, links or references to this site may be freely posted.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
            <online>
                <url>http://data.gios.asu.edu/cap/HarvestListFileShow.php?id=395</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <contact>
            <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <address>
                <deliveryPoint>Global Institute for Sustainability</deliveryPoint>
                <deliveryPoint>Arizona State University</deliveryPoint>
                <deliveryPoint>POB 875402</deliveryPoint>
                <city>Tempe</city>
                <postalCode>85287-5402</postalCode>
                <country>USA</country>
            </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(480) 965 2975</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">(480) 965-8087</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>caplter.data@asu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <methods>
            <methodStep>
                <description>
                    <section>
                        <title>sampling design</title>
            <para>
                            Three land cover types were chosen: desert fringe, desert remnant, and
                mesiscaped urban. The desert fringe sites were typical creosote-dominated Sonoran
                desert community found in desert parks on the outskirts of the urbanized areas.
                Other plants in the community include mesquite shrubs, palo verde shrubs, cactus,
                herbaceous perennials, annuals, and brittlebush. The desert remnant sites had the
                same plant community structure of the desert fringe sites, but were located in large
                desert parks (&gt; 5 km2) within the urban matrix. The mesiscaped urban sites
                were dominated by buildings providing shade, nearby impervious surfaces, trees, and
                grass and herbaceous cover. Three sites for each land cover type were chosen as
                replicates, for a total of nine sites. Sites were chosen randomly, but were limited
                by the ability to obtain permits, where vandalism was a low risk, and where a water
                source was available. The three desert fringe sites were located in parks near the
                Phoenix metropolitan area (Usery 46 Park, White Tanks, and Estrella Park). The three
                desert remnant sites were located in desert parks within the Phoenix metropolitan
                area (South Mountain Park, Desert Botanical Garden, and behind the Community
                Services Building, Arizona State University). The three mesiscaped urban sites were
                located within three school yards in the Phoenix metropolitan area (Meyer
                Elementary, Excelencia Elementary, and, Arizona State
                University-Tempe).
            </para>
            <para>
                            Within each site, 60 genetically different potted (5 gallon) plants
                were placed on the ground within a fenced area. The 9-12 month old plants, 43.6 &#177;
                11.2 cm in height (mean &#177; SD), were purchased from a local wholesale nursery and
                placed at the sites in the fall of 2006. There were holes in the bottom of the pots
                that allowed the roots to grow into the ground. Due to the intense sunlight in the
                Sonoran desert, each pot was covered with Reflectix&#174; insulating material, reflecting
                97% of radiant heat. The soil in the pots contained a slow release fertilizer
                (Osmocote&#174;). Water was delivered individually to each plant through polyvinyl
                tubing, controlled by timers. All the plants received water on an optimal schedule
                (4 times/week at 20 minutes 1 time/day) until the water treatments were initiated
                the last week of November 2006. One third of the plants (20) at each site were
                exposed to a low watering schedule (1 day/week), another third to a medium water
                treatment (2 days/week), and the rest (20) remained on the high water treatment (4
                days/week). The plants received about 1.3 L per 20 minutes of watering, with some
                variation depending on local water pressure. In addition, the plants received
                ambient water from precipitation. Drip irrigation and sprinklers were turned off
                where the pots were located in the mesiscaped urban sites for 47 the duration of the
                experiment. The water schedule was increased in early February, to compensate for
                lack of ambient water, but the differentiation between the treatments remained the
                same. Thus, across all land cover types, the plants received the exact same amount
                of water and had nearly similar soil conditions.
            </para>
          </section>
          <section>
                        <title>sampling</title>
            <para>
                            Beginning 14 February 2007 and ending 16 May 2007, all sites were
                visited once per week on the same day, for a total of 14 weeks. Presence or absence
                of flowers was recorded for each plant at each site. No data was collected during
                week 3; however, presence of flowers the previous week was interpolated based on
                whether or not dried flowers were present. More frequent visits and counts of the
                number of flowers on each plant were not done due to time constraints. Data
                collection ended in May because this was when the water treatments ended and when
                the plants began to die because of the summer heat. Pots do not buffer temperature
                to protect plant roots as well as plants in the ground. Time to first flower, length
                of flowering, and percentage of plants flowering were calculated based on the
                presence/absence data collected each week from each plant.
            </para>
            <para>
                            Pan-trapping was used to collect potential pollinators from each site.
                Despite pan-trapping being considered inferior to netting and because of bias and
                underestimating abundance and richness (Cane et al. 2000), it enabled collection
                over a long period of time at many sites and prevented bias in individually netting
                60 plants about 2 feet from each other. It was also used in a previous bee
                pollinator study conducted in the Phoenix metropolitan area (McIntyre and Hostetler
                2001). Pan-trapping, even with one color, is sufficient to capture richness and
                abundance of bees (Stephen and Rao 2005, Toler et al. 48 2005), albeit these studies
                did not address non-bee pollinators. Beginning 23 March 2007 and ending 16 May 2007,
                all sites were visited twice per week on the same days, for a total of 9 weeks. On
                the first visit of each week, three plastic, 8-oz, yellow bowls were set out on the
                ground, in full sun, at semi-random spots at each site. Yellow bowls were chosen
                because brittlebush flowers are yellow. The bowls were filled to the brim with soapy
                tap water (3 ml unscented Ivory soap per gallon of water) and left out for 48 hours.
                The bowls were left out for 48 hours to allow a long enough period of time to
                collect pollinators throughout the day, especially early morning, but not long
                enough to allow all of the water to evaporate. All bowls were set out between 7 a.m.
                and 2 p.m. On the second visit of each week, the contents of each bowl were
                collected into one glass jar per site in the same order as put out and within the
                same time frame. The same day the potential pollinators were collected, the soapy
                water was filtered and the arthropods were stored in 70% ethanol for later
                identification. Data collection ended in May when the phenology observations
                ended.
            </para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <dataTable id="arthropods">
      <entityName>62_arthropods_1.csv</entityName>
      <entityDescription>individual count per species</entityDescription>
      <physical>
                <objectName>62_arthropods_1.csv</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">65536</size>
        <dataFormat>
                    <textFormat>
                        <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
                            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
                    <online>
                        <url>http://data.gios.asu.edu/datasets/cap/62_arthropods_1.csv</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList id="arthropods.attributeList">
        <attribute id="arthropods.sample_id">
          <attributeName>sample_id</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>automatcially generated sequential ID number</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="MySQL">integer</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically
                    generated.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="arthropods.taxon">
          <attributeName>taxon</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>arthropod taxon name</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="MySQL">string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>arthropod taxon name</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="arthropods.site_id">
          <attributeName>site_id</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>site ID as used in sites table</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="MySQL">string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>site ID as used in sites table</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="arthropods.replicate">
          <attributeName>replicate</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>number for replicate</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="MySQL">integer</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>number for replicate</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="arthropods.individual_count">
          <attributeName>individual_count</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>number of individuals</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="MySQL">integer</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
    <dataTable id="flower_phenology">
      <entityName>62_flower_phenology_1.csv</entityName>
      <entityDescription>phonology of brittle bush</entityDescription>
      <physical>
                <objectName>62_flower_phenology_1.csv</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">28672</size>
        <dataFormat>
                    <textFormat>
                        <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
                            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
                    <online>
                        <url>http://data.gios.asu.edu/datasets/cap/62_flower_phenology_1.csv</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList id="flower_phenology.attributeList">
        <attribute id="flower_phenology.phenology_id">
          <attributeName>phenology_id</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>automatically generated sequential ID number</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="MySQL">integer</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically
                    generated.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="flower_phenology.site_id">
          <attributeName>site_id</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>site ID as used in sites table</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="MySQL">string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>site ID as used in sites table</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="flower_phenology.sample_id">
          <attributeName>sample_id</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>field sample ID used by researcher</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="MySQL">string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>field sample ID used by researcher</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="flower_phenology.water">
          <attributeName>water</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>watering conditions</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="MySQL">float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <enumeratedDomain>
                                    <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>1</code>
                    <definition>low</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>2</code>
                    <definition>medium</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>3</code>
                    <definition>high</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="flower_phenology.cage">
          <attributeName>cage</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>cage over plant or not</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="MySQL">float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <enumeratedDomain>
                                    <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>1</code>
                    <definition>no cage</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                                        <code>2</code>
                    <definition>cage</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="flower_phenology.firstflower">
          <attributeName>firstflower</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>weeks to first flower</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="MySQL">float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>nominalWeek</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="flower_phenology.length">
          <attributeName>length</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>weeks of flowering</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="MySQL">float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>nominalWeek</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="flower_phenology.adjfirstflow">
          <attributeName>adjfirstflow</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>number of weeks to first flower adjusted to beginning of treatment.
            Accounts for plants that had to be replaced.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="MySQL">float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
                        <ratio>
                            <unit>
                                <standardUnit>nominalWeek</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
    <dataTable id="sites">
      <entityName>62_sites_1.csv</entityName>
      <entityDescription>site descriptions</entityDescription>
      <physical>
                <objectName>62_sites_1.csv</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">4096</size>
        <dataFormat>
                    <textFormat>
                        <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
                            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
                    <online>
                        <url>http://data.gios.asu.edu/datasets/cap/62_sites_1.csv</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList id="sites.attributeList">
        <attribute id="sites.id">
          <attributeName>id</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>record id</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="MySQL">float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically
                    generated.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="sites.site_id">
          <attributeName>site_id</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>ID for site</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="MySQL">string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>ID for site</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="sites.name">
          <attributeName>name</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>name of site</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="MySQL">string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>name of site</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="sites.type">
          <attributeName>type</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>type of site (desert remnant, desert fringe, mesic
            yard)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="MySQL">string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>type of site (desert remnant, desert fringe, mesic yard)</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
</eml:eml>