<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.175.180944" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Below-Ground Net Primary Production (BNPP): Root Ingrowth Donuts in Chihuahuan Desert Grassland and Creosote Shrubland at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico (2005- )</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Amaris</givenName>
      <surName>Swann</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-8119</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>amswann@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">15021</userId>
  </creator>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Scott</givenName>
      <surName>Collins</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, MSC03 2020, 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>scollins@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">12275</userId>
  </creator>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Amaris</givenName>
      <surName>Swann</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-8119</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>amswann@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">15021</userId>
    <role>data manager</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Stephanie</givenName>
      <surName>Baker</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-8119</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>srbaker@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Megan</givenName>
      <surName>McClung</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico, 167 Castetter Hall, MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>mmcclung@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>John</givenName>
      <surName>Mulhouse</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico, 167 Castetter Hall, MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States of America</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>mulhouse@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">15417</userId>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Stephanie</givenName>
      <surName>Baker</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-8119</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>srbaker@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <role>labcrew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>John</givenName>
      <surName>Mulhouse</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico, 167 Castetter Hall, MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States of America</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>mulhouse@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">15417</userId>
    <role>labcrew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <pubDate>2011</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>In 2005, annually harvested root ingrowth donut structures were co-located with previously established mini-rhizotron tubes established at four sites on McKenzie Flats located on the east side of Sevilleta NWR: 10 replicate structures in both burned and unburned blue and black grama dominated grassland plots at Deep Well, 10 replicates each on nitrogen fertilization plots and respective control plots on McKenzie Flats(20 total), 10 replicates in creosote dominated shrubland at the Five Points Creosote Core site and in 2011, 13 structures were put in the Monsoon site.  Roots and soil are harvested annually in late fall after the growing season, and structures are reestablished in situ for consecutive harvests each year. Each structure allows roots to be harvested at two depths (0-15 and 15-30 cm) to estimate root production, or below ground net primary productivity. In order to compare estimates of root production from two methods, root ingrowth donuts were collocated with mini-rhizotron tubes at all localities except for the burned grassland plot at Deep Well.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>primary production</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>depth</keyword>
    <keyword>field methods</keyword>
    <keyword>cores</keyword>
    <keyword>burning</keyword>
    <keyword>harvesting</keyword>
    <keyword>fertilizer</keyword>
    <keyword>soil</keyword>
    <keyword>grasslands</keyword>
    <keyword>grasses</keyword>
    <keyword>roots</keyword>
    <keyword>vegetation</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>Additional Information on the personnel associated with the Data Collection / Data ProcessingSevilleta Field Crew Employee History Megan McClung, April 2013-present, Stephanie Baker, October      2010-Present, John Mulhouse, August 2009-Present, Amaris Swann, August      25, 2008-January 2013, Maya Kapoor, August 9, 2003-January 21, 2005   and    April 2010-March 2011, Terri Koontz,  February 2000-August 2003   and    August 2006-August 2010, Yang Xia, January 31, 2005-April 2009,   Karen    Wetherill,  February 7, 2000-August 2009, Michell Thomey,   September 3,    2005-August 2008, Jay McLeod, January 2006-August 2006,   Charity Hall,    January 31, 2005-January 3, 2006, Tessa Edelen, August   15, 2004-August    15, 2005, Seth Munson, September 9, 2002-June 2004,   Caleb Hickman,    September 9, 2002-November 15, 2004, Heather  Simpson,  August 2000-August    2002, Chris Roberts, September  2001-August 2002,  Mike Friggens,    1999-September 2001, Shana  Penington, February  2000-August 2000.</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/2585</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Black Butte Mixed Grass site is located just inside the gate and to the south of Black Butte. This site is grassland, characterized by Oryzopsis hymenoides, Sporobolus giganteus, Sporobolus flexuosus, Bouteloua eriopoda, and occasional shrubs, including Gutierrezia sarothrae and Yucca glauca.&#160; Forbs include Senecio douglasii, Baileyi multiradiata, and Sphaeralcea spp. This site contains the fertilizer study plots, which are located less than one mile from the Black Butte gate on the east side of the road to Five Points.Landform: Basalt formation., Vegetation: Grasses include blue grama (Bouteloua gracilis), black grama (B. eriopoda), galleta grass (Pleuraphis jamesii), dropseed (Sporobolus spp.), Indian ricegrass (Oryzopsis hymenoides), and burro grass (Scleropogon brevifolius).  Creosotebush (Larrea tridentata) also occurs frequently. , siteid: 47</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.683</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.683</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.408</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.408</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1666</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1666</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: Deep Well is located on McKenzie Flats and is site of the longest running SEV LTER met station, number 40, which has been active since 1988.&#160; In addition to studies of meteorological variables, core line-intercept vegetation transects and line-intercept transects from the 1995 and 2001 Deep Well fires are sampled here.&#160; The mini-rhizotron study, blue and black grama compositional comparison, blue and black grama patch dynamics investigation, and kangaroo rat population assessement are all ongoing here.&#160; Deep Well Blue/Black Grama Mixed is also the location of the warming and monsoon experiments, as well as portions of the line-intercept and vegetation removal studies.
On August 4, 2009, a lightning-initiated fire began on the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge. By August 5, 2009, the fire had reached the area of Deep Well Blue/Black Grama Mixed.&#160; While portions of this site were burned, the entirety was not.&#160; See individual projects for further information on the effects of the fire.Vegetation: The vegetation of Deep Well Blue/Black Grama Mixed is Chihuahuan Desert Grassland, dominated by black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda) and blue grama (B. gracilis).  Other grasses found at the site include dropseeds (Sporobolus spp.) and threeawns (Aristida spp.).  Shrubs are uncommon but those that occur include Yucca glauca, Ephedra torreyi, and four-wing saltbush (Atriplex canescens). Herbaceous plants include Plantago purshii, Hymenopappus filifolius, and globe mallows (Sphaeralcea spp.).

 , </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1600</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1600</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Five Points area emcompasses both the Five Points Black Grama and Five Points Creosote study sites.&#160; Five Points falls along the transition between the Chihuahuan Desert Scrub and Desert Grassland habitats.&#160; Both core sites are subject to intensive research activities, including NPP measurements, phenology observations, pollinator diversity studies, and ground dwelling arthropod and rodent population assessments.&#160; There are rain-out shelters for drought studies in both the Five Points Black Grama and Five Points Creosote sites.Vegetation: The Five Points Creosote site is characterized as Chihuahuan Desert Scrub, dominated by a creosote overstory, with broom snakeweed, purple pricklypear (Opuntia macrocentra), and soapweed yucca as co-occurring shrubs. The site is also characterized by numerous, dense, grass-dominated patches, reflecting proximity to the Five Points Black Grama Site.  Dominant grasses are black grama, fluffgrass (Dasyochloa pulchellum), burrograss (Scleropogon brevifolia), bushmuhly (Muhlenbergia porteri), and galleta (Pleuraphis jamesii).  Notable forbs include field bahia (Bahia absinthifolia), baby aster (Chaetopappa ericoides), plains hiddenflower (Cryptantha crassisepala), Indian rushpea (Hoffmannseggia glauca), Fendlers bladderpod (Lesquerella fendleri), and globemallows (Sphaeralcea spp.)., siteid: 3</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The fertilizer plots are located less than one mile from the Black Butte gate on the east side of the road to Five Points.Vegetation: Vegetation includes blue grama (Bouteloua gracilis), black grama (B. eriopoda), galleta grass (Pleuraphis jamesii), dropseed (Sporobolus spp.), and burro grass (Scleropogon brevifolius)., History: The site was burned in 2003 during a prescribed fire conducted by the US Fish and Wildlife Service., siteid: 30</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.678</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.678</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.601</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.601</southBoundingCoordinate>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Monsoon site is located within Five Points Black Grama, just to the north of the grassland drought plots.&#160;On August 4, 2009, a lightning-initiated fire began on the Sevilleta  National Wildlife Refuge. The Monsoon site was entirely burned on this date, with all plots subjected to fire of comparable intensity.Vegetation: The Monsoon site is dominated by black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda).  Other prevalent grasses include Sporobolus contractus, S. cryptandrus, S. flexuosus, Muhlenbergia arenicola, and Bouteloua gracilis., siteid: 35</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.41489</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.41489</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.20143</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.20143</southBoundingCoordinate>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>2005-11-01</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2012-11-12</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <maintenance>
    <description>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>23 Jan 2009All data sets (2005-2008) were combined and checked for errors in excel and exported  into Navicat. From the 2007 data, I  converted the dry root mass from grams to milligrams and  changed depth data to be 0-15 and 15-30 cm. QA/QC'd data. I deleted data line from DWB sample 7,  depth 15-30 cm with volume 2600 ml because it was a duplicate. I also changed the depth of DWB  sample 12, depth 15-30 cm with volume 2000 to the depth 0-15 cm because the depth 15-30 cm was  duplicated. -Changed missing data on volume and weight due to plant being dead to  -888. -Changed missing data on volume and weight due to human error to -999. --A. Swann</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </description>
  </maintenance>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
      <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint> 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Experimental Design Annually harvested root ingrowth donut structures are co-located with previously established mini-rhizotron tubes established at four sites on the McKenzie Flats on the east side of Sevilleta NWR: 10 replicate structures in both burned and unburned blue and black grama dominated grassland plots at Deep Well, 10 replicates each on nitrogen fertilization plots and respective control plots on McKenzie Flats (20 total), and 10 replicates in creosote dominated shrubland at the Five Points Creosote Core site. Methods were adapted from Milchunas et al (2005). We use a formidable 10 diameter soil core to create cylindrical holes in the ground to a depth of 30cm without disturbing soil profile at the cylinder walls. The soil core was inserted with a slide hammer and had to be removed each time with a come-along mounted on a steel-pipe tripod. Walls were subsequently lined with plastic cross-stitch craft work canvas (macram mesh) which supports cylinder walls through time but allows roots to pass through. Two pieces of 6 diameter PVC were placed in the center of the larger cylindrical hole, set in place with bags filled with sand that act as ballasts. The two pieces of PVC were beveled on opposite ends to fit together and prevent movement of the donut center. The top cylinder went to a depth of 15 cm and the bottom piece went to a depth of 30 cm, representing 0-15 and 15-30 cm in the soil profile when stacked upon one another. Finally, sifted soil from the location was used to fill the space between the plastic canvas lining the hole wall and the PVC pipe placed in the center. It is this soil which is harvested annually at two depths. A PVC cap was placed on top of the PVC to eliminate water infiltration from rain through the donut center and to keep sunlight from disintegrating the sand bag ballast. All root ingrowth donuts were GPSed. Sample Harvest  Root donuts are harvested annually in November after the growing season. Roots are harvested by first removing the sand bags from the top cylinder and placing a bowl into the center of the cylinder. The top cylinder is then removed. Soil and roots are cut away from the cylinder wall and collected. This harvest procedure is then repeated for the lower half of the donut structure. Soil and roots collected are placed in a separate plastic bag for each depth. Once the soil and roots are harvested, the root ingrowth structure is rebuilt. After harvest, soil and root samples are stored in a chest freezer until they can be processed. Sample Processing The total volume of soil from each sample is measured and recorded.  Soils are filtered through a series of sieves in which to harvest the roots present in the sample. The roots are then repeatedly rinsed  to remove all the soil from the sample, dried at 60 degrees C, and then weighed.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
    <qualityControl>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>Filtered data in Excel then exported it into Navicat using the import wizard.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </qualityControl>
  </methods>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>sev175_rootingrowth_01232013.txt</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data for SEV175</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>sev175_rootingrowth_01232013.txt</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url>http://sev.lternet.edu/sites/default/files/data/sev-175/sev175_rootingrowth_01232013.txt</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2005-11-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2012-11-12</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Date</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Date</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Year data were collected.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Site</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Site</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Site where data were collected.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>C </code>
                  <definition> Five-Points Creosote Core Site</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>DWB </code>
                  <definition> Deep Well Burned</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>DW </code>
                  <definition> Deep Well Unburned</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>F </code>
                  <definition> Fertilizer</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>M </code>
                  <definition> Monsoon</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Sample</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Sample</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Sample number</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Sample number</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Depth</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Depth</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>What depth was the sample taken from.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Volume</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Volume</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Total volume of sample</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>milliliters</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Root_Weight</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Root_Weight</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Dry root mass weight.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>milligram</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Notes</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Notes</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Notes</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Notes</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
    <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
<ns2:unit id="milliliters" />
    </ns2:unitList>
  </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>