<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.201.232463" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Point-Quarter Distance and Dimension Measurements to Calculate Shrub Density and Estimate Shrub ANPP in a Chihuahuan Desert Creosote Shurbland at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico (2007- )</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Douglas I.</givenName>
      <surName>Moore</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Sevilleta LTER, 167 Castetter Hall, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>dmoore@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">9661</userId>
  </creator>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Scott</givenName>
      <surName>Collins</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, MSC03 2020, 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>scollins@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">12275</userId>
  </creator>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Amaris</givenName>
      <surName>Swann</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-8119</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>amswann@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">15021</userId>
    <role>data manager</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Stephanie</givenName>
      <surName>Baker</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-8119</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>srbaker@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Megan</givenName>
      <surName>McClung</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico, 167 Castetter Hall, MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>mmcclung@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>John</givenName>
      <surName>Mulhouse</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico, 167 Castetter Hall, MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States of America</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>mulhouse@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">15417</userId>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <pubDate>2011</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>In an effort to better quantify NPP of Creosotebush in the Five-Points region, it was decided to test the Point-Quarter method against the standard 1-m2 quadrat method that has been in use since 1998. Transects were laid out across the 5 mammal trapping webs as well as across burned and unburned plots of the Mixed Shrub site (MS). Repeated measures of the same bushes are performed seasonally. Whole shrubs of various size classes are collected, sorted, and weighed to develop regressions for biomass.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>primary production</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>measurements</keyword>
    <keyword>net primary productivity</keyword>
    <keyword>annual net primary production</keyword>
    <keyword>temperature</keyword>
    <keyword>seasonality</keyword>
    <keyword>cores</keyword>
    <keyword>transects</keyword>
    <keyword>burning</keyword>
    <keyword>deserts</keyword>
    <keyword>grasses</keyword>
    <keyword>shrubs</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>Additional Information on the personnel associated with the Data Collection / Data Processing In January 2011, the Sevilleta NWR experienced an extreme freeze  with temperatures reaching below -25 degrees Celcius. These low  temperatures negatively impacted the vegetation on the shrubs, resulting  in the inablilty to measure the creosote shrubs during that season.  Measurements were resumed the following spring of 2011.Sevilleta Field Crew Employee History Megan McClung, April 2013-present, Stephanie Baker, October       2010-Present, John Mulhouse, August 2009-Present, Amaris Swann, August       25, 2008-January 2013, Maya Kapoor, August 9, 2003-January 21, 2005    and    April 2010-March 2011, Terri Koontz,  February 2000-August 2003    and    August 2006-August 2010, Yang Xia, January 31, 2005-April  2009,   Karen    Wetherill,  February 7, 2000-August 2009, Michell  Thomey,   September 3,    2005-August 2008, Jay McLeod, January  2006-August 2006,   Charity Hall,    January 31, 2005-January 3, 2006,  Tessa Edelen, August   15, 2004-August    15, 2005, Seth Munson,  September 9, 2002-June 2004,   Caleb Hickman,    September 9,  2002-November 15, 2004, Heather  Simpson,  August 2000-August    2002,  Chris Roberts, September  2001-August 2002,  Mike Friggens,     1999-September 2001, Shana  Penington, February  2000-August 2000.</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/1796</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: Five Points is the area which encompasses the Five Points Black Grama and Five Points Creosote Core study sites and falls along the transition between Chihuahuan Desert Scrub and Desert Grassland habitats. Both sites are subject to intensive research activity, including NPP measurement, phenology observation, pollinator diversity studies, and ground dwelling arthropod and rodent population assessments. There are drought rain-out shelters in both the Black Grama and Creosote sites, as well as the mixed-ecotone, with co-located ET Towers.Vegetation: The Five Points Creosote site is characterized as Chihuahuan Desert Scrub, dominated by a creosotebush overstory with broom snakeweed, purple pricklypear (O. macrocentra) and soapweed yucca as notable shrubs. The site is also characterized by numerous dense grass dominated patches, reflecting proximity to the Five Points Black Grama site and the relatively recent appearance of creosotebush. Dominant grasses are black grama, fluffgrass (Dasyochloa pulchellum), burrograss (Scleropogon brevifolia), bush muhly (M. porteri), and galleta (Pleuraphis jamesii). Notable forb species include field bahia (Bahia absinthifolia), baby aster (Chaetopappa ericoides), plains hiddenflower (Cryptantha crassisepala), Indian rushpea (Hoffmannseggia glauca), Fendlers bladderpod (Lesquerella fendleri), and globemallow (Sphaeralcea spp.).  Five Points Black Grama habitat is ecotonal in nature, bordering Chihuahuan Desert Scrub at its southern extent and Plains-Mesa Grassland at its northern, more mesic boundary.  There is also a significant presence of shrubs, particularly broom snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae), along with less abundant fourwing saltbush (Atriplex canescens), Mormon tea (Ephedra torreyana), winterfat (Krascheninnikovia lanata), tree cholla (Opuntia imbricata), club cholla (O. clavata), desert pricklypear (O. phaeacantha), soapweed yucca (Yucca glauca), and what are presumed to be encroaching, yet sparsely distributed, creosotebush (Larrea tridentata).  Characteristically, the dominant grass is black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda). Spike, sand, and mesa dropseed grasses (Sporobolus contractus, S. cryptandrus, S. flexuosus) and sand muhly (Muhlenbergia arenicola) could be considered co-dominant throughout, along with blue grama (B. gracilis) in a more mesic, shallow swale on the site.  Notable forb species include trailing four o&#8217;clock (Allionia incarnata), horn loco milkvetch (Astragalus missouriensis), sawtooth spurge (Chamaesyce serrula), plains hiddenflower (Cryptantha crassisepala), blunt tansymustard (Descarania obtusa), wooly plaintain (Plantago patagonica), globemallow (Sphaeralcea wrightii), and mouse ear (Tidestromia lanuginosa)., siteid: 2</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>106.717</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>106.717</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3381</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3381</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Five Points area emcompasses both the Five Points Black Grama and Five Points Creosote study sites.&#160; Five Points falls along the transition between the Chihuahuan Desert Scrub and Desert Grassland habitats.&#160; Both core sites are subject to intensive research activities, including NPP measurements, phenology observations, pollinator diversity studies, and ground dwelling arthropod and rodent population assessments.&#160; There are rain-out shelters for drought studies in both the Five Points Black Grama and Five Points Creosote sites.Vegetation: The Five Points Creosote site is characterized as Chihuahuan Desert Scrub, dominated by a creosote overstory, with broom snakeweed, purple pricklypear (Opuntia macrocentra), and soapweed yucca as co-occurring shrubs. The site is also characterized by numerous, dense, grass-dominated patches, reflecting proximity to the Five Points Black Grama Site.  Dominant grasses are black grama, fluffgrass (Dasyochloa pulchellum), burrograss (Scleropogon brevifolia), bushmuhly (Muhlenbergia porteri), and galleta (Pleuraphis jamesii).  Notable forbs include field bahia (Bahia absinthifolia), baby aster (Chaetopappa ericoides), plains hiddenflower (Cryptantha crassisepala), Indian rushpea (Hoffmannseggia glauca), Fendlers bladderpod (Lesquerella fendleri), and globemallows (Sphaeralcea spp.)., siteid: 3</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The mixed shrub (MS) location consists of burned and unburned areas.&#160; Both the mixed shrub burned (MSB) and mixed shrub unburned (MSU) areas are on the north side of the road running southeast from Five Points.Vegetation: This area is dominated by creosotebush (Larrea tridenta) but also maintains a relatively dense understory of black grama in comparison to true shrub land., History: The northwest half of the site was burned in June 2003. The southeast half was used as the control. Plots were established in spring 2004., siteid: 33</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.696</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.696</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.31426</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.31426</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1640</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1640</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>2007-02-20</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2012-05-29</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <purpose>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>Data was collected initially to determine density and dimensions of creosote bush in the Five points area on core rodent webs and on burned and unburned plots following the 2003 prescribed burn.  It was decided to expand the project by continuing measurements through time to quantify the change in shrub size and with simultaneous harvest of shrubs to measure NPP.</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </purpose>
  <maintenance>
    <description>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>July 2011- All new data were combined and QA/QC. No shrub measurements were taken in February of 2011 due to the fact that there was a shrub die off caused by extremely low temperatures on the refuge (-20F).--A. SwannFebruary 2009-All new data were combined and QA/QC. On web 4 at the creosote site, shrub 124  was measured twice because it was unknown about if it was one or two bushes and what had been  measured in the past. It was identified that sometimes in the past two bushes instead of one was  measured. Made note of this to reduce the chance of this happening in the future.  At the mixed  shrub unburned, shrub 114 and 132 are the same shrub.  --A. Swann January 2009 -All data  from 2007 and 2008 were combined. Changed the order of variables on datasets to match metadata  variable order. Went through the raw data and changed blank distances or ones with -99.00 to  -888.00 to denote missing data. Changed missing data on height and weight due to plant being dead  to -888. Changed missing data on height and weight due to human error to -999. -Imported excel  raw data into Navicat using the wizard. --A. Swann</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </description>
  </maintenance>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
      <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint> 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Experimental Design The point-quarter technique is used to quantify the density of the shrubs at both the FivePoints Creosote and the Mixed Shrub (MS) sites. At the rodent webs two, 100 m transects are laid out across the diameter of each web.  These transects were laid out using the existing trap locating rebar at 10 m intervals.  The rebar used are those on the spoke running from 60 to 50 and then from 122 to 132 rebars at 5 m intervals. The stake at the center of the web is not used. This results in 20 points across each web or 80 shrubs per web. At the mixed shrub site a different arrangement was used.  Every other rebar was used along every other line as a measuring point. The rebars were also staggered by 1 rebar from line to line. Ultimately there were 12 rebars used in each plot for a total of 48 shrubs per plot.Shrub Measurements In the initial sampling the shrub nearest the rebar in each quadrant was identified and the distance from the rebar to the rooting point of that shrub was measured.  The height of the shrub was measured as well as the diameter of the crown at its widest point and also a diameter perpendicular to this first diameter. Repeated measures of the same bushes are performed seasonally.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
    <qualityControl>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>Data were scanned by eye to catch mistakes. Data were then filtered in excel to determine if all parameters were met.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </qualityControl>
  </methods>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>sev201_pointquarter_11122013.txt</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data for SEV201.</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>sev201_pointquarter_11122013.txt</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url>http://sev.lternet.edu/sites/default/files/data/sev-201/sev201_pointquarter_11122013.txt</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2007-02-22</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2013-11-06</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>date</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>date</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The date on which data or a sample was collected.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>MM/DD/YY</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>year</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>year</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The year in which data was collected.  </attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>season</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>season</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The season in which data was collected.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1 </code>
                  <definition> winter</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>2 </code>
                  <definition> spring</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3 </code>
                  <definition> fall</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>site</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>site</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The site at which data was collected.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>C </code>
                  <definition> Creosote site</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>MS </code>
                  <definition> Mixed shrub site</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>CG </code>
                  <definition> Creosote grid site</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>treatment</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>treatment</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The treatment applied to a site.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>B </code>
                  <definition> burned</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>C </code>
                  <definition> control (unburned)</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>web</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>web</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The number of the web being sampled, which can range from 1-5 depending on site and project.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The number of the web being sampled, which can range from 1-5 depending on site and project.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>rebar</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>rebar</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The number of the rebar from which a measurement was taken.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The number of the rebar from which a measurement was taken.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>quadrant</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>quadrant</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The compass direction of the quadrant in which a shrub was measured.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>NW </code>
                  <definition> Northwest quadrant</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>NE </code>
                  <definition> Northeast quadrant</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>SE </code>
                  <definition> Southeast quadrant</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>SW </code>
                  <definition> Southwest quadrant</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>distance</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>distance</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The distance from rebar to the center of a shrub.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>meters</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>tag</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>tag</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The number of a shrub as designated by a permanent tag.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The number of a shrub as designated by a permanent tag.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>new_tag</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>new_tag</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The number of a shrub as designated by a second tag, affixed after the first.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The number of a shrub as designated by a second tag, affixed after the first.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>height</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>height</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The height from the ground to the tallest point on a shrub.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>centimeters</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.5</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">1.6</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">76</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>width_1</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>width_1</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The diameter of a shrub at the widest point.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>centimeters</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>width_2</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>width_2</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The diameter of a shrub perpendicular to width_1.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>centimeters</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>comments</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>comments</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>A special statement related to an observation.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>na </code>
                  <definition> not applicable</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
    <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
<ns2:unit abbreviation="" id="meters" name="meters" unitType=""><ns2:description /></ns2:unit>

<ns2:unit id="centimeters" />
    </ns2:unitList>
  </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>