<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-jrn.20050720.9887" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=JRN, o=lter, dc=ecoinformatics, dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Transect Soil Water Potential - 1988</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>John</givenName>
      <surName>Anderson</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>
	Jornada LTER

	New Mexico State University

	P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>janderso@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <metadataProvider>
    <organizationName>The Jornada</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>2995 Knox Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-4842</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <onlineUrl>http://jornada.nmsu.edu</onlineUrl>
  </metadataProvider>
  <pubDate>1988</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para> Soil water potential recorded on data sheets for
 psychrometers along treatment and control transects every 5
 stations at 5cm, 15cm and 30cm depths. Soil temperatures at these
 depths and calibration slope and intercept for each psychrometer
 are included in order to convert microvolt readings to -bar
 readings.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>completed</keyword>
    <keyword>inorganic nutrients</keyword>
    <keyword>signature</keyword>
    <keyword>soil</keyword>
    <keyword>soil moisture</keyword>
    <keyword>soil temperature</keyword>
    <keyword>soil water potential</keyword>
    <keyword>transects</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Jornada Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout> In the spring of 1982, as part of the establishment of the Jornada
 Long-Term Ecological Research site in southern New Mexico, a 135 ha
 portion of a 1500 ha, internally drained, watershed was exclosed
 from grazing by domestic livestock. Prior to exclosure the
 watershed, as well as the rest of the Jornada basin, had been
 moderately to heavily grazed for the past 100 years. Concurrent
 with grazing, the vegetation had undergone a dramatic change from
 desert grassland, with an almost continuous cover of C4 perennial
 grasses, to isolated patches of the original grassland in a
 mosaic with desert shrub dominated plant communities (Buffington
 and Herbel, 1965).

 The exclosure lies along a northeast facing piedmont slope at the
 base of a steep isolated mountain peak, and covers a variety of
 component landforms from the foot of the mountain to the basin
 floor. The northeast side of the exclosure is immediately upslope
 of the College Playa located near the NMSU College Ranch.

 Three parallel transects (2.7 km in length) run from the middle of
 the College Playa up into the foot of Mt. Summerford. The Control
 transect is to the west, the Treatment transect on the east side of
 the Control transect, and the Alternate Control to the east of the
 Treatment transect. Each transect is 30 meters wide with a 45
 meter buffer zone between each transect. The Treatment transect
 was treated annually until 1987 with NHNO3 in a concentration equal
 to 10g N/m2. The station markers at 30 meter intervals along each
 transect.</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>Objectives:
The Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System (JIMS) provides protocol and services for data collection, verification, organization, archives, and distribution in accordance with recommendations and guidelines developed by the LTER Information Managers Committee (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html).

Disclaimer:
While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is". The Jornada Basin LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of data sets.

Quality Assurance Policy:
Data managers interact with researchers during the entire scientific process--from the initial planning of sampling designs and field data collection to archiving and distribution of data. The goal of data management is to build and maintain an archive of Jornada Basin LTER data files that are fully documented, error free, and organized in useful ways. Our protocol for data collection and processing seeks maximum interaction between researchers and data management personnel to avoid confusion and potential loss of data or problems with integrity of data; e.g., identification of historical site treatments that may impact a proposed study or incomplete data set variable descriptions. Site and Data Manager involvement begins during the Project Design phase with the completion of the Jornada Notification of Research form by the researcher prior to the start of work; this alerts both Site and Data Manager to the new study and potential LTER data sets. Upon initiation of a new study, the researcher completes Project Documentation that provides the second level of "metadata" documentation.
In the Data Collection phase, the data manager helps researchers design field and laboratory data sheets that facilitate data entry and analysis. Prior to JIMS data entry the investigator completes Data Set Documentation to provide the metadata that fully describe the data set. Both Project and Data set documentation are provided with the data set when it is requested or obtained from our Web site. JIMS data entry programs error-check and verify data as they are entered. Computer files are subjected to further verification by graphing and/or error-checking programs, and/or examination by field investigators. Final quality assurance of the data rests with the investigator who submits data for inclusion in the Data Management System. Direct communication with the Site Manager, or through a collaborating JRN P.I., is used to encourage the timely submission of documentation and of data by researchers.

Error-checked data files are stored with associated documentation files on the file server. Archived data files are maintained in ASCII format on 30-yr magneto-optical (MO) disks, portable hard drives, CD-R media, and DVD media to guard against loss of data access that can result from changing technology. This may also include proprietary binary format files to facilitate recovery of working versions. Image data are archived on 8mm tape. Routine tape data backups of the file server are done daily, weekly, and monthly. One set of off-site copies are maintained elsewhere on the NMSU campus of routine backup tapes, MO disks, CD disks, and DVD disks with a second set of MO, CD and DVD disks maintained off-campus in case of a catastrophe on campus. The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data manag ement staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data management staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

Policy on Submission of data:
Data submission into JIMS is expected from LTER researchers, LTER collaborators, and their graduate students where data and information is derived from publicly funded research in the U.S. LTER Network, totally or partially from LTER funds from NSF, Institutional Cost-Share, or Partner Agency or Institution where a formal memorandum of understanding with LTER has been established. Other Jornada Basin researchers are encouraged to submit their documented data for inclusion within JIMS to provide them with an archived backup, ensure its longevity, and provide online access to encourage synthesis efforts. Minimally, for non-LTER associated researchers, we request that publications be provided of research conducted on the Jornada Basin.
Initial documentation for a data set must be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager within 90 days of initiation of data collection. Documentation forms are available at http://jornada-www.nmsu.edu/site/dm/readme.php . These consist of Project Abstract and Data Set and Attribute documentation forms, which include objectives of the study, methods, as well as format and content of the data. All data collected during a calendar year should be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager prior to July first of the following year. First time data submissions must be submitted with updated standard Jornada Basin LTER forms previously submitted.

Data Access Policy:
Data will be made publicly available no later than 2 years after submission of the data unless an earlier date is specified by the principal investigator. In the event that an extension of the 2 year period is necessary, the principal investigator may petition the Jornada Basin LTER Executive Committee for a longer protected period. Graduate student research data will be available online after degree completion and they have the opportunity to publish their research.

Policies for re-use, distribution, or the production of derivatives:
Data re-use, distribution and production of derivative products are governed by the LTER Network data policies (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html) in the spirit of having the potential to increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines. Appropriate citation, acknowledgement, notification and collaboration are outlined and recommended. No commercial redistribution of data and derived products are allowed.

Data Acknowledgment Policy:
Please send notification to the Information Manager and Responsible Investigator(s) of the data sets you are downloading and your intended use.
Individuals and institutions utilizing data from the Jornada Basin LTER database are requested to place the following acknowledgment in any publication in which these data are mentioned:
Data sets were provided by the Jornada Basin Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) project. Funding for these data was provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210).

Please send 1 copy of any publication that cites Jornada Basin LTER data to:
     John P. Anderson
     Jornada Experimental Range
     P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
     New Mexico State University
     Las Cruces, NM 88003-0003</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <coverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>1988-01-06</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>1988-12-29</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <maintenance>
    <description>
      <para>
        <literalLayout> mm/dd/yyyy - Date of Comment
 Int - Initials of person making Comment
 KJL = Kevin J. La Fleur
 JPA = John P. Anderson
 MAB = Michelle A. Buonopane
 KR = Ken Ramsey

 Changes/Updates - List any changes made to document

 mm/dd/yyyy Int Changes/Updates
 ---------- --- -----------------------------------------------
 12/04/2002 MAB Completed form.
 08/09/2003 JPA Updated keywords.
 07/21/2005 KR Added Dataset and Project IDs to top of form.
 07/27/2005 KR Changed format of Responsible Investigator and
 Researchers sections.
 Changed format of Associated Files section.
 08/22/2005 KR Changed format of Attributes Measured section.
 Incorporated Missing Values section into
 Attributes Measured section.
 11/21/2005 JPA Changed section 5 commence date to match dataset.
 11/19/2011 JPA Changed responsible investigator for contact person
 to John Anderson per Deb Peters</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </description>
  </maintenance>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Data</givenName>
      <surName>Manager</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>PO Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>The Jornada</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Field data sheets</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout> Readings from Wescor screen-cage soil psychrometers taken every 2
 weeks using WESCOR HR-33T microvoltmeter. Half of control and
 matching half of treatment transects read on one day. Other half of
 control and treatment readings done the following day.

 PROCEDURE FOR CLEANING AND CALIBRATING SCREEN-CAGE SOIL
 PSYCHROMETERS

 PSYCHROMETER CLEANING PROCEDURE

 1. Use wooden dowel to remove screen-cage by slipping it over the
 end of the screen-cage on psychrometer. Grasp near base of dowel
 with plyers and hold firmly to psychrometer boot while pulling
 the screen-cage straight out from the boot. Use great care while
 removing the screen-cage to avoid damage to the very fragile
 junction wires mounted on the end of the boot within the screen-
 cage. Inspect junction wires to insure that they are not broken.
 If broken, save psychrometer for possible repair.

 2. Using 95% ethanol in a water bottle, wash the junction wires
 and the boot thoroughly.

 3. Using deionized water in a water bottle, rinse the junction
 wires and the boot thoroughly.

 4. Using compressed air that has been filtered with cotton to
 remove possible oil droplets added from air supply, thoroughly
 dry junction wires and boot. Pay special attention to the groove
 which the screen-cage slips down into since water left there will
 be forced up under the screen-cage when it is replaced. (The
 screen-cage consists of 2 layers of wire mesh. The inner mesh is
 impermeable to liquid water and thus will trap water which will
 later affect calibration values.) When dry, carefully set aside
 so that there is no chance that the junction wires will be
 damaged while the screen-cage is being cleaned.

 5. To wash the screen-cage, hold with forceps and swish
 vigorously and thoroughly in boiling deionized water. While
 still holding with forceps, use filtered compressed air to
 thoroughly dry inside and out. Set screen-cage back in wooden
 dowel without touching it (to avoid contamination of screen-cage
 with salts from hands). Carefully replace screen-cage on
 psychrometer. If there are any loose or dangling wires on the
 screen-cage or caught in the boot-groove, carefully cut these off
 (if attached) or pull free (if in boot-groove).

 6. Inspect psychrometer cable for punctures. If present, use
 electrical tape and tightly wrap punctures to prevent water
 damage when immersed in water bath.

 7. Screen-cage psychrometer is now clean and care should be
 taken to insure that it remains so.

 8. Record psychrometers in data book labeled "Soil Psychrometers"
 in numerical order by I.D. # along with "pi-v" value and
 calibration values as these are acquired.

 CALIBRATION PROCEDURE

 A. Calibrating Psychrometers

 1. Prepare the following calibration solutions:

 0.05m NaCl = 2.923g NaCl in exactly 1L deionized water
 0.5m NaCl = 29.227g NaCl in exactly 1L deionzied water
 *1.0m NaCl = 58.454g NaCl in exactly 1L deionzied water
 1.5m NaCl = 87.681g NaCl in exactly 1L deionzied water
 *Need only be used if unable to calibrate using 1.5m NaCl.

 2. Construct calibration chambers as follows:
 a. Use clean 13x100 test tubes (1 per psychrometer). Store
 upside-down in test tube rack.
 b. Insert 1 rolled filter paper ( 9cm diameter) as far as
 possible into test tube . (Rolling the filter paper around
 a pencil and then sliding it off works well and is the
 right size for the test tube.)
 c. Add 2ml of 0.05m NaCl to each test tube making sure to wet
 filter paper as it is added.
 d. Place a pre-drilled and cut #000 stopper around the cable
 of each psychrometer at a distance from the screen-cage end
 such that the end of the psychrometer will be 1.5-2 inches
 from the bottom of the test tube when inserted. It
 should not be immersed in calibration solution at bottom of
 test tube at any time. Carefully work the stopper as far
 into the test tube as possible so there is a complete seal
 around the psychrometer cable. It may be necessary to add
 a small quantity of high vaccuum grease around the cable to
 insure a tight seal.
 e. Place test tube rack with test tube calibration chambers
 into a water bath that has been preheated to 25 degrees C.
 (Preheat with water bath covered by aluminum foil to prevent
 evaporation and to help maintain temperature.) Leave the
 minimum length extended out of water bath that is
 required to reach microvoltmeter (HR33T). Keep the rest of
 the cable in water bath and seal waterbath with aluminum
 foil. It is very important that psychrometers be
 maintained at constant temperature as an improper cover
 over the water bath will encourage temperature fluctuation
 which will result in faulty calibration.
 f. Allow psychrometers to stabilize for approximately 3
 hours before proceeding with calibration procedure given
 below.

 3. The following applies to use of HR33T Dew Point Microvoltmeter
 in calibrating psychrometers:
 a. Set range switch to anticipated range.
 b. Set function switch to SHORT.
 c. Make sure toggle switch is in uV mode.
 d. Turn instrument on.
 e. Plug psychrometer into instrument (match the notch in
 plug to notch in socket).
 f. Turn function switch to READ.
 g. Get temperature reading by switching toggle switch to
 C. Check range and use correct scale on meter
 (top 0 to 10 scale for microvolt readings of 0-10 and
 readings of 30-100, bottom 0 to 3 scale for microvolt
 readings of 0-30 and 100-300). Wait for temperature to
 stabilize before taking a reading.
 h. Switch back to uV mode.
 i. Calibrate instrument according to the individual
 psychrometer's cooling coefficent, "pi-v". (# found on
 tag on psychrometer lead or on data sheet) by:
 (1) Adjustment must be made to the cooling coefficent
 (pi-v) according to the difference bewteen the
 soil temperature and 25 degrees C. The correction
 factor, (T - 25degrees C) X 0.7, must be added to
 the factory specified "pi-v" found on the
 psychrometer's lead in order to obtain the correct
 cooling coefficient to be used in dewpoint
 measurements. (where T = soil temperature)
 (2) Press in and hold down "pi-v" button while turning
 "pi-v" set knob to the adjusted cooling
 coefficient that was just calculated. ADJUST
 USING TOP SCALE.
 (3) If "pi-v" is not known, see NOTE to determine its
 value.
 j. Set the zero by turning the zero offset knob until the
 meter needle is exactly on zero. Use coarse and fine
 adjustment knobs as needed. The instrument is now ready to
 take dew point readings.
 * k. Turn fuction switch to COOL for 20 seconds for
 0.05m NaCl calibration solution.
 l. Turn function switch to D.P. (dew point). Needle
 will drop. Take reading when needle stops. If needle
 stops briefly then begins to drift slowly, take reading
 at first stop. Be sure to read on correct scale and range.
 This value is the dew point in uV and should be
 recorded in SOIL PSYCHROMETERS data book.
 m. Turn function switch to SHORT before unplugging
 psychrometer.
 n. To retake a reading, switch function knob to HEAT for
 5 to 10 seconds, turn function switch to SHORT, then
 repeat steps f - m after waiting 5 minutes.
 o. When reading a number of psychrometers at the same time,
 it is not necessary to turn the machine off between
 readings, but the function knob must be switched to
 SHORT before plugging or unplugging psychrometer.

 NOTE: Determine "pi-v" as follows:
 (1) Allow psychrometer to equilibrate in a dry
 calibration chamber in water bath at 25C.
 (2) With the FUNCTION switch in the READ position,
 push "pi-v" button and adjust top scale to about 70
 using "pi-v" set knob.
 (2) With the RANGE switch set to 30 uvolts, adjust
 the ZERO OFFSET control to bring the meter reading to
 zero. It is necessary to accurately zero the meter
 before determining "pi-v".
 (3) Switch the FUNCTION switch to COOL for a few
 seconds, then switch to DEW POINT. Depending upon the
 position of the "pi-v" SET knob, the meter will tend to
 (a) fall back toward zero, (b)hold steady, or (3)climb
 upscale. Rotate "pi-v" SET until the meter holds
 relatively steady and the reading is between 15 and 30
 on the bottom scale. (If the needle is rising or
 pegged upscale, rotate the control clockwise.)
 (4) When the "pi-v" button is depressed, the meter
 will give a reading proportional to the position of the
 "pi-v" SET control. The numerical value of the reading
 on the 100 uvolt scale is the cooling coefficient,
 "pi-v", of the psychrometer being used.

 * Cooling time is dependent on soil moisture. Cooling times
 required will vary from 5 seconds or less for very wet
 soils to 30 seconds or more for dry soils. Once the
 necessary cooling time has been determined for a given
 water potential range, this time should be used for all
 measurements within that range, including calibration
 measurements. To determine cooling time: The time it
 takes during COOL cycle for needle to stop (or almost
 stop) when calibrating the first couple of
 psychrometers is the time to use for the rest of the
 psychrometers for that particular calibration
 solution.
 If during COOL, needle rises higher than the adjusted
 cooling coefficient, "pi-v", the calibration solution
 is "too dry" to read. This is most likely to happen
 with the 1.5m NaCl solution. If it does, you must
 recalibrate that psychrometer using 1.0m NaCl solution.

 4. Make sure HR33T microvoltmeter is switched OFF when finished
 with your readings.

 5. You have now finished calibrating your psychrometers with the
 first of 3 calibration solutions. You must now --- re-clean the
 psychrometers as per the Cleaning Procedure and repeat steps 2
 through 4 of the Calibration Procedure --- for calibration
 solutions 0.5m NaCl and 1.5m NaCl. Only for those psychrometers
 that have a "pi-v" too low to read using 1.5m NaCl will you have
 to use the calibration solution of 1.0m NaCl.

 6. PROCEDURE AT END OF EACH CALIBRATION
 You need to carefully remove stoppers from test tubes without
 pulling on psychrometer cable. Clean all psychrometers as per
 procedure. Rinse stoppers well. They must be dry before
 reusing. Store in plastic bag until ready to use. Pull used
 filters out of test tubes with forceps and return test tubes to
 stockroom for cleaning. Get clean 13x100 test tubes from
 stockroom and rinse these thoroughly with deionized water. (They
 may be "clean" but they've been sitting in the open collecting
 dust.) You can either (1)dry these upside down in a test tube
 rack or, (2)if you will need them soon, shake excess water out of
 them, place them upright in test tube rack, cover them completely
 with paper towels to keep out air-borne contaminants, and set
 them in a drying oven for a couple of hours.

 B. Performing Linear Regression

 1. You must verify that the values recorded for the calibration
 solutions confirm a "good" psychrometer. Also, slope and y-
 intercept must be calculated for later conversion of field data.

 2. Using the HP11C calculator, calculate m(slope), b(y-intercept),
 and r(correlation coefficient) for each psychrometer:

 a. Clear memory by pushing "f" "E"
 b. Enter data pairs: uV value "ENTER"
 *calibration soln in bars " "
 Repeat for each calibration solution used, for each
 psychrometer.
 d. Push "f" "y,r" "x y" and record the resulting r in data book.

 * 0.05m NaCl = 2.34 bars
 0.5m NaCl = 22.81 bars
 1.0m NaCl = 46.40 bars
 1.5m NaCl = 71.34 bars

 Value should be no less than 0.9995. If it is less,
 evaluate uV readings for that psychrometer and redo any or
 all of calibration readings as necessary. If r remains low,
 this psychrometer must be considered "bad". Save it for
 possible repair.
 e. Push "f" "L.R." and record resulting y-intercept in
 SOIL PSYCHROMETERS data book.
 f. Push "x y" and record resulting slope in SOIL
 PSYCHROMETERS data book.

 CONVERSION OF MICROVOLTS TO -BARS:
 BARS = (DEWPOINT - INTERCEPT) DIVIDED BY SLOPE.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
    <qualityControl>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout> Responsible investigator(s):
 ----------------------------
 Walter G. Whitford, Feb1986-Dec1988;
 John P. Anderson, Feb1986-Dec1988
 ************************************
 THEORY NOTE: The cooling coefficient (pi-v) determines the
 ultimate limit of the thermocouple's range in measuring water
 potential since it represents the maximum temperature depression
 that can be reached by the junction through Peltier cooling. If the
 dew point is below this temperature, no measurement can be made in
 the dew point mode since it will not be possible to condense water
 from the sample onto the junction. Thus, the lowest water potential
 (in bars) that can be measured by the junction is equal to the pi-v
 value divided by -0.75uvolts per bar.
 NOTE: DP (dewpoint) readings that are negative indicate that soil
 was too dry to read (beyond the thermocouple's range). Calculated
 soil water potential values are based on the individual
 psychrometer sensitivity as determined from its pi-v value (cooling
 coefficient). Values for these indicate soil water potentials of
 at least the given value but are very likely much drier.
 NOTE: Positive bar values result since regression wasn't forced
 through 0. Microvolt readings in field were zero or close to it
 which indicate very wet soil. The higher the microvolt reading the
 drier the soil.

 The 1988 data set has separate documentation due to different data
 formatting.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </qualityControl>
  </methods>
  <project>
    <title>Jornada LTER</title>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
        <givenName>Debra</givenName>
        <surName>Peters</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-2777</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">575-646-5889</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>debpeter@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Lead Principal Investigator</role>
    </personnel>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Data</givenName>
        <surName>Manager</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Information Manager</role>
    </personnel>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>The Jornada Basin Long Term Ecological Research program, in collaboration with 
                         the USDA ARS Jornada Experimental Range, studies the causes and consequences of 
                         desertification: the broad scale expansion of woody plants into grasslands that 
                         results in more "desert like" conditions. We are interested in spatial and 
                         temporal variation in desertification dynamics, and how historic legacies, the 
                         geomorphic template, transport vectors (wind, water, animals), and environmental 
                         drivers (climate, land use, disturbance) interact with the patch structure of the 
                         vegetation to determine past, present, and future ecosystem dynamics across 
                         scales.
                        
                         Our study site is located in the northern Chihuahuan Desert, approximately 25 km 
                         northeast of Las Cruces, New Mexico, USA (+32.5 N, -106.8 W, elevation 1188 m). 
                         Annual precipitation is 24 cm and maximum temperatures average 13 C in January 
                         and 36 C in June. Our study site includes the 78,000 ha Jornada Experimental 
                         Range operated by the USDA Agricultural Research Service, and the 22,000 ha 
                         Chihuahuan Desert Rangeland Research Center (CDRRC) operated by New Mexico State 
                         University. The Jornada Basin LTER project was established in 1982, and is 
                         administered by New Mexico State University. This site is a member of the LTER 
                         Network, one of  more than 25 long term sites funded by the U.S. National Science 
                         Foundation.</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <funding>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210)</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </funding>
  </project>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>swp88.dat</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data file information for the following Jornada data set: Transect Soil Water Potential - 1988</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>swp88.dat</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <numHeaderLines>29</numHeaderLines>
          <numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
          <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>Tab-delimited</fieldDelimiter>
            <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url function="download">http://jornada-data.nmsu.edu/sites/jornada-data.nmsu.edu/files/data_files/swp88.dat</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1988-01-06</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>1988-12-29</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>MMDDYY</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_soil_water_potential_1988_mmddyy</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Date (mmddyy)</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>mmddyy</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>STA</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_soil_water_potential_1988_sta</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Station and treatment
tss, where t  = Treatment (C = Control, T = Fertilized) and
                                       ss = Station Number (1-89)</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Station and treatment
tss, where t  = Treatment (C = Control, T = Fertilized) and
                                       ss = Station Number (1-89)</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>DEPTH</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_soil_water_potential_1988_depth</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil Depth</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>cm</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>TEMP</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_soil_water_potential_1988_temp</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Temperature</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>Celsius</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> bad or missing values resulting from equipment problems to  the ground being frozen</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Bar5</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_soil_water_potential_1988_bar5</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil Water Potential</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>-MPa</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> bad or missing values resulting from equipment problems to the ground being frozen</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>DRY</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_soil_water_potential_1988_dry</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Error Code</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>0 </code>
                  <definition> calulations performed normally as indicated by BARS above  </definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1 </code>
                  <definition> soil was too dry for the sensitivity of the psychrometer. However, based on the soil temperature and Pi-V (cooling coefficient), a value for soil water potential was obtained reflecting the max possible soil water potential. It is highly probable though that the soil was drier that indicated.</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
    <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
<ns2:unit id="cm" />
<ns2:unit id="Celsius" />
<ns2:unit id="-MPa" />
    </ns2:unitList>
  </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>