<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-cdr." scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd"><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=CDR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataset scope="document"><alternateIdentifier>knb-lter-cdr.hoe133.1</alternateIdentifier><shortName>hoe133</shortName><title>Soil moisture: Effect of Burning Patterns on Vegetation in the Fish Lake Burn Compartments</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Peter</givenName><surName>Reich</surName></individualName></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><organizationName>Cedar Creek LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Cedar Creek Ecosystem Science Reserve</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>100 Ecology Building</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>1987 Upper Buford Circle</deliveryPoint><city>Saint Paul</city><administrativeArea>MN</administrativeArea><postalCode>55108</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">612-625-5740</phone><phone phonetype="fax">612-624-6777</phone><electronicMailAddress>webmaster@cedarcreek.umn.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.cedarcreek.umn.edu/</onlineUrl></metadataProvider><pubDate>2012-06-14</pubDate><abstract><para>This study examines the effects of long-term prescribed burning treatments on vegetation structure and composition, productivity, and nutrient cycling in upland oak savanna and woodland vegetation. The basis for the study is an ongoing, experimental prescribed burning program begun in 1964 at Cedar Creek, and a similar program operating since 1962 on the adjacent Helen Allison Savanna property (owned by The Nature Conservancy). These prescribed burning programs are designed to subject upland oak communities (and some old fields) to different burn frequencies and patterns of burning, with the ultimate objectives of 1) restoring and maintaining the historically important savanna and open woodland vegetation, and 2) providing information about the effects of different burning patterns on vegetation structure and composition. This study addresses the latter of these two purposes and expands on it by also investigating possible influences of fire on resource availability (nutrients, water, and light) and net primary productivity. This study represents a continuation and expansion of experiments 015 and 094.</para></abstract><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage id="geoReferenceID" scope="document"><geographicDescription>The Cedar Creek Ecosystem Science Reserve is located in Anoka and Isanti counties, approximately 30 miles north of Saint Paul, MN. CCNHA lies at the boundary between prairie and forest. It is a mosaic of uplands dominated by oak savanna, prairie, hardwood forest, pine forests,and abandoned agricultural fields and of lowlands comprised of ash and cedar swamps, acid bogs, marshes, and sedge meadows. Large tracts of the pre-agricultural ecosystems of the region are preserved within its boundaries, as is a successional chronosequence of more than 80 old fields of known history.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-93.22445</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-93.16289</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>45.44138</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>45.384865</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1999</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2002</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Dan</givenName><surName>Bahauddin</surName></individualName><organizationName>Cedar Creek Ecosystem Science Reserve</organizationName><positionName>Information Manager</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Ecology Evolution and Behaviour Dept. University Of Minnesota</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>100 Ecology Building</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>1987 Upper Buford Circle</deliveryPoint><city>Saint Paul</city><administrativeArea>MN</administrativeArea><postalCode>55108</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">612-625-5740</phone><phone phonetype="fax">612-624-6777</phone><electronicMailAddress>webmaster@cedarcreek.umn.edu</electronicMailAddress></contact><methods><methodStep><description><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Field Operations: Prescribed Burning</para></listitem><listitem><para>A prescribed burning program was initiated at CCESR in 1964 to restore and maintain oak savanna and woodland vegetation and to test the effectiveness of different prescribed burning treatments. An area of about 210 hectares was divided into 14 management units of 2.4 to 30 hectares each. Each unit was assigned to one of seven burn frequency treatments, ranging from annual burns to complete fire exclusion, which are shown in the following table. 
Cedar Creek Burn Units - Prescribed Burning Record  
	 	 	 
Year	101	102	103	104	105	106	107	108	109	110	111	113	115	116	117	201	209	401	409	AS1	AS2	AS3 
1962																					26-Apr	26-Apr 
1963																					30-Aug	2-May 
1964	23-Apr																	23-Apr				12-Apr 
1965	28-Apr	7-May	7-Apr	7-May	7-May													28-Apr				 
1966	13-Apr	12-Apr	25-Apr	13-Apr	25-Apr	25-Apr	30-Aug											13-Apr				 
1967	27-Apr	1-Apr	14-Apr	5-May	5-May	31-Jul	6-Sep	10-Apr								27-Apr		27-Apr				 
1968		15-Apr	26-Apr	26-Apr				29-Apr				29-Apr				26-Apr						12-Apr 
1969			12-May	12-May		23-Apr	23-Apr				14-May										27-Aug	 
1970	4-May			4-May		19-May												4-May				 
1971			21-Apr	29-Apr	29-Apr			12-May														 
1972	8-May	17-Apr	18-May	25-Apr	25-Apr	17-Apr		25-Apr								8-May		8-May				17-Apr 
1973	26-Apr	26-Apr	16-May	26-Apr	16-May	15-May	16-May									26-May		26-Apr				 
1974		16-Apr	16-Apr	18-May																	19-Jul	24-Apr 
1975		5-May		5-May		12-May	12-May	12-May														24-May 
1976	26-Apr		26-Apr	29-Apr		29-Apr						6-May				26-Apr		25-Apr				1-May 
1977	25-Apr		25-Apr	26-Apr	26-Apr											25-Apr		25-Apr				 
1978	1-May	28-Apr	28-Apr		15-May	1-May		10-May														 
1979		23-Apr	23-Apr	23-Apr		15-May	23-Apr	15-May								16-May						 
1980			17-Apr	14-May			14-May									21-May						 
1981	12-May	7-May	7-May	20-May		5-May	18-May				12-May											 
1982	20-Apr					24-May		26-Apr														 
1987			4-May											6-May						6-Oct		 
1988				19-May		18-May		11-Apr														 
1989			25-Apr	12-May	12-May		25-Apr							11-May								 
1990		3-May	3-May	3-May	3-May	3-May								5-May								 
1991	14-May			14-May		14-May										14-May						 
1992	14-May	8-May	8-May	14-May		14-May		8-May					8-May	8-May		14-May						 
1992																						 
1993	5-May		12-May	12-May		5-May										5-May						 
1994			5-May	22-Apr	22-Apr	20-Apr		10-May			20-Apr	12-May				21-Apr		21-Apr				 
1994																						 
1995	3-May	29-Jan	5-May	12-May												3-May		3-May				 
1995																						 
1996			7-May	16-May	16-May	29-Apr	29-Apr							30-Apr		7-May		7-May	13-May			 
1997	1-May		25-Apr			21-Apr		28-Apr					6-May	6-May		17-Apr		1-May	29-Apr			 
1998			17-Apr																			 
1999		28-Apr		26-Apr	26-Apr	24-Apr	24-Apr												26-Apr			 
2000	2-May		24-May	24-Apr		28-Apr		26-Apr					2-May		2-May				26-Apr			 
2000																						 
2001	11-Oct	11-Oct																				 
2001			11-Oct	11-Oct												11-Oct		11-Oct				 
2001																						 
2001									11-Oct													 
2001					11-Oct																	 
2002		14-May	30-Apr	14-May		26-Apr	26-Apr							30-Apr								 
2003	24-Apr		11-Apr	12-Apr	12-Apr	8-Apr		9-Apr			25-Apr		8-Apr	8-Apr	23-Apr	24-Apr		24-Apr	9-Apr			 
2004			22-Apr													22-Apr		22-Apr	24-Apr			 
2005	15-Apr	14-Apr	14-Apr	14-Apr	14-Apr	21-Apr	21-Apr						21-Apr	21-Apr	21-Apr	15-Apr		15-Apr	14-Apr			 
2006				27-Apr	27-Apr	19-Apr						24-Apr				19-Apr			27-Apr			 
2007	20-Apr	20-Apr	20-Apr	20-Apr	20-Apr		19-Apr	19-Apr								20-Apr		20-Apr	20-Apr			 
2008	1-May					1-May							1-May	1-May	1-May	1-May						 
2009	28-Apr	28-Apr	28-Apr	11-May	11-May	22-Apr										28-Apr		28-Apr	5-May			 
2010			19-Apr	22-Apr			18-Apr	19-Apr							9-Apr	9-Apr				19-Apr        	 	 	 
 
 
Notes: 
 
5/20/1992	98	e98 Started 
5/5/1994	12	12 started 
5/5/1995	B	All burned Wild Fire 
-/-/1998	503	Possibly burned 
4/29/2000	502	Western Half Burned 
10/11/2001	103	Wild Fire 
10/11/2001	104	Wild Fire 
10/11/2001	105	Wild Fire/Soutthwest 1/3 didn't burn10/11/2001	109	Wild Fire/Eastern Edge 
10/11/2001	201	Wild Fire 
10/11/2001	204	Wild Fire 
10/11/2001	301	Wild Fire 
10/11/2001	401	Wild Fire 
10/11/2001	701	Wild Fire/+North of 701 to Hub Street 
4/24/2006	113	Arson/+Northwest of Bicon 
4/15/2009	113*	NW across road of 113 
 
 
The first burn was conducted in 1964, and all units not designated for fire protection had been burnt at least once by 1969. Two additional burn units west of East Bethel Blvd. received prescribed burns beginning in 1987 and 1992. Additional burn units have been added to the program in 1996, including 3 units along the west side of East Bethel Blvd., and one unit (409) that is a portion of one of the original "no burn" units. The Nature Conservancy began a similar prescribed burning experiment in 1962 on their 20 hectare Helen Allison Savanna property, which is adjacent to the Cedar Creek burn units. Eight rectangular 1-ha burn units were outlined on the east end of the property in a 4x2 design. The remaining 12 hectares were managed with protection from fire until 1987, when this unit was added to the burning program for conservation purposes. Prescribed fires are generally conducted in the spring using a form of the strip-headfire method. Firebreaks are disked in the spring prior to burning to remove most fuels. In areas where permanent fire breaks do not exist, the grass layer is mowed to produce a 1-2 meter wide fuel break. A backfire is started along the lee side of the burn unit, to widen the firebreak. Flanking fires are then lit along the sides of the units and monitored until a sufficiently wide blackline is produced. Finally, a headfire is started along the windward edge of the unit to complete the burn.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Sampling: Permanent Plots</para></listitem><listitem><para>A series of permanent plots have been established in the burn units to facilitate repeated sampling of tree, shrub, and herbaceous community composition. Plots are sampled every 5-6 years to monitor changes in structure and composition. The first twelve of these were established in CCNHA Fish Lake burn units in 1984 as part of experiment 015. Additional plots were added in 1990 as part of experiment 094, including four additional plots in the Fish Lake burn units, five in the "Davis grid" savanna area west of East Bethel boulevard, and three in the Allison Savanna burn units. Finally, three new plots were added in 1995, two in old fields and one in burn unit 104. Each plot consists of four parallel 50-meter transects placed 25 meters apart, outlining an area 50m x 75m. Points for quadrat sampling of herb and shrub cover are placed at 10 meter intervals along each transect for a total of 24 sample points per plot. (Note: the two old field plots, 22 and 28, were laid out as two 110-meter transects placed 25 meters apart, again producing 24 sample points.) Endpoints of each transect are marked with fenceposts (T-posts). The fencepost on the front end of each transect (points 1, 7, 13 and 19) are labeled with aluminum tags identifying the experiment (E133), plot number, and transect number. Interior sample points on each transect were marked by rebar posts starting in 1995 to facilitate true repeated sampling at each point.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Sampling: Trees</para></listitem><listitem><para>All trees within the 50m x 75m area were tagged in 1995 using numbered round aluminum tags. Tags were nailed to the tree at a height of 1.3-1.7 meters and facing the front of the plot (the long side with labeled fenceposts). Trees on many of the plots were previously tagged as part of experiment 094. These foil tags appear to have been highly susceptible to fire and animal damage, however, and were missing from a large proportion of the trees. Old and new tag numbers were matched up for the vast majority of trees, however, so individual trees can still be followed over time. The aluminum nails from the old tags are valuable, however, because the E094 diameter measurements were made 1 centimeter above this nail. The 1995 measurements were made at "breast height" (about 1.35 meters) as determined by the field crews, so there may be some inconsistencies between 1990 and 1995 measurements. Trees were surveyed in 1995 for species identification, status (alive, dead, snag, fallen), and diameter at breast height (dbh). Previous surveys also recorded approximate tree height and crown vigor (ordinal scale, 1-5) on some plots. On many of the plots, trees were also mapped to the nearest 0.1 meter using the "Topcon Total Station" surveying equipment. Since readings were taken to the edge of the tree, the true accuracy is probably somewhere between 0.1 and 0.4 meters. The mapping process included all tagged trees (&gt;= 5 cm) and the understory vegetation sample points.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Sampling: Oak seedling survival and demographics</para></listitem><listitem><para>This portion of the study is designed to improve our understanding of the influence of fire frequency and canopy cover on the spatial patterns, growth, and mortality/survival rates of oak seedlings. Belt transects have been established in five burn units representing the complete range of burn frequencies: unit 110 (no burns), 113 (4 burns/32 years), 107 (11/32), 105 (15/32), and 104 (26/32). In burn unit 104, there are four 100-m long transects placed within the macroplot (see E134). In the remaining units, there are three transects of 40 meters each within the permanent plots used for this study. Oak stems, both new germinants and older seedlings/sprouts have been tagged for long-term demographic studies. All oak stems less than 5 cm dbh that lie within 0.5 meter on either side of the transect are tagged with numbered aluminum tags. If an individual has multiple stems, only one stem is tagged. Tag number, location, species, height, and diameter are recorded for each individual at the time it is tagged. The position of each individual relative to the tree canopy is also noted as one of the following: under canopy, canopy edge, or open. Individuals are surveyed annually to assess both mortality and deer browse.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Sampling: Nitrogen cycling</para></listitem><listitem><para>Annual and seasonal nitrogen mineralization rates were estimated on 20 of the permanent plots in 1995. Six of these plots have been designated for long-term monitoring of N mineralization. N mineralization was measured over 5 incubation periods (approx. 30-45 days each) throughout the active growing season (mid-April to mid-October) in 1995. Eight replicates were used in each plot, corresponding to the same eight sample points used in the root core and litter trap samples (points 8-11, 14-17). We used a modified buried bag method to measure N mineralization as developed by Dave Wedin. At each point, a 0.75 inch diameter by 15 cm long soil core was removed from the sample area. This was our "initial" sample. A paired core was placed within 10 cm of the "initial" sample by pounding a sharpened piece of 0.75" diameter PVC pipe into the ground to a depth of 15 cm. The top of the pipe was plugged with a rubber cork to prevent water flow through the pipe. Air holes drilled between the soil surface and the cork facilitated ventilation of the sample during incubation. At the end of the incubation period, the PVC cores were extracted and returned to the laboratory for processing. Samples (both initial and final) were processed using standard Cedar Creek methods and will be described only briefly here. Samples are first homogenized. Soil nitrogen is extracted in 50 ml of 1 molar KCL solution and processed through the Cedar Creek autoanalyzer . Soil moisture content is determined gravimetrically. Additional soil cores were removed in fall of 1995 for purposes of measuring total soil carbon and nitrogen. At each of the 160 sample points used for the N mineralization measurements, four soil cores (0.75" diam. by 30 cm length) were removed from roughly evenly-spaced points along a 0.75 meter strip adjacent to the herbaceous vegetation sampling area. Each of these cores were divided into three depth segments (0-5, 5-15, and 15-30 cm) and pooled by depth. Two cores were extended to a depth of 50 cm and these two subsamples were pooled to produce a fourth depth sample (30-50 cm). Samples were dried and sifted to remove root material. A subsample was homogenized using a coffee mill and stored in a plastic sample bag for carbon and nitrogen analysis. The remainder of the sample was placed in a larger sample bag and archived for future use. 
Permanent Plot Data Collection - 1995/1996 Field Seasons  
	 	 	 
Burn Unit 	Plot No. 	Tree Tags 	Tree Survey 	Sample Points Mapped 	Trees Mapped 	Shrub Layer Survey 	Herb Layer Survey 	Canopy LAI Readings 	Tree Cores 	N Min. 	Root Core 
101 	1 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 
101 	*21 	- 	- 	Y 	- 	- 	Y 	- 	- 	- 	- 
102 	*22 	- 	- 	Y 	- 	- 	Y 	- 	- 	- 	- 
103 	3 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 
104 	4 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 
104 	24 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 
105 	5 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 
106 	6 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 
107 	7 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 
108 	8 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 
108 	*28 	- 	- 	Y 	- 	- 	Y 	Y 	- 	- 	- 
109 	15 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 
109 	18 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 
110 	10 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	Y 	Y 
111 	11 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	Y 	- 
113 	13 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 
115 	903 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 
115 	904 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	Y 	Y 
116 	901 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	Y 	- 
116 	902 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	Y 	- 
117 	905 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	Y 	- 
201 	16 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 
209 	9 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 
409 	17 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	- 	Y 	Y 	- 	- 	- 
409 	19 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	- 	- 
CCN 	20 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	- 	- 
AS1 	101 	X 	Y 	- 	- 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	- 	- 
AS2 	102 	X 	Y 	- 	- 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	- 	- 
AS3 	103 	X 	Y 	- 	- 	Y 	Y 	Y 	- 	- 	-	 	 	 
 
* denotes old field plot</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></description></methodStep></methods><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>e133_Soil moisture</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>e133_Soil moisture.txt</objectName><size unit="rows">2206</size><characterEncoding>ASCCII</characterEncoding><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines><recordDelimiter>\r</recordDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>\t</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution id="dist_knb-lter-cdr." scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-cdr.&amp;urlTail=lno_data_request.php?input=hoe133</url></online><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=CDR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Sampling</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Sampling #</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ordinal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Sampling #</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></ordinal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Date</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Date</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>DD-MMM-YY</formatString><dateTimePrecision>Day</dateTimePrecision></dateTime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Plot</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Plot</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Plot</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Point</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Point Identifier</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Point Identifier</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Method</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Method Type</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Method Type</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>VolumetricWaterContent%_0-20cm</attributeName><attributeDefinition>percent soil H2O</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>percent</customUnit></unit><precision>0.0000001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>TargetBurnFrequency(burns/year)</attributeName><attributeDefinition>TargetBurnFrequency(burns/year)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>Burns/Year</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><metadata><ns2:unitList convention="CML"><ns2:unit constantToSI="0.0" id="percent" multiplierToSI="1.0" name="percent"><ns2:description>percent</ns2:description></ns2:unit><ns2:unit constantToSI="0.0" id="Burns/Year" multiplierToSI="1.0" name="Burns/Year"><ns2:description>Burns/Year</ns2:description></ns2:unit></ns2:unitList></metadata></additionalMetadata></eml:eml>