<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-jrn.20060120.9845" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=JRN, o=lter, dc=ecoinformatics, dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <shortName>JornadaStudy_086_smes_rabbit_survey_line_data</shortName>
  <title>SMES rabbit survey data</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Brandon</givenName>
      <surName>Bestelmeyer</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>
	USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range

	P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>bbestelm@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <metadataProvider>
    <organizationName>The Jornada</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>2995 Knox Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-4842</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <onlineUrl>http://jornada.nmsu.edu</onlineUrl>
  </metadataProvider>
  <pubDate>1995</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para> Introduction.

 Animal consumers have important roles in ecosystems (Chew
 1974, 1976), determining plant species composition and structure
 (Harper 1969, Pacala and Crawley 1992, Crawley 1983, 1989),
 regulating rates of plant production and nutrient cycling (Naiman
 1988, McNaughton et al. 1989, Holland et al. 1992), and altering
 soil structure and chemistry (Milchunas et al. 1993, Huntly
 1991).

 Desertification of semi-arid grasslands in the Southwest
 United States by domestic livestock provides an important example
 of herbivore regulation of ecosystem structure and function
 (Schlesinger et al. 1990). The species composition and physical
 structure of these desert grassland ecosystems were significantly
 altered by alien herbivores about 100 years ago (Bahre 1991, York
 and Dick-Peddie 1968, Gardner 1951, Hastings and Turner 1980,
 Buffington and Herbel 1965, Dick-Peddie 1993). To what extent the
 spatial patterns of semi-arid shrubland and grassland plant
 production and soil characteristics are currently controlled by
 plant resource use, abiotic factors, or consumers is not known.

 Desertification is an ecosystem-level phenomenon occurring
 on a global scale with great relevance to human welfare (Nelson
 1988). In order to understand the processes that contribute to
 desertification, we must fully understand interactions among the
 components of arid-land ecosystems. Schlesinger et al. (1990)
 suggest that in the absence of continued livestock perturbations,
 plant resource use and abiotic factors appear to be the principal
 factors accounting for the persistence of desert shrublands in
 desertified semi-arid grasslands. However, Brown and Heske
 (1990a) provide evidence that indigenous small mammal consumers
 may also have a major role in determining vegetation structure in
 those desert ecosystems.

 Brown and Heske (1990a, Heske et al. 1993) found that the
 exclusion of rodents from Chihuahuan Desert creosotebush
 shrubland areas resulted in a significant increase in grass cover
 over a 12 year period. Brown and Heske (1990a) concluded that
 rodents were keystone species in those desert shrub communities,
 greatly influencing vegetation structure. Rodents are also known
 to have significant influences on plant species composition and
 diversity in desert communities (Inouye et al. 1980, Heske et al.
 1993, Brown et al. 1986). Several species of granivorous rodents
 (Family: Heteromidae, genera: Dipodomys, Perognathus,
 Chaetodipus) appear to have the greatest influence on vegetation
 herbivory.

 Soil disturbance through the digging activities of rodents
 can have profound local effects on plant species composition and
 vegetation structure in the Chihuahuan Desert (Moroka et al.
 1982). Digging activities of desert rodents intermix surface
 soils with subsurface soils (Abaturov 1972), and increase
 rainfall infiltration (Soholt 1975). Reported measures of the
 percentage of desert soil surface areas disturbed by rodent
 digging activities in desert enviroments range from 10% (Abaturov
 1972) to 4.5% (Soholt 1975). Burrowing activities increase local
 soil nutrient and water status, creating favorable sites for
 increased plant densities, biomass production, and increased
 species diversity (Morehead et al. 1989, Mun and Whitford 1990).

 Rabbits (Lagomorpha: Black-tailed jackrabbits, Lepus
 californicus, and desert cottontail rabbits, Sylvilagus aduboni)
 are also important consumers of desert vegetation (Brown 1947,
 Johnson and Anderson 1984, Steinberger and Whitford 1983, Ernest
 1994). Rabbits can have significant effects on plant species
 composition and structure resulting from selective herbivory
 (Gibbens et al. 1993, Clark and Wagner 1984, Norris 1950,
 Zeevalking and Fresco 1977). Gibbens et al. (1993) found that
 excluding rabbits from Chihuahuan Desert creosotebush (Larrea
 tridentata) communities over a period of 50 years increased the
 canopy cover of some grasses, and also increased canopy cover of
 some shrub species.

 Small mammal (rodent and rabbit) populations may fluctuate
 considerably with variation in climate and annual plant
 production (Brown et al. 1979, Brown and Heske 1990, Brown and Zeng
 1989, Whitford 1976, Johnson and Anderson 1984). Reproduction in
 desert rodents is known to be induced by plant foliage production
 (Reichman and Van De Graff 1975, Beatley 1969). If small mammals
 are keystone species affecting plant species composition and
 structure in desert ecosystems, then the impacts of small mammals
 on vegetation are probably linked with variation in climate and
 plant production.

 A reciprocal plant-herbivore/granivore feedback system may
 result, where small mammal populations and thus impacts on
 vegetation, are initially determined by climate influences on
 plant food resource availability to the small mammals. Thus, the
 effects of small mammals during dry years will probably be
 different from the effects during wet years because of different
 population sizes. If this is so, one should be able to measure
 differential effects of small mammals on plant communities over
 series of wet or dry years, such as El Nino and La Nina cycles
 (Nicholls 1988). Such reciprocal interactions should also occur
 in relation to long-term (decades) climate change.

 The effects of any one small mammal species population on the
 biotic community will be complicated by competitive
 interactions with other mammal species (Munger and Brown 1981,
 Brown and Zeng 1989, Brown and Heske 1990), however overall impacts
 on vegetation and soils by the combined effects of all small
 mammal species may be closely linked with variation in
 precipitation and plant production. Depending upon the
 persistence of plant food resources such as foliage or seeds, lag
 times in consumer impacts may be expected following periods of
 precipitation and plant production.

 In desert ecosystems, widely scattered shrubs produce a
 patch pattern of fertile islands with high plant biomass
 production and soil nutrients, surrounded by relatively
 unproductive barren soil (West and Klemmedson 1978, Crawford and
 Gosz 1982). Researchers at the Jornada Long-Term Ecological
 Research site in New Mexico have proposed a desertification model
 suggesting that perturbations caused by domestic livestock
 grazing and climate change initiated processes transforming
 grasslands with relatively homogeneous resource distributions to
 shrubland environments with relatively heterogenous resource
 distributions (Schlesinger et al. 1990). This patchy
 vegetation/resource distribution pattern is stable under present
 climate regimes, and appears to be maintained by plant resource
 use and abiotic soil processes (Schlesinger et al. 1990).
 However, Wagner (1976, page 195) suggested that small mammals
 were probably maintaining shrubland dominated ecosystems at the
 Jornada by suppressing grasses through selective herbivory.


 Research Hypotheses.

 The purpose of this study is to determine whether or not the
 activities of small mammals regulate plant community structure,
 plant species diversity, and spatial vegetation patterns in
 Chihuahuan Desert shrublands and grasslands. What role if any do
 indigenous small mammal consumers have in maintaining desertified
 landscapes in the Chihuahuan Desert? Additionally, how do the
 effects of small mammals interact with changing climate to affect
 vegetation patterns over time? This study will provide long-term
 experimental tests of the roles of consumers on ecosystem pattern
 and process across a latitudinal climate gradient. The following
 questions or hypotheses will be addressed.

 1) Do small mammals influence patterns of plant species
 composition and diversity, vegetation structure, and spatial
 patterns of vegetation canopy cover and biomass in Chihuahuan
 Desert shrublands and grasslands? Are small mammals keystone
 species that determine plant species composition and physiognomy
 of Chihuahuan Desert communities as Brown and Heske (1990a) and
 Gibbens et al. (1993) suggest? Do small mammals have a
 significant role in maintaining the existence of shrub islands
 and spatial heterogeneity of creosotebush shrub communities?

 2) Do small mammals affect the taxonomic composition and
 spatial pattern of vegetation similarly or differently in
 grassland communities as compared to shrub communities? How do
 patterns compare between grassland and shrubland sites, and how
 do these relatively small scale patterns relate to overall
 landscape vegetation patterns?

 3) Do small mammals interact with short-term (annual) and
 long-term (decades) climate change to affect temporal changes
 in vegetation spatial patterns and species composition?


 Other Consumers.

 Ants are important consumers in Chihuahuan Desert ecosystems
 (MacKay 1991), and granivorous ants are known to have competitive
 interactions with rodents (Brown and Davidson 1977, Brown et al.
 1979) for plant seed resources. Termites are important
 detritivores in Chihuahuan Desert ecosystems (MacKay 1991) and
 appear to have key roles in plant litter decomposition and
 nutrient cycling (Whitford et al. 1982, Schaefer and Whitford
 1981), and in altering soil structure and hydrologic processes
 (Elkins et al. 1986). Grasshoppers are important herbivores in
 Chihuahuan Desert ecosystems (Rivera 1986, Wisdom 1991, Richman
 et al. 1993), with various species specializing on most of the
 different plant species present in any location (Otte 1976, Joern
 1979). Since manipulations of small mammals will probably affect
 these arthropod consumers, we will monitor these other consumers
 on the measurement plots to document any changes.

 Documentation of changes or lack of changes in ant, termite,
 and grasshopper consumer groups will be needed to interpret the
 results of small mammal manipulations on vegetation and soils.
 For example, if removal of rodents results in an increase of
 seed-harvesting ants, changes or lack of changes in vegetation
 and soils may be attributed to compensatory granivory from the
 increase in ants. Small mammals are the consumer group that
 appears to have the greatest influence on Chihuahuan Desert
 communities (see literature citations above). Given the known
 ecological importance of small mammals and the complexity and
 difficulties that would be associated with manipulating small
 mammals and arthropods, we have chosen to start with experiments
 on small mammals first. If these other consumer groups appear to
 have important interactions with small mammals, we will pursue
 additional experiments in the future to focus on those
 interactions, and to elucidate the ecological roles of these
 arthropod consumers.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>animal</keyword>
    <keyword>Black-tailed jackrabbit</keyword>
    <keyword>Desert cottontail</keyword>
    <keyword>Lepus californicus</keyword>
    <keyword>longterm</keyword>
    <keyword>ongoing</keyword>
    <keyword>plant-animal interactions</keyword>
    <keyword>populations</keyword>
    <keyword>rabbit demography</keyword>
    <keyword>signature</keyword>
    <keyword>Sylvilagus audubonii</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Jornada Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout> There are two roads that the survey is conducted on, one in a
 creosotebush habitat and the other in a grassland habitat.

 For the creosotebush route (Road 1), drive to the USDA-ARS
 Jornada Experimental Range (JER) south entrance on Jornada Road and
 turn left (west) at Stone Pillars. Begin the survey here. This
 road continues to the south boundary gate of NMSU Chihuahuan Desert
 Rangeland Research Center (CDRRC) located at the powerline crossing.
 Turn right here (north) and go through the gate. Continue north on
 this powerline road and veer right when the road forks. Continue
 past LTER sites C-GRAV, Upper Trailer, C-SAND, and LTER Weather
 Station. The survey is complete for the creosote habitat when you
 reach the gate immediately north of the Weather Station. Route is
 6.2 miles long.

 The grassland route (Road 3), drive to USDA-ARS JER South Well on
 Jornada Road. The route begins 1/4 mile from the South Well
 cattleguard on the road going northwest just after crossing the
 cattleguard on the east side of South Well. There is a yucca on the
 right side of the road about 4 feet high that serves as the starting
 point. Follow this road far side of Pasture 13 (boundary fence with
 CDRRC is next to road on your left while crossing Pasture 13). Turn
 right (northeast) just before cattle guard (don't cross into Pasture
 8C), and proceed along fenceline. You will need to pass through a
 large green gate and continue the survey on the same road on into
 Pasture 11A. Dale Gillette's Scrape Site will be off on your right
 within a quarter mile after the green gate. The survey ends at the
 fork in the road encountered at about mile 6.3 shortly before it
 joins Jornada Road.</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>Objectives:
The Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System (JIMS) provides protocol and services for data collection, verification, organization, archives, and distribution in accordance with recommendations and guidelines developed by the LTER Information Managers Committee (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html).

Disclaimer:
While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is". The Jornada Basin LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of data sets.

Quality Assurance Policy:
Data managers interact with researchers during the entire scientific process--from the initial planning of sampling designs and field data collection to archiving and distribution of data. The goal of data management is to build and maintain an archive of Jornada Basin LTER data files that are fully documented, error free, and organized in useful ways. Our protocol for data collection and processing seeks maximum interaction between researchers and data management personnel to avoid confusion and potential loss of data or problems with integrity of data; e.g., identification of historical site treatments that may impact a proposed study or incomplete data set variable descriptions. Site and Data Manager involvement begins during the Project Design phase with the completion of the Jornada Notification of Research form by the researcher prior to the start of work; this alerts both Site and Data Manager to the new study and potential LTER data sets. Upon initiation of a new study, the researcher completes Project Documentation that provides the second level of "metadata" documentation.
In the Data Collection phase, the data manager helps researchers design field and laboratory data sheets that facilitate data entry and analysis. Prior to JIMS data entry the investigator completes Data Set Documentation to provide the metadata that fully describe the data set. Both Project and Data set documentation are provided with the data set when it is requested or obtained from our Web site. JIMS data entry programs error-check and verify data as they are entered. Computer files are subjected to further verification by graphing and/or error-checking programs, and/or examination by field investigators. Final quality assurance of the data rests with the investigator who submits data for inclusion in the Data Management System. Direct communication with the Site Manager, or through a collaborating JRN P.I., is used to encourage the timely submission of documentation and of data by researchers.

Error-checked data files are stored with associated documentation files on the file server. Archived data files are maintained in ASCII format on 30-yr magneto-optical (MO) disks, portable hard drives, CD-R media, and DVD media to guard against loss of data access that can result from changing technology. This may also include proprietary binary format files to facilitate recovery of working versions. Image data are archived on 8mm tape. Routine tape data backups of the file server are done daily, weekly, and monthly. One set of off-site copies are maintained elsewhere on the NMSU campus of routine backup tapes, MO disks, CD disks, and DVD disks with a second set of MO, CD and DVD disks maintained off-campus in case of a catastrophe on campus. The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data manag ement staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data management staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

Policy on Submission of data:
Data submission into JIMS is expected from LTER researchers, LTER collaborators, and their graduate students where data and information is derived from publicly funded research in the U.S. LTER Network, totally or partially from LTER funds from NSF, Institutional Cost-Share, or Partner Agency or Institution where a formal memorandum of understanding with LTER has been established. Other Jornada Basin researchers are encouraged to submit their documented data for inclusion within JIMS to provide them with an archived backup, ensure its longevity, and provide online access to encourage synthesis efforts. Minimally, for non-LTER associated researchers, we request that publications be provided of research conducted on the Jornada Basin.
Initial documentation for a data set must be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager within 90 days of initiation of data collection. Documentation forms are available at http://jornada-www.nmsu.edu/site/dm/readme.php . These consist of Project Abstract and Data Set and Attribute documentation forms, which include objectives of the study, methods, as well as format and content of the data. All data collected during a calendar year should be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager prior to July first of the following year. First time data submissions must be submitted with updated standard Jornada Basin LTER forms previously submitted.

Data Access Policy:
Data will be made publicly available no later than 2 years after submission of the data unless an earlier date is specified by the principal investigator. In the event that an extension of the 2 year period is necessary, the principal investigator may petition the Jornada Basin LTER Executive Committee for a longer protected period. Graduate student research data will be available online after degree completion and they have the opportunity to publish their research.

Policies for re-use, distribution, or the production of derivatives:
Data re-use, distribution and production of derivative products are governed by the LTER Network data policies (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html) in the spirit of having the potential to increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines. Appropriate citation, acknowledgement, notification and collaboration are outlined and recommended. No commercial redistribution of data and derived products are allowed.

Data Acknowledgment Policy:
Please send notification to the Information Manager and Responsible Investigator(s) of the data sets you are downloading and your intended use.
Individuals and institutions utilizing data from the Jornada Basin LTER database are requested to place the following acknowledgment in any publication in which these data are mentioned:
Data sets were provided by the Jornada Basin Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) project. Funding for these data was provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210).

Please send 1 copy of any publication that cites Jornada Basin LTER data to:
     John P. Anderson
     Jornada Experimental Range
     P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
     New Mexico State University
     Las Cruces, NM 88003-0003</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="download">http://jornada-data.nmsu.edu/files/dataset_packages/JornadaStudy_086_smes_rabbit_survey_line_data.zip</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>1996-04-09</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2012-01-09</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <maintenance>
    <description>
      <para>
        <literalLayout> mm/dd/yyyy - Date of Comment
 Int - Initials of person making Comment
 JPA = John P. Anderson
 DL = David Lightfoot
 KR = Ken Ramsey
 Changes/Updates - List any changes made to document

 mm/dd/yyyy Int Changes/Updates
 ---------- --- -----------------------------------------------
 11/10/2000 DL Form completed by investigator
 11/21/2001 JPA Form converted to new format, methodology
 edited, added: attributes, dates of researchers
 involvement added, keywords, site location
 clarified.
 11/29/2001 JPA Note added to Methodology identifying beginning use
 of new rangefinder.
 10/17/2007 JPA Changed Data Set Access to Unrestricted as per DL.
 09/23/2009 KR Changed Responsible Investigator to Brandon
 Bestelmeyer per Deb Peters. Also added time
 periods to Responsible Investigators and Researchers.
 Added EC attribute definition.
 11/15/2011 JPA Changed responsible investigator for contact person
 to Brandon Bestelmeyer per Deb Peters.
 Added PRJ and DSL ID numbers to top of file. They
 had been previously assigned but were not on this
 form.
 03/13/2012 JPA Updated variable names to longer descriptive names.
 Changed SMESRABS.DAT to smesrabs.csv.</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </description>
  </maintenance>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Data</givenName>
      <surName>Manager</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>PO Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>The Jornada</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Field data forms</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout> Night road surveys are conducted four times each year during a
 full moon in winter (January/February), spring (April/May), summer
 (July/August), and autumn (October/November). The counts can be
 conducted during the full moon of either of the two months for a
 season, when ever the weather is best. The portion of road surveyed
 through the creostoebush environment (Route 1) runs 6.2 miles (9.98
 kilometers) across the east bajada of the Dona Ana Mountains
 (dominated with creosotebush with scattered mesquite), from
 the USDA, JER south entrance on Jornada Road at the rock pillars, to
 the power-line road, past the C-GRAV and C-SAND sites, to the
 Weather Trailer gate. The grassland portion of the road (Route 3)
 runs 6.3 miles (10.14 kilometers) from South Well to USDA Pasture
 13, along the west boundary of Pasture 13, then along the north
 boundary of Pasture 13 to Jornada Road at the "wind tunnel" site.

 One open bed pickup truck is driven approximately 12 miles per
 hour along each road route. The driver (data recorder) of the truck
 sets the trip odometer to zero at the start of each of the road
 segments (creosotebush and grassland). Two people (observers) in
 the back of the truck scan each side of the road for rabbits, each
 using a 100,000 candle-power spotlight. The observers shine the
 light beam in a 90 degree arc from the road ahead to the area
 perpendicular to the truck. The observers should watch for rabbits,
 and the reddish reflection of rabbits eyes in the light. Each time
 a rabbit is observed, the truck stops, and the observer guides the
 truck to a position perpendicular to the rabbit. The observer then
 calls out information to the driver who records the following
 information in the data book.

 (1) Date
 (2) Road route number (1 = creosotebush; 2 = grassland)
 (3) Rabbit species (LECA for black-tailed jackrabbit) or SYAU for
 desert cottontail, or UNKN for unknown if the observer cannot
 identify the rabbit to species),
 (4) Odometer mileage (when perpendicular on the road to the
 rabbit)
 (5) Perpendicular distance from the center of the road
 (truck) to the rabbit measured to the nearest meter by use
 of a metric rangefinder.
 (6) Direction of the rabbit (L=left of road center; R=right
 of road center; C=exact center of road)
 (7) Time (24 hour or military time).
 (8) Comments

 In addition, the data recorder must record the road mileage from
 the odometer for the START and END points as well as the mileage and
 time for the GATE that is passed through along each route. The
 terms START, END, and GATE are entered into the species field on the
 data sheet.

 At the start of each route, Comments must be made by the data
 recorder on the Moon Phase (full moon) at the beginning of the first
 route. Weather conditions (for example, scattered high clouds,
 mostly clear, no wind) should be commented on at the beginning and
 end of each route since wind and cloud cover conditions may change.

 NOTE: Rabbit surveys are conducted only when the moon is full,
 the skies are mostly clear, and winds are light ( less than 10 mph).

 NOTE: Bushnell Yardage Pro Compact 800 rangefinder (laser
 rangefinder) used beginning January 2002. See ASCII file,
 Bushnell800_rangefinder.inf for specs and other information related
 to the unit.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
    <qualityControl>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout> Responsible investigator(s):
 ----------------------------
 Brandon Bestelmeyer, Oct2004-present;
 David Lightfoot, Oct1995-Sep2003
 *************************************</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </qualityControl>
  </methods>
  <project>
    <title>Jornada LTER</title>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
        <givenName>Debra</givenName>
        <surName>Peters</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-2777</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">575-646-5889</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>debpeter@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Lead Principal Investigator</role>
    </personnel>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Data</givenName>
        <surName>Manager</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Information Manager</role>
    </personnel>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>The Jornada Basin Long Term Ecological Research program, in collaboration with 
                         the USDA ARS Jornada Experimental Range, studies the causes and consequences of 
                         desertification: the broad scale expansion of woody plants into grasslands that 
                         results in more "desert like" conditions. We are interested in spatial and 
                         temporal variation in desertification dynamics, and how historic legacies, the 
                         geomorphic template, transport vectors (wind, water, animals), and environmental 
                         drivers (climate, land use, disturbance) interact with the patch structure of the 
                         vegetation to determine past, present, and future ecosystem dynamics across 
                         scales.
                        
                         Our study site is located in the northern Chihuahuan Desert, approximately 25 km 
                         northeast of Las Cruces, New Mexico, USA (+32.5 N, -106.8 W, elevation 1188 m). 
                         Annual precipitation is 24 cm and maximum temperatures average 13 C in January 
                         and 36 C in June. Our study site includes the 78,000 ha Jornada Experimental 
                         Range operated by the USDA Agricultural Research Service, and the 22,000 ha 
                         Chihuahuan Desert Rangeland Research Center (CDRRC) operated by New Mexico State 
                         University. The Jornada Basin LTER project was established in 1982, and is 
                         administered by New Mexico State University. This site is a member of the LTER 
                         Network, one of  more than 25 long term sites funded by the U.S. National Science 
                         Foundation.</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <funding>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210)</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </funding>
  </project>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>JornadaStudy_086_smes_rabbit_survey_line_data.csv</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data file information for the following Jornada data set: SMES rabbit survey data</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>JornadaStudy_086_smes_rabbit_survey_line_data.csv</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <numHeaderLines>17</numHeaderLines>
          <numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
          <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url function="download">http://jornada-data.nmsu.edu/sites/jornada-data.nmsu.edu/files/data_files/JornadaStudy_086_smes_rabbit_survey_line_data.csv</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1996-04-09</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2012-01-09</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>date</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_rabbit_survey_date</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Month/day/year data was collected
</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>mm/dd/yyyy</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>route</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_rabbit_survey_route</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Road route
</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1 </code>
                  <definition> Creosotebush</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3 </code>
                  <definition> Grassland</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>species code</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_rabbit_survey_spp</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Species Code, LECA or SYAU</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>LECA</code>
                  <definition>Lepus californicus</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>SYAU</code>
                  <definition>Sylvilagus audubonii</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>UNKN</code>
                  <definition>unknown rabbit species</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>START</code>
                  <definition>beginning of route</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>GATE</code>
                  <definition>gate</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>END</code>
                  <definition>end of route</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>milage</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_rabbit_survey_milage</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>vehicle odometer mileage (miles) along rabbit route.
</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>miles</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>distance</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_rabbit_survey_distance</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>distance in meters perpendicular from center of road to rabbit
</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>meters</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>direction</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_rabbit_survey_direction</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>rabbit is on left or right side of road center, or exact center of road
</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>L</code>
                  <definition>rabbit is on left side of road center</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>R</code>
                  <definition>rabbit is on right side of raod center</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>C</code>
                  <definition>rabbit is on exact center of road</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>time</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_rabbit_survey_time</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>hour and minute of observation (24hr)
</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>hhmm</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Comment code</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_rabbit_survey_comment_code</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>comment code</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>0</code>
                  <definition>no comment</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1</code>
                  <definition>there is a comment</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>comment</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_smes_rabbit_survey_comment</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>comments, anything unusual

</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>comments, anything unusual

</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
    <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
<ns2:unit id="miles" />
<ns2:unit abbreviation="" id="meters" name="meters" unitType=""><ns2:description /></ns2:unit>

    </ns2:unitList>
  </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>