<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.221.48336" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV, o=lter, dc=ecoinformatics, dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Vegetation Surveys in Chihuahuan Desert Grassland and Shrubland Sites Associated with Coyote Scat Surveys at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Virginia</givenName>
      <surName>Seamster</surName>
    </individualName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>vas6f@cms.mail.virginia.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">14900</userId>
  </creator>
  <metadataProvider>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Sevilleta LTER</givenName>
      <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
    </individualName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>vanderbi@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </metadataProvider>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Virginia</givenName>
      <surName>Seamster</surName>
    </individualName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>vas6f@cms.mail.virginia.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">14900</userId>
    <role>data manager</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Virginia</givenName>
      <surName>Seamster</surName>
    </individualName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>vas6f@cms.mail.virginia.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">14900</userId>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Virginia</givenName>
      <surName>Seamster</surName>
    </individualName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>vas6f@cms.mail.virginia.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">14900</userId>
    <role>labcrew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <pubDate>2011</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>This data set contains information regarding vegetation structure at sites in grama grassland and both creosote and mesquite shrubland habitats at the Sevilleta NWR. This information was collected at randomly selected sites throughout the refuge. Each site is within 100 meters of one of the 22 road-based transects(20 in 2008) that were used to carry out coyote scat surveys during three seasons (spring, summer and fall) in 2009 (see "Coyote scat surveys in grassland and shrubland sites at the Sevilleta NWR, spring, summer and fall 2009" data set). Data was collected within at total of 22 circular vegetation plots (40 in 2008), each of which is 30m in diameter. Each plot was surveyed a total of three times, specifically in: April (spring), July (summer), and October (fall) 2009. Variables were selected based on their relevance to patterns of coyote habitat use, as well as their utility in calibrating Landsat images of the study site and the likelihood that they would vary seasonally. Measured variables include: average percent live woody vegetation cover, average percent live grass cover, average percent live forb cover, and average woody plant height. Information on woody plant species with individuals greater than 0.5 m in height is also presented.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>populations</keyword>
    <keyword>primary production</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>species</keyword>
    <keyword>measurements</keyword>
    <keyword>interception</keyword>
    <keyword>transects</keyword>
    <keyword>surveys</keyword>
    <keyword>roads</keyword>
    <keyword>grasslands</keyword>
    <keyword>plants</keyword>
    <keyword>grasses</keyword>
    <keyword>vegetation</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>Additional Information on the personnel associated with the Data Collection / Data ProcessingOther Field Crew Members:Amanda BoutzMichael DonovanTeresa SeamsterTerri KoontzKelly BowmanKarles McQuade</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This data belongs to the Sevilleta LTER.  </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: McKenzie Flats is located within the northeastern section of the Sevilleta NWR, encompassing an area from Black Butte south  to Palo Duro Canyon and east to the Los Pinos.Landform: McKenzie Flats is a broad, nearly flat grassland plain between the Los Pinos Mountains and the breaks on the east side of the Rio Grande., Geology: Deep (20,000 ft) alluvial and aeolian deposits., Soils: Turney Series:  fine-loamy, mixed, thermic Typic Calciorthids.  Berino Series:  fine-loamy, mixed, thermic Typic Haplargids., Hydrology: Surface water only during rain events, no arroyos.  Run-on plain for Los Pinos Mountains., Vegetation: The terrain is generally a mixed-species desert grassland, dominated by black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda), blue grama (B. gracilis), sand muhly (Muhlenbergia arenicola), various drop seeds and sacatons (Sporobolus spp.), purple three-awn (Aristida purpurea), and burrow grass (Scleropogon brevifolia).  Shrubs are common in the area around Five Points, including creosote bush (Larrea tridentata) and snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae)., Climate: Long-term mean annual precipitation is 243 mm, about 60% of which occurs during the summer.  Long-term mean monthly temperatures for January and July are 1.5 degrees C and 25.1 degrees C, respectively., History: McKenzie Flats encompasses an area of approximately 50 square miles and was one of the primary livestock grazing areas within what is now the Sevilleta NWR.  Cattle have been excluded from the site since 1974-76.  The ranch headquarters buildings and corrals were located at the junction of Legs C and D of the coyote survey.  , siteid: 25</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>106.691</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>106.691</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Rio Salado is an ephemeral  tributary of the Rio Grande on the west side of the Sevilleta NWR,  flowing west by northwest to east by southeast. Rio Salado Grassland and  Rio Salado Larrea are two study sites established in 1989. These sites were established&#160;as counterparts to sites at Five Points. Between 1989 and 1998, vegetation, litter decomposition, and  ground dwelling arthropod and rodent populations were studied at both sites.  Core studies at these sites were largely terminated in 1998, although  rodent populations are still monitored at the Rio Salado Larrea site  because the Small Mammal Exclosure Study's Larrea plots are  co-located there. Rio Salado Grassland is the location Met Station 44.The Rio Salado study sites are accessed by taking the San Acacia exit, going west and then taking the frontage road back north to the Sevilleta NWR gate.&#160; After entering the refuge turn left after 0.2 mi and take this road 1.4 mi to a "T" in the road at the power 	lines.&#160;  An earthen berm stops road travel here and the 	met station is located about 300 m west on the blocked road.&#160;Vegetation: The Rio Salado Larrea site is characterized as Chihuahuan Desert Scrub, dominated by creosotebush (Larrea tridentata), with honey mesquite, fourwing saltbush, purple pricklypear (O. macrocentra), and broom snakeweed as co-occurring shrubs. Dominant grasses are black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda), galleta (Pleuraphis jamesii), burrograss (Scleropogon brevifolia), and fluffgrass (Dasyochloa pulchellum). Common forb species include desert holly (Acourtia nana), spectaclepod (Dimorphocarpa spp.), blackfoot daisey (Melampodium leucanthum), twinleaf (Senna bauhinoides), globemallow (Sphaeralcea wrightii), and plains hiddenflower (Cryptantha crassisepala). While individual creosote bushes tend to be larger, overall plant cover is less than at the creosote core site at Five Points, with more exposed embedded stones and gravel on the soil surface, creating a pavement-like appearance., </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>106.9267</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>106.9267</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.296</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.296</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1503</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1503</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: Bronco Well is located near the northern boundary of the Sevilleta NWR, approximately four miles west of the ATandT on the road to Red Tank.siteid: 14</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.934</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.934</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.406</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.406</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1547</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1547</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: There are 2 road based carnivore scat transects near Five Points. The beginning point for the first transect (D) is located 7.1 miles from the gate at Black Butte and is along Contreas rd, which leads west from the sign at Five Points. The second one (K) begins 2.0 miles south of the sign for Five Points (i.e. intersection of 5 roads) on Palo Duro Rd.Landform: Located on the soutwestern edge of McKenzie Flats and is in the transition zone from grama grassland to creosote shrubland. Five Points is a little north of a valley, which has a large arroyo., Geology: Very shallow and thick caliche layer., Soils: Turney Loam grading into Nickle-Caliza type of soil in the desert shrubland, Hydrology: Surface water is present only during heavy rainfall events. No major arroyos are present in this area, although Palo Duro Canyon borders the southern part of the Five Points study area., Vegetation: Transition from Desert Grassland to Chihuahuan Desert Scrub, which is dominated by creosote (Larrea tridentata)., Climate: There is a meteorological station at Five Points. For further climate details and data, consult the "Sevilleta meteorological" data set., History: This study area was  part of the piece of land that was turned into the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge in December, 1973, siteid: 66</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.735</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.735</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.337</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.337</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: South Gate is the major entry point onto the southeast side of the Sevilleta  NWR. Just north of the gate is Met Station 41. Research here has included a  Gunnison's prairie dog reintroduction as well as re-sampling of historic BLM  1976 vegetation transects, and juniper-creosote distribution. Vegetation is  highly impacted by historical cattle grazing and is sparse. Burro grass  (Scleropogon brevifolius) is dominant.siteid: 11</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.795</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.795</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.217</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.217</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1538</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1538</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>2008-07-30</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2009-11-01</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
      <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
    </individualName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint> 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>&#160;Experimental Design:&#160;Vegetation surveys were carried out at grassland and shrubland sites located throughout the Sevilleta NWR. In 2008, two plot locations were randomly elected for each of twenty road based scat transects that were surveyed during the same field season. Vegetation plot location was determined by randomly selecting the following: a distance from the beginning of each mile long, road-based scat transect; side of the road (left or right); and a distance from the road (30-100m).&#160;One of the two plots associated with each of the 20 scat transects surveyed in 2008 was randomly selected and surveyed in each of the three seasons in which scat surveys were conducted in 2009. Two new vegetation plots, one for each of two new scat transects, were also surveyed in 2009.Sampling Design:&#160;Each vegetation plot was circular with a 30m diameter intended to match the spatial scale of a Landsat satellite image pixel. In 2008, each of 40 plots was surveyed once between July 30th and August 20th, 2008. &#160;At each plot, measurements were collected along 4 x 15m line intercept transects, one per cardinal direction, and in 5 x 1m^2 quadrats located at random distances and angles from the plot center. In 2009, half of these plots and two new ones were each surveyd three times, once in each of the following three months: April, July, October. &#160;At each plot, measurements were collected along 4 x 15m line intercept transects, one per cardinal direction.Field Methods:&#160;The coordinates of the center of each vegetation plot were determined using a GPS unit. In 2008, percent woody vegetation cover was measured, to the nearest 0.1m, along the 4 x 15m line intercept transects described in the sampling design section. This data was later combined to obtain estimates of percent woody cover for 2 x 30m transects that passed through the plot center and were perpendicular to one another such that one ran north-south and the other ran east-west. An attempt was made to measure percent cover only for live woody plants with a height of 0.5 m or greater. A plant was considered to be alive if it had green leaves on some part of it. The one exception to this rule was Gutierrezia sarothrae, for which percent cover was assessed for both plants with green leaves and plants with dead flowers but no green leaves. Each woody plant that crossed the line intercept transects was identified to species and, for each plant with a height of 0.5m or greater, the height was recorded and two perpendicular axes of the plant were measured. 5 interplant distances were measured from the first woody plant (0.5m or taller) that was encountered along each of the 4 line intercept transects in a plot. These distances were measured to the 5 closest woody plants that were also at least 0.5m tall and were within the plot and therefore represent nearest neighbor distances. When no woody plants were encountered along the line intercept transects, measurements were made from the woody plant closest to the first 1m^2 quadrat (described in sampling design section). Fewer than 5 distances were measured when there were fewer than 6 woody plants found within the plot boundaries.&#160;Measurements of percent grass cover were made in the 5 x 1m^2 quadrats described in the sampling design section. For each quadrat, the dominant grass, defined as the grass with the highest percent cover, was identified to genus and a small sample was collected. Two grass genera were recorded in cases where the two grasses had similar values for percent cover. A small sample of each woody plant species (excluding cholla and other cactus species) found within the plot was also collected. In 2009, percent live woody vegetation, grass and forb cover was measured, to the nearest 0.1m, along the 4 x 15m line intercept transects described in the sampling design section. This data was later combined to obtain estimates of percent woody, grass and forb cover for 2 x 30m transects that passed through the plot center and were perpendicular to one another such that one ran north-south and the other ran east-west. A plant was considered to be "live" if there were green leaves or stalks. For a given plant that intersected a line intercept transect, if only part of the plant had green leaves or stalks, then only that part was measured and included in the calculation of percent live vegetation cover. Each woody plant that crossed the line intercept transects was identified to species and, for each plant with a height of 0.5m or greater, the height was measured to the nearest 0.1m and recorded. As a result, a list of woody plant species with individuals of a height greater than or equal to 0.5m that crossed the line intercept transects is presented for each plot. A small sample of the dominant woody plant species (excluding cholla and other cactus species) and one of the dominant grass species found within the plot was collected. Dominance was determined based on vegetation data collected in 2008. In particular, dominance was defined as follows: woody plant species with the highest value for percent cover within the plot; grass species with the highest percentage cover in at least one of 5 1m^2 quadrats that was surveyed in each plot.Laboratory Procedures:&#160;All plant samples were dried for 24 hours at 60 degrees Celsius and, in future, will be prepared and run through a stable carbon isotope analysis.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
    <qualityControl>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>Data were recorded in the field and entered into a spreadsheet in Excel. Extraneous information, for example information on woody plants less than 0.5m in height, was removed. No automated or quantitative data quality checks were performed.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </qualityControl>
  </methods>
</dataset>
</eml:eml>