<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-jrn.20050680.9874" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=JRN, o=lter, dc=ecoinformatics, dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Root Chemistry</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>John</givenName>
      <surName>Anderson</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>
	Jornada LTER

	New Mexico State University

	P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>janderso@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <metadataProvider>
    <organizationName>The Jornada</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>2995 Knox Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-4842</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <onlineUrl>http://jornada.nmsu.edu</onlineUrl>
  </metadataProvider>
  <pubDate>1986</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para> *We designed a study to examine the long-term spatial and temporal
 patterns of mass loss, changes in nitrogen content and chemical
 composition during decomposition of roots in a desert watershed.
 Because nitrogen availability has been hypothesized to affect
 decomposition rates of buried litter in deserts, we studied
 decomposition of roots along a transect on a desert watershed that
 had been fertilized with ammonium nitrate and compared these results
 with the decomposition of roots along a transect that had not been
 fertilized.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>acid solubles</keyword>
    <keyword>carbohydrates</keyword>
    <keyword>completed</keyword>
    <keyword>decomposition</keyword>
    <keyword>inorganic nutrients</keyword>
    <keyword>lignin</keyword>
    <keyword>nitrogen</keyword>
    <keyword>non-polar substance</keyword>
    <keyword>organic matter</keyword>
    <keyword>plant</keyword>
    <keyword>root</keyword>
    <keyword>signature</keyword>
    <keyword>tannin</keyword>
    <keyword>transects</keyword>
    <keyword>water solubles</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Jornada Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout> In the spring of 1982, as part of the establishment of the Jornada
 Long-Term Ecological Research site in southern New Mexico, a 135 ha
 portion of a 1500 ha, internally drained, watershed was exclosed
 from grazing by domestic livestock. Prior to exclosure the
 watershed, as well as the rest of the Jornada basin, had been
 moderately to heavily grazed for the past 100 years. Concurrent
 with grazing, the vegetation had undergone a dramatic change from
 desert grassland, with an almost continuous cover of C4 perennial
 grasses, to isolated patches of the original grassland in a
 mosaic with desert shrub dominated plant communities (Buffington
 and Herbel, 1965).

 The exclosure lies along a northeast facing piedmont slope at the
 base of a steep isolated mountain peak, and covers a variety of
 component landforms from the foot of the mountain to the basin
 floor. The northeast side of the exclosure is immediately upslope
 of the College Playa located near the NMSU College Ranch.

 Three parallel transects (2.7 km in length) run from the middle of
 the College Playa up into the foot of Mt. Summerford. The Control
 transect is to the west, the Treatment transect on the east side of
 the Control transect, and the Alternate Control to the east of the
 Treatment transect. Each transect is 30 meters wide with a 45
 meter buffer zone between each transect. The Treatment transect
 was treated annually until 1987 with NHNO3 in a concentration equal
 to 10g N/m2. The station markers at 30 meter intervals along each
 transect.</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>Objectives:
The Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System (JIMS) provides protocol and services for data collection, verification, organization, archives, and distribution in accordance with recommendations and guidelines developed by the LTER Information Managers Committee (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html).

Disclaimer:
While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is". The Jornada Basin LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of data sets.

Quality Assurance Policy:
Data managers interact with researchers during the entire scientific process--from the initial planning of sampling designs and field data collection to archiving and distribution of data. The goal of data management is to build and maintain an archive of Jornada Basin LTER data files that are fully documented, error free, and organized in useful ways. Our protocol for data collection and processing seeks maximum interaction between researchers and data management personnel to avoid confusion and potential loss of data or problems with integrity of data; e.g., identification of historical site treatments that may impact a proposed study or incomplete data set variable descriptions. Site and Data Manager involvement begins during the Project Design phase with the completion of the Jornada Notification of Research form by the researcher prior to the start of work; this alerts both Site and Data Manager to the new study and potential LTER data sets. Upon initiation of a new study, the researcher completes Project Documentation that provides the second level of "metadata" documentation.
In the Data Collection phase, the data manager helps researchers design field and laboratory data sheets that facilitate data entry and analysis. Prior to JIMS data entry the investigator completes Data Set Documentation to provide the metadata that fully describe the data set. Both Project and Data set documentation are provided with the data set when it is requested or obtained from our Web site. JIMS data entry programs error-check and verify data as they are entered. Computer files are subjected to further verification by graphing and/or error-checking programs, and/or examination by field investigators. Final quality assurance of the data rests with the investigator who submits data for inclusion in the Data Management System. Direct communication with the Site Manager, or through a collaborating JRN P.I., is used to encourage the timely submission of documentation and of data by researchers.

Error-checked data files are stored with associated documentation files on the file server. Archived data files are maintained in ASCII format on 30-yr magneto-optical (MO) disks, portable hard drives, CD-R media, and DVD media to guard against loss of data access that can result from changing technology. This may also include proprietary binary format files to facilitate recovery of working versions. Image data are archived on 8mm tape. Routine tape data backups of the file server are done daily, weekly, and monthly. One set of off-site copies are maintained elsewhere on the NMSU campus of routine backup tapes, MO disks, CD disks, and DVD disks with a second set of MO, CD and DVD disks maintained off-campus in case of a catastrophe on campus. The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data manag ement staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data management staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

Policy on Submission of data:
Data submission into JIMS is expected from LTER researchers, LTER collaborators, and their graduate students where data and information is derived from publicly funded research in the U.S. LTER Network, totally or partially from LTER funds from NSF, Institutional Cost-Share, or Partner Agency or Institution where a formal memorandum of understanding with LTER has been established. Other Jornada Basin researchers are encouraged to submit their documented data for inclusion within JIMS to provide them with an archived backup, ensure its longevity, and provide online access to encourage synthesis efforts. Minimally, for non-LTER associated researchers, we request that publications be provided of research conducted on the Jornada Basin.
Initial documentation for a data set must be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager within 90 days of initiation of data collection. Documentation forms are available at http://jornada-www.nmsu.edu/site/dm/readme.php . These consist of Project Abstract and Data Set and Attribute documentation forms, which include objectives of the study, methods, as well as format and content of the data. All data collected during a calendar year should be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager prior to July first of the following year. First time data submissions must be submitted with updated standard Jornada Basin LTER forms previously submitted.

Data Access Policy:
Data will be made publicly available no later than 2 years after submission of the data unless an earlier date is specified by the principal investigator. In the event that an extension of the 2 year period is necessary, the principal investigator may petition the Jornada Basin LTER Executive Committee for a longer protected period. Graduate student research data will be available online after degree completion and they have the opportunity to publish their research.

Policies for re-use, distribution, or the production of derivatives:
Data re-use, distribution and production of derivative products are governed by the LTER Network data policies (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html) in the spirit of having the potential to increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines. Appropriate citation, acknowledgement, notification and collaboration are outlined and recommended. No commercial redistribution of data and derived products are allowed.

Data Acknowledgment Policy:
Please send notification to the Information Manager and Responsible Investigator(s) of the data sets you are downloading and your intended use.
Individuals and institutions utilizing data from the Jornada Basin LTER database are requested to place the following acknowledgment in any publication in which these data are mentioned:
Data sets were provided by the Jornada Basin Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) project. Funding for these data was provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210).

Please send 1 copy of any publication that cites Jornada Basin LTER data to:
     John P. Anderson
     Jornada Experimental Range
     P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
     New Mexico State University
     Las Cruces, NM 88003-0003</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <coverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>1986-10-10</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>1990-04-06</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <maintenance>
    <description>
      <para>
        <literalLayout> mm/dd/yyyy - Date of Comment
 Int - Initials of person making Comment
 KJL = Kevin J. La Fleur
 JPA = John P. Anderson
 MAB = Michelle A. Buonopane
 KR = Ken Ramsey

 Changes/Updates - List any changes made to document

 mm/dd/yyyy Int Changes/Updates
 ---------- --- -----------------------------------------------
 12/06/2002 MAB Completed form.
 08/09/2003 JPA Updated keyword list
 07/21/2005 KR Added Dataset and Project IDs to top of form.
 07/27/2005 KR Changed format of Responsible Investigator and
 Researchers sections.
 Changed format of Associated Files section.
 08/22/2005 KR Changed format of Attributes Measured section.
 Incorporated Missing Values section into
 Attributes Measured section.
 11/17/2005 JPA Added acceptable value codes to variable "S"
 obtained from data set header.
 10/12/2007 KR Changed Date Data Collection Commenced from
 11/08/1986 to 10/10/1986 to reflect records in
 data file.
 11/18/2011 JPA Changed responsible investigator for contact person
 to John Anderson per Deb Peters</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </description>
  </maintenance>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Data</givenName>
      <surName>Manager</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>PO Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>The Jornada</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout> *Roots were collected from areas on the watershed adjacent to the
 study transects. The roots were gently washed to remove adhering
 soil particles, then dried to a constant mass at 50 C. Roots were
 collected from species that comprise more than 10% of the vegetative
 cover. Between one and three root segments of the woody sub-shrub,
 Gutierrezia sarothrae, and the most common summer herbaceous annual,
 Baileya multiradiata, were tethered with fine wire attached to an
 aluminum tag labeled with the identity code and intial mass.
 Approximately 1 g of roots fo each species: black grama grass
 (Bouteloua eriopoda), fluff grass (Erioneuron pulchellum) and the
 grass from the dry lake basin (Panicum obtusum), were placed in each
 12 cm X 12 cm fiberglass mesh bag (mesh size=1mm). We made 960
 bundles of G. sarothrae roots and 960 bags of E. pulchellum roots.
 There were 160 bags or root bundles of the other species. Each
 bundle or bag was attached to a unique number tag connected to a 30
 cm wire. Teh study was deisgned for the retrieval fo 8 units of
 each species from each watershed location and each transect on ten
 sample dates. Roots were buried in short trenches (3 m long)
 separated by approximately 3 m between trenches. Each bag or root
 bundle was separated from others in a trench by a minimum of 50 cm.
 The trenches were located at the appoximate mid-section of the
 fertilized transect of the basin slope and 80 bundles were buried in
 the mid-section of the un-fertilized transect of the basin slope.

 The roots of P. obtusum were placed in the dry lake basin, the roots
 of B. eriopoda were placed in the black grama grasss zone at teh top
 of the watershed, and the roots of B. multiradiata were placed in
 teh basin slope. Roots of G. sarothrae and E. pulchellum were
 placed in all vegetation zones because these species occur in all
 the zones on the watershed. The other species are restricted to one
 zone, and although B. multiradiata occurs in four zones, its highest
 abundance is in the basin slope zone. At all sites, roots and root
 bags were buried at 5-10 cm soil depth. Eight samples of each
 species were retrieved after 1, 3, 6, 12, 18, 24, 30, and 36 months
 in the field. The sequence of removal was determined by drawing
 numbers from the remaining bags at random. Although this study was
 designed for 48 months duration, parts of teh study had to be
 terminated early. At 42 months the trenches were completely and
 carefully excavated and the remaining material recovered. We were
 unable to retrieve complete samples of roots except for G.
 sarothrae. The small number of root samples that were collected in
 month 42 were pooled by site and treatment in order to obtain
 sufficient material for the chemical analyses. After retrieval,
 roots were removed from the bags, gently washed in distilled water
 to remove adhering soil particles and dried to a constant mass at
 50C. After the final dry mass measurement, the roots were ground in
 a laboratory mill equipped with a 1 mm screen. An exponential decay
 model was used to estimate the mass loss rate:

 X/Xo = ln -kt

 where X = mass remaining at time t (months), Xo = original weight,
 ln is the natural logarithm and k is the decomposition constant
 (Olson 1963).

 For the analysis of total nitrogen, sub-samples of ground roots were
 treated by Kjeldahl digestion in a block digestor. Ammonium
 nitrogen was analyzed by an automated salicylate procedure in a
 Scientific Instruments autoanalyzer (Fisher et al. 1987). Three
 organic matter fractions (water and non-polar solubles, acid
 solubles, and acid insolubles) were analyzed in the remaining root
 material. Non polar and water soluble substances were extracted
 using dichloromethane followed by hot (100 C) water (McGlaugherty et
 al. 1984). Acid soluble fiber, which was largely holocellulose, was
 separted from acid-soluble fiber (largely lignin and suberin) using
 a two-stage digestion in sulfuric acid (Effland 1977).</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
    <qualityControl>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout> History of Responsible investigator(s):
 H. T. Mun, Nov1986-Apr1990;
 Walter G. Whitford, Nov1986-Apr1990
 ***********************************
 *Taken from Mun (1998); see key literature.

 Note: Zone/site variable information was determined from review of
 published article; no documentation of codes from original data
 sets or documentation.

 Note: 'CARA' and 'CARC' were originally documented with units
 mg/g; these were changed to mg/l as per 'NITW' and 'NITA' variables.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </qualityControl>
  </methods>
  <project>
    <title>Jornada LTER</title>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
        <givenName>Debra</givenName>
        <surName>Peters</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-2777</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">575-646-5889</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>debpeter@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Lead Principal Investigator</role>
    </personnel>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Data</givenName>
        <surName>Manager</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Information Manager</role>
    </personnel>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>The Jornada Basin Long Term Ecological Research program, in collaboration with 
                         the USDA ARS Jornada Experimental Range, studies the causes and consequences of 
                         desertification: the broad scale expansion of woody plants into grasslands that 
                         results in more "desert like" conditions. We are interested in spatial and 
                         temporal variation in desertification dynamics, and how historic legacies, the 
                         geomorphic template, transport vectors (wind, water, animals), and environmental 
                         drivers (climate, land use, disturbance) interact with the patch structure of the 
                         vegetation to determine past, present, and future ecosystem dynamics across 
                         scales.
                        
                         Our study site is located in the northern Chihuahuan Desert, approximately 25 km 
                         northeast of Las Cruces, New Mexico, USA (+32.5 N, -106.8 W, elevation 1188 m). 
                         Annual precipitation is 24 cm and maximum temperatures average 13 C in January 
                         and 36 C in June. Our study site includes the 78,000 ha Jornada Experimental 
                         Range operated by the USDA Agricultural Research Service, and the 22,000 ha 
                         Chihuahuan Desert Rangeland Research Center (CDRRC) operated by New Mexico State 
                         University. The Jornada Basin LTER project was established in 1982, and is 
                         administered by New Mexico State University. This site is a member of the LTER 
                         Network, one of  more than 25 long term sites funded by the U.S. National Science 
                         Foundation.</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <funding>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210)</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </funding>
  </project>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>rootchem.dat</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data file information for the following Jornada data set: Root Chemistry</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>rootchem.dat</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <numHeaderLines>40</numHeaderLines>
          <numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
          <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>Tab-delimited</fieldDelimiter>
            <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url function="download">http://jornada-data.nmsu.edu/sites/jornada-data.nmsu.edu/files/data_files/rootchem.dat</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1986-10-10</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>1990-04-06</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>SEA</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_root_decomposition_chemistry_sea</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Season and year (yys, where yy = year and s = season (S=spring, F=fall, W=winter))
</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Season and year (yys, where yy = year and s = season (S=spring, F=fall, W=winter))
</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>MO</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_root_decomposition_chemistry_mo</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Month</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1  </code>
                  <definition> January</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>2  </code>
                  <definition> February</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3  </code>
                  <definition> March</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>4  </code>
                  <definition> April</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>5  </code>
                  <definition> May</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>6  </code>
                  <definition> June</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>7  </code>
                  <definition> July</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>8  </code>
                  <definition> August</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>9  </code>
                  <definition> September</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>10 </code>
                  <definition> October</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>11 </code>
                  <definition> November</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>12 </code>
                  <definition> December</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>DD</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_root_decomposition_chemistry_dd</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Day</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>N/A</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">31</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>T</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_root_decomposition_chemistry_t</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Treatment</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>A </code>
                  <definition> alternate control</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>T </code>
                  <definition> fertilized</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>S</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_root_decomposition_chemistry_s</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Site (zone)</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>PL </code>
                  <definition> playa or dry lake</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>B1 </code>
                  <definition> Basin 1</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>B2 </code>
                  <definition> Basin 2</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>L </code>
                  <definition> Larrea dominated</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>M </code>
                  <definition> Mixed</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>G </code>
                  <definition> Black Gramma dominated</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>SPEC</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_root_decomposition_chemistry_spec</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Species</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>BAMU </code>
                  <definition> Baileya multiradiata</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>ERPU </code>
                  <definition> Erioneuron pulchellum</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>XASA </code>
                  <definition> Xanthocephalum sarothrae</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>PAOB </code>
                  <definition> Panicum obtusum</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>BOER </code>
                  <definition> Boutelou eriopoda</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>TANN</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_root_decomposition_chemistry_tann</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Total Tannin</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mg/g</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> Missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>LIG</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_root_decomposition_chemistry_lig</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Total Lignin</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mg/g</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> Missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>CARA</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_root_decomposition_chemistry_cara</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Carbohydrates/acid</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mg/l</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> Missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>CARC</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_root_decomposition_chemistry_carc</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Carbohydrates/water</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mg/l</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> Missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>TOTN</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_root_decomposition_chemistry_totn</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Total Nitrogen</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mg/g</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> Missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>NITW</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_root_decomposition_chemistry_nitw</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Nitrogen/water</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mg/l</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> Missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>NITA</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_root_decomposition_chemistry_nita</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Nitrogen/acid</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mg/l</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> Missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>WAS</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_root_decomposition_chemistry_was</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Total Water Solubles</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mg/g</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> Missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>ASC</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_root_decomposition_chemistry_asc</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Total Acid Solubles</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mg/g</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> Missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>NPL</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_root_decomposition_chemistry_npl</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Total Non-polar Substance</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mg/g</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> Missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
    <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
<ns2:unit id="N/A" />
<ns2:unit id="mg/g" />
<ns2:unit id="mg/l" />
    </ns2:unitList>
  </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>