<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-jrn.20050610.9880" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=JRN, o=lter, dc=ecoinformatics, dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Transect Soil Phosphate</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>John</givenName>
      <surName>Anderson</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>
	Jornada LTER

	New Mexico State University

	P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>janderso@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <metadataProvider>
    <organizationName>The Jornada</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>2995 Knox Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-4842</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <onlineUrl>http://jornada.nmsu.edu</onlineUrl>
  </metadataProvider>
  <pubDate>1985</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para> PO4-P levels in CaCl2 and NaHCO3 extracts of soils collected at
 each station along transect. Moisture content of soil samples is
 also included. No soil samples were collected along the fertilized
 (treated transect) in January 1985; January 1986 data contains both
 fertilized (treated) and control transect samples.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>aqueous extracts</keyword>
    <keyword>bicarbonate extracts</keyword>
    <keyword>completed</keyword>
    <keyword>desert</keyword>
    <keyword>dilute salt extracts</keyword>
    <keyword>inorganic nutrients</keyword>
    <keyword>phosphate</keyword>
    <keyword>signature</keyword>
    <keyword>soil</keyword>
    <keyword>soil nutrients</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Jornada Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout> In the spring of 1982, as part of the establishment of the Jornada
 Long-Term Ecological Research site in southern New Mexico, a 135 ha
 portion of a 1500 ha, internally drained, watershed was exclosed
 from grazing by domestic livestock. Prior to exclosure the
 watershed, as well as the rest of the Jornada basin, had been
 moderately to heavily grazed for the past 100 years. Concurrent
 with grazing, the vegetation had undergone a dramatic change from
 desert grassland, with an almost continuous cover of C4 perennial
 grasses, to isolated patches of the original grassland in a
 mosaic with desert shrub dominated plant communities (Buffington
 and Herbel, 1965).

 The exclosure lies along a northeast facing piedmont slope at the
 base of a steep isolated mountain peak, and covers a variety of
 component landforms from the foot of the mountain to the basin
 floor. The northeast side of the exclosure is immediately upslope
 of the College Playa located near the NMSU College Ranch Headquarters

 Three parallel transects (2.7 km in length) run from the middle of
 the College Playa up into the foot of Mt. Summerford. The Control
 transect is to the west, the Treatment transect on the east side of
 the Control transect, and the Alternate Control to the east of the
 Treatment transect. Each transect is 30 meters wide with a 45
 meter buffer zone between each transect. The Treatment transect
 was treated annually until 1987 with NHNO3 in a concentration equal
 to 10g N/m2. The station markers at 30 meter intervals along each
 transect.</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>Objectives:
The Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System (JIMS) provides protocol and services for data collection, verification, organization, archives, and distribution in accordance with recommendations and guidelines developed by the LTER Information Managers Committee (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html).

Disclaimer:
While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is". The Jornada Basin LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of data sets.

Quality Assurance Policy:
Data managers interact with researchers during the entire scientific process--from the initial planning of sampling designs and field data collection to archiving and distribution of data. The goal of data management is to build and maintain an archive of Jornada Basin LTER data files that are fully documented, error free, and organized in useful ways. Our protocol for data collection and processing seeks maximum interaction between researchers and data management personnel to avoid confusion and potential loss of data or problems with integrity of data; e.g., identification of historical site treatments that may impact a proposed study or incomplete data set variable descriptions. Site and Data Manager involvement begins during the Project Design phase with the completion of the Jornada Notification of Research form by the researcher prior to the start of work; this alerts both Site and Data Manager to the new study and potential LTER data sets. Upon initiation of a new study, the researcher completes Project Documentation that provides the second level of "metadata" documentation.
In the Data Collection phase, the data manager helps researchers design field and laboratory data sheets that facilitate data entry and analysis. Prior to JIMS data entry the investigator completes Data Set Documentation to provide the metadata that fully describe the data set. Both Project and Data set documentation are provided with the data set when it is requested or obtained from our Web site. JIMS data entry programs error-check and verify data as they are entered. Computer files are subjected to further verification by graphing and/or error-checking programs, and/or examination by field investigators. Final quality assurance of the data rests with the investigator who submits data for inclusion in the Data Management System. Direct communication with the Site Manager, or through a collaborating JRN P.I., is used to encourage the timely submission of documentation and of data by researchers.

Error-checked data files are stored with associated documentation files on the file server. Archived data files are maintained in ASCII format on 30-yr magneto-optical (MO) disks, portable hard drives, CD-R media, and DVD media to guard against loss of data access that can result from changing technology. This may also include proprietary binary format files to facilitate recovery of working versions. Image data are archived on 8mm tape. Routine tape data backups of the file server are done daily, weekly, and monthly. One set of off-site copies are maintained elsewhere on the NMSU campus of routine backup tapes, MO disks, CD disks, and DVD disks with a second set of MO, CD and DVD disks maintained off-campus in case of a catastrophe on campus. The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data manag ement staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data management staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

Policy on Submission of data:
Data submission into JIMS is expected from LTER researchers, LTER collaborators, and their graduate students where data and information is derived from publicly funded research in the U.S. LTER Network, totally or partially from LTER funds from NSF, Institutional Cost-Share, or Partner Agency or Institution where a formal memorandum of understanding with LTER has been established. Other Jornada Basin researchers are encouraged to submit their documented data for inclusion within JIMS to provide them with an archived backup, ensure its longevity, and provide online access to encourage synthesis efforts. Minimally, for non-LTER associated researchers, we request that publications be provided of research conducted on the Jornada Basin.
Initial documentation for a data set must be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager within 90 days of initiation of data collection. Documentation forms are available at http://jornada-www.nmsu.edu/site/dm/readme.php . These consist of Project Abstract and Data Set and Attribute documentation forms, which include objectives of the study, methods, as well as format and content of the data. All data collected during a calendar year should be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager prior to July first of the following year. First time data submissions must be submitted with updated standard Jornada Basin LTER forms previously submitted.

Data Access Policy:
Data will be made publicly available no later than 2 years after submission of the data unless an earlier date is specified by the principal investigator. In the event that an extension of the 2 year period is necessary, the principal investigator may petition the Jornada Basin LTER Executive Committee for a longer protected period. Graduate student research data will be available online after degree completion and they have the opportunity to publish their research.

Policies for re-use, distribution, or the production of derivatives:
Data re-use, distribution and production of derivative products are governed by the LTER Network data policies (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html) in the spirit of having the potential to increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines. Appropriate citation, acknowledgement, notification and collaboration are outlined and recommended. No commercial redistribution of data and derived products are allowed.

Data Acknowledgment Policy:
Please send notification to the Information Manager and Responsible Investigator(s) of the data sets you are downloading and your intended use.
Individuals and institutions utilizing data from the Jornada Basin LTER database are requested to place the following acknowledgment in any publication in which these data are mentioned:
Data sets were provided by the Jornada Basin Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) project. Funding for these data was provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210).

Please send 1 copy of any publication that cites Jornada Basin LTER data to:
     John P. Anderson
     Jornada Experimental Range
     P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
     New Mexico State University
     Las Cruces, NM 88003-0003</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <coverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>1985-01-29</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>1986-01-15</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <maintenance>
    <description>
      <para>
        <literalLayout> mm/dd/yyyy - Date of Comment
 Int - Initials of person making Comment
 JPA = John P. Anderson
 WGW = Walter G. Whitford
 SMG = Sophia M. Gehlhausen
 MAB = Michelle A. Buonopane
 KR = Ken Ramsey

 Changes/Updates - List any changes made to document

 mm/dd/yyyy Int Changes/Updates
 ---------- --- -----------------------------------------------
 04/15/1985 WGW Form completed by investigator
 05/01/1997 SMG Form updated to current format
 11/20/2002 MAB Completed and/or corrected fields.
 01/21/2003 JPA Updated data set description with information
 on transects sampled.
 01/21/2003 JPA Updated Zone description in Attributes Measured
 to reflect information found in original
 spreadsheet.
 06/11/2003 JPA Added "soil" to data set title.
 07/21/2005 KR Added Dataset and Project IDs to top of form.
 07/27/2005 KR Changed format of Responsible Investigator and
 Researchers sections.
 Changed format of Associated Files section.
 08/22/2005 KR Changed format of Attributes Measured section.
 Incorporated Missing Values section into
 Attributes Measured section.
 11/17/2005 JPA Modified attribute description name from
 "Treatment station" to "LTER-I Transect station".
 11/19/2011 JPA Changed responsible investigator for contact person
 to John Anderson per Deb Peters</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </description>
  </maintenance>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Data</givenName>
      <surName>Manager</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>PO Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>The Jornada</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Electronic data forms </literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout> Samples are collected near each station on alternate sides of the
 transect. Distances from the station and from the control transect
 are designated prior to collection. Soil samples are collected from
 0-10cm after removing surface litter. Soils are oven-dried at 50
 degrees Celcius. Samples are extracted in a 10:1 ratio of standing
 0.5 M NaHCO3 and in a 5:1 ratio of standing 0.01 M CaCl2 for 24
 hours. PO4-P is measured in both extracts using an automated
 version of the Molybdenum blue-ascorbic acid method described by
 Watanabe and Olsen (1965). The NaHCO3 extracts are color-corrected
 by running the analysis without ascorbic acid (Watanabe and Olsen
 1965).</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
    <qualityControl>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout> Responsible investigator(s):
 ----------------------------
 Walter G. Whitford, Jan1985-Jan1986;
 Fred Fisher, Jan1985-Jan1986
 ************************************
 Samples taken in January 1986 were taken on both control and
 fertilized transects; 1985 data contains only control samples.

 Note outlier CaCl2 week 211 C78.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </qualityControl>
  </methods>
  <project>
    <title>Jornada LTER</title>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
        <givenName>Debra</givenName>
        <surName>Peters</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-2777</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">575-646-5889</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>debpeter@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Lead Principal Investigator</role>
    </personnel>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Data</givenName>
        <surName>Manager</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Information Manager</role>
    </personnel>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>The Jornada Basin Long Term Ecological Research program, in collaboration with 
                         the USDA ARS Jornada Experimental Range, studies the causes and consequences of 
                         desertification: the broad scale expansion of woody plants into grasslands that 
                         results in more "desert like" conditions. We are interested in spatial and 
                         temporal variation in desertification dynamics, and how historic legacies, the 
                         geomorphic template, transport vectors (wind, water, animals), and environmental 
                         drivers (climate, land use, disturbance) interact with the patch structure of the 
                         vegetation to determine past, present, and future ecosystem dynamics across 
                         scales.
                        
                         Our study site is located in the northern Chihuahuan Desert, approximately 25 km 
                         northeast of Las Cruces, New Mexico, USA (+32.5 N, -106.8 W, elevation 1188 m). 
                         Annual precipitation is 24 cm and maximum temperatures average 13 C in January 
                         and 36 C in June. Our study site includes the 78,000 ha Jornada Experimental 
                         Range operated by the USDA Agricultural Research Service, and the 22,000 ha 
                         Chihuahuan Desert Rangeland Research Center (CDRRC) operated by New Mexico State 
                         University. The Jornada Basin LTER project was established in 1982, and is 
                         administered by New Mexico State University. This site is a member of the LTER 
                         Network, one of  more than 25 long term sites funded by the U.S. National Science 
                         Foundation.</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <funding>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210)</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </funding>
  </project>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>phosphat.dat</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data file information for the following Jornada data set: Transect Soil Phosphate</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>phosphat.dat</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <numHeaderLines>46</numHeaderLines>
          <numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
          <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>Tab-delimited</fieldDelimiter>
            <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url function="download">http://jornada-data.nmsu.edu/sites/jornada-data.nmsu.edu/files/data_files/phosphat.dat</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1985-01-29</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>1986-01-15</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>FILEID</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_soil_phosphate_fileid</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>File identification code</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>File identification code</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>WK</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_soil_phosphate_wk</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Week number = 29 Jan 1985</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>N/A</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>TST</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_soil_phosphate_tst</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>LTER-I Transect station (A##, where A = Treatment(C = control transect) and ## = Station Number(1-90) )


</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>LTER-I Transect station (A##, where A = Treatment(C = control transect) and ## = Station Number(1-90) )


</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>EC</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_soil_phosphate_ec</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Error code (0 = no error)</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>0 </code>
                  <definition> no error</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1 </code>
                  <definition> error, see history file</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>BICARB</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_soil_phosphate_bicarb</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Bicarbonate extractable PO4-P (per kg oven-dry soil)</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mg/kg</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>SALT</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_soil_phosphate_salt</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Dilute salt extractable PO4-P (per kg oven-dry soil)</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mg/kg</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>MC</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_soil_phosphate_mc</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil moisture content</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>%</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Date</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_soil_phosphate_date</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Date of processing (mm/dd/yy)</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>mm/dd/yy</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Zone</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_soil_phosphate_zone</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Vegetation Zone</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1  </code>
                  <definition> playa</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>2  </code>
                  <definition> Mesquite fringe</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3A </code>
                  <definition> Mixed basin slope (subcategory)</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3B </code>
                  <definition> Mixed basin slope (subcategory)</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3C </code>
                  <definition> Mixed basin slope (subcategory)</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3D </code>
                  <definition> Mixed basin slope (subcategory)</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3E </code>
                  <definition> Mixed basin slope (subcategory)</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>4  </code>
                  <definition> Creosotebush</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>5  </code>
                  <definition> Lower Grassland</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>6  </code>
                  <definition> Upper Grassland</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>7  </code>
                  <definition> Mountain slope</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Simp</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_soil_phosphate_simp</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Simple zone</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1 </code>
                  <definition> playa</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>2 </code>
                  <definition> Mesquite fringe</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3 </code>
                  <definition> Mixed basin slope</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>4 </code>
                  <definition> Creosotebush</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>5 </code>
                  <definition> Lower Grassland</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>6 </code>
                  <definition> Upper Grassland</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>7 </code>
                  <definition> Mountain slope</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Land</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_transect_soil_phosphate_land</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Landform</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1 </code>
                  <definition> playa</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>2 </code>
                  <definition> Alluvial plain</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3 </code>
                  <definition> Nonburied Remnant</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>4 </code>
                  <definition> Alluvial Fan Apron</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>5 </code>
                  <definition> Erosional Fan Remnant</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>6 </code>
                  <definition> Fan Collar</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>7 </code>
                  <definition> Mountain</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
        <missingValueCode>
          <code>. </code>
          <codeExplanation> missing value</codeExplanation>
        </missingValueCode>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
    <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
<ns2:unit id="N/A" />
<ns2:unit id="mg/kg" />
<ns2:unit id="%" />
    </ns2:unitList>
  </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>